<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">Bioinformation</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Bioinformation</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="epub">0973-2063</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17597905</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1891696</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">69-1-2006</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Web Database</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Database of cell signaling enzymes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gowthaman</surname>
            <given-names>Ragul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="COR1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Venugopal</surname>
            <given-names>Ramya</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Dayanandam</surname>
            <given-names>Dhiviya</given-names>
          </name>
        </contrib>
        <aff>Department of Bioinformatics, School of Chemical and Biotechnology, Shanmugha Arts Science Technology &amp; Research Academy (SASTRA), 
     SASTRA UNIVERSITY, Tanjore, Tamilnadu, India</aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="COR1"><label>*</label>Ragul Gowthaman    
           E-mail:
           <email> ragul@bioinfo.sastra.edu</email>; Corresponding author</corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="collection">
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>28</day>
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>1</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>265</fpage>
      <lpage>268</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; 2005 Biomedical Informatics Publishing Group</copyright-statement>
        <copyright-year>2005</copyright-year>
        <license license-type="open-access">
          <p>This is an open-access article, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction 
				in any medium, for non-commercial purposes, provided the original author and source are credited.</p>
        </license>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>This paper describes a database for cell signaling enzymes. Our web database 
offers methods to study, interpret and compare cell-signaling enzymes. 
Searching and retrieving data from this database has been made easy and user 
friendly and it is well integrated with other related databases. We believe the 
end user will be benefited from this database.</p>
        <sec id="sble">
          <title>Availability</title>
          <p>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sastra.edu/dcse/index.html">http://www.sastra.edu/dcse/index.html</ext-link>
          </p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <kwd>cell signaling</kwd>
        <kwd>enzymes</kwd>
        <kwd>web database</kwd>
        <kwd>pBLAST</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Background</title>
      <p>A cell communicates with its neighbors and environment by sending and 
receiving information in the form of chemical signals. These signals are 
converted into intracellular second messenger signals that ultimately make the 
cells respond appropriately by dividing, moving or even dying. The external 
signals may enter the cell through enzymes, G-protein coupled receptors, 
hydrophobic molecules and ion channels. When the receptor sensing the signal is 
a catalyst such as enzyme, the response is amplified. Thus cell signaling 
governs the basic cellular activities and coordinates the cell action. Errors 
in cell signaling is the cause for many serious diseases/disorders including 
cancer, autoimmune diseases, diabetes etc. By understanding cell signaling we 
can treat these diseases effectively and potentially. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R01">1</xref>] However, no attempts have been made 
so far to curate and catalog the enzymes involved in cell signaling.</p>
      <p>DCSE, the Database of Cell Signaling Enzymes covers a gamut of cell 
signaling enzymes, which includes kinases, phosphatases, adenylyl cyclases, 
caspases, phosphodiesterases, phospholipases, prenyltransferases etc. As 
mentioned above the defect in cell signaling mechanism is the major cause for 
diseases and hence the cell signaling enzymes are considered to be potential 
target in rational drug design approach.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="methods" id="s2">
      <title>Methodology</title>
      <p>DCSE was developed using MySQL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R02">
2</xref>], a relational database management system, at the back-end for 
storing data. The database can be regularly updated. The data for the database 
were collected from SwissProt [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R03">3</xref>
], the repository of protein sequence information. PHP [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R04">4</xref>], a widely used general purpose 
scripting language that is especially suited for web development, was used to 
design the database interface.</p>
      <p>The database can be accessed over the Internet. A screenshot of the home 
page is shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F1">Figure 1</xref>.The database can 
be searched by specifying keywords such as name, Enzyme Commission Number and 
species. For each enzyme in the database a unique identifier called DCSE ID has 
been assigned. The ID consists of two parts. The first part tells about the 
enzyme class and the second part indicates the number of that enzyme in that 
class. The two fields are separated by an underscore (_). Each enzyme has been 
defined with its name, Enzyme commission number, and the species from which it 
has been sequenced. Crossreference details to other databases are also 
provided. The functional and other sequence related informations are provided 
by SwissProt, the domain classification and function is provided by InterPro 
[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R05">5</xref>], the protein family 
classification is provided by Pfam [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R06">
6</xref>] and the structural details are provided by PDB. [
<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R07">7</xref>] A hyperlink has been provided 
to corresponding entry page in the abovementioned databases.</p>
      <p>The sequence is also displayed in raw-text format. One can retrieve the 
sequence in FASTA format using the &#x2018;Retrieve in Fasta format&#x2019; 
option available with each entry. An advanced search can also be performed by 
filling an advanced query form that takes input as DCSE id, name, EC number, 
Species, other database id such as SwissProt, InterPro, Pfam and PDB. The 
fields in the search form are joined together by AND operator. BLAST (Basic 
Local Alignment Search Tool) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="R08">8</xref>
] is an algorithm for comparing biological sequences. Given a library 
or database of sequences, a BLAST search enables a researcher to look for 
sequences that resemble a given sequence of interest. A standalone BLAST has 
been installed and it can be used for similarity search purpose. BLAST can be 
done against SwissProt, DCSE or PD.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Usability/Accessibility</title>
      <p>There are three ways in which a user can query the database. The first is 
the &#x2018;keyword search&#x2019; that can be done by specifying exact or 
likely keywords such as name, Enzyme Commission Number and species. The second 
search option is the &#x2018;Advanced Search&#x2019; wherein the user can 
fill a form by specifying the details for various fields such as DCSE id, 
Enzyme name, Enzyme commission number, SwissProt accession number, InterPro 
domain ID, Pfam id or PDB id. The fields are joined together by AND operator. 
Alternatively the users can also browse the database by the 21 different 
categories of cell signaling enzymes. Whenever the database is searched the 
search returns the result with number of hits found for that query along with a 
summary of details for each entry with its id, name and species. The user can 
then select the appropriate hit by following the link on it. This displays a 
page with all the available details of the enzyme in the database such as name, 
EC number, sequence information and cross-reference to already existing 
databases as shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F2">Figure 2</xref>. A 
hyperlink has been provided to corresponding entry page in the cross-referenced 
databases for easy access. The sequence is displayed in raw-text format. One 
can retrieve the sequence in FASTA format using the &#x2018;Retrieve in Fasta 
format&#x2019; option available with each entry. A BLAST search can also be 
done to search for similar sequences within the database or in general. A link 
has been provided in the tools page. The BLAST input page and result page are 
shown in <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F3">figure 3</xref> and <xref ref-type="fig" rid="F4">4</xref>.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Utility to the biological community</title>
      <p>Since DCSE gather together all the information on biological molecules, 
sequences, structures, functions, and biological reactions, which transfer the 
cellular signals, this database has the potential of becoming a major hub of 
resource for the biological community. This database provides a mechanism by 
which researchers and students can transform information about interactions 
between biomolecules into knowledge about a cellular process.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Caveats</title>
      <p>The database needs to be updated from time to time as the data has been 
obtained from other sources. Despite our efforts to collect information from 
various sources and check them for consistency, the quality of the information 
depends heavily on the original source.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s6">
      <title>Future development</title>
      <p>The coiled-coil structure is important for protein interaction. Since the 
cell signaling also involves protein interaction, a tool to predict coiled-coil 
structure is of importance.</p>
      <p>There are few tools for this purpose like MultiCoil. The Multicoil program 
just gives the probability for a residue to be in coiled-coil region. We intend 
to develop a coiled-coil prediction tool based on artificial neural networks 
that could tell whether a residue is in coiled-coil region if it crosses a 
threshold computed from a training set consisting of proteins with known 
coiled-coil structure.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors are grateful to Dr. K.N. Somasekharan, Dean - School of Chemical 
&amp; Biotechnology, Dr. S. Swaminathan, Dean - Sponsored Research &amp;
 Director CeNTAB and Prof. K. Usha Devi, Dean - School of Computing, SASTRA 
University for their support.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="R01">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Persidis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nat Biotechnol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1082</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9831041</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R02">
        <label>02</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.mysql.com/">http://www.mysql.com/</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R03">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.expasy.org/sprot">http://www.expasy.org/sprot</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R04">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.php.net/">http://www.php.net/</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R05">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/">http://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R06">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Pfam/">http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/Pfam/</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R07">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="web">
          <comment>
            <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rcsb.org">http://www.rcsb.org</ext-link>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="R08">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altschul</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <source>Nucleic Acids Res</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>3389</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9254694</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <sec sec-type="display-objects">
      <title>Figures and Tables</title>
      <fig id="F1" position="float">
        <label>Figure 1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>DCSE home page</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="97320630001265F1"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F2" position="float">
        <label>Figure 2</label>
        <caption>
          <p>An DCSE entry</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="97320630001265F2"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F3" position="float">
        <label>Figure 3</label>
        <caption>
          <p>BLAST input page</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="97320630001265F3"/>
      </fig>
      <fig id="F4" position="float">
        <label>Figure 4</label>
        <caption>
          <p>BLAST result page</p>
        </caption>
        <graphic xlink:href="97320630001265F4"/>
      </fig>
    </sec>
    <fn-group>
      <fn id="FN1" fn-type="other">
        <p>
      <bold>Citation:</bold>Gowthaman
       <italic>et al.</italic>, Bioinformation 1(7): 265-268 (2006)</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>