<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Breast Cancer Res Treat</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Breast Cancer Research and Treatment</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0167-6806</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-7217</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17260092</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2045691</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9486</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10549-006-9486-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Preclinical Study/Clinical Trial/Epidemiology/Invited Commentary</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Differential effects of tamoxifen and anastrozole on optic cup size in breast cancer survivors</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Eisner</surname>
            <given-names>Alvin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+1-503-4182590</phone>
            <fax>+1-503-4182501</fax>
            <email>eisnera@ohsu.edu</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Toomey</surname>
            <given-names>Maureen D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Falardeau</surname>
            <given-names>Julie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Samples</surname>
            <given-names>John R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vetto</surname>
            <given-names>John T.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Neurological Sciences Institute , Oregon Health &amp; Science University, West Campus, 505 NW 185th Avenue, Portland, OR  97239 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Casey Eye Institute, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, Portland, OR 97239 USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Division of Surgical Oncology, Oregon Health &amp; Science University, Portland, OR 97239 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>106</volume>
      <issue>2</issue>
      <fpage>161</fpage>
      <lpage>170</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Introduction</title>
          <p>The main purpose of this study was to determine whether the optic cups of tamoxifen users and anastrozole users differ in size, with the cups of the tamoxifen users being smaller.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Optic nerve head (ONH) topography was measured using a commercially available, confocal scanning laser ophthalmoscope for three populations of amenorrheic women ages 40&#x2013;69&#xA0;years: subjects using (1) tamoxifen (20&#xA0;mg/day) or (2) anastrozole (1&#xA0;mg/day) for&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;2&#xA0;years as adjuvant therapy after successful primary treatment for breast cancer, and (3) control subjects with no breast cancer histories and not using any hormonal medication. All subjects had excellent visual acuity and healthy eyes, based on conventional photographic assessment.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>The cup volumes of the tamoxifen users were shown to be significantly smaller than the cup volumes of the anastrozole users, which were indistinguishable from normal. Because the cup volumes of the tamoxifen users decreased markedly with age at about 50&#xA0;years and because anastrozole is indicated only for post-menopausal women, comparisons were reassessed for subjects older than 50&#xA0;years. For these subjects, the cup volumes of the tamoxifen users averaged less than half of the volumes for each of the other two subject groups, and significant between-group differences existed in both the lateral (cup area) and axial (cup depth) directions. In contrast, any between-group differences at the ONH margin were small and not significant.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>The results of this study suggest that the ONH be assessed biomorphometrically for tamoxifen users reporting visual change that cannot be attributed to non-tamoxifen causes. The ability of modern intraocular imaging techniques to reveal anatomic change on the order of tens of microns may be useful for assessing tamoxifen-induced effects occurring simultaneously elsewhere in the brain, particularly since the presence of small cups is consistent with the possibility of tamoxifen-induced astrocytic swelling.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Adjuvant endocrine therapy</kwd>
        <kwd>Anastrozole</kwd>
        <kwd>Breast cancer</kwd>
        <kwd>Eye</kwd>
        <kwd>Optic cup</kwd>
        <kwd>Optic nerve head</kwd>
        <kwd>Tamoxifen</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC. 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMS) and aromatase inhibitors are the two major classes of medications used in the United States as adjuvant endocrine therapy for early-stage, hormone-receptor-positive breast cancer. Of the SERMS that are FDA-approved for this purpose [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], tamoxifen has been the most widely used, and for several decades it has been prescribed extensively for women of all ages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The first aromatase inhibitor to be FDA-approved for early-stage breast cancer was anastrozole (Arimidex<sup>&#xAE;</sup>), in 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. However, because aromatase inhibitors do not block estrogen production adequately for pre-menopausal women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], they are indicated for use by post-menopausal women only [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], for whom estrogen production is entirely non-ovarian [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Initial reports indicate that anastrozole is more effective than tamoxifen at preventing cancer recurrence [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Thus, anastrozole now is being recommended for many women who would have been prescribed tamoxifen several years ago [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Because the use of aromatase inhibitors is likely to continue to increase and because the use of tamoxifen may become progressively more restricted to younger women, the potential side effects of anastrozole need to be evaluated, and the influence of age on tamoxifen side-effects needs to be closely examined.</p>
      <p>Of all the documented or putative effects of tamoxifen on the visual system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], tamoxifen retinopathy may be the most widely known. However, tamoxifen retinopathy is uncommon [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and possibly cumulative-dose-dependent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In contrast, Eisner et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] found that short-term tamoxifen users (i.e., &#x2264;2&#xA0;years of use) often have smaller optic cups than age-matched female control subjects, in a study of women who had been selected for the absence of any overt eye disease. This result was consistent with the possibility that tamoxifen often causes a subclinical degree of swelling at the optic cup, particularly since tamoxifen is a potent blocker (at least in culture) of swelling-activated chloride channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], such as those in astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], and astrocytes are the predominant glial cell in the cup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. If tamoxifen indeed causes optic-cup swelling via its ability to block swelling-activated chloride channels, the cup sizes of anastrozole users would be expected to more closely resemble those of female control subjects than those of tamoxifen users. The present study tested this prediction.</p>
      <p>Because of changing trends in adjuvant breast cancer treatment, the present study also assessed the effect of age on optic nerve head (ONH) parameters. The results support the inference that tamoxifen usage can lead to small cups, although apparently mainly for women older than about 50&#xA0;years. All measurements for this study were obtained using confocal scanning laser ophthalmoscopy with the Heidelberg Retina Tomograph II (HRT). This commercial instrument was introduced in 1999 for routine clinical use, but until now, it has been used mainly to assess glaucoma and related conditions.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Subjects</title>
        <p>Three groups of amenorrheic women ages 40&#x2013;69&#xA0;years old were recruited for this study: (1) women using the standard dose of 20&#xA0;mg tamoxifen daily as adjuvant therapy for breast cancer for at least 4&#xA0;months but no longer than 2&#xA0;years, (2) women using the standard dose of 1&#xA0;mg anastrozole daily as adjuvant therapy for breast cancer for at least 4&#xA0;months but no longer than 2&#xA0;years, and (3) women not using any hormonally acting medications. This third group served as an approximately age-matched control group. The 2-year duration-of-use requirement was based on results from several studies of vision [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and the eye [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] indicating that short- versus long-term tamoxifen use can be distinguished operationally using a 2-year cutoff. The 4-month duration-of-use requirement was included to help ensure that the medications had time to act and that the body&#x2019;s response had a chance to stabilize [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
        <p>All tamoxifen and anastrozole users had completed primary treatment for breast cancer, and all were fully active and able to perform their daily pre-cancer activities without restriction. None of the control subjects had positive breast cancer histories or had previously used breast cancer medication for any purpose. Similarly, none of the tamoxifen users had previously used a hormonally acting breast cancer medication other than tamoxifen, and none of the anastrozole users had previously used a hormonally acting breast cancer medication other than anastrozole. In addition, none of the subjects in any group had ever used the SERM raloxifene.</p>
        <p>With one exception, all analyses for this report are based on data from subjects who had been amenorrheic for at least 6&#xA0;months at the time of testing. The one exception is an analysis comparing data from control subjects with data from an additional group of women (the fourth subject group overall) who met the same eligibility criteria as the control group, except for the absence of menses.</p>
        <p>All subjects, regardless of group, met a rigorous set of eligibility criteria for excellent ocular health in order to reduce the roles of confounding factors that could complicate the data. These are the same criteria we have used previously for several types of studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. These criteria are: (1) 20/20 or better visual acuity in one eye and 20/25 or better visual acuity in the other eye, (2) no evidence or suspicion of eye disease on undilated direct ophthalmoscopic examination and on subsequent evaluation of individuals&#x2019; stereoscopic color fundus and ONH photographs by a glaucoma specialist (author JRS) who was masked from identifying subject information, (3) no history of eye disease or ocular hypertension, (4) no diabetes, (5) intraocular pressure (IOP) &#x2264;22&#xA0;mmHg on Goldmann applanation and no between-eye IOP difference &gt;2&#xA0;mm Hg, (6) no myopia &gt;5 diopters, (7) no use of any medication (other than tamoxifen) known to affect vision, (8) no history of ocular surgery, and (9) normal color vision (i.e., no worse than a single minor transposition error on the D-15 test conducted under Macbeth illumination). There was no suggestion of papilledema for any subject (as for criterion #2).</p>
        <p>Demographic data for eligible subjects with usable HRT data (see second paragraph of Procedures) are given in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> for each of the three amenorrheic subject groups plus the additional group comprised of women without breast cancer histories and still experiencing menses. The mean ages of the tamoxifen users were slightly lower than the mean ages of the anastrozole users and amenorrheic control subjects possibly because some tamoxifen users were not menopausal despite being amenorrheic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. For reference, the median age of natural menopause in American society is 51&#xA0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>].
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Demographic data for each of the subject groups</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2"/><th align="left" colspan="3">Amenorrheic subjects 40&#x2013;69&#xA0;years old</th><th align="left" colspan="3">Amenorrheic subjects 51&#x2013;69&#xA0;years old</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Not amenorrheic, no breast cancer history <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;19</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Anastrozole <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;20</th><th align="left">Tamoxifen <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;34</th><th align="left">Control, no breast cancer history <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;32</th><th align="left">Anastrozole <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;18</th><th align="left">Tamoxifen <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;25</th><th align="left">Control, no breast cancer history <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;29</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td align="left">58.2 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;6.8)</td><td align="left">54.5 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;5.2)</td><td align="left">57.2 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;6.0)</td><td align="left">59.6 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;5.4)</td><td align="left">56.5 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;4.7)</td><td align="left">58.2 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;5.1)</td><td align="left">48.0 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;3.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">IOP (mmHg)</td><td align="left">15.7 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.9)</td><td align="left">15.5 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.3)</td><td align="left">15.6 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.9)</td><td align="left">15.7 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;3.0)</td><td align="left">15.5 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.5)</td><td align="left">15.7 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;3.0)</td><td align="left">15.5 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.3)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Duration of medication use (years)</td><td align="left">1.07 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.45)</td><td align="left">1.31 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.49)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">1.09 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.47</td><td align="left">1.36 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.48)</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left">0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>IOPs are from subjects&#x2019; test eyes only</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>All subjects were unpaid volunteers. Recruitment methods have been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. All subjects were Caucasian, except for one Asian subject still experiencing menses. After being informed of the nature and possible consequences of the study, all subjects gave written informed consent to participate in this study. The study protocol adhered to the tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki and was approved by the OHSU Institutional Review Board and the OHSU Cancer Institute. For each subject, HRT data and IOP measurements were obtained at the same testing session. Subject recruitment and assessment lasted several years, until usable HRT data had been collected for 20 eligible anastrozole users.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Procedures</title>
        <p>ONH scans were obtained using the HRT II according to standard techniques, after which a contour line is drawn on the average of three rapid-succession scans to define the margin of the ONH (i.e., of the optic disk) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Stereo color photographs of the ONH were used to assist with contour-line placement, and extensive use was made of the ability of the HRT II software to rotate images in three dimensions. Contour lines were drawn with the grader masked from all other subject information, including subject group and age. Additional details have been presented previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. However, we had previously placed the contour line as close as possible to the dark-to-light color change in the HRT reflectance image in order to define the margin of the ONH [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>], but for the present study we ensured that the contour line was placed on stable rim tissue on top of the ring of Elschnig [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], which is often most discernable from the underside of the 3D image, as a ridge circumscribing the ONH. With these 3D-based contour lines, the mean measured disk areas for each of our subject groups were very nearly centered within the norms provided by Heidelberg Engineering on the HRT II printout. Thus, with one exception, all analyses of HRT values are based on the contour lines drawn according to the more recent set of criteria, which are intended to place the contour line exactly at the disk margin, rather than slightly within it. The one exception was made to assess the importance (or lack of importance) of the precise contour line placement for documenting between-group differences. Thus, we conclude the Results section by briefly reporting the results of analyses based on data obtained using the earlier contour-line placement criteria.</p>
        <p>Eyes were considered to have usable HRT data only if the average standard deviation for the height of each pixel in the 3 HRT scans did not exceed 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;m, since average topographic standard deviation values above 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;m are considered by Heidelberg Engineering to signify &#x201C;low image quality&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Image quality was equally good for each subject group. The mean average-topographic-standard-deviation for each of the three amenorrheic subject groups ranged from 20 to 22 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;7&#x2013;8) &#x3BC;m for all eligible subjects and also for subjects older than 50&#xA0;years. Among women still experiencing menses, the mean was 23 (SD&#xA0;=&#xA0;9) &#x3BC;m.</p>
        <p>Although HRT scans were obtained for each subject&#x2019;s 2 eyes, only one eye per subject was used for data analysis for this paper. In this way, analyses could be limited to eyes with 20/20 or better acuity for a maximal number of subjects. Thus, test eyes were defined initially using the following steps applied in order as necessary: (a) the eye with the better acuity, even by 1 letter, than the fellow eye, (b) the eye with a lesser degree of spherical equivalent refractive error than the fellow eye, and (c) subject preference. In cases where the initially designated test eye had an HRT average topographic standard deviation value exceeding 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;m, the fellow eye became the test eye for analysis purposes, but only if the fellow eye had 20/20 or better acuity and an HRT average topographic standard deviation value &#x2264;50&#xA0;&#x3BC;m. These are the same methods we used previously to designate test eyes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Data analyses</title>
        <p>Comparisons of central tendency across more than two subject groups were made using Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis non-parametric analyses of variance (ANOVAS) because the distributions of some of the HRT indices were significantly non-Gaussian (1-sample Kolmogorov-Smirnov test) in ways consistent with the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Similarly, post hoc comparisons between pairs of groups were made using Mann&#x2013;Whitney U tests. Relations of HRT indices to age were evaluated for significance using Spearman rank-order coefficients because the strongest age trends were not linear. None of the reported <italic>P</italic>-values have been adjusted for multiple comparisons, but the P-values required for statistical significance of post-hoc tests as determined using a step-down Bonferroni procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>] are provided in the legend to Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. All analyses were conducted using SYSTAT 10.2 (Richmond, CA). All P-values are for 2-sided tests.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>ONH indices: between-group comparisons (subjects 40&#x2013;69 years old)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">ANOVA (Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis)</th><th align="left">Anastrozole versus tamoxifen </th><th align="left">Tamoxifen versus control </th><th align="left">Anastrozole versus control </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cup volume</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.021</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.007</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.052</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.560 </td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximum cup depth</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.016 </bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.008</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.036</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.430</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean cup depth</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.028</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.011</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.050</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.645</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.074</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.028</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.106</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.612</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup/disk area ratio</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.030</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.013</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.045</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.763</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup shape</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.593</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.325</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.797</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.429</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rim area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.115</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.173</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.053</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.492</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rim volume</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.084</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.059</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.061</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.940</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disk area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.510</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.474</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.653</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.232</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean RNFL thickness</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.718</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.654</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.438</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.735</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RNFL cross sectional area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.562</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.573</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.287</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.721</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Height variation contour</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.617</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.375</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.893</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.387</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Left-most data column&#x2013;&#x2013;<italic>P</italic>-values for the non-parametric ANOVAS (Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis) across all three amenorrheic subject-groups simultaneously. Comparisons based on the results for the larger contour circles (see Methods). Right 3 columns&#x2013;&#x2013;unadjusted <italic>P</italic>-values for the post hoc comparisons (Mann&#x2013;Whitney <italic>U</italic> tests) between pairs of subject-groups. The top 6 rows of variables are for cup data, the next 2 rows are for rim data, and the bottom 4 rows are for disk-margin data. The bold entries signify <italic>P</italic>-values that are considered statistically significant. For the ANOVAS, statistical significance was considered to be p&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;0.05. For the post-hoc comparisons, a step-down Bonferroni approach was used, so that the first (i.e., the most significant) comparison required a significant ANOVA plus <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;0.05/3, the second most significant comparison required a significant first comparison plus <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;0.05/2, and the third most significant comparison required a significant second comparison plus <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;0.05. &#x201C;RNFL&#x201D; signifies retinal nerve fiber layer thickness. The height variation contour signifies the maximal minus the minimal retinal nerve fiber layer thickness, as defined in the text</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The optic cup volumes, maximum optic cup depths, and cup/disk area ratios were each significantly smaller for the tamoxifen users than for the anastrozole users. In contrast, none of the comparisons between anastrozole users and control subjects approached significance for any cup dimension. Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> provides <italic>P</italic>-values for the between-group comparisons for every summary ONH index. The cup-volume results are represented graphically as a function of age in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, which presents the data from the three groups of amenorrheic subjects: tamoxifen users (filled symbols), anastrozole users, (shaded symbols), and control subjects (unfilled symbols).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Graph of cup volume versus age for all amenorrheic subjects. Filled circles represent tamoxifen users, shaded circles represent anastrozole users, and unfilled circles represent control subjects</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>The data in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> indicate that among tamoxifen users, cup volumes tended to be relatively small mainly for those subjects older than about 50&#xA0;years. Indeed, cup volumes decreased significantly with age (Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;0.41, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.018) among tamoxifen users. However, a correlational analysis would necessarily reduce or obscure the significance of any age-related change if such change occurred predominantly within a narrow age range. Thus, although the corresponding results for cup area (Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;0.33), maximum cup depth (Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;0.30), and cup/disk area ratio (Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;0.34) were each non-significant when assessed using correlations, the cup volumes, cup areas, maximum cup depths and cup/disk area ratios were each significantly lower (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;.05) for subjects older than 50&#xA0;years compared to subjects 50&#xA0;years and younger when based on between-group comparisons of central tendencies. An age cutoff at 51 rather than 50&#xA0;years yielded the same result. For each of these 2 age cutoffs, the difference in cup volumes between the older and younger tamoxifen users was highly significant (p&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;.005).</p>
      <p>Among control subjects and anastrozole users, there were not enough younger subjects to make meaningful comparisons between these same 2 age classes. However, we also tested an additional group of women without breast cancer histories, comprised of subjects who met all the same eligibility criteria as the control group, except for the absence of menses. None of the ONH indices differed significantly between the amenorrheic control group (32 women with an average age of 57.2&#xA0;years) and this additional group (19 women with an average age of 48.0&#xA0;years), and there was no suggestion of any differences in the cup indices specifically. For example, the median cup volume equaled 0.077&#xA0;mm<sup>3</sup> for the 32 control subjects and 0.076&#xA0;mm<sup>3</sup> for the 19 subjects still experiencing menses. Similarly, the median cup/disk area ratio equaled 0.20 for the 32 control subjects and 0.21 for these 19 additional subjects. Among the 32 control subjects themselves, cup volume was not correlated with age (Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;&#x2212;0.08). Among anastrozole users, Spearman <italic>r</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.27 (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.255), but the regression line relating cup volume to age accounted for only 5% of the total variance, and for only 2% when the calculation was restricted to subjects older than 50&#xA0;years.</p>
      <p>Because cup dimensions varied appreciably with age only for tamoxifen users, and because this variation appeared to be quite marked at about age 50&#xA0;years, we recomputed the between-group comparisons of all the ONH indices for subjects older than 50&#xA0;years. (None of the 19 women still experiencing menses were included in any of these comparisons). The results are shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. As expected, all of the between-group differences that were significant when the data were compared for all subjects remained significant when the data were compared for only the older subjects, and many of the comparisons between tamoxifen users and control subjects became significant (e.g., for cup volume). In addition, rim volumes (i.e., the volume above and outside the cup but within the disk) now differed significantly between groups when compared for all three groups simultaneously, but not when compared for any two groups on subsequent post hoc analysis. Had we used a less conservative means of comparison (a parametric ANOVA followed by Tukey&#x2019;s HSD test), the rim volumes of the tamoxifen users would have been considered to be significantly larger than the rim volumes of the anastrozole users and also than the rim volumes of the control users. This is probably the appropriate interpretation, since rim volumes, unlike cup volumes, were fairly normally distributed, allowing the use of parametric statistics.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>ONH indices: between-group comparisons (subjects 51&#x2013;69 years old)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">ANOVA (Kruskal&#x2013;Wallis)</th><th align="left">Anastrozole versus tamoxifen </th><th align="left">Tamoxifen versus control </th><th align="left">Anastrozole versus control </th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Cup volume</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.006</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.003</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.019</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.330</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Maximum cup depth</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.007</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.005</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.014</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.309</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean cup depth</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.016</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.007</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.038</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.463</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup area</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.025</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.009</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.051</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.431</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup/disk area ratio</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.011</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.005</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.020</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.540</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cup shape</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.340</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.146</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.400</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.463</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rim area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.113</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.161</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.049</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.511</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Rim volume</td><td char="." align="char"><bold><italic>P</italic></bold><bold>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.030</bold></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.018</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.035</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.678</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Disk area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.435</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.301</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.883</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.217</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mean RNFL thickness</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.542</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.350</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.336</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.000</td></tr><tr><td align="left">RNFL cross sectional area</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.482</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.369</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.259</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.878</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Height variation contour</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.341</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.160</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.775</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.242</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Same as Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, except based on data from subjects older than 50&#xA0;years)</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> presents the means and standard errors of the mean, along with the corresponding medians, for every ONH index for each of the three groups of subjects restricted to women older than 50&#xA0;years. Note that the means and medians for many ONH indices (e.g., rim volume) were similar within groups, but that for some ONH indices (e.g., cup volume), means and medians were dissimilar, signifying a skewed distribution. Thus, Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> present between-group comparisons of medians with interquartile intervals plus overall ranges for cup volume (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), cup area (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>), maximum cup depth (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>), cup/disk area ratio (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>), and rim volume (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>), in all cases for subjects older than 50&#xA0;years. Although the cup areas of the tamoxifen users were not significantly smaller than those of the control subjects, their cup/disk ratios were significantly lower, probably because a major source of anatomic variability unrelated to tamoxifen use now was factored out.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>ONH indices: means and standard errors of the mean, and medians (subjects 51&#x2013;69 years old)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Anastrozole <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;18</th><th align="left">Tamoxifen <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;25</th><th align="left">Control <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;29</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Cup volume (mm<sup>3</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.107&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.017</td><td align="left">0.043&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.015</td><td align="left">0.090&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.017</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.104</td><td align="left">0.012</td><td align="left">0.073</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Maximum cup depth (mm)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.611&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.047</td><td align="left">0.423&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.040</td><td align="left">0.559&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.040</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.591</td><td align="left">0.378</td><td align="left">0.594</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Mean cup depth (mm)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.207&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.017</td><td align="left">0.145&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.014</td><td align="left">0.189&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.014</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.206</td><td align="left">0.130</td><td align="left">0.198</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Cup area (mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.476&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.059</td><td align="left">0.275&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.050</td><td align="left">0.423&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.057</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.523</td><td align="left">0.139</td><td align="left">0.385</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Cup/disk area ratio</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.207&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.022</td><td align="left">0.123&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.021</td><td align="left">0.193&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.022</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.229</td><td align="left">0.079</td><td align="left">0.192</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Cup shape</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">&#x2212;0.229&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.015</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.199&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.012</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.219&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.013</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">&#x2212;0.229</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.205</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.210</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rim area (mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">1.724&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.066</td><td align="left">1.895&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.071</td><td align="left">1.697&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.061</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">1.797</td><td align="left">1.867</td><td align="left">1.732</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Rim volume (mm<sup>3</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.453&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.025</td><td align="left">0.593&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.042</td><td align="left">0.475&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.028</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.461</td><td align="left">0.580</td><td align="left">0.506</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Disk area (mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">2.200&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.094</td><td align="left">2.169&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.074</td><td align="left">2.120&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.067</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">2.316</td><td align="left">2.156</td><td align="left">2.154</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Mean RNFL thickness (mm)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.245&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.010</td><td align="left">0.264&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.014</td><td align="left">0.246&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.008</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.246</td><td align="left">0.262</td><td align="left">0.242</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">RNFL cross sectional area (mm<sup>2</sup>)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">1.281&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.059</td><td align="left">1.366&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.014</td><td align="left">1.266&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.049</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">1.282</td><td align="left">1.335</td><td align="left">0.242</td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Height variation contour (mm)</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.359&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.019</td><td align="left">0.401&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.019</td><td align="left">0.383&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.015</td></tr><tr><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.375</td><td align="left">0.388</td><td align="left">0.391</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Box plot of cup volume for women older than 50&#xA0;years for each of the three amenorrheic subject groups. For each group, the horizontal line inside the box represents that group&#x2019;s median value. The bottom and top of the box represent the upper and lower hinges, respectively, i.e., the first and third quartiles between which lie 50% of all the values. The whiskers represent the range of values that fall within a distance <italic>D</italic> from the hinges, where <italic>D</italic> equals 1.5 times the inter-quartile range. Asterisks represent individual points that fall between a distance of <italic>D</italic> and 2<italic>D</italic> from the hinges. Open circles represent individual points that are more distant outliers</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Same as Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, except that box plots are for cup areas</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Same as Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, except that box plots are for maximum cup depths</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Same as Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, except that box plots are for cup/disk area ratios</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Same as Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, except that box plots are for rim volumes</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10549_2006_9486_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      <p>When the between-group comparisons of the ONH indices were further restricted by excluding tamoxifen and anastrozole users using these medications for less than 1&#xA0;year, every comparison that was significant (bold numerical entries in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) remained significant. In addition, the duration of medication use was observed to matter little or not at all for the anastrozole users. For instance, the regression line relating cup volume to the duration of anastrozole use accounted for only 5% of the total cup-volume variance among all 20 anastrozole users, and for only 4% when the calculation was restricted to the 18 anastrozole users older than 50&#xA0;years. These several sets of results indicate that the cup differences between the tamoxifen and anastrozole groups did not occur because the anastrozole users had experienced too short a period of medication use.</p>
      <p>The bottom 4 indices listed in Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> represent biomorphometric assessments at the disk margin alone. These are: (1) disk area, (2) mean retinal nerve fiber layer (RNFL) thickness, (3) RNFL cross-sectional area, and (4) the height variation contour, calculated as the maximal minus the minimal RNFL thickness along the contour line. None of these indices differed significantly between groups, although there was some suggestion of greater RNFL thickness for the tamoxifen users (see Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>).</p>
      <p>As stated in the Methods section, we also conducted analyses using the ONH indices derived from contour lines placed slightly interior to the anatomic disk margin rather than exactly at the disk margin. Every statistically significant result concerning the cup remained significant when based on the smaller contours. Conversely, whereas some of the cup-area comparisons involving tamoxifen users were not statistically significant when based on the larger contours (see Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), every corresponding comparison became significant when based on the smaller contours. In particular, the cup-area values for the older tamoxifen users (&gt;50&#xA0;years) became significantly lower than the cup-area values for the older control subjects (&gt;50&#xA0;years), presumably because using the smaller contours enhanced the importance of effects occurring predominantly within the interior of the cup.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Because tamoxifen users and anastrozole users share similar medical histories, the results indicate that tamoxifen often leads to reductions of optic-cup size among middle-aged women older than about 50&#xA0;years. Any effects of anastrozole at the ONH remain unproven, and if they exist at all, they are probably minor and opposite to the effects of tamoxifen. In contrast to tamoxifen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], there seem to be no reports in the peer-reviewed literature concerning any visual or ocular side effects of anastrozole. One study has found that anastrozole can cause regression of breast cancer metastases within the choroid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p>
      <p>Because all of the women in this study met a rigorous set of criteria for excellent ocular health, any cup-size changes presumably would be designated as subclinical. Data from several reports suggest that the color vision of tamoxifen users is often altered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], although such alterations either are subtle or can be revealed only under specialized laboratory conditions, and there is no evidence that color vision changes are caused by effects occurring at the ONH. A recent survey found that about 13% of tamoxifen users reported experiencing vision changes that they attributed to tamoxifen [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>], but the nature of these purported changes was not specified, nor were the subjects&#x2019; reports related to the results of any eye examination. Nevertheless, the subjects reporting vision changes had significantly higher serum levels of tamoxifen and a potent tamoxifen metabolite (N-DMT) than did the women not reporting these changes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. In contrast, reports of well-known side effects associated with tamoxifen use, such as hot flashes and vaginal dryness, were not related significantly to these same serum levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Cases of tamoxifen-induced optic neuropathy have been described in the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], but such cases usually are considered rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. Perhaps tamoxifen users sometimes experience a degree of optic neuropathy that would not be detected or confirmed on a presenting eye examination owing to the wide range of normal cup appearances. If so, the results of this study point to a potential new application for intraocular imaging devices such as the HRT, which provides spatial resolution at the ONH on the order of tens of microns and is designed to detect longitudinal change [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. Several types of high-resolution intraocular imaging device are now available clinically [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>], and they allow high-resolution biomorphometric data to be collected in ways that are non-invasive and not intimidating to patients. The ease of data collection with these devices may allow patients who report tamoxifen-related vision change to be evaluated before and after cessation of tamoxifen use, and also after any rechallenge. Until this is done, and then only if changes in vision are shown to correspond to anatomical changes, might it be justified for the type of results described in this study to direct therapy. Presently, the only assured clinical application is to alert ophthalmologists and neurologists that assessment of the ONH for conditions such as glaucoma or optic neuritis may be complicated by the use of tamoxifen.</p>
      <p>A human-subjects study such as ours cannot definitively identify the mechanism(s) by which tamoxifen may reduce optic-cup size in vivo. Nevertheless, there is evidence to suggest that tamoxifen might reduce cup size via astrocytic swelling. First, tamoxifen is a potent blocker of swelling- (or &#x201C;volume-&#x201D;) activated chloride channels for astrocytes assessed in culture [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>], and astrocytes are abundant in the optic cup [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]. Second, although astrocytes are present in the RNFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], they comprise proportionally more of the neural volume as the cup is descended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], and astrocytes along with ganglion cell axons are abundant at the base of the cup and also within the sides [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. However, if the ganglion cell axons increased in volume, one would expect more visual dysfunction than is observed. In addition, there is evidence that tamoxifen-induced development of posterior subcapsular cataracts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] may involve the blockage of volume-activated chloride channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>], and that the utility of high-dose tamoxifen as salvage therapy for astrocytomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>] may depend partly on the ability of tamoxifen to cause astrocytic swelling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>]. Based on photographic assessment of the ONH and retina by a neuro-ophthalmologist (author JF), there did not appear to be any difference in the vasculature of the three subject groups that would have led to the between-group cup differences quantified in this study and also observed in the ONH photographs when examined for groups of subjects rather than for isolated subjects.</p>
      <p>The presence of a steep reduction of cup size with age at about 50&#x2013;51&#xA0;years among the tamoxifen users suggests that any ability of tamoxifen to reduce cup size, by whatever means, depends on the absence or near absence of natural female hormones, given that the median age of natural menopause is 51&#xA0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] and given that tamoxifen elevates the estrogen levels of pre-menopausal women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Hormone replacement therapy might, in principle, prevent or alleviate tamoxifen-induced reductions in cup size, but hormone replacement is generally contraindicated for breast cancer survivors, especially for women who have had hormone-receptor-positive tumors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>] (although diverse opinions exist [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">48</xref>]). Hormonal reduction by itself, whether occurring naturally or induced by anastrozole, does not appear to result in cup-size reductions of nearly the magnitude or the frequency inferred for the older tamoxifen users, at least not for the age range that we investigated. The presence of small cups among the tamoxifen users probably did not result from selectively low IOP levels, since the measured IOPs for each subject group were quite similar, differing by no more than 0.2&#xA0;mmHg on average. Because the presence of small cups among tamoxifen users appeared to be unaccompanied by corresponding significant effects at the disk margin, the effects of tamoxifen on the ONH may be regarded as predominantly localized to the cup.</p>
      <p>For this study, we found no evidence of any age-related change of ONH indices for healthy women not using hormonally acting medications. However, a recent study of hundreds of subjects has documented the presence of ONH differences between healthy men and women older than 65&#xA0;years [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. In that study, several ONH indices were found to differ significantly between men and women, but the greatest percentage difference was for cup area, which averaged about 14% smaller for women than for men [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">49</xref>]. There is separate evidence that cup areas can depend slightly on the phase of the natural menstrual cycle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">50</xref>]. These 2 sets of results along with our own results suggest that further studies be conducted to elucidate the effects of hormonally acting medications on the ONH. Such studies should include elderly women using tamoxifen, if possible, since elderly women have higher circulating levels of tamoxifen than do younger women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">51</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>The authors would like to thank the Oregon and Southwest Washington affiliate of the Susan G. Komen Breast Cancer Foundation for assistance with subject recruitment, Cindy Blachly for assistance with contour line placement, and Claude Burgoyne, M.D. for critiquing the manuscript. This research was funded by NIH grant R01 EY014594 (to A. Eisner) and by an unrestricted grant to the Casey Eye Institute from Research to Prevent Blindness (New York, N.Y.).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wolff</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Davidson</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of SERMs for the adjuvant therapy of early-stage breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Ann N Y Acad Sci</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>949</volume>
          <fpage>80</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wolff AC, Davidson NE (2001) Use of SERMs for the adjuvant therapy of early-stage breast cancer. Ann N Y Acad Sci 949:80&#x2013;88 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11795384</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colozza</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Azambuja</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardoso</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Breast cancer: achievements in adjuvant systemic therapies in the pre-genomic era</article-title>
          <source>Oncologist</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>111</fpage>
          <lpage>125</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1634/theoncologist.11-2-111</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Colozza M, de Azambuja E, Cardoso F et al (2006) Breast cancer: achievements in adjuvant systemic therapies in the pre-genomic era. Oncologist 11:111&#x2013;125 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16476832</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tredway</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buraglio</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hemsey</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A phase I study of the pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and safety of single- and multiple-dose anastrozole in healthy, premenopausal female volunteers</article-title>
          <source>Fertil Steril</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1587</fpage>
          <lpage>1593</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.fertnstert.2004.04.059</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tredway DR, Buraglio M, Hemsey G et al (2004) A phase I study of the pharmacokinetics, pharmacodynamics, and safety of single- and multiple-dose anastrozole in healthy, premenopausal female volunteers. Fertil Steril 82:1587&#x2013;1593 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15589864</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clemons</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coleman</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verma</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Aromatase inhibitors in the adjuvant setting: bringing the gold to a standard?</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Treat Rev</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>325</fpage>
          <lpage>332</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ctrv.2004.03.004</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Clemons M, Coleman RE, Verma S (2004) Aromatase inhibitors in the adjuvant setting: bringing the gold to a standard? Cancer Treat Rev 30:325&#x2013;332 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15145507</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Simpson</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sources of estrogen and their importance</article-title>
          <source>J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>225</fpage>
          <lpage>230</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0960-0760(03)00360-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Simpson ER (2003) Sources of estrogen and their importance. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol 86:225&#x2013;230 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14623515</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baum</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adjuvant endocrine therapy in postmenopausal women with early breast cancer: where are we now?</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Cancer</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1667</fpage>
          <lpage>1677</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejca.2005.05.006</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Baum M (2005) Adjuvant endocrine therapy in postmenopausal women with early breast cancer: where are we now? Eur J Cancer 41:1667&#x2013;1677 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16046117</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Howell</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New developments in the treatment of postmenopausal breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Trends Endocrinol Metab</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>420</fpage>
          <lpage>428</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Howell A (2005) New developments in the treatment of postmenopausal breast cancer. Trends Endocrinol Metab 16:420&#x2013;428 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16213745</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nabholtz</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Role of anastrozole across the breast cancer continuum: from advanced to early disease and prevention</article-title>
          <source>Oncology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000091180</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nabholtz JM (2006) Role of anastrozole across the breast cancer continuum: from advanced to early disease and prevention. Oncology 70:1&#x2013;12 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16439860</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nayfield</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gorin</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tamoxifen-associated eye disease</article-title>
          <source>A review. J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1018</fpage>
          <lpage>1026</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nayfield SG, Gorin MB (1996) Tamoxifen-associated eye disease. A review. J Clin Oncol 14:1018&#x2013;1026 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gorin</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costantino</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long-term tamoxifen citrate use and potential ocular toxicity</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>125</volume>
          <fpage>493</fpage>
          <lpage>501</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9394(99)80190-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gorin MB, Day R, Costantino JP et al (1998) Long-term tamoxifen citrate use and potential ocular toxicity. Am J Ophthalmol 125:493&#x2013;501 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9559735</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tang</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schiffman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Retinal changes associated with tamoxifen treatment for breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Eye</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <issue>Pt 3</issue>
          <fpage>295</fpage>
          <lpage>297</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tang R, Shields J, Schiffman J et al (1997) Retinal changes associated with tamoxifen treatment for breast cancer. Eye 11(Pt 3):295&#x2013;297 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9373465</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eisner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Malley</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Incognito</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Small optic cup sizes among women using tamoxifen: assessment with scanning laser ophthalmoscopy</article-title>
          <source>Curr Eye Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>379</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/02713680600602547</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eisner A, O&#x2019;Malley JP, Incognito LJ et al (2006) Small optic cup sizes among women using tamoxifen: assessment with scanning laser ophthalmoscopy. Curr Eye Res 31:367&#x2013;379 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16603470</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sardini</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Amey</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weylandt</surname>
              <given-names>KH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cell volume regulation and swelling-activated chloride channels</article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>1618</volume>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <lpage>162</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamem.2003.10.008</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sardini A, Amey JS, Weylandt KH et al (2003) Cell volume regulation and swelling-activated chloride channels. Biochim Biophys Acta 1618:153&#x2013;162 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14729152</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jentsch</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinreich</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular structure and physiological function of chloride channels</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Rev</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>503</fpage>
          <lpage>568</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jentsch TJ, Stein V, Weinreich F et al (2002) Molecular structure and physiological function of chloride channels. Physiol Rev 82:503&#x2013;568 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11917096</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Darby</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuzmiski</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panenka</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP released from astrocytes during swelling activates chloride channels</article-title>
          <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <fpage>1870</fpage>
          <lpage>1877</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1152/jn.00510.2002</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Darby M, Kuzmiski JB, Panenka W et al (2003) ATP released from astrocytes during swelling activates chloride channels. J Neurophysiol 89:1870&#x2013;1877 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12686569</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimelberg</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Astrocytic swelling in cerebral ischemia as a possible cause of injury and target for therapy</article-title>
          <source>Glia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>397</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.20174</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kimelberg HK (2005) Astrocytic swelling in cerebral ischemia as a possible cause of injury and target for therapy. Glia 50:389&#x2013;397 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15846797</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bussow</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The astrocytes in the retina and optic nerve head of mammals: a special glia for the ganglion cell axons</article-title>
          <source>Cell Tissue Res</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>206</volume>
          <fpage>367</fpage>
          <lpage>378</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00237966</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bussow H (1980) The astrocytes in the retina and optic nerve head of mammals: a special glia for the ganglion cell axons. Cell Tissue Res 206:367&#x2013;378 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6771013</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hernandez</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The optic nerve head in glaucoma: role of astrocytes in tissue remodeling</article-title>
          <source>Prog Retin Eye Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>321</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1350-9462(99)00017-8</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hernandez MR (2000) The optic nerve head in glaucoma: role of astrocytes in tissue remodeling. Prog Retin Eye Res 19:297&#x2013;321 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10749379</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eisner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Incognito</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The color appearance of stimuli detected via short-wavelength-sensitive cones for breast cancer survivors using tamoxifen</article-title>
          <source>Vision Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>1816</fpage>
          <lpage>1822</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.visres.2005.11.003</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eisner A, Incognito LJ (2006) The color appearance of stimuli detected via short-wavelength-sensitive cones for breast cancer survivors using tamoxifen. Vision Res 46:1816&#x2013;1822 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16364390</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eisner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Austin</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samples</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Short wavelength automated perimetry and tamoxifen use</article-title>
          <source>Br J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>130</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/bjo.88.1.125</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eisner A, Austin DF, Samples JR (2004) Short wavelength automated perimetry and tamoxifen use. Br J Ophthalmol 88:125&#x2013;130 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14693789</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morales</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neven</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Timmerman</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute effects of tamoxifen and third-generation aromatase inhibitors on menopausal symptoms of breast cancer patients</article-title>
          <source>Anticancer Drugs</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>753</fpage>
          <lpage>760</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001813-200409000-00003</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Morales L, Neven P, Timmerman D et al (2004) Acute effects of tamoxifen and third-generation aromatase inhibitors on menopausal symptoms of breast cancer patients. Anticancer Drugs 15:753&#x2013;760 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15494636</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loprinzi</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zahasky</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sloan</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tamoxifen-induced hot flashes</article-title>
          <source>Clin Breast Cancer</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>52</fpage>
          <lpage>56</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Loprinzi CL, Zahasky KM, Sloan JA et al (2000) Tamoxifen-induced hot flashes. Clin Breast Cancer 1:52&#x2013;56 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11899390</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eisner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samples</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>High blood pressure and visual sensitivity</article-title>
          <source>J Opt Soc Am A Opt Image Sci Vis</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1681</fpage>
          <lpage>1693</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1364/JOSAA.20.001681</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eisner A, Samples JR (2003) High blood pressure and visual sensitivity. J Opt Soc Am A Opt Image Sci Vis 20:1681&#x2013;1693 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12968642</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mourits</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vries</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willemse</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tamoxifen treatment and gynecologic side effects: a review</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>855</fpage>
          <lpage>866</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0029-7844(00)01196-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mourits MJ, De Vries EG, Willemse PH et al (2001) Tamoxifen treatment and gynecologic side effects: a review. Obstet Gynecol 97:855&#x2013;866 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11336777</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McKinlay</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brambilla</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Posner</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The normal menopause transition</article-title>
          <source>Maturitas</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>115</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-5122(92)90003-M</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McKinlay SM, Brambilla DJ, Posner JG (1992) The normal menopause transition. Maturitas 14:103&#x2013;115 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1565019</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fingaret</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flanagan</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liebmann</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The essential HRT primer</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <publisher-loc>San Ramon, CA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Jacoto Advertising Inc</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fingaret M, Flanagan JG, Liebmann JM (2005) The essential HRT primer. Jacoto Advertising Inc., San Ramon, CA </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burgoyne</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Downs</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellezza</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Three-dimensional reconstruction of normal and early glaucoma monkey optic nerve head connective tissues</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>4388</fpage>
          <lpage>4399</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.04-0022</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Burgoyne CF, Downs JC, Bellezza AJ et al (2004) Three-dimensional reconstruction of normal and early glaucoma monkey optic nerve head connective tissues. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 45:4388&#x2013;4399 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15557447</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">http://www.heidelbergengineering.com. search FAQ</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saruhan</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Orgul</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kocak</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Descriptive information of topographic parameters computed at the optic nerve head with the Heidelberg Retina Tomograph</article-title>
          <source>J Glaucoma</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>420</fpage>
          <lpage>429</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00061198-199812000-00012</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Saruhan A, Orgul S, Kocak I et al (1998) Descriptive information of topographic parameters computed at the optic nerve head with the Heidelberg Retina Tomograph. J Glaucoma 7:420&#x2013;429 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9871866</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ludbrook</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple comparison procedures updated</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>1032</fpage>
          <lpage>1037</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1440-1681.1998.tb02179.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ludbrook J (1998) Multiple comparison procedures updated. Clin Exp Pharmacol Physiol 25:1032&#x2013;1037 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9888002</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manquez</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shields</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of choroidal metastases from breast carcinomas using aromatase inhibitors</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>251</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.icu.0000193105.22960.f6</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Manquez ME, Brown MM, Shields CL et al (2006) Management of choroidal metastases from breast carcinomas using aromatase inhibitors. Curr Opin Ophthalmol 17:251&#x2013;256 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16794437</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gallicchio</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lord</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tkaczuk</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Association of tamoxifen (TAM) and TAM metabolite concentrations with self-reported side effects of TAM in women with breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Breast Cancer Res Treat</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <fpage>89</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/B:BREA.0000021050.92539.b0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gallicchio L, Lord G, Tkaczuk K et al (2004) Association of tamoxifen (TAM) and TAM metabolite concentrations with self-reported side effects of TAM in women with breast cancer. Breast Cancer Res Treat 85:89&#x2013;97 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15039600</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Noureddin</surname>
              <given-names>BN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seoud</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bashshur</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ocular toxicity in low-dose tamoxifen: a prospective study</article-title>
          <source>Eye</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>Pt 6</issue>
          <fpage>729</fpage>
          <lpage>733</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Noureddin BN, Seoud M, Bashshur Z et al (1999) Ocular toxicity in low-dose tamoxifen: a prospective study. Eye 13(Pt 6):729&#x2013;733 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10707134</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Colley</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elston</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tamoxifen optic neuropathy</article-title>
          <source>Clin Exp Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>105</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1442-9071.2004.00769.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Colley SM, Elston JS (2004) Tamoxifen optic neuropathy. Clin Exp Ophthalmol 32:105&#x2013;106 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Therssen</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jansen</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leys</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Screening for tamoxifen ocular toxicity: a prospective study</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>234</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Therssen R, Jansen E, Leys A et al (1995) Screening for tamoxifen ocular toxicity: a prospective study. Eur J Ophthalmol 5:230&#x2013;234 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8963159</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pugesgaard</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eyben</surname>
              <given-names>FE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral optic neuritis evolved during tamoxifen treatment</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>58</volume>
          <fpage>383</fpage>
          <lpage>386</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0142(19860715)58:2&lt;383::AID-CNCR2820580232&gt;3.0.CO;2-I</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pugesgaard T, Von Eyben FE (1986) Bilateral optic neuritis evolved during tamoxifen treatment. Cancer 58:383&#x2013;386 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3719532</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ashford</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donev</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tiwari</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reversible ocular toxicity related to tamoxifen therapy</article-title>
          <source>Cancer</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>61</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/1097-0142(19880101)61:1&lt;33::AID-CNCR2820610107&gt;3.0.CO;2-I</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ashford AR, Donev I, Tiwari RP et al (1988) Reversible ocular toxicity related to tamoxifen therapy. Cancer 61:33&#x2013;35 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3334951</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Fraunfelder FT, Fraunfelder FW (2001) Drug-induced ocular side effects. Butterworth-Heinemann, Boston, pp 471&#x2013;474</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burgoyne</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Image analysis of optic nerve disease</article-title>
          <source>Eye</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>1207</fpage>
          <lpage>1213</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/sj.eye.6701544</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Burgoyne CF (2004) Image analysis of optic nerve disease. Eye 18:1207&#x2013;1213 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15534606</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kimelberg</surname>
              <given-names>HK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased release of excitatory amino acids by the actions of ATP and peroxynitrite on volume-regulated anion channels (VRACs) in astrocytes</article-title>
          <source>Neurochem Int</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>511</fpage>
          <lpage>519</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuint.2003.11.002</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kimelberg HK (2004) Increased release of excitatory amino acids by the actions of ATP and peroxynitrite on volume-regulated anion channels (VRACs) in astrocytes. Neurochem Int 45:511&#x2013;519 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15186917</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Minckler</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLean</surname>
              <given-names>IW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tso</surname>
              <given-names>MO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distribution of axonal and glial elements in the rhesus optic nerve head studied by electron microscopy</article-title>
          <source>Am J Ophthalmol</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>179</fpage>
          <lpage>187</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Minckler DS, McLean IW, Tso MO (1976) Distribution of axonal and glial elements in the rhesus optic nerve head studied by electron microscopy. Am J Ophthalmol 82:179&#x2013;187 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">821348</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Shields MB (1998) Optic nerve head and peripapillary retina. Textbook of Glaucoma. Williams &amp; Wilkins, Baltimore, pp 72&#x2013;107</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jacob</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Volume regulation in the bovine lens and cataract. The involvement of chloride channels</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>971</fpage>
          <lpage>978</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zhang JJ, Jacob TJ (1996) Volume regulation in the bovine lens and cataract. The involvement of chloride channels. J Clin Invest 97:971&#x2013;978 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8613551</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chamberlain</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kormanik</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Salvage chemotherapy with tamoxifen for recurrent anaplastic astrocytomas</article-title>
          <source>Arch Neurol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>703</fpage>
          <lpage>708</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/archneur.56.6.703</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chamberlain MC, Kormanik PA (1999) Salvage chemotherapy with tamoxifen for recurrent anaplastic astrocytomas. Arch Neurol 56:703&#x2013;708 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10369310</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ransom</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neal</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sontheimer</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Volume-activated chloride currents contribute to the resting conductance and invasive migration of human glioma cells</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>7674</fpage>
          <lpage>7683</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ransom CB, O&#x2019;Neal JT, Sontheimer H (2001) Volume-activated chloride currents contribute to the resting conductance and invasive migration of human glioma cells. J Neurosci 21:7674&#x2013;7683 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11567057</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Klijn</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beex</surname>
              <given-names>LV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauriac</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Combined treatment with buserelin and tamoxifen in premenopausal metastatic breast cancer: a randomized study</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>903</fpage>
          <lpage>911</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/92.11.903</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Klijn JG, Beex LV, Mauriac L et al (2000) Combined treatment with buserelin and tamoxifen in premenopausal metastatic breast cancer: a randomized study. J Natl Cancer Inst 92:903&#x2013;911 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10841825</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Genazzani</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gadducci</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gambacciani</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Controversial issues in climacteric medicine II. Hormone replacement therapy and cancer. International Menopause Society Expert Workshop. 9&#x2013;12 June 2001, Opera del Duomo, Pisa, Italy</article-title>
          <source>Climacteric</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>181</fpage>
          <lpage>193</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1080/713605096</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Genazzani AR, Gadducci A, Gambacciani M (2001) Controversial issues in climacteric medicine II. Hormone replacement therapy and cancer. International Menopause Society Expert Workshop. 9&#x2013;12 June 2001, Opera del Duomo, Pisa, Italy. Climacteric 4:181&#x2013;193 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11588941</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <label>48.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Batur</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blixen</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Menopausal hormone therapy (HT) in patients with breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Maturitas</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>123</fpage>
          <lpage>132</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.maturitas.2005.03.004</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Batur P, Blixen CE, Moore HC et al (2006) Menopausal hormone therapy (HT) in patients with breast cancer. Maturitas 53:123&#x2013;132 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16368466</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <label>49.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vernon</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hawker</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ainsworth</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Laser scanning tomography of the optic nerve head in a normal elderly population: the Bridlington Eye Assessment Project</article-title>
          <source>Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>2823</fpage>
          <lpage>2828</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1167/iovs.05-0087</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vernon SA, Hawker MJ, Ainsworth G et al (2005) Laser scanning tomography of the optic nerve head in a normal elderly population: the Bridlington Eye Assessment Project. Invest Ophthalmol Vis Sci 46:2823&#x2013;2828 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16043856</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <label>50.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akar</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taskin</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yucel</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of the menstrual cycle on optic nerve head analysis in healthy women</article-title>
          <source>Acta Ophthalmol Scand</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>741</fpage>
          <lpage>745</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1600-0420.2004.00351.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Akar ME, Taskin O, Yucel I et al (2004) The effect of the menstrual cycle on optic nerve head analysis in healthy women. Acta Ophthalmol Scand 82:741&#x2013;745 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15606474</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <label>51.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gallicchio</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tkaczuk</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lord</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Medication use, tamoxifen (TAM), and TAM metabolite concentrations in women with breast cancer</article-title>
          <source>Cancer Lett</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>211</volume>
          <fpage>57</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.canlet.2004.04.001</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gallicchio L, Tkaczuk K, Lord G et al (2004) Medication use, tamoxifen (TAM), and TAM metabolite concentrations in women with breast cancer. Cancer Lett 211:57&#x2013;67 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15194217</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>