<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Cancer Causes Control</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Cancer Causes &amp; Control </journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0957-5243</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-7225</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18085414</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2323031</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9102</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10552-007-9102-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Brief Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Cancer screening in France: subjects&#x2019; and physicians&#x2019; attitudes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Eisinger</surname>
            <given-names>Fran&#xE7;ois</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+33-4-91223541</phone>
            <fax>+33-4-91223857</fax>
            <email>eisinger@marseille.inserm.fr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Blay</surname>
            <given-names>Jean-Yves</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mor&#xE8;re</surname>
            <given-names>Jean-Fran&#xE7;ois</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rixe</surname>
            <given-names>Olivier</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff8">8</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Calazel-Benque</surname>
            <given-names>Anne</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff9">9</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cals</surname>
            <given-names>Laurent</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff10">10</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Coscas</surname>
            <given-names>Yvan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff11">11</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dolbeault</surname>
            <given-names>Sylvie</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff12">12</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Namer</surname>
            <given-names>Mo&#xEF;se</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff13">13</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Serin</surname>
            <given-names>Daniel</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff14">14</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Roussel</surname>
            <given-names>Claire</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff15">15</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pivot</surname>
            <given-names>Xavier</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff16">16</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff17">17</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <collab>on behalf of the EDIFICE Committee</collab>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Oncogenetics Screening and Prevention, Paoli-Calmettes Institute, Marseille, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>INSERM U599, 232, Boulevard Sainte-Marguerite, B.P. 156, 13273 Marseille Cedex 9, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Edouard Herriot Hospital, Lyon, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>INSERM U590, L. B&#xE9;rard &amp; Conticanet Centre, Lyon, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Avicenne University Hospital, Bobigny, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Paris XII University, Paris, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Piti&#xE9;-Salp&#xEA;tri&#xE8;re Hospital, AP-HP, Paris, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff8"><label>8</label>Paris VI University, Paris, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff9"><label>9</label>Capio Clinique du Parc, Toulouse, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff10"><label>10</label>Font-Pr&#xE9; Hospital, Toulon, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff11"><label>11</label>Porte de Saint-Cloud Clinic, Boulogne-Billancourt, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff12"><label>12</label>Psycho-Oncology Unit, Institut Curie, Paris, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff13"><label>13</label>Azurean Centre of Cancerology, Mougins, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff14"><label>14</label>Sainte-Catherine Institute, Avignon, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff15"><label>15</label>ROCHE S.A, Neuilly-sur-Seine, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff16"><label>16</label>Besan&#xE7;on University Hospital, Besancon, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff17"><label>17</label>INSERM U645, Besancon, France </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>19</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>431</fpage>
      <lpage>434</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>Since screening for cancer has been advocated, funded, and promoted in France, it is important to evaluate the attitudes of subjects in the general population and general practitioners (GPs) toward cancer screening strategies.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>EDIFICE is a nationwide opinion poll that was carried out by telephone among a representative sample of 1,504 subjects living in France and aged between 40 and 75&#xA0;years and among a representative sample of 600&#xA0;GPs. The questionnaire administered to subjects queried about previous screening for cancer.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Ninety-three percent of women stated that they had undergone at least one mammography. Although rated &#x201C;A&#x201D; recommendation&#x2014;strongly recommended&#x2014;by the US Preventive Services Task Force, screening for colorectal cancer received less attention than prostate cancer screening which is rated &#x201C;I&#x201D;&#x2014;insufficient evidence&#x2014;(reported screening rates of 25% and 36%, respectively). Six percent of subjects stated that they had undergone lung cancer screening. GPs&#x2019; attitudes toward cancer screening showed similar inconsistencies.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>It thus appears that understanding of cancer screening practices in the French general population does not match scientific evidence. To a lesser extent, this also holds for GPs.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Mass-screening</kwd>
        <kwd>Compliance</kwd>
        <kwd>Health care opinion poll</kwd>
        <kwd>Health services research</kwd>
        <kwd>Health services misuse</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Early detection of cancer can theoretically prolong overall survival of the screened subjects. Reductions in cancer-related mortality have been demonstrated for mammography for breast cancer (BC) and fecal occult blood test (FOBT) for colorectal cancer (CRC) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. For these two cancers, mass-screening programs are implemented in France, in which targeted subjects are contacted by mail. The US Preventive Services Task Force guidelines rate CRC screening as &#x201C;A&#x201D; (strongly recommended), BC screening as &#x201C;B&#x201D; (recommended), and both prostate cancer (PC) and lung cancer (LC) screenings as &#x201C;I&#x201D; (evidence insufficient to come down in favor or against screening) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. The objectives of the nationwide EDIFICE opinion poll carried out in France were to collect data at the national level (the level of funding) about (1) subjects&#x2019; individual access to cancer screening procedures (through organized programs or on subjects&#x2019; own initiative) and (2) about general practitioners&#x2019; (GPs) attitudes toward cancer screening. Four frequent cancer types were selected on the grounds of their different screening statuses: BC and CRC for evidence of efficacy of screening and existence of a national screening program and prostate and lung cancers for neither evidence of efficacy of screening nor official screening program.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>General population opinion poll</title>
        <p>The population-based EDIFICE opinion poll was carried out by telephone from 18 January to 2 February, 2005 among a representative sample of 1,504 subjects living in France and between 40 and 75&#xA0;years old (1,609 subjects minus 105 who had already been affected by cancer). Sample representativeness was assessed, in relation to the statistics of the French Employment Survey in year 2002 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], based on the following criteria: sex, age (five categories), profession (eight categories), community size (five categories), and regional distribution (nine categories).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>General practitioner opinion poll</title>
        <p>A nationwide opinion poll was carried out by telephone from 31 January to 18 February, 2005 among a representative sample of 600 GPs practicing in France. Sample representativeness was assessed based on the following criteria: age (four categories) and regional distribution (five categories).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The main results of EDIFICE opinion poll are summarized in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Almost all (93%) interviewed women stated that they had undergone at least one mammography. In contrast, 25%, 36%, and 6% of the interviewed subjects stated that they had undergone screening tests for CRC, PC, and LC, respectively.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Adherence to cancer screening strategies according to the French nationwide EDIFICE opinion poll (1,504 subjects, 600 general practitioners). In France, there are organized mass-screening programs for breast cancer by mammography (100% of the population covered at the time of the opinion poll) and for colorectal cancer using Hemoccult (almost 30% of the population covered). In contrast, there is no mass-screening program for prostate cancer and lung cancer. For subjects in the general population, figures indicate the rates of subjects stating that they had undergone at least one screening test. For general practitioners, figures indicate the rates of general practitioners stating that they systematically recommended cancer screening</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10552_2007_9102_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>The corresponding percentages of GPs who stated that they recommended cancer screening tests to their patients were consistent with the proportions of subjects who had undergone screening tests for each tumor type: 68%, 18%, 58%, and 4% of the interviewed GPs stated that they systematically recommended screening for BC, CRC, PC and LC, respectively.</p>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Reasons given to explain why screening tests had not been performed</title>
        <p>Physicians and subjects provided contrasting answers as to why cancer-screening tests had not been performed. Physicians mainly focused on subjects&#x2019; fears while subjects denied this reason. Fear of results was cited by 44% of physicians as the main explanation why subjects did not undergo BC screening tests versus only 18% of subjects. For CRC screening, the figures were 16% and 3%, respectively. The corresponding odds ratios for fear being elicited by subjects versus GPs as the reason for not undergoing BC or CRC screening tests were 0.29 and 0.15, respectively (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Furthermore, subjects focused on a lack of advice on cancer screening from their physicians whereas GPs rarely did so. Lack of advice from the physicians was cited by 11% of subjects as the main explicative factor for subjects not undergoing BC screening tests versus only 1% of GPs. For CRC screening, the figures were 16% and 9%, respectively. The corresponding odds ratios for lack of medical advice being elicited by subjects versus GPs as the reason for subjects not undergoing BC or CRC screening tests were 11.65 and 1.93, respectively (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Reasons cited by subjects in the general population and general practitioners why subjects did not undergo screening tests for breast cancer (BC) or colorectal cancer (CRC)</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Reasons cited</th><th align="left" colspan="2">For not undergoing BC screening tests</th><th align="left" colspan="2">For not undergoing CRC screening tests</th></tr><tr><th align="left">Female subjects <italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;38</th><th align="left">General practitioners <italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;600</th><th align="left">Subjects <italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;725</th><th align="left">General practitioners <italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;600</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Subjects fearing the result <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left">7 (18)</td><td align="left">264 (44)</td><td align="left">20 (3)</td><td align="left">96 (16)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">OR (CI<sub>95%</sub>)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.29 (0.12&#x2013;0.66)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">0.15 (0.09&#x2013;0.24)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Lack of physician&#x2019;s advice <italic>n</italic> (%)</td><td align="left">4 (11)</td><td align="left">6 (1)</td><td align="left">116 (16)</td><td align="left">54 (9)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">OR (CI<sub>95%</sub>)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">11.65 (3.14&#x2013;43.23)</td><td align="left" colspan="2">1.93 (1.37&#x2013;2.71)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>OR indicates odds ratio; CI<sub>95%</sub> indicates confidence interval at the risk &#x3B1;&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In the present study, we describe the adherence to different screening programs for four types of cancers (BC, CRC, PC, and LC) in France. It is important to point out that this opinion poll does not report an accurate incidence of subjects actually screened for cancer but indeed the proportion of subjects stating that they had undergone at least one screening test. It is also worth mentioning that the French national health insurance system currently makes the corresponding screening tests (FOBT, mammography, prostate specific antigen&#x2014;PSA&#x2014;testing and X-ray) available for free (or almost free) to all affiliates.</p>
      <p>The major finding of this report is the obvious disagreement between evidence-based official recommendations and actual practice is both subjects in the general population and GPs in France. Despite a high level of evidence of reduction in cancer-related mortality of similar magnitude (&#x223C;15&#x2013;20%) with both BC and CRC mass-screenings [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], 93% of women undergo mammography screening whereas only 25% of subjects in the same age range have access to CRC screening tools. In contrast, 36% of men aged between 50 and 74&#xA0;years have undergone a screening test for PC (mainly PSA testing) even though the benefit of PC screening remains unknown [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>EDIFICE showed, on the one hand, two &#x201C;rational rates&#x201D; of screening&#x2014;high rate of women having undergone mammography and low rate of subjects having performed LC screening&#x2014;and, on the other hand, two &#x201C;inadequate rates&#x201D; of screening&#x2014;abnormally low rate of CRC screening (nationwide coverage by the on-going program is expected by the end of 2007) and abnormally high rate of PC screening. Even more striking, the French GPs&#x2019; behavioral pattern of recommending individual cancer screening exhibited the same inconsistencies.</p>
      <p>Three reasons can be suggested to explain the observed relationships between subjects&#x2019; and GPs&#x2019; behaviors. First, subjects in the general population may be influenced by medical counseling. Alternatively, physicians may endorse their patients&#x2019; views and agree &#x201C;under pressure&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Lastly, both subjects and GPs are exposed to similar not evidence-supported recommendations/information, with the &#x201C;magic touch&#x201D; of blood analysis for PC screening being attractive to them. Appropriate information of subjects and physicians, including the possible benefits and risks of PC screening through PSA testing, could make these erroneous behaviors less frequent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>Whereas GPs&#x2019; and subjects&#x2019; statements in EDIFICE appeared in rather good agreement with respect to the proportions of interviewed subjects having undergone cancer screening tests and of GPs recommending cancer screening to their patients, the reasons put forward why screening tests were not performed are different, indeed even opposite: based on their statements, GPs overestimated the negative impact of fear of the results on subjects&#x2019; participation in cancer screening and they underestimated their own role. Nevertheless, both GPs and subjects interestingly seem to attach a more dreadful meaning to the result of BC screening than to the result of CRC screening. Indeed, fear of the result acting as a check upon carrying out cancer screening tests was cited by 18% of the subjects for BC screening whereas only 3% cited this reason for not undergoing CRC screening tests. Comparatively, 44% and 16% of GPs cited fear of the result as the reason for subjects not undergoing BC and CRC screening tests, respectively.</p>
      <p>It thus appears that there is a need for more research in social science as well as in biology and public health to improve the effectiveness of cancer screening in the framework of a national health system.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>This research was supported by a grant from ROCHE S.A., Neuilly-sur-Seine, France.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Gotzsche PC, Nielsen M (2006) Screening for breast cancer with mammography. Cochrane Database Syst Rev CD001877</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pignone</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rich</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teutsch</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berg</surname>
              <given-names>AO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lohr</surname>
              <given-names>KN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Screening for colorectal cancer in adults at average risk: a summary of the evidence for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force</article-title>
          <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>132</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pignone M, Rich M, Teutsch SM, Berg AO, Lohr KN (2002) Screening for colorectal cancer in adults at average risk: a summary of the evidence for the U.S. Preventive Services Task Force. Ann Intern Med 137:132&#x2013;141 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12118972</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">U.S. Preventive Services Task Force (2006) The guide to Clinical Preventive Services 2006: Agency for Healthcare Research and Quality</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Institut National des Statistiques et des Etudes Economiques (INSEE) (2002) Enqu&#xEA;te emploi, Mars 2002. &#x201C;Soci&#xE9;t&#xE9;&#x201D; r&#xE9;sultats d&#xE9;taill&#xE9;s no. 5</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frankel</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donovan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neal</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Screening for prostate cancer</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>361</volume>
          <fpage>1122</fpage>
          <lpage>1128</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0140-6736(03)12890-5</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Frankel S, Smith GD, Donovan J, Neal D (2003) Screening for prostate cancer. Lancet 361:1122&#x2013;1128 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12672328</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haggerty</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tudiver</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herbert</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciampi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guibert</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Patients&#x2019; anxiety and expectations: how they influence family physicians&#x2019; decisions to order cancer screening tests</article-title>
          <source>Can Fam Physician</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1658</fpage>
          <lpage>1659</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Haggerty J, Tudiver F, Brown JB, Herbert C, Ciampi A, Guibert R (2005) Patients&#x2019; anxiety and expectations: how they influence family physicians&#x2019; decisions to order cancer screening tests. Can Fam Physician 51:1658&#x2013;1659 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16926946</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lamplugh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmore</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quinlan</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornford</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PSA testing: are patients aware of what lies ahead?</article-title>
          <source>Ann R Coll Surg Engl</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>284</fpage>
          <lpage>288</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1308/003588406X98685</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lamplugh M, Gilmore P, Quinlan T, Cornford P (2006) PSA testing: are patients aware of what lies ahead? Ann R Coll Surg Engl 88:284&#x2013;288 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16720000</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>