<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Childs Nerv Syst</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Child's Nervous System</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0256-7040</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1433-0350</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18236049</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2413122</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">578</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00381-007-0578-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Secondary meningioma in a long-term survivor of atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumour with a germline <italic>INI1</italic> mutation</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ammerlaan</surname>
            <given-names>A. C. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Houben</surname>
            <given-names>M. P. W. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tijssen</surname>
            <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wesseling</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hulsebos</surname>
            <given-names>T. J. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-20-5663024</phone>
            <fax>+31-20-5669312</fax>
            <email>t.j.hulsebos@amc.uva.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Neurogenetics, Academic Medical Center, Meibergdreef 9, 1105 AZ Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Neurology, St. Elisabeth Hospital, Tilburg, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, Nijmegen Center for Molecular Life Sciences, Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre, Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>31</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>24</volume>
      <issue>7</issue>
      <fpage>855</fpage>
      <lpage>857</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>We report on a patient who developed a meningioma more than two decades after removal at a young age of an atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumour (AT/RT), which was due to a germline <italic>INI1</italic> mutation, and radio- and chemotherapy.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Materials and methods</title>
          <p>We present genetic evidence that the meningioma is not a recurrence or metastasis of the AT/RT and not due to the <italic>INI1</italic> mutation, but is a radiation-induced tumour.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>This is the first case illustrating that improved survival of young patients with an AT/RT after aggressive treatment may be gained at the cost of an increased risk for the development of radiation-induced, non-<italic>INI1</italic>-related tumours.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Meningioma</kwd>
        <kwd>Radiation therapy</kwd>
        <kwd>Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumour</kwd>
        <kwd>Genetic predisposition</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>INI1</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>We previously reported on a family in which four cousins developed an atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumour (AT/RT) at young age, due to inheritance of a germline G&gt;A mutation in the donor splice site of exon 4 of the tumour suppressor gene <italic>INI1</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. More than 20&#xA0;years after resection of the AT/RT, the oldest of the four cousins developed an intracranial meningioma and, after an additional year, a myoepithelioma of the lip. In addition to the constitutional <italic>INI1</italic> mutation and loss of the normal <italic>INI1</italic> allele, we detected an identical rearrangement in the <italic>NF2</italic> gene, not affecting its coding regions, in the AT/RT and myoepithelioma of the patient and concluded that they both originated from a common precursor cell. However, the rearrangement in <italic>NF2</italic> and loss of the normal <italic>INI1</italic> allele could not be demonstrated in the meningioma. Despite this, the development of the meningioma may be the consequence of the presence of the constitutional <italic>INI1</italic> mutation, because mutations in this gene have been identified in meningiomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Alternatively, the meningioma could be induced by the radiation therapy, which our patient received after removal of the AT/RT and which is a well-known consequence of this treatment [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. We investigated the meningioma for the presence of genetic changes reported in radiation-induced meningiomas and performed a comparative loss of heterozygosity (LOH) analysis to demonstrate that such radiation-induced genetic changes are absent in the AT/RT and myoepithelioma of our patient.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Tumour samples and DNA isolation</title>
        <p>DNA from the AT/RT and the myoepithelioma was isolated from formalin-fixed and paraffin-embedded tumour material, and DNA from the meningioma was isolated from a fresh frozen tumour sample using commercially available kits (Qiagen, Venlo, The Netherlands).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>SNP analysis</title>
        <p>A genome-wide single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP) analysis of normal and meningioma DNA was conducted with the Affymetrix GeneChip Human Mapping 10K Array Xba 142 2.0. The array contains 10,204 SNPs distributed across the genome. The GeneChips were processed by an authorised Affymetrix Service Provider using standard Affymetrix protocols (Service XS, Leiden, The Netherlands). LOH regions were identified by comparing the SNP profiles of normal and meningioma DNA and scoring heterozygous SNP markers (AB) in the normal DNA that were reduced to homozygosity (AA or BB) in the meningioma DNA. Intervals were determined on the basis of locations of SNP markers in the UCSC Genome Browser, March 2006 Build, at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://genome.ucsc.edu/">http://genome.ucsc.edu/</ext-link>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>LOH analysis</title>
        <p>Loss of heterozygosity (LOH) analysis was performed with microsatellite markers as described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] using primer sequences and conditions for polymerase chain reaction given by The Genome Database at <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.gdb.org/">http://www.gdb.org/</ext-link>. Because of rather extensive degradation of DNA extracted from the AT/RT, only markers generating PCR fragments smaller than 150&#xA0;bp were used.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>History</title>
        <p>Our patient was diagnosed with a tumour in the fourth ventricle and right cerebellar hemisphere at the age of 4.5&#xA0;years. Resection of the tumour was incomplete. The tumour was originally classified as anaplastic ependymoma WHO grade III, but upon extensive genetic analysis and histopathological re-evaluation, reclassified as AT/RT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. He received adjuvant chemotherapy (methotrexate, vincristine and prednisolone) followed by craniospinal radiotherapy (3,300&#xA0;cGy in 22 doses) with a boost of 2,100&#xA0;cGy on the location of the tumour. Fifteen years later, a brain CT without contrast showed no signs of recurrent disease or of other new pathology. Almost 6&#xA0;years later, 20.5&#xA0;years after initial diagnosis, he presented again with bifrontal headaches, increasing ataxic gait disturbances and fatigue. CT examination showed a large isodens space-occupying lesion in the left temporal region with oedema, midline shift and contrast enhancement. One year after resection of this tumour, he developed a myoepithelioma of the upper lip. The patient is alive at 29&#xA0;years of age.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Histological findings</title>
        <p>Histopathological examination of the left temporal tumour revealed an atypical meningothelial meningioma WHO grade II with many vessels and up to six mitoses per 2&#xA0;mm<sup>2</sup>.</p>
        <p><bold>SNP and LOH analysis</bold> Radiation-induced meningiomas usually display a complex karyotype [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. To determine the genetic changes, we performed a genome-wide scan by SNP analysis of the meningioma and corresponding normal DNA. The identified chromosomal regions displaying LOH are listed in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Next, we tested several markers from within each of the five largest deleted regions by conventional microsatellite analysis to determine their LOH status in the meningioma and in the AT/RT and myoepithelioma. Presence of LOH in the meningioma, but absence of LOH in AT/RT and myoepithelioma was found for <italic>D1S199</italic> in 1pter-p34.3 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a), <italic>D2S327</italic> in 2pter-p12, <italic>D3S3727</italic> in 3p26.1-cen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b), <italic>D16S3020</italic> in 16pter-p12.1 and <italic>D17S1872</italic> in 17qcen-q21.31 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c). In contrast, as determined previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and exemplified by marker <italic>D22S430</italic> in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, there was LOH for chromosome 22 markers in the AT/RT and myoepithelioma, but not in the meningioma.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>LOH analysis using markers from chromosome regions <bold>a</bold> 1pter-p34.3 (<italic>D1S199</italic>), <bold>b</bold> 3p26.1-cen (<italic>D3S3727</italic>), <bold>c</bold> 17qcen-q21.31 (<italic>D17S1872</italic>) and <bold>d</bold> 22q (<italic>D22S430</italic>) of AT/RT (<italic>A</italic>), meningioma (<italic>M</italic>) and myoepithelioma (<italic>My</italic>) DNAs of the patient. <italic>N</italic> denotes normal DNA derived from the patient&#x2019;s blood leucocytes. <italic>Arrowhead</italic> indicates position of lost allele</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="381_2007_578_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>LOH regions in the meningioma, as determined by SNP analysis</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Chromosome region</th><th>Exact interval (Mb)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1pter-p34.3</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">0&#x2013;38.90</td></tr><tr><td>1p33-p33</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">46.99&#x2013;51.09</td></tr><tr><td>1p32.2-1p31.3</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">58.19&#x2013;65.50</td></tr><tr><td>2pter-p12</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">0&#x2013;79.28</td></tr><tr><td>3p26.1-cen</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">6.11&#x2013;88.84</td></tr><tr><td>7q36.1-qter</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">150.04&#x2013;158.66</td></tr><tr><td>16pter-p12.1</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">0&#x2013;22.75</td></tr><tr><td>16q23.1-q23.3</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">73.46&#x2013;81.33</td></tr><tr><td>17cen-q21.31</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">23.09&#x2013;40.35</td></tr><tr><td>19pter-p13.2</td><td char="&#x2013;" align="char">0&#x2013;8.83</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In a previous study, we provided evidence for the involvement of <italic>INI1</italic>, by constitutional mutation and independent somatic loss, in the development of both the AT/RT and the myoepithelioma of our patient. Moreover, we could demonstrate that these tumours originated from an identical precursor cell [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Although involvement of <italic>INI1</italic> has been described in sporadic meningiomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], until now meningiomas have not been reported to occur as a consequence of the inheritance of an <italic>INI1</italic> mutation. However, this might be due to the extreme rarity of families with an inherited <italic>INI1</italic> mutation, with only four published cases so far [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In this context, it is interesting to note that (as demonstrated before and exemplified by marker D22S430 in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d) the meningioma of our patient has no LOH 22 and the retained <italic>INI1</italic> allele carries no additional inactivating mutation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], indicating that this tumour is not the result of inheritance of the mutated <italic>INI1</italic> gene. In contrast, the meningioma displayed genetic changes that are characteristic for radiation-induced meningiomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>], such as a complex karyotype, as evidenced by the SNP analysis (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), including extensive losses on chromosome arm 1p, but no loss of chromosome 22, and no mutation in the <italic>NF2</italic> gene [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The genetic changes found in the meningioma proved not to be present in the AT/RT or myoepithelioma (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a&#x2013;c, and data not shown), demonstrating that the meningioma is genetically not related to these tumours and should not be considered as a late and more differentiated recurrence or metastasis of the AT/RT.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, the clinical and genetic characteristics of the meningioma clearly indicate that the tumour developed as a consequence of the radiation therapy. Recent evidence suggests that long-term survival of patients with a childhood AT/RT can occur especially after aggressive treatment including radiotherapy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. The possible late effects of radiation therapy have been considered as serious drawbacks of this treatment. This is the first case in literature in which such a possible consequence in the form of a radiation-induced meningioma is actually documented in a long-term survivor of an AT/RT. Compared to sporadic meningiomas, radiation-induced meningiomas are more aggressive and have a higher chance to recur [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Because of this unfavourable prognosis, continuous medical surveillance of our patient is warranted.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>We gratefully acknowledge the financial support from the Dutch Cancer Society, grants KUN 2003-2975 (PW) and UVA 2001-2561 (TH).</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mefty</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Topsakal</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pravdenkova</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sawyer</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiation-induced meningiomas: clinical, pathological, cytokinetic, and cytogenetic characteristics</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>1002</fpage>
          <lpage>1013</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Al Mefty O, Topsakal C, Pravdenkova S, Sawyer JR, Harrison MJ (2004) Radiation-induced meningiomas: clinical, pathological, cytokinetic, and cytogenetic characteristics. J Neurosurg 100:1002&#x2013;1013 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15200115</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Ammerlaan ACJ, Ararou A, Houben MPWA, Baas F, Tijssen CC, Teepen JLJM, Wesseling P, Hulsebos TJM (2007) Long-term survival and transmission of INI1-mutation via nonpenetrant males in a family with rhabdoid tumour predisposition syndrome. Br J Cancer, DOI 10.1038/sj.bjc.6604156</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bijlsma</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voesten</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bijleveld</surname>
              <given-names>EH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Troost</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westerveld</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merel</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hulsebos</surname>
              <given-names>TJM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular analysis of genetic changes in ependymomas</article-title>
          <source>Genes Chromosomes Cancer</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>272</fpage>
          <lpage>277</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/gcc.2870130407</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bijlsma EK, Voesten AM, Bijleveld EH, Troost D, Westerveld A, Merel P, Thomas G, Hulsebos TJM (1995) Molecular analysis of genetic changes in ependymomas. Genes Chromosomes Cancer 13:272&#x2013;277 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7547635</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolfe</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitnick</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sachdev</surname>
              <given-names>VP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiation-induced meningiomas: experience at the Mount Sinai Hospital and review of the literature</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosurg</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>564</fpage>
          <lpage>574</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Harrison MJ, Wolfe DE, Lau TS, Mitnick RJ, Sachdev VP (1991) Radiation-induced meningiomas: experience at the Mount Sinai Hospital and review of the literature. J Neurosurg 75:564&#x2013;574 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1885974</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hulsebos</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plomp</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolterman</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robanus-Maandag</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baas</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wesseling</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Germline mutation of INI1/SMARCB1 in familial schwannomatosis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>805</fpage>
          <lpage>810</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/513207</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hulsebos TJ, Plomp AS, Wolterman RA, Robanus-Maandag EC, Baas F, Wesseling P (2007) Germline mutation of INI1/SMARCB1 in familial schwannomatosis. Am J Hum Genet 80:805&#x2013;810 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17357086</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Janson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nedzi</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>David</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schorin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walsh</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bhattacharjee</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pridjian</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Judkins</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Biegel</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Predisposition to atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor due to an inherited INI1 mutation</article-title>
          <source>Pediatr Blood Cancer</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>279</fpage>
          <lpage>284</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/pbc.20622</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Janson K, Nedzi LA, David O, Schorin M, Walsh JW, Bhattacharjee M, Pridjian G, Tan L, Judkins AR, Biegel JA (2006) Predisposition to atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor due to an inherited INI1 mutation. Pediatr Blood Cancer 47:279&#x2013;284 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16261613</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ragel</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular genetics of meningiomas</article-title>
          <source>Neurosurg Focus</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>E9</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3171/foc.2005.19.5.10</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ragel BT, Jensen RL (2005) Molecular genetics of meningiomas. Neurosurg Focus 19:E9 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16398473</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmitz</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mueller</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sevenet</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Delattre</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deimling</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>INI1 mutations in meningiomas at a potential hotspot in exon 9</article-title>
          <source>Br J Cancer</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>199</fpage>
          <lpage>201</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/bjoc.2000.1583</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmitz U, Mueller W, Weber M, Sevenet N, Delattre O, von Deimling A (2001) INI1 mutations in meningiomas at a potential hotspot in exon 9. Br J Cancer 84:199&#x2013;201 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11161377</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shoshan</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chernova</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Juen</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Somerville</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Israel</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnett</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cowell</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Radiation-induced meningioma: a distinct molecular genetic pattern</article-title>
          <source>J Neuropathol Exp Neurol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>59</volume>
          <fpage>614</fpage>
          <lpage>620</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Shoshan Y, Chernova O, Juen SS, Somerville RP, Israel Z, Barnett GH, Cowell JK (2000) Radiation-induced meningioma: a distinct molecular genetic pattern. J Neuropathol Exp Neurol 59:614&#x2013;620 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10901233</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Squire</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chan</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marcus</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor: the controversy behind radiation therapy</article-title>
          <source>J Neurooncol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11060-006-9196-z</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Squire SE, Chan MD, Marcus KJ (2007) Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumor: the controversy behind radiation therapy. J Neurooncol 81:97&#x2013;111 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16855864</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gokgoz</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrulis</surname>
              <given-names>IL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mainprize</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drake</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rutka</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Familial posterior fossa brain tumors of infancy secondary to germline mutation of the hSNF5 gene</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>66</volume>
          <fpage>1403</fpage>
          <lpage>1406</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/302833</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Taylor MD, Gokgoz N, Andrulis IL, Mainprize TG, Drake JM, Rutka JT (2000) Familial posterior fossa brain tumors of infancy secondary to germline mutation of the hSNF5 gene. Am J Hum Genet 66:1403&#x2013;1406 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10739763</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tekautz</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fuller</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blaney</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fouladi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broniscer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Merchant</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krasin</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalton</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hale</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kun</surname>
              <given-names>LE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wallace</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilbertson</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gajjar</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (ATRT): improved survival in children 3&#xA0;years of age and older with radiation therapy and high-dose alkylator-based chemotherapy</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Oncol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1491</fpage>
          <lpage>1499</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1200/JCO.2005.05.187</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tekautz TM, Fuller CE, Blaney S, Fouladi M, Broniscer A, Merchant TE, Krasin M, Dalton J, Hale G, Kun LE, Wallace D, Gilbertson RJ, Gajjar A (2005) Atypical teratoid/rhabdoid tumors (ATRT): improved survival in children 3&#xA0;years of age and older with radiation therapy and high-dose alkylator-based chemotherapy. J Clin Oncol 23:1491&#x2013;1499 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15735125</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>