<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetologia</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Diabetologia</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0012-186X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-0428</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18317720</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2292425</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">970</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-008-0970-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Short Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Association analysis of the <italic>IGF1</italic> gene with childhood growth, IGF-1 concentrations and type 1 diabetes</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vella</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bouatia-Naji</surname>
            <given-names>N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Heude</surname>
            <given-names>B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff5">5</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Cooper</surname>
            <given-names>J. D.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lowe</surname>
            <given-names>C. E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Petry</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ring</surname>
            <given-names>S. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff7">7</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Dunger</surname>
            <given-names>D. B.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Todd</surname>
            <given-names>J. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ong</surname>
            <given-names>K. K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ken.ong@mrc-epid.cam.ac.uk</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff6">6</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Juvenile Diabetes Research Foundation/Wellcome Trust Diabetes and Inflammation Laboratory, Department of Medical Genetics, Cambridge Institute for Medical Research, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Mayo Clinic, Rochester, MN USA </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>MRC Epidemiology Unit, Institute of Metabolic Science, Addenbrooke&#x2019;s Hospital P.O. Box 285, Cambridge, CB2 0QQ UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>INSERM Unit 780, IFR69, Villejuif, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff5"><label>5</label>Faculty of Medicine, University Paris-Sud, Orsay, France </aff>
        <aff id="Aff6"><label>6</label>Department of Paediatrics, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff7"><label>7</label>Department of Community-Based Medicine, University of Bristol, Bristol, UK </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>4</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>51</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>811</fpage>
      <lpage>815</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>2</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Aims/hypothesis</title>
          <p>Insulin-like growth factor-1 is a major childhood growth factor and promotes pancreatic islet cell survival and growth in vitro. We hypothesised that genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> might be associated with childhood growth, glucose metabolism and type 1 diabetes risk. We therefore examined the association between common genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> and predisposition to type 1 diabetes, childhood growth and metabolism.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Materials and methods</title>
          <p>Variants in <italic>IGF1</italic> were identified by direct resequencing of the exons, exon&#x2013;intron boundaries and 5&#x2032; and 3&#x2032; regions in 32 unrelated type 1 diabetes patients. A tagging subset of these variants was genotyped in a collection of type 1 diabetes families (3,121 parent&#x2013;child trios). We also genotyped a previously reported CA repeat in the region 5&#x2032; to <italic>IGF1</italic>. A subset of seven tag single nucleotide polymorphism (SNPs) that captured variants with minor allele frequency (MAF) &#x2265;0.05 was genotyped in 902 children from the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents And Children with data on growth, IGF-1 concentrations, insulin secretion and insulin action.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Resequencing detected 27 SNPs in <italic>IGF1</italic>, of which 11 had a MAF&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05 and were novel. Variants with MAF&#x2009;&#x2265;&#x2009;0.10 were captured by a set of four tag-SNPs. These SNPs showed no association with type 1 diabetes. In children, global variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> was weakly associated with IGF-1 concentrations, but not with other phenotypes. The CA repeat in the region 5&#x2032; to <italic>IGF1</italic> showed no association with any phenotype.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/interpretation</title>
          <p>Common genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> alters IGF-1 concentrations but is not associated with growth, glucose metabolism or type 1 diabetes.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00125-008-0970-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorised users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Children</kwd>
        <kwd>Genetic variation</kwd>
        <kwd>Growth</kwd>
        <kwd>IGF-1</kwd>
        <kwd>Insulin-like growth factor-1</kwd>
        <kwd>Microsatellite</kwd>
        <kwd>Single nucleotide polymorphism</kwd>
        <kwd>SNP</kwd>
        <kwd>Tag-SNPs</kwd>
        <kwd>Type 1 diabetes</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Type 1 diabetes is a common autoimmune disorder that arises by an interaction between genes and the environment. To date, ten loci have been identified including the HLA class II genes, the cytotoxic T-lymphocyte associated protein 4 (<italic>CTLA4</italic>) locus, protein tyrosine phosphatase, non-receptor type 22 (lymphoid) (<italic>PTPN22</italic>), IL-2 receptor, alpha (<italic>IL2RA</italic>), interferon induced with helicase C domain 1 (<italic>IFIH1</italic>) and four novel loci identified by a genome-wide association study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>The protein products of these genes play important roles in antigen presentation and the cellular immune response, highlighting the importance of the immune system in the pathogenesis of type 1 diabetes. However, not all patients with evidence of islet autoimmunity develop complete beta cell failure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Given the evidence to suggest that early weight gain and growth in childhood are associated with type 1 diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], it is possible that factors influencing insulin action (body weight and fat mass) and islet function may predispose to or influence the presentation of type 1 diabetes.</p>
      <p>Lower IGF-1 concentrations predict the development of glucose intolerance in adults [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. George et al. reported that islet overexpression of <italic>IGF1</italic> in diabetic mice enabled islet regeneration and gradual correction of hyperglycaemia and hypoinsulinaemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. A microsatellite in the region 5&#x2032; to <italic>IGF1</italic> has been associated with adult height, cardiovascular risk, osteoporosis and type 2 diabetes in some [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] but not all [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] studies.</p>
      <p>Since common variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> could alter circulating IGF-1 concentrations and therefore body habitus, insulin action and beta cell secretion, we sought to determine the associations, if any, between <italic>IGF1</italic> and circulating IGF-1 concentrations, size at birth, both fasting and postprandial insulin concentrations, and type 1 diabetes.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Polymorphism identification</title>
        <p>DNA samples from 32 randomly selected type 1 diabetic probands were amplified using specifically designed forward and reverse primers. This provided 88% probability of detecting single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) with minor allele frequencies (MAF) of 0.033, 96% probability for MAF 0.05 and 99.8% for MAF 0.10 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Resequencing included the 3&#xA0;kb region 5&#x2032; to the gene, all exons and exon&#x2013;intron boundaries and 3&#x2032; untranslated region. Four 1&#xA0;kb segments in the second intron, ~10&#xA0;kb intervals apart, were also resequenced.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Tag-SNP selection</title>
        <p>The resequencing genotype data were used to select SNP subsets that predicted the genotypes of the remainder, using a coefficient of determination, <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>, which measures the ability to predict each known SNP genotype by linear regression on the tag-SNP genotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. We considered only SNPs with a MAF&#x2009;&#x2265;&#x2009;0.10 in the type 1 diabetes collection and &#x2265;0.05 in the Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents And Children (ALSPAC) cohort (for details see below and Electronic supplementary material [<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM6">ESM</xref>]), using a minimum <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> of 0.8.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Genotyping</title>
        <p>All genotyping data were double-scored to minimise error. All genotypes were in Hardy&#x2013;Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Populations studied</title>
      <p>All DNA samples were collected after ethics approval and informed consent had been obtained.</p>
      <p><bold>Type 1 diabetes family collection</bold> Type 1 diabetes families were of white European descent, with two parents and at least one affected child. The populations studied have been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
      <p><bold>ALSPAC</bold> Details of this birth cohort are available on the ALSPAC website (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.alspac.bris.ac.uk">www.alspac.bris.ac.uk</ext-link>). The children in this study are from a 10% &#x2018;Children in Focus&#x2019; sub-cohort (1,335 full-term singleton infants) randomly selected from the last 6&#xA0;months of recruitment for more detailed measurements of growth. Birthweight was noted from hospital records, and length and head circumference were measured after birth. At age 7&#xA0;years (mean age 7.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.1&#xA0;years), body weight and height were measured. Body composition was assessed at age 9&#xA0;years by whole-body dual-energy X-ray absorptiometry. Internal SD scores were calculated for all parameters of growth to adjust for age and sex. IGF-1 concentrations were measured in cord blood samples (birth) and in venous blood (7 or 8&#xA0;years of age). Fasting insulin sensitivity was assessed by the homeostatic model assessment index (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.dtu.ox.ac.uk/homa/">www.dtu.ox.ac.uk/homa/</ext-link>) and insulin secretion at 30&#xA0;min post oral glucose by the insulinogenic index at age 8&#xA0;years.</p>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All statistical analyses to test the association between <italic>IGF1</italic> and type 1 diabetes were performed in either Stata (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.stata.com/">www.stata.com/</ext-link>) or R (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.r-project.org/">www.r-project.org/</ext-link>) statistical systems. Additional routines may be downloaded (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www-gene.cimr.cam.ac.uk/clayton/software/">www-gene.cimr.cam.ac.uk/clayton/software/</ext-link>). Missing tag-SNP genotypes were imputed under the null hypothesis and were analysed using a multilocus test [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The microsatellite, 5&#x2032; <italic>IGF1</italic> CA repeat, was analysed using TRANSMIT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. The global effect of the <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNP set on each outcome variable was entered into a multi-locus regression model. <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> change was taken as the contribution to the total variation in each outcome. Associations of <italic>IGF1</italic> SNPs with growth and metabolic phenotypes were analysed using univariate ANOVA (general linear models). The association of the 5&#x2032; <italic>IGF1</italic> CA repeat was analysed by comparing the wild-type allele (192&#xA0;bp) to all other alleles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
        <p>For further details on <xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref> section, see ESM.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic></title>
        <p>Resequencing identified 27 novel polymorphisms consisting of 24 SNPs, one rare non-synonymous SNP in exon 3 (Ala to Thr) and two deletion/insertion polymorphisms. Eleven SNPs had a MAF&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05. Four tag-SNPs (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) were selected and genotyped in the type 1 diabetes families studied. In ALSPAC, seven tag-SNPs were selected (ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM1">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>A summary of <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNPs genotyped in 2,396 families</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Parameter</th><th colspan="4">Tag-SNP</th></tr><tr><th>rs35140968<sup>a</sup></th><th>rs6214</th><th>rs3730220</th><th>s6219</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Sequence</td><td>AAATAACT[-/AT]CTCAAATA</td><td>GACTTAAC[A/G]TGTTTTCT</td><td>CAGGTTGG[A/T]CTCAAACT</td><td>AACCTCAA[A/G]CTGTCTAC</td></tr><tr><td>Allele coding, 1 (minor)/2</td><td>Ins/Del</td><td>A/G</td><td>T/A</td><td>A/G</td></tr><tr><td>MAF in parents</td><td>0.277</td><td>0.443</td><td>0.493</td><td>0.0769</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Minor allele transmissions</td></tr><tr><td>Transmitted</td><td>815</td><td>1309</td><td>915</td><td>446</td></tr><tr><td>Untransmitted<sup>b</sup></td><td>790</td><td>1386</td><td>942</td><td>446</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Genotype 2/2</td></tr><tr><td>Transmitted</td><td>1,150 (53.1)</td><td>947 (33.3)</td><td>798 (33.0)</td><td>2,501 (84.8)</td></tr><tr><td>Untransmitted<sup>b</sup></td><td>3,478 (53.6)</td><td>2,724 (31.9)</td><td>2,352 (32.4</td><td>7,489 (84.6)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Genotype 2/1</td></tr><tr><td>Transmitted</td><td>849 (39.2)</td><td>1,382 (48.5)</td><td>885 (36.6)</td><td>423 (14.3)</td></tr><tr><td>Untransmitted<sup>b</sup></td><td>2,541 (39.1)</td><td>4,226 (49.5)</td><td>2,685 (37.0)</td><td>1,297 (14.7)</td></tr><tr><td colspan="5">Genotype 1/1</td></tr><tr><td>Transmitted</td><td>166 (7.7)</td><td>519 (18.2)</td><td>737 (30.5)</td><td>27 (0.91)</td></tr><tr><td>Untransmitted<sup>b</sup></td><td>476 (7.3)</td><td>1,594 (18.7)</td><td>2,223 (30.6)</td><td>67 (0.8)</td></tr><tr><td>OR for minor allele (95% CI)</td><td>1.03 (0.93&#x2013;1.14)</td><td>0.94 (0.87&#x2013;1.01)</td><td>0.97 (0.89&#x2013;1.06)</td><td>1.00 (0.88&#x2013;1.14)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Deletion/insertion polymorphism</p><p><sup>b</sup>Untransmitted (pseudocontrol) genotypes are estimated as previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]</p><p>Multilocus test <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.425</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title><italic>IGF1</italic> and type 1 diabetes</title>
        <p>The selected tag-SNPs were genotyped in 2,439 families (3,121 parent&#x2013;child trios). The multilocus test of the <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNPs provided no evidence of an association with type 1 diabetes (<italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sub>4</sub><sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.4; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.356; Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The microsatellite, 5&#x2032; <italic>IGF1</italic> CA repeat, was genotyped in 2,109 families and analysed using TRANSMIT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. There was no evidence of association (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.358) (ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM2">2</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium data</title>
        <p>We used data from the Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (WTCCC) genome-wide association study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] to test association of the extended <italic>IGF1</italic> region with type 1 diabetes. The region contained 22 SNPs. When the WTCCC data were analysed using a logistic regression model adjusted for variation in allele frequencies across Great Britain, no evidence of association of these SNPs within the region was found (ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM3">3</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Association with IGF-1 concentrations</title>
        <p>In the ALSPAC children, multilocus regression models showed that the <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNP set was associated with IGF-1 protein levels at birth (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.063; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.029) and weakly associated at age 7 to 8&#xA0;years (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.030; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.055; ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM4">4</xref>). Results of IGF-1 protein level associations with individual SNPs are shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. However, the multilocus <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNP set did not associate with any other childhood growth or metabolic phenotype (ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM4">4</xref>). No associations were observed between the <italic>IGF1</italic> CA repeat and IGF-1 concentrations or any growth or metabolic phenotype (ESM Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="" rid="MOESM5">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>IGF-1 protein levels (ng/ml) at birth and at age 7 or 8&#xA0;years by genotypes of seven <italic>IGF1</italic> tag-SNPs in a representative birth cohort</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Parameter</th><th><italic>n</italic></th><th colspan="3">Genotype (%)</th><th><italic>p</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>rs35140968</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>I/D (58)</td><td>I/I (35)</td><td>D/D (7)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;At birth</td><td>315</td><td>88.1 (2.8)</td><td>91.1 (3.6)</td><td>105.0 (8.9)</td><td>0.179</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>547</td><td>147.8 (2.9)</td><td>147.3 (3.9)</td><td>157.4 (9.1)</td><td>0.581</td></tr><tr><td>rs6214</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>G/G (34)</td><td>G/A (50)</td><td>A/A (16)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;At birth</td><td>305</td><td>88.6 (3.6)</td><td>87.7 (3.2)</td><td>102.43 (5.30)</td><td>0.048</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>556</td><td>144.1 (4.0)</td><td>148.9 (3.1)</td><td>155.83 (5.70)</td><td>0.239</td></tr><tr><td>rs3730220</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>A/A (38)</td><td>A/T (54)</td><td>T/T (9)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Birth</td><td>299</td><td>94.1 (3.8)</td><td>88.6 (2.9)</td><td>89.6 (7.4)</td><td>0.509</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>548</td><td>152.0 (3.8)</td><td>145.7 (3.0)</td><td>141.8 (8.1)</td><td>0.331</td></tr><tr><td>rs6219</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>G/G (84)</td><td colspan="2">*/A (16)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Birth</td><td>300</td><td>91.0 (2.4)</td><td colspan="2">85.0 (5.7)</td><td>0.329</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>547</td><td>150.1 (2.5)</td><td colspan="2">138.8 (5.8)</td><td>0.072</td></tr><tr><td>rs2946831</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>T/T (89)</td><td colspan="2">*/G (11)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Birth</td><td>294</td><td>90.0 (2.3)</td><td colspan="2">95.2 (7.2)</td><td>0.501</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>541</td><td>148.0 (2.4)</td><td colspan="2">153.9 (7.1)</td><td>0.432</td></tr><tr><td>rs3730204</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>T/T (97)</td><td colspan="2">*/C (3)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Birth</td><td>294</td><td>111.3 (13.5)</td><td colspan="2">90.3 (2.3)</td><td>0.126</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>548</td><td>173.8 (12.9)</td><td colspan="2">147.5 (2.3)</td><td>0.046</td></tr><tr><td>rs12579108</td><td>&#xA0;</td><td>C/C (97)</td><td colspan="2">*/A (3)</td><td>&#xA0;</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Birth</td><td>301</td><td>90.0 (2.2)</td><td colspan="2">101.4 (12.1)</td><td>0.358</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;7 or 8&#xA0;years</td><td>554</td><td>147.6 (2.3)</td><td colspan="2">176.8 (15.9)</td><td>0.017</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Values are mean (SE) for IGF-1 concentration and per cent for genotype</p><p>*Additive models, adjusted for age and sex</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We used a UK birth cohort, ALSPAC, and a large family collection of type 1 diabetes to explore association with a subset of SNPs generated by in-depth resequencing of the <italic>IGF1</italic> locus. A subset of SNPs that effectively predicted the genotype of the remainder was subsequently genotyped in these cohorts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. We report no evidence to support the hypothesis that genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> is associated with major susceptibility to type 1 diabetes. However, genetic variation in this locus may modestly influence circulating IGF-1 concentrations, at least at birth and during childhood.</p>
      <p>Prior studies examining the role of genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> in predisposition to common human disease have focused on a microsatellite in the region 5&#x2032; to <italic>IGF1</italic>. This variant has been inconsistently associated with adult height and type 2 diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Perplexingly, the same allele has been associated with high [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] and low [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] IGF-1 concentrations. It is possible that other common genetic variants, in different degrees of linkage disequilibrium with this variant, alter IGF-1 concentrations and explain the discrepancy in the published studies.</p>
      <p>We found no association between this microsatellite and circulating IGF-1 concentrations, growth or type 1 diabetes. To exclude the possibility that other polymorphisms in the gene predispose to disease, we undertook a systematic analysis of <italic>IGF1</italic> gene variation using tagging SNPs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Our relatively large white type 1 diabetes family collection of European ancestry provided ~84% power to detect a causal allele for type 1 diabetes predisposition with MAF&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.1 and OR of 1.2 at the 5% significance level. The study was therefore adequately powered to detect weak predisposition to type 1 diabetes conferred by <italic>IGF1</italic>. We did not directly examine whether these variants alter the age at diagnosis of type 1 diabetes, since there was no primary evidence of association.</p>
      <p>The possibility remains that variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> could alter insulin secretion or action as well as childhood growth. Therefore, to examine these associations, we adopted the same strategy in an established birth cohort. While we demonstrate that common genetic variation in <italic>IGF1</italic> modestly influences circulating IGF-1 concentrations at birth and during childhood, we did not find a major contribution of <italic>IGF1</italic> to birthweight, growth or response to oral glucose. It remains possible that maternal <italic>IGF1</italic> genotypes that influence maternal metabolism might alter birth size, but they are unlikely to significantly impact on childhood growth.</p>
      <p>In summary, this large systematic study shows that common <italic>IGF1</italic> variants modestly influence circulating IGF-1 concentrations at birth and during childhood. However, these variants are not associated with birthweight, childhood growth and insulin secretion or action. Moreover they do not alter type 1 diabetes risk.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="N0x19d1250N0x2f22640" content-type="local-data">
        <p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material.
</p>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM1_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;1</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic>IGF1</italic> SNPs genotyped in ALSPAC children (PDF 16.2 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM2_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM2" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>TRANSMIT analysis for association of the microsatellite in the 5&#x2032; region of <italic>IGF1</italic> with type 1 diabetes (PDF 62.5 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM3_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM3" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Summary of 23 WTCCC SNPs in the extended <italic>IGF1</italic> region (PDF 28.6 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM4_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM4" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;4</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Multilocus test for associations with IGF-1 protein levels, childhood growth and glucose metabolism in a representative birth cohort (PDF 17.1 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM5_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM5" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;5</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Association testing for the 5&#x2032; <italic>IGF1</italic> CA repeat with childhood growth and glucose metabolism in a representative birth cohort (PDF 72.3 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2008_970_MOESM6_ESM.pdf" id="MOESM6" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="pdf">
          <label>ESM Table&#xA0;6</label>
          <caption>
            <p>ESM Text (PDF 81.3 KB)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We gratefully acknowledge the participation of all of the type 1 diabetic patients and family members. We also thank the Human Biological Data Interchange and Diabetes UK for USA and UK multiplex families, respectively, as well as C. Ionescu-Tirgoviste and C. Guja for the Romanian families, D. Undlien for the Norwegian families and D. Savage for the Northern Ireland families. Thanks also to GET1FIN (J. Tuomilehto, L. Kinnunen, E. Tuomilehto-Wolf, V. Harjutsalo and T. Valle) for the Finnish families and to the Academy of Finland, the Sigrid Juselius Foundation and the JDRF for funding. We are extremely grateful to all the families who took part in the ALSPAC study, the midwives for their help in recruiting them and the whole ALSPAC team, which includes interviewers, computer and laboratory technicians, clerical workers, research scientists, volunteers, managers, receptionists and nurses. The UK Medical Research Council, the Wellcome Trust and the University of Bristol provide core support for ALSPAC. We thank H. Rance, T. Hassanali, J. Hutchings, G. Coleman, S. Field, T. Mistry, K. Bourget, S. Clayton, M. Hardy, J. Keylock, P. Lauder, M. Maisuria, W. Meadows, M. Sebastian and S. Wood for preparing DNA samples. This study makes use of data generated by the WTCCC. A full list of the investigators who contributed to the generation of those data is available from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.wtccc.org.uk">www.wtccc.org.uk</ext-link>. Funding for the project was provided by the Wellcome Trust under award 076113. A. Vella is supported by the Mayo Clinic and by the National Institutes of Health DK078646-01. B. Heude was funded by the Danone Institute.</p>
      <p><bold>Duality of interest</bold> The authors declare that there is no duality of interest associated with this manuscript.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Todd</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walker</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Robust associations of four new chromosome regions from genome-wide analyses of type 1 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Nat Genet</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>857</fpage>
          <lpage>864</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ng2068</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Todd JA, Walker NM, Cooper JD et al (2007) Robust associations of four new chromosome regions from genome-wide analyses of type 1 diabetes. Nat Genet 39:857&#x2013;864 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17554260</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borg</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gottsater</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernlund</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sundkvist</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A 12-year prospective study of the relationship between islet antibodies and beta-cell function at and after the diagnosis in patients with adult-onset diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>1754</fpage>
          <lpage>1762</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.51.6.1754</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Borg H, Gottsater A, Fernlund P, Sundkvist G (2002) A 12-year prospective study of the relationship between islet antibodies and beta-cell function at and after the diagnosis in patients with adult-onset diabetes. Diabetes 51:1754&#x2013;1762 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12031962</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johansson</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Samuelsson</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ludvigsson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A high weight gain early in life is associated with an increased risk of type 1 (insulin-dependent) diabetes mellitus</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>94</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00428783</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Johansson C, Samuelsson U, Ludvigsson J (1994) A high weight gain early in life is associated with an increased risk of type 1 (insulin-dependent) diabetes mellitus. Diabetologia 37:91&#x2013;94 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8150235</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yakar</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setser</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rosen</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of circulating IGF-I: lessons from human and animal models</article-title>
          <source>Endocrine</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>248</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1385/ENDO:19:3:239</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yakar S, Wu Y, Setser J, Rosen CJ (2002) The role of circulating IGF-I: lessons from human and animal models. Endocrine 19:239&#x2013;248 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12624423</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>George</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ayuso</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Casellas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Costa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Devedjian</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bosch</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beta cell expression of IGF-I leads to recovery from type 1 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>1153</fpage>
          <lpage>1163</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">George M, Ayuso E, Casellas A, Costa C, Devedjian JC, Bosch F (2002) Beta cell expression of IGF-I leads to recovery from type 1 diabetes. J Clin Invest 109:1153&#x2013;1163 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11994404</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vaessen</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heutink</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janssen</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A polymorphism in the gene for IGF-I: functional properties and risk for type 2 diabetes and myocardial infarction</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>637</fpage>
          <lpage>642</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.50.3.637</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vaessen N, Heutink P, Janssen JA et al (2001) A polymorphism in the gene for IGF-I: functional properties and risk for type 2 diabetes and myocardial infarction. Diabetes 50:637&#x2013;642 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11246885</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Frayling</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hattersley</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ben-Shlomo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conflicting results on variation in the IGFI gene highlight methodological considerations in the design of genetic association studies</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1605</fpage>
          <lpage>1606</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-002-0951-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Frayling TM, Hattersley AT, Smith GD, Ben-Shlomo Y (2002) Conflicting results on variation in the IGFI gene highlight methodological considerations in the design of genetic association studies. Diabetologia 45:1605&#x2013;1606 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12498159</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vella</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Howson</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barratt</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lack of association of the Ala(45)Thr polymorphism and other common variants of the NeuroD gene with type 1 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1158</fpage>
          <lpage>1161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.53.4.1158</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vella A, Howson JM, Barratt BJ et al (2004) Lack of association of the Ala(45)Thr polymorphism and other common variants of the NeuroD gene with type 1 diabetes. Diabetes 53:1158&#x2013;1161 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15047635</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vella</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowe</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Localization of a type 1 diabetes locus in the IL2RA/CD25 region by use of tag single-nucleotide polymorphisms</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>773</fpage>
          <lpage>779</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/429843</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vella A, Cooper JD, Lowe CE et al (2005) Localization of a type 1 diabetes locus in the IL2RA/CD25 region by use of tag single-nucleotide polymorphisms. Am J Hum Genet 76:773&#x2013;779 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15776395</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Clayton</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A generalization of the transmission/disequilibrium test for uncertain-haplotype transmission</article-title>
          <source>Am J Hum Genet</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>1170</fpage>
          <lpage>1177</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/302577</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Clayton D (1999) A generalization of the transmission/disequilibrium test for uncertain-haplotype transmission. Am J Hum Genet 65:1170&#x2013;1177 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10486336</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>ALSPAC</term>
          <def>
            <p>Avon Longitudinal Study of Parents And Children</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>MAF</term>
          <def>
            <p>minor allele frequency</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SNP</term>
          <def>
            <p>single nucleotide polymorphism</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>WTCCC</term>
          <def>
            <p>Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>A. Vella and N. Bouatia-Naji contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The online version of this article (doi:10.1007/s00125-008-0970-7) contains supplementary material, which is available to authorised users.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>