<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Diabetologia</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Diabetologia</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0012-186X</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-0428</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17216283</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1794135</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">534</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0534-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Adiponectin receptor genes: mutation screening in syndromes of insulin resistance and association studies for type 2 diabetes and metabolic traits in UK populations</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Collins</surname>
            <given-names>S. C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Luan</surname>
            <given-names>J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thompson</surname>
            <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Daly</surname>
            <given-names>A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Semple</surname>
            <given-names>R. K.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>O&#x2019;Rahilly</surname>
            <given-names>S.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wareham</surname>
            <given-names>N. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Barroso</surname>
            <given-names>I.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ib1@sanger.ac.uk</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Metabolic Disease Group, The Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, The Wellcome Trust Genome Campus, Hinxton, Cambridgeshire, CB10 1SA UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>MRC Epidemiology Unit, Elsie Widdowson Laboratory, Fulbourn Road, Cambridge, UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Clinical Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Medicine, University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>50</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>555</fpage>
      <lpage>562</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Aims/hypothesis</title>
          <p>Adiponectin is an adipokine with insulin-sensitising and anti-atherogenic properties. Several reports suggest that genetic variants in the adiponectin gene are associated with circulating levels of adiponectin, insulin sensitivity and type 2 diabetes risk. Recently two receptors for adiponectin have been cloned. Genetic studies have yielded conflicting results on the role of these genes and type 2 diabetes predisposition. In this study we aimed to evaluate the potential role of genetic variation in these genes in syndromes of severe insulin resistance, type 2 diabetes and in related metabolic traits in UK Europid populations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Materials and methods</title>
          <p>Exons and splice junctions of the adiponectin receptor 1 and 2 genes (<italic>ADIPOR1</italic>; <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>) were sequenced in patients from our severe insulin resistance cohort (<italic>n</italic>=129). Subsequently, 24 polymorphisms were tested for association with type 2 diabetes in population-based type 2 diabetes case&#x2013;control studies (<italic>n</italic>=2,127) and with quantitative traits in a population-based longitudinal study (<italic>n</italic>=1,721).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>No missense or nonsense mutations in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> were detected in the cohort of patients with severe insulin resistance. None of the 24 polymorphisms (allele frequency 2.3&#x2013;48.3%) tested was associated with type 2 diabetes in the case&#x2013;control study. Similarly, none of the polymorphisms was associated with fasting plasma insulin, fasting and 2-h post-load plasma glucose, 30-min insulin increment or BMI.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions/interpretation</title>
          <p>Genetic variation in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> is not a major cause of extreme insulin resistance in humans, nor does it contribute in a significant manner to type 2 diabetes risk and related traits in UK Europid populations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
          <p>The online version of this article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-006-0534-7">doi:10.1007/s00125-006-0534-7</ext-link>) contains supplementary material, which is accessible to authorised users.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>
          <italic>ADIPOR1</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>
        </kwd>
        <kwd>Association studies</kwd>
        <kwd>Insulin resistance</kwd>
        <kwd>Polymorphisms</kwd>
        <kwd>Type 2 diabetes</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Adiponectin, encoded by the gene <italic>ADIPOQ</italic> (also known as 30-kDa adipocyte complement-related protein, Acrp30, APM-1, APM1, ACDC, and gelatin-binding protein-28 or GBP28), is an adipokine with insulin-sensitising [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and anti-atherogenic actions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Its levels correlate strongly with insulin sensitivity in humans and animal models, and increasing levels of plasma adiponectin produce a sensitising effect to the biological action of insulin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Several genetic reports have detected association between adiponectin gene variants and obesity, insulin resistance, type 2 diabetes, and adiponectin levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Recently, two adiponectin receptors were identified, adiponectin receptor 1 (<italic>ADIPOR1</italic>), cloned from a human skeletal muscle expression library, and adiponectin receptor 2 (<italic>ADIPOR2</italic>), identified using computational tools by Yamauchi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In mice, <italic>Adipor1</italic> is expressed ubiquitously, with higher levels in skeletal muscle, and has a higher affinity for the globular form of adiponectin. <italic>Adipor2</italic>, on the other hand, is most abundant in the liver and preferentially binds the full-length form of adiponectin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. In contrast, both human <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> (375aa) and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> (311aa) were predominantly expressed in skeletal muscle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>].</p>
      <p>In Mexican Americans, glucose-tolerant individuals with a family history of type 2 diabetes were reported to exhibit significantly lower levels of mRNA for <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> in skeletal muscle than subjects without a family history of diabetes. mRNA levels of both receptors were also reported to positively correlate with glucose disposal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. It is possible therefore that lower expression or altered function of the receptors would predispose to increased insulin resistance and type 2 diabetes. In fact, common variants in the <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> gene were recently tested for association in a case&#x2013;control study with white and African American individuals, but no association was reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Two additional studies have evaluated the role of adiponectin receptor variants and risk of type 2 diabetes. In the Old Order Amish population, two intronic variants in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> were reported to associate with risk of type 2 diabetes, while in <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> an extended haplotype block was associated with increased risk of disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In contrast, in a Japanese population no associations between polymorphisms in adiponectin receptor genes and risk of type 2 diabetes were detected [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. More recently, studies in French and Finnish populations reported no association between <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) and type 2 diabetes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], although evidence for association between rs767870 in <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> and type 2 diabetes in a French population has been suggested [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. In light of these studies, and the potential role of these receptors in insulin action and diabetes, we sought to identify and investigate the effects of genetic variants in these genes in UK populations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Subjects and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Participants</title>
        <p><bold>Severe insulin resistance cohort</bold> A cohort of human patients with severe insulin resistance (SIR cohort) was collected at the University of Cambridge, UK. The inclusion criteria for this cohort were: (1) fasting insulin &gt;150&#xA0;pmol/l or exogenous insulin requirement &gt;200&#xA0;U/day; (2) acanthosis nigricans; and (3) BMI &lt;33&#xA0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>. In the present study, 129 patients from this cohort were screened for mutations in exons and splice junctions of <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> genes. Cambridge Local Research Ethics Committee approval was obtained, and informed consent was received from all individuals before participation.</p>
        <p><bold>Cambridgeshire Case&#x2013;Control Study</bold> The Cambridgeshire Case&#x2013;Control Study has been described previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Briefly, this population-based case&#x2013;control study consists of 552 type 2 diabetes patients and matched control subjects. DNA was available from 516 cases and control subjects for this study. The cases were a random sample of Europid men and women with type 2 diabetes, aged 47 to 75&#xA0;years, from a population-based diabetes register in a geographically defined region in Cambridgeshire, UK. The presence of type 2 diabetes in these participants was defined as onset of diabetes after the age of 30&#xA0;years without use of insulin therapy in the first year after diagnosis. The control participants were individually matched to each of the diabetic subjects by age, sex and geographical location, but not by BMI. Potential control subjects with HbA<sub>1c</sub> levels greater than 6% were excluded, as this subgroup could have contained a higher proportion of individuals with previously undiagnosed diabetes. Ethical approval for the study was granted by the Cambridge Local Research Ethics Committee.</p>
        <p><bold>EPIC-Norfolk participants</bold> This is a nested case&#x2013;control study within the EPIC-Norfolk prospective cohort study; both the case&#x2013;control and full cohort study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] have been described in detail previously. Briefly, the case&#x2013;control study consists of 417 incident type 2 diabetes cases and two sets of 417 control subjects, matched on age, sex, time in study and family physician, with the second set additionally matched for BMI. A case was defined by a physician&#x2019;s diagnosis of type 2 diabetes, with no insulin prescribed within the first year after diagnosis, and/or HbA<sub>1c</sub> &gt;7% at baseline or the follow-up health check. Controls were selected from those in the cohort who had not reported diabetes, cancer, stroke or myocardial infarction at baseline, and who had not developed diabetes by the time of selection. Potential control subjects with measured HbA<sub>1c</sub> levels &gt;6% were excluded. DNA was available for this analysis from 354 cases and 741 control subjects. Ethical approval for the study was granted by the Norwich Local Research Ethics Committee.</p>
        <p><bold>Ely Study</bold> This is a population-based cohort study of the aetiology and pathogenesis of type 2 diabetes and related metabolic disorders in the UK [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. It uses an ethnically homogeneous Europid population, in which phenotypic data were recorded at the outset and after 4.5&#xA0;years. The cohort was recruited from a population sampling frame with a high response rate (74%), making it representative of the general population for this area in Eastern England. This analysis included 1,721 men and women, aged 35&#x2013;79&#xA0;years and without diagnosed diabetes, who attended the study clinic for a health check between 2000 and 2004. Of these, 1,005 were attending a follow-up health check, while the remaining 716 were newly recruited in 2000 from the original population sampling frame. Participants attending the health check underwent standard anthropometric measurements and a 75-g oral glucose tolerance test. Plasma glucose was measured using the hexokinase method. Plasma insulin was measured by two-site immunometric assays with either <sup>125</sup>I or alkaline phosphatase labels. Cross-reactivity with intact proinsulin was less than 0.2% and interassay CVs were less than 7%. Ethical approval for the study was granted by the Cambridge Local Research Ethics Committee.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>PCR and sequencing</title>
        <p>Genomic DNA from patients was randomly preamplified in a GenomiPhi reaction (GE Healthcare UK, Chalfont St. Giles, UK) prior to amplification with gene-specific primers. Primers were designed using Primer3 software [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] to cover all coding exons and splice junctions. PCR primers and expected product sizes are described in <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">Electronic supplementary material</xref> (ESM) Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">1</xref>. Following PCR, performed using standard conditions, products were purified using exonuclease I and shrimp alkaline phosphatase (USB Corporation, Cleveland, OH, USA), and bi-directional sequencing was performed using a DNA sequencing kit (Big Dye Terminator 3.1; Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). Sequencing reactions were run on ABI3700 capillary machines (Applied Biosystems) and sequences were analysed using Mutation Surveyor version.2.20 (SoftGenetics LLC, State College, PA, USA).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Genotyping</title>
        <p><bold>SNP selection</bold> All SNPs with a minor allele frequency greater than 2% in our SIR cohort were selected for genotyping. To increase coverage in areas not re-sequenced, a number of dbSNPs were selected in an attempt to eliminate gaps, between genotyped SNPs, of greater than 2.5&#x2013;3&#xA0;kb on average (additional SNPs were selected prior to HapMap phase I data release). SNP choice was based on the following criteria: (1) all putative non-synonymous SNPs in dbSNP were selected irrespective of whether or not there was frequency or validation information for the SNP; (2) SNPs with frequency information were selected if their minor allele frequency was greater than or equal to 5%; (3) for SNPs with no frequency information the choice was based on whether the SNP was a double-hit SNP, had been validated by-cluster or by-submitter; and finally (4) some SNPs with no validation information were included to try and eliminate gaps of greater than 2.5&#x2013;3&#xA0;kb between SNPs selected for genotyping.</p>
        <p><bold>Genotyping and quality control</bold> Samples were arrayed on 96-well plates with three replicates and one water control per plate. For the case&#x2013;control populations, cases and control samples were randomly distributed across each 96-well plate, with approximately the same number of cases and controls per plate. Genotyping of samples was performed in 384-well plates at the Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Cambridge, using an adaptation of the homogenous MassExtend protocol for the MassArray system (Sequenom, San Diego, CA, USA) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Assay results for case&#x2013;control are described in ESM Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">2</xref>. The following criteria were used to pass assays resulting from genotyping: (1) call rates had to be greater than or equal to 90% (in one case a call rate of 88% was accepted); (2) concordance rates between duplicate samples had to be greater than or equal to 98%; (3) minor allele frequency had to be greater than or equal to 1% in the genotyped populations; (4) agreement with Hardy&#x2013;Weinberg equilibrium was tested separately in cases and controls using a <italic>&#x3C7;</italic>2 goodness-of-fit test, and if <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01 in controls, the assay was failed, while if <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01 in cases, the assay was flagged but included in primary analysis. Assays that failed quality control were excluded from further analysis. In total we analysed results from nine SNPs in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and 15 SNPs from <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>All analyses used SAS 8.02 (SAS Institute, Cary, NC, USA) or Stata 7.0 (Stata Corporation, College Station, TX, USA) statistical programs, unless otherwise stated. All used genotypes were in Hardy&#x2013;Weinberg equilibrium. The pair-wise linkage disequilibrium (LD) coefficient for the controls (r<sup>2</sup>) was calculated for genotyped SNPs and is represented in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. For each SNP, two primary models were used to assess association with diabetes and quantitative traits, the linear trend (additive model) on 1df and the general model on 2df. Since the results from these analyses were not materially different, we present only the results from the linear trend test. Tests for association were performed by logistic regression combined in the two case&#x2013;control populations adjusting for age, sex and population. Between-study heterogeneity was tested by log-likelihood ratio tests. Quantitative trait analysis was undertaken in the Ely Study population. Association between fasting plasma insulin, fasting and 2-h post-load plasma glucose, 30-min insulin increment (30-min insulin minus fasting insulin over 30-min glucose in an OGTT), BMI and genotype was tested in a multiple regression model, adjusted for age and sex.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Genomic structure and pair-wise marker <italic>LD</italic> in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> (<bold>a</bold>) and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> (<bold>b</bold>). The location of <italic>SNPs</italic> identified in this study and/or genotyped is represented along the gene (<italic>bold type</italic>: <italic>SNPs</italic> selected for genotyping, and failed or monomorphic <italic>SNPs</italic>). Exons are represented in <italic>boxes</italic> (<italic>black for coding</italic> and <italic>open for untranslated</italic>). Introns and flanking sequences appear as <italic>lines</italic>. The pair-wise marker <italic>LD</italic> measured by <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> statistics is shown <italic>below</italic> the genomic structures and indicated by the <italic>shade of grey blocks</italic> (<italic>white</italic> to <italic>black</italic>) and the <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> value. <bold>a</bold>, <bold>b</bold>, isoforms <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold> in <italic>ADIPOR2</italic></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="125_2006_534_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>To evaluate whether genetic variation in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> contributed to severe insulin resistance in humans, we sequenced exons and splice junctions in both genes in 129 individuals from our SIR cohort. These individuals were unrelated and had a variety of syndromes of severe insulin resistance [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. We identified 13 and 29 polymorphisms in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> respectively, none of which altered the protein sequence of either gene (ESM Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">3</xref>). This suggests that no functional mutations were identified in these genes. We next tested whether common variants at these genes impacted on type 2 diabetes predisposition or related quantitative traits in UK Europid populations. We selected all variants with a minor allele frequency greater than 2% in the SIR cohort and supplemented our SNP selection with additional variants from the dbSNP database plus SNPs with significant association results in other published studies. Thirteen polymorphisms from <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and 23 polymorphisms from <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> were selected for genotyping in two type 2 diabetes case&#x2013;control studies (<italic>n</italic>=2,127) and one metabolic quantitative trait study (<italic>n</italic>=1,721) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Those SNPs that passed our genotyping quality control criteria (described in methods) were used to investigate the degree of LD in control individuals across <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>. In total nine SNPs in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and 15 SNPs in <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> were included in the analysis. LD was measured by <italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup> statistic and is depicted in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Under both general and linear trend models no evidence was found for statistically significant associations between SNPs and disease risk (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In <italic>ADIPOR1</italic>, SNPs rs2275738, rs2275735 and rs10581 were removed from the quantitative trait analysis as they were out of Hardy&#x2013;Weinberg equilibrium (<italic>p</italic>&lt;0.01). For the remaining SNPs there was also no evidence for association of the SNPs tested with BMI, fasting and 2-h glucose levels, fasting insulin or 30-min insulin incremental response (ESM Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">4</xref>). In <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> a few SNPs showed nominally significant association with BMI and 2-h glucose levels. However, these results are likely to be chance findings given the number of statistical tests performed (ESM Table <xref ref-type="supplementary-material" rid="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300">4</xref>). 
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p><italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> SNP association results with type 2 diabetes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Gene</th><th rowspan="2">&#xA0;SNP</th><th>Allele</th><th colspan="3">Cases</th><th colspan="3">Controls</th><th>Odds ratio</th><th rowspan="2"><italic>p</italic> value trend</th><th rowspan="2" colspan="3"><italic>p</italic> value homogeneity</th></tr><tr><th>1/2</th><th>11 (%)</th><th>12 (%)</th><th>22 (%)</th><th>11 (%) </th><th>12 (%) </th><th>22 (%)</th><th>(95% CI)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="9"><italic>ADIPOR1</italic></td><td>rs6666089</td><td>G/A</td><td>378 (47.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">340 (42.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">76 (9.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">536 (46.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">525 (45.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">100 (8.6)</td><td>1.00 (0.86,1.15)</td><td>0.9601</td><td colspan="3">0.750</td></tr><tr><td>rs1539355</td><td>A/G</td><td>374 (46.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">346 (43.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">82 (10.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">558 (45.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">547 (45.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">111 (9.1)</td><td>1.02 (0.89,1.18)</td><td>0.7350</td><td colspan="3">0.649</td></tr><tr><td>rs2275738</td><td>C/T</td><td>277 (34.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">379 (47.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">149 (18.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">395 (34.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">551 (47.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">216 (18.6)</td><td>0.97 (0.85,1.1)</td><td>0.6109</td><td colspan="3">0.496</td></tr><tr><td>IVS3+85</td><td>C/G</td><td>707 (92.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">61 (7.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td char="(" align="char">1046 (92.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">82 (7.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">2 (0.2)</td><td>1.03 (0.73,1.45)</td><td>0.8721</td><td colspan="3">0.654</td></tr><tr><td>rs2275735</td><td>C/T</td><td>763 (92.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">66 (8.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td char="(" align="char">1152 (93.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">79 (6.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (0.1)</td><td>1.24 (0.88,1.75)</td><td>0.2239</td><td colspan="3">0.228</td></tr><tr><td>rs1342387</td><td>C/T</td><td>249 (30.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">414 (50.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">156 (19.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">362 (29.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">634 (51.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">231 (18.8)</td><td>0.96 (0.85,1.1)</td><td>0.5909</td><td colspan="3">0.603</td></tr><tr><td>rs10581</td><td>G/A</td><td>741 (93.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (5.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (0.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">1079 (95.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (4.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">3 (0.3)</td><td>1.35 (0.92,1.97)</td><td>0.1281</td><td colspan="3">0.466</td></tr><tr><td>rs7539542</td><td>C/G</td><td>373 (47.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">336 (42.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">78 (9.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">554 (46.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">510 (43.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">117 (9.9)</td><td>1.00 (0.87,1.15)</td><td>0.9566</td><td colspan="3">0.193</td></tr><tr><td>rs2185781</td><td>C/T</td><td>532 (63.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">256 (30.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">49 (5.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">789 (63.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">398 (32.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">50 (4.0)</td><td>1.08 (0.92,1.26)</td><td>0.3425</td><td colspan="3">0.495</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="15"><italic>ADIPOR2</italic></td><td>rs1029629</td><td>A/C</td><td>353 (44.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">372 (47.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">67 (8.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">537 (44.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">528 (44.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">132 (11.0)</td><td>0.94 (0.81,1.08)</td><td>0.3497</td><td colspan="3">0.265</td></tr><tr><td>rs11061971</td><td>A/T</td><td>228 (28.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">409 (50.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">174 (21.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">349 (29.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">589 (49.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">246 (20.8)</td><td>1.05 (0.93,1.20)</td><td>0.4394</td><td colspan="3">0.092</td></tr><tr><td>rs4766415</td><td>A/T</td><td>207 (25.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">411 (50.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">192 (23.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">323 (27.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">586 (49.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">282 (23.7)</td><td>1.04 (0.92,1.19)</td><td>0.5159</td><td colspan="3">0.074</td></tr><tr><td>rs767870</td><td>A/G</td><td>575 (71.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">214 (26.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">18 (2.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">857 (72.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">310 (26.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">19 (1.6)</td><td>1.08 (0.9,1.3)</td><td>0.3843</td><td colspan="3">0.095</td></tr><tr><td>rs2286384</td><td>G/C</td><td>214 (25.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">429 (51.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">190 (22.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">329 (26.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">618 (50.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">282 (22.9)</td><td>1.03 (0.9,1.17)</td><td>0.6837</td><td colspan="3">0.037<sup>*</sup></td></tr><tr><td>rs2286383</td><td>C/T</td><td>237 (28.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">418 (50.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">174 (21.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">368 (30.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">602 (49.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">253 (20.7)</td><td>1.05 (0.92,1.19)</td><td>0.4598</td><td colspan="3">0.068</td></tr><tr><td>I290</td><td>C/A</td><td>618 (75.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">193 (23.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">11 (1.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">940 (77.9)</td><td char="(" align="char">252 (21.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">14 (1.2)</td><td>1.18 (0.97,1.44)</td><td>0.0985</td><td colspan="3">0.118</td></tr><tr><td>rs9805042</td><td>C/T</td><td>603 (75.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">180 (22.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">12 (1.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">900 (79.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">225 (19.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">14 (1.2)</td><td>1.17 (0.96,1.43)</td><td>0.1282</td><td colspan="3">0.051</td></tr><tr><td>rs2286382</td><td>G/A</td><td>791 (94.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">45 (5.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">1 (0.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">1159 (94.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">71 (5.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">0 (0)</td><td>0.98 (0.67,1.43)</td><td>0.9054</td><td colspan="3">0.664</td></tr><tr><td>rs12342</td><td>C/T</td><td>370 (44.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">376 (45.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">84 (10.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">543 (44.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">540 (44.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">142 (11.6)</td><td>0.96 (0.84,1.1)</td><td>0.5461</td><td colspan="3">0.398</td></tr><tr><td>rs1044471</td><td>C/T</td><td>227 (27.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">420 (51.5)</td><td char="(" align="char">169 (20.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">334 (27.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">592 (49.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">282 (23.3)</td><td>0.93 (0.82,1.05)</td><td>0.2500</td><td colspan="3">0.115</td></tr><tr><td>rs2286380</td><td>A/T</td><td>621 (77.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">176 (21.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">10 (1.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">947 (79.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">238 (19.8)</td><td char="(" align="char">15 (0.0125)</td><td>1.12 (0.91,1.37)</td><td>0.2762</td><td colspan="3">0.155</td></tr><tr><td>rs13219</td><td>T/C</td><td>251 (30.2)</td><td char="(" align="char">403 (48.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">178 (21.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">369 (30.1)</td><td char="(" align="char">618 (50.4)</td><td char="(" align="char">238 (19.4)</td><td>1.04 (0.91,1.18)</td><td>0.5610</td><td colspan="3">0.276</td></tr><tr><td>rs2286379</td><td>T/C</td><td>259 (31.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">399 (47.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">178 (21.3)</td><td char="(" align="char">376 (30.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">614 (50.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">239 (19.4)</td><td>1.03 (0.91,1.17)</td><td>0.6427</td><td colspan="3">0.269</td></tr><tr><td>rs3815325</td><td>G/A</td><td>490 (60.6)</td><td char="(" align="char">273 (33.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">46 (5.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">712 (58.7)</td><td char="(" align="char">437 (36.0)</td><td char="(" align="char">64 (5.3)</td><td>0.96 (0.82,1.11)</td><td>0.5785</td><td colspan="3">0.263</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>11</italic>, homozygous for allele 1, <italic>12</italic>, heterozygous, <italic>22</italic>, homozygous for allele 2. Genotype counts are shown with frequency (%), odds ratios are shown per allele 2 with significance calculated for the linear trend (<italic>p</italic> value trend). Homogeneity in results from association between EPIC and Cambridge Case&#x2013;Control populations was tested (<italic>p</italic> value homogeneity)</p><p>*<italic>p</italic> values&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;0.05</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The current study, including sequencing of 129 patients with syndromes of severe insulin resistance and genotyping of both population-based type 2 diabetes case&#x2013;control studies (<italic>n</italic>=2,127) and a metabolic quantitative trait study (<italic>n</italic>=1,721), suggests that <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> genetic variants are unlikely to be major risk factors for type 2 diabetes and insulin resistance in UK Europid populations.</p>
      <p>Although sequencing of <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> genes in a cohort of patients with syndromes of severe insulin resistance (<italic>n</italic>=129) led to the identification of 42 polymorphisms, including 21 novel rare variants, none altered the protein sequence. Given that this group of patients comprises a heterogeneous cohort representative of a variety of syndromes of extreme insulin resistance, the lack of variants affecting the protein sequence suggests that functional mutations in the genes <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> are not major causes of extreme insulin resistance in humans.</p>
      <p>For <italic>ADIPOR1</italic>, our data in case&#x2013;control studies are consistent with previous reports showing that SNPs in this gene are not associated with type 2 diabetes risk in Europid [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], African [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] or Japanese populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. This is in contrast to evidence from the Old Order Amish, where an association of rs2275738 (and rs2275737 which is in perfect LD with it) and rs1342387 with type 2 diabetes risk has been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Since the Amish represent an isolated population, it is possible that variants in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> play a role in type 2 diabetes predisposition among them, which is not apparent in more heterogeneous populations. However, given that both reported associated SNPs are present in all populations, it is unlikely that either is the true causal variant, although they could be detecting, through LD, the effect of an untested SNP. Alternatively, given the relative small sample sizes used and lack of adjustment for multiple testing, the authors may have reported a false&#x2013;positive association.</p>
      <p>For <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> the data are less consistent. While no evidence of association between <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> SNPs and type 2 diabetes was present in a Japanese population [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>], an association has been suggested between SNP rs767870 and type 2 diabetes risk in French populations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Our data, and those from the Old Order Amish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>], do not support this finding. Notably, in the French population, meta-analysis of rs767870, including 1,380 individuals with type 2 diabetes and 1,496 controls, demonstrated allelic association of nominal significance only (<italic>p</italic>=0.02), while the most significant result was under a recessive model (<italic>p</italic>=0.0018). Our study has only 23% power to detect such small recessive effects (odds ratio 1.3) with an allele frequency of 0.15, and this could explain our discrepant result. Further large scale studies of this SNP in additional populations will be required to elucidate its role in conferring risk of disease. A haplotype was also reported to increase risk of diabetes in the Old Order Amish [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. However, when we performed haplotype analyses in both <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>, we were unable to detect any significant associations with diabetes risk (data not shown), and this discrepancy might also be accounted for by differences in the populations studied.</p>
      <p>With regard to quantitative metabolic traits, to date two studies have reported nominally significant results with insulin sensitivity and body size [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The first study showed nominally significant associations between two tightly linked SNPs (rs6666089 and an intronic &#x2013;1927 SNP) in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and decreased insulin sensitivity and increased HbA<sub>1c</sub> levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. We did not test association with HbA<sub>1c</sub>, but have not replicated any association with insulin sensitivity (including with SNP rs6666089) as assessed by fasting insulin measurements. Recently Kantartzis and colleagues reported that the association between rs6666089 and insulin sensitivity is observed only in more obese, but not in lean individuals [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This dependence on the degree of adiposity could explain some of the discrepant results observed for this SNP, if there are substantial differences in mean BMI between populations tested. To explore this hypothesis, we performed SNP&#xD7;BMI interaction tests (using BMI both as a continuous trait and splitting the population above and below the median) on all <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> SNPs tested. Our data provided no evidence for such an interaction (data not shown). We also specifically tested for association between rs6666089, and measures of insulin and glucose in participants with BMI above and below 25. Again we found no statistically significant difference between the two groups (<italic>p</italic>&gt;0.3). Therefore, it is unlikely that BMI differences between populations are at the root of our discrepant results. Of note, our data cannot exclude possible small effects of this SNP on insulin sensitivity, in particular if this effect is only observed in subjects with higher BMI. The second study suggested there was evidence of association between two markers (rs10920534 and rs2275738) and BMI, but this evidence came from men only. Furthermore, three other markers (rs10920534, rs12045862 and rs7539542) were reported to associate with fasting and 2-h insulin levels, particularly in men at baseline [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. We did not test rs10920534, but did test rs6666089 (<italic>D</italic>&#x2032;=<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>=1 with rs10920534) and found no evidence for SNP&#xD7;sex interaction on any of the quantitative traits we analysed. Our data also did not replicate the sex effect of SNP rs7539542 on insulin measurements. Although we did not test SNP rs12045862, previously published data was conflicting. Thus while the C allele was suggested to be associated with higher 2-h insulin levels in men (<italic>p</italic>=0.027), in women the T allele was associated with higher levels (<italic>p</italic>=0.029) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Given that neither we, nor others [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], have found evidence for sex&#xD7;SNP interaction effects on measures of insulin sensitivity, we suggest that further confirmatory studies are required to test this hypothesis.</p>
      <p>Until recently, remaining uncertainty regarding the identity of the true physiological receptors for adiponectin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] had hampered interpretation of the functional relevance of polymorphisms in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> with respect to adiponectin&#x2019;s insulin sensitising effects. However, a recent yeast two-hybrid screen identified an <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> interacting molecule, APPL1, thought to mediate many of the effects of adiponectin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]. This molecule was shown to interact with both <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> in an adiponectin-sensitive manner, and was shown to mediate many of adiponectin&#x2019;s insulin-sensitising effects. This suggests that <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> could be therapeutic targets for drug development and should renew interest in association studies, such as those we present here, testing polymorphisms in <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> for effects on type 2 diabetes risk and metabolic traits.</p>
      <p>In summary, sequencing of <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> genes in a cohort of patients with syndromes of severe insulin resistance (<italic>n</italic>=129) suggests that functional mutations in these genes are not a major cause of extreme insulin resistance in humans. Furthermore, testing of common genetic variants (<italic>n</italic>=24) did not find evidence for association of these genes with type 2 diabetes risk (<italic>n</italic>=2,127) or with five additional quantitative metabolic traits (<italic>n</italic>=1,721). These data suggest that <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> variants are unlikely to be major risk factors for type 2 diabetes and insulin resistance in UK Europid populations, although more detailed analyses of gene variants may be required to exclude a potential minor role of these genes in insulin resistance and glucose homeostasis.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="supplementary-material">
      <title>Electronic supplementary material</title>
      <supplementary-material id="N0x1cf8f40N0x2d33300" content-type="local-data">
        <p>Below is the link to the electronic supplementary material. 
</p>
        <media xlink:href="125_2006_534_MOESM1_ESM.doc" id="MOESM1" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <label>Table&#xA0;1</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Primer sequences and PCR product sizes used for sequencing <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> (DOC 46&#xA0;kb)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2006_534_MOESM2_ESM.doc" id="MOESM2" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <label>Table&#xA0;2</label>
          <caption>
            <p>Genotyping assay results for case-control studies (DOC 61&#xA0;kb)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2006_534_MOESM3_ESM.doc" id="MOESM3" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <label>Table&#xA0;3</label>
          <caption>
            <p>SNPs detected by sequencing <italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> in severely insulin-resistant patients (DOC 78&#xA0;kb)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
        <media xlink:href="125_2006_534_MOESM4_ESM.doc" id="MOESM4" mimetype="application" mime-subtype="msword">
          <label>Table&#xA0;4</label>
          <caption>
            <p><italic>ADIPOR1</italic> and <italic>ADIPOR2</italic> SNP association results with quantitative traits (DOC 215&#xA0;kb)</p>
          </caption>
        </media>
      </supplementary-material>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank S. Bumpstead for genotyping support. I. Barroso is funded by the Wellcome Trust. S. O&#x2019;Rahilly and I. Barroso acknowledge support from EU FP6 funding (contract no. LSHM-CT-2003-503041). The EPIC-Norfolk study is funded by MRC UK and Cancer Research UK. The MRC Ely Study is funded by the MRC and Wellcome Trust (to N. J. Wareham). We are grateful to all patients, volunteers, referring physicians and staff of the SIR, Cambridgeshire Case&#x2013;Control, EPIC-Norfolk, and MRC Ely studies.</p>
      <p><bold>Duality of interest</bold> The authors declare that no conflicts of interest exist.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berg</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Combs</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Du</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brownlee</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scherer</surname>
              <given-names>PE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The adipocyte-secreted protein Acrp30 enhances hepatic insulin action</article-title>
          <source>Nat Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>947</fpage>
          <lpage>953</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/90992</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Berg AH, Combs TP, Du X, Brownlee M, Scherer PE (2001) The adipocyte-secreted protein Acrp30 enhances hepatic insulin action. Nat Med 7:947&#x2013;953 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11479628</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamauchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Minokoshi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adiponectin stimulates glucose utilization and fatty-acid oxidation by activating AMP-activated protein kinase</article-title>
          <source>Nat Med</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>1288</fpage>
          <lpage>1295</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nm788</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamauchi T, Kamon J, Minokoshi Y et al (2002) Adiponectin stimulates glucose utilization and fatty-acid oxidation by activating AMP-activated protein kinase. Nat Med 8:1288&#x2013;1295 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12368907</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ouchi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kihara</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arita</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adipocyte-derived plasma protein, adiponectin, suppresses lipid accumulation and class A scavenger receptor expression in human monocyte-derived macrophages</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>1057</fpage>
          <lpage>1063</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ouchi N, Kihara S, Arita Y et al (2001) Adipocyte-derived plasma protein, adiponectin, suppresses lipid accumulation and class A scavenger receptor expression in human monocyte-derived macrophages. Circulation 103:1057&#x2013;1063 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222466</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamauchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waki</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The fat-derived hormone adiponectin reverses insulin resistance associated with both lipoatrophy and obesity</article-title>
          <source>Nat Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>941</fpage>
          <lpage>946</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/90984</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamauchi T, Kamon J, Waki H et al (2001) The fat-derived hormone adiponectin reverses insulin resistance associated with both lipoatrophy and obesity. Nat Med 7:941&#x2013;946 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11479627</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boutin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mori</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic variation in the gene encoding adiponectin is associated with an increased risk of type 2 diabetes in the Japanese population</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>540</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hara K, Boutin P, Mori Y et al (2002) Genetic variation in the gene encoding adiponectin is associated with an increased risk of type 2 diabetes in the Japanese population. Diabetes 51:536&#x2013;540 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11812766</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Menzaghi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ercolino</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paola</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A haplotype at the adiponectin locus is associated with obesity and other features of the insulin resistance syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>2306</fpage>
          <lpage>2312</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Menzaghi C, Ercolino T, Di Paola R et al (2002) A haplotype at the adiponectin locus is associated with obesity and other features of the insulin resistance syndrome. Diabetes 51:2306&#x2013;2312 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12086965</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vasseur</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helbecque</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dina</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Single-nucleotide polymorphism haplotypes in the both proximal promoter and exon 3 of the APM1 gene modulate adipocyte-secreted adiponectin hormone levels and contribute to the genetic risk for type 2 diabetes in French Caucasians</article-title>
          <source>Hum Mol Genet</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>2607</fpage>
          <lpage>2614</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/hmg/11.21.2607</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vasseur F, Helbecque N, Dina C et al (2002) Single-nucleotide polymorphism haplotypes in the both proximal promoter and exon 3 of the APM1 gene modulate adipocyte-secreted adiponectin hormone levels and contribute to the genetic risk for type 2 diabetes in French Caucasians. Hum Mol Genet 11:2607&#x2013;2614 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12354786</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Froguel</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetics of the APM1 locus and its contribution to type 2 diabetes susceptibility in French Caucasians</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>2977</fpage>
          <lpage>2983</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gibson F, Froguel P (2004) Genetics of the APM1 locus and its contribution to type 2 diabetes susceptibility in French Caucasians. Diabetes 53:2977&#x2013;2983 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15504979</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Qi</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rimm</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The +276 polymorphism of the APM1 gene, plasma adiponectin concentration, and cardiovascular risk in diabetic men</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1607</fpage>
          <lpage>1610</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Qi L, Li T, Rimm E et al (2005) The +276 polymorphism of the APM1 gene, plasma adiponectin concentration, and cardiovascular risk in diabetic men. Diabetes 54:1607&#x2013;1610 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855354</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamauchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning of adiponectin receptors that mediate antidiabetic metabolic effects</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>423</volume>
          <fpage>762</fpage>
          <lpage>769</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nature01705</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamauchi T, Kamon J, Ito Y et al (2003) Cloning of adiponectin receptors that mediate antidiabetic metabolic effects. Nature 423:762&#x2013;769 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12802337</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Civitarese</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkinson</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richardson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adiponectin receptors gene expression and insulin sensitivity in non-diabetic Mexican Americans with or without a family history of type 2 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>816</fpage>
          <lpage>820</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-004-1359-x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Civitarese AE, Jenkinson CP, Richardson D et al (2004) Adiponectin receptors gene expression and insulin sensitivity in non-diabetic Mexican Americans with or without a family history of type 2 diabetes. Diabetologia 47:816&#x2013;820 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15105989</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jia</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adiponectin receptor 1 gene (ADIPOR1) as a candidate for type 2 diabetes and insulin resistance</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>2132</fpage>
          <lpage>2136</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang H, Zhang H, Jia Y et al (2004) Adiponectin receptor 1 gene (ADIPOR1) as a candidate for type 2 diabetes and insulin resistance. Diabetes 53:2132&#x2013;2136 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15277397</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Damcott</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ott</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pollin</surname>
              <given-names>TI</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic variation in adiponectin receptor 1 and adiponectin receptor 2 is associated with type 2 diabetes in the Old Order Amish</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>2245</fpage>
          <lpage>2250</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Damcott CM, Ott SH, Pollin TI et al (2005) Genetic variation in adiponectin receptor 1 and adiponectin receptor 2 is associated with type 2 diabetes in the Old Order Amish. Diabetes 54:2245&#x2013;2250 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15983228</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horikoshi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitazato</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Absence of an association between the polymorphisms in the genes encoding adiponectin receptors and type 2 diabetes</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1307</fpage>
          <lpage>1314</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-005-1806-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hara K, Horikoshi M, Kitazato H et al (2005) Absence of an association between the polymorphisms in the genes encoding adiponectin receptors and type 2 diabetes. Diabetologia 48:1307&#x2013;1314 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15918014</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vaxillaire</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dechaume</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vasseur-Delannoy</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic analysis of ADIPOR1 and ADIPOR2 candidate polymorphisms for type 2 diabetes in the Caucasian population</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>856</fpage>
          <lpage>861</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diabetes.55.03.06.db05-0665</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vaxillaire M, Dechaume A, Vasseur-Delannoy V et al (2006) Genetic analysis of ADIPOR1 and ADIPOR2 candidate polymorphisms for type 2 diabetes in the Caucasian population. Diabetes 55:856&#x2013;861 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16505255</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siitonen</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pulkkinen</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mager</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Association of sequence variations in the gene encoding adiponectin receptor 1 (ADIPOR1) with body size and insulin levels. The Finnish Diabetes Prevention Study</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>1795</fpage>
          <lpage>1805</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-006-0291-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Siitonen N, Pulkkinen L, Mager U et al (2006) Association of sequence variations in the gene encoding adiponectin receptor 1 (ADIPOR1) with body size and insulin levels. The Finnish Diabetes Prevention Study. Diabetologia 49:1795&#x2013;1805 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16724230</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barroso</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luan</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Middelberg</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Candidate gene association study in type 2 diabetes indicates a role for genes involved in beta-cell function as well as insulin action</article-title>
          <source>PLoS Biol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>E20</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1371/journal.pbio.0000020</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Barroso I, Luan J, Middelberg RP et al (2003) Candidate gene association study in type 2 diabetes indicates a role for genes involved in beta-cell function as well as insulin action. PLoS Biol 1:E20 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14551916</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harding</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khaw</surname>
              <given-names>KT</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dietary fat and the risk of clinical type 2 diabetes: the European Prospective Investigation of Cancer&#x2014;Norfolk study</article-title>
          <source>Am J Epidemiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/aje/kwh004</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Harding AH, Day NE, Khaw KT et al (2004) Dietary fat and the risk of clinical type 2 diabetes: the European Prospective Investigation of Cancer&#x2014;Norfolk study. Am J Epidemiol 159:73&#x2013;82 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14693662</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oakes</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luben</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>EPIC-Norfolk: study design and characteristics of the cohort. European Prospective Investigation of Cancer</article-title>
          <source>Br J Cancer</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>103</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Day N, Oakes S, Luben R et al (1999) EPIC-Norfolk: study design and characteristics of the cohort. European Prospective Investigation of Cancer. Br J Cancer 80 (Suppl 1):95&#x2013;103 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10466767</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Williams</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wareham</surname>
              <given-names>NJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Undiagnosed glucose intolerance in the community: the Isle of Ely Diabetes Project</article-title>
          <source>Diabet Med</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Williams DR, Wareham NJ, Brown DC et al (1995) Undiagnosed glucose intolerance in the community: the Isle of Ely Diabetes Project. Diabet Med 12:30&#x2013;35 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7712700</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rozen</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Skaletsky</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers</article-title>
          <source>Methods Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>132</volume>
          <fpage>365</fpage>
          <lpage>386</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rozen S, Skaletsky H (2000) Primer3 on the WWW for general users and for biologist programmers. Methods Mol Biol 132:365&#x2013;386 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10547847</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Whittaker</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bumpstead</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Downes</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ghori</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deloukas</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Celis</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carter</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simons</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Small</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunter</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>SNP analysis by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry</article-title>
          <source>Cell biology: a laboratory handbook</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <edition>3</edition>
          <publisher-loc>San Diego</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Academic</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Whittaker P, Bumpstead S, Downes K, Ghori J, Deloukas P (2006) SNP analysis by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry. In: Celis J, Carter N, Simons K, Small JV, Hunter T (eds) Cell biology: a laboratory handbook, 3rd edn. Academic, San Diego </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barroso</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurnell</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crowley</surname>
              <given-names>VE</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dominant negative mutations in human PPARgamma associated with severe insulin resistance, diabetes mellitus and hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>402</volume>
          <fpage>880</fpage>
          <lpage>883</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Barroso I, Gurnell M, Crowley VE et al (1999) Dominant negative mutations in human PPARgamma associated with severe insulin resistance, diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Nature 402:880&#x2013;883 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10622252</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stefan</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machicao</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staiger</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Polymorphisms in the gene encoding adiponectin receptor 1 are associated with insulin resistance and high liver fat</article-title>
          <source>Diabetologia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>2282</fpage>
          <lpage>2291</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00125-005-1948-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stefan N, Machicao F, Staiger H et al (2005) Polymorphisms in the gene encoding adiponectin receptor 1 are associated with insulin resistance and high liver fat. Diabetologia 48:2282&#x2013;2291 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16205883</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kantartzis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fritsche</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Machicao</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haring</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stefan</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The -8503 G/A polymorphism of the adiponectin receptor 1 gene is associated with insulin sensitivity dependent on adiposity</article-title>
          <source>Diabetes Care</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>464</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2337/diacare.29.02.06.dc05-2020</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kantartzis K, Fritsche A, Machicao F, Haring HU, Stefan N (2006) The -8503 G/A polymorphism of the adiponectin receptor 1 gene is associated with insulin sensitivity dependent on adiposity. Diabetes Care 29:464 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16443913</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hug</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahmad</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bogan</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsao</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lodish</surname>
              <given-names>HF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>T-cadherin is a receptor for hexameric and high-molecular-weight forms of Acrp30/adiponectin</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>10308</fpage>
          <lpage>10313</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0403382101</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hug C, Wang J, Ahmad NS, Bogan JS, Tsao TS, Lodish HF (2004) T-cadherin is a receptor for hexameric and high-molecular-weight forms of Acrp30/adiponectin. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 101:10308&#x2013;10313 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15210937</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mao</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kikani</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riojas</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>APPL1 binds to adiponectin receptors and mediates adiponectin signalling and function</article-title>
          <source>Nat Cell Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>516</fpage>
          <lpage>523</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ncb1404</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mao X, Kikani CK, Riojas RA et al (2006) APPL1 binds to adiponectin receptors and mediates adiponectin signalling and function. Nat Cell Biol 8:516&#x2013;523 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16622416</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <glossary>
      <title>Abbreviations</title>
      <def-list>
        <def-item>
          <term>
            <italic>ADIPOR1</italic>
          </term>
          <def>
            <p>adiponectin receptor 1</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>
            <italic>ADIPOR2</italic>
          </term>
          <def>
            <p>adiponectin receptor 2</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>LD</term>
          <def>
            <p>linkage disequilibrium</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SIR</term>
          <def>
            <p>severe insulin resistance (cohort)</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
        <def-item>
          <term>SNP</term>
          <def>
            <p>single nucleotide polymorphism</p>
          </def>
        </def-item>
      </def-list>
    </glossary>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>
          <bold>Electronic supplementary material</bold>
        </p>
        <p>The online version of this article (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s00125-006-0534-7">doi:10.1007/s00125-006-0534-7</ext-link>) contains supplementary material, which is accessible to authorised users.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>