<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur J Clin Pharmacol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>European Journal of Clinical Pharmacology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0031-6970</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1041</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17712551</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2039832</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">354</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00228-007-0354-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Pharmacokinetics and Disposition</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Evaluation of limited sampling strategies for tacrolimus</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Op den Buijsch</surname>
            <given-names>Robert A. M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-43-3876686</phone>
            <fax>+31-43-3874692</fax>
            <email>RBUY@klinchem.azm.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van de Plas</surname>
            <given-names>Afke</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stolk</surname>
            <given-names>Leo M. L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Christiaans</surname>
            <given-names>Maarten H. L.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van Hooff</surname>
            <given-names>Johannes P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Undre</surname>
            <given-names>Nas A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van Dieijen-Visser</surname>
            <given-names>Marja P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bekers</surname>
            <given-names>Otto</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Clinical Chemistry, University Hospital Maastricht, P.O. Box 5800, 6202 AZ Maastricht, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Clinical Pharmacy, University Hospital Maastricht, Maastricht, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Internal Medicine, University Hospital Maastricht, Maastricht, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Astellas, Munich, Germany </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>22</day>
        <month>8</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>63</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <fpage>1039</fpage>
      <lpage>1044</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Objective</title>
          <p>In literature, a great diversity of limited sampling strategies (LSS) have been recommended for tacrolimus monitoring, however proper validation of these strategies to accurately predict the area under the time concentration curve (AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>) is limited. The aim of this study was to determine whether these LSS might be useful for AUC prediction of other patient populations.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>The LSS from literature studied were based on regression equations or on Bayesian fitting using MWPHARM 3.50 (Mediware, Groningen, the Netherlands). The performance was evaluated on 24 of these LSS in our population of 37 renal transplant patients with known AUCs. The results were also compared with the predictability of the regression equation based on the trough concentrations C<sub>0</sub> and C<sub>12</sub> of these 37 patients. Criterion was an absolute prediction error (APE) that differed less than 15% from the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> calculated by the trapezoidal rule.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Thirteen of the 18 (72%) LSS based on regression analysis were capable of predicting at least 90% of the 37 individual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> within an APE of 15%. Additionally, all but three LSS examined gave a better prediction of the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> in comparison with the trough concentrations C<sub>0</sub> or C<sub>12</sub> (mean 62%). All six LSS based on Bayesian fitting predicted &lt;90% of the 37 complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> correctly (mean 67%).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>The present study indicated that implementation of LSS based on regression analysis could produce satisfactory predictions although careful evaluation is necessary.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Tacrolimus</kwd>
        <kwd>Limited sampling strategy</kwd>
        <kwd>Trough level</kwd>
        <kwd>AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The calcineurin-inhibitor tacrolimus, used widely after organ transplantation, has a narrow therapeutic index and highly variable pharmacokinetic characteristics. Close monitoring of the drug concentration is required to achieve an optimum efficiency by minimizing the risk of subtherapeutic and toxic blood concentrations. Efficacy and side effects of tacrolimus are highly correlated with the area under the time concentration curve (AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Elevated tacrolimus concentrations may lead to severe side effects such as nephrotoxicity, neurotoxicity and hyperglycaemia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>], while subtherapeutic tacrolimus concentrations increase the risk of transplant rejection enormously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
      <p>The most exact way to monitor the total tacrolimus exposure is by creating 12-h pharmacokinetic profiles, which implies that the tacrolimus concentration should be measured at at least six different time points. The AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> can then be calculated according to the trapezoidal rule using the tacrolimus concentrations measured at different time points. Since recording a complete 12-h pharmacokinetic profile for every patient is not feasible in clinical practice, traditionally many transplant centres have used tacrolimus trough (C<sub>0</sub>) concentrations to estimate the tacrolimus exposure. Although tacrolimus C<sub>0</sub> concentrations are generally considered to be a good indication of the total systemic drug exposure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], its usefulness in differentiating graft rejection episodes from nephrotoxicity has been questioned [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Recently, the correlation between individual tacrolimus concentrations and AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> has been studied in kidney [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>], liver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], heart [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] and lung [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] transplant recipients. In these studies, a poor association was found between the tacrolimus C<sub>0</sub> concentrations and the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>, while tacrolimus concentrations measured at other time points showed much better correlations with the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>. Additionally, strategies have been developed that included a limited number of sampling time points within a short time post-dose, the so-called limited sampling strategies (LSS). Several two- and three-time-point sampling strategies showed a high correlation with the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> in published studies and were able to predict the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> more accurately than the C<sub>0</sub> concentration alone [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
      <p>Based on the number of published studies regarding LSS for tacrolimus, there seems to be a growing interest for non-C<sub>0</sub> concentration measurements as an indicator of between-patient variability and as a guide for dose adjustments. Most of these studies recommend different LSS, but these strategies have not been validated with an independent population. Ting et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] recently reported that validation of the different LSS with an independent transplant population is an absolute prerequisite. The question was whether the LSS described in literature could be used in other centres with different populations. Predictive value of LSS from literature was evaluated using our own renal post-transplant group of 37 patients with known AUCs. Also the predictive value of trough levels (C<sub>0</sub> and C<sub>12</sub>) determined in our own population was investigated.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Patient population</title>
        <p>In total, 37 Caucasian renal transplant recipients for whom a complete 12-h time tacrolimus concentration curve had been determined in a past clinical trial were included in this study (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The transplant recipients underwent a renal transplantation at least 1&#xA0;year ago. Patients taking medication known to interact with tacrolimus, who suffered from gastro-intestinal or liver disease, pre-transplantation diabetes mellitus or other disorders that could have altered the absorption of tacrolimus were excluded from this study as illustrated in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Demographic characteristics of renal-transplant recipients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Demographic characteristics</th><th>Patients (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;37)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Gender (male/female)</td><td>24/13</td></tr><tr><td>Age (years, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>51.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.9</td></tr><tr><td>Length (cm, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>174&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.4</td></tr><tr><td>Weight (kg, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>77.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.5</td></tr><tr><td>Body mass index (kg/m<sup>2</sup>, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>25.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.42</td></tr><tr><td>Primary kidney disease (<italic>n</italic>)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Glomerulonephritis</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Chronic pyelonephritis</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;IgA nephropathy</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Hypertensive nephropathy</td><td>7</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Diabetes mellitus nephropathy</td><td>0</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Polycystic kidney disease</td><td>8</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Unknown</td><td>4</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Other</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Transplantation number (<italic>n</italic>)</td><td/></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;First</td><td>30</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Second</td><td>6</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Third or more</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Tacrolimus mono therapy (<italic>n</italic>)</td><td>29</td></tr><tr><td>Tacrolimus dose (mg kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>0.054&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.029</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>0</sub> (ng/mL, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>6.59&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.39</td></tr><tr><td>AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> (ng&#xD7;h/mL, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>122.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;31.1</td></tr><tr><td>C<sub>max</sub> (ng/mL, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>20.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.5</td></tr><tr><td>T<sub>max</sub> (h, mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD)</td><td>1.24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.43</td></tr><tr><td>Use of azothioprine/MMF/rapamycine/steroids</td><td>3/4/0/2</td></tr><tr><td>Time since transplantation (days, mean and range)</td><td>1,542 (453&#x2013;4,128)</td></tr><tr><td>Haemoglobin (mmol/L, ref. M: 8.2&#x2013;11.0, F: 7.3&#x2013;9.7)</td><td>8.52&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.83</td></tr><tr><td>Haematocrit fraction (ref. M: 0.41&#x2013;0.52, F: 0.36&#x2013;0.48)</td><td>0.41&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.04</td></tr><tr><td>ALAT (units/L, ref. M: &lt;45, F: &lt;35)</td><td>24&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13</td></tr><tr><td>ASAT (units/L, ref. M: &lt;35, F: &lt;30)</td><td>17&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10</td></tr><tr><td>Serum albumin (g/L, ref. 34&#x2013;45)</td><td>37.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.84</td></tr><tr><td>Serum creatinine (&#x3BC;mol/L, ref. M: 71&#x2013;110, F: 53&#x2013;97)</td><td>128&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;29</td></tr><tr><td>Creatinine clearance (Cockcroft-Gault; mL/min, ref. 90&#x2013;140)</td><td>58.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;26.6</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><italic>Ref.</italic> are the reference values applied in the Clinical Chemistry and Haematology Laboratory of the University Hospital in Maastricht. <italic>M</italic> Male, <italic>F</italic> female, <italic>MMF</italic> mycophenolate mofetil</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Prior to the blood sample collection, there was no tacrolimus dose change for at least 1&#xA0;week. After overnight fasting, the blood samples were collected immediately before (C<sub>0</sub>) and 0.5 (C<sub>0.5</sub>), 1 (C<sub>1</sub>), 2 (C<sub>2</sub>), 3 (C<sub>3</sub>), 4 (C<sub>4</sub>), 5 (C<sub>5</sub>), 7.5 (C<sub>7.5</sub>) and 12 (C<sub>12</sub>) h after the morning tacrolimus administration. Patients were not allowed to take food until 1&#xA0;h after ingesting the tacrolimus dose and were advised to avoid grapefruit intake to prevent alterations in the tacrolimus metabolism. Demographic as well as clinical data were determined at the time of recording the 12-h time tacrolimus concentration curve. The study was performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki and its amendments. The protocol was approved by the local Medical Ethics Committee and written informed consent for participation in this study was obtained from all patients.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Determination of tacrolimus concentrations</title>
        <p>The tacrolimus blood concentrations were determined in ethylene diamine tetra-acetic acid (EDTA) whole blood, using a method based on high-pressure liquid chromatography tandem mass spectrometry (HPLC-MS/MS). The assay is linear from 1 to 300&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/l. Intra-assay precision and accuracy were 3.4, 2.2, and 3.0% and 102, 94 and 94% respectively at 3.04, 6.23 and 13.0&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/l (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6). Inter-assay precision and accuracy were 8.2, 5.2, and 4.6% and 102, 94 and 93% (<italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;9) respectively. Lower limit of quantification was 1.0&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/l. The laboratory participates in the International Tacrolimus Proficiency Testing Scheme.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Limited sampling strategies investigated</title>
        <p>In our opinion, a suitable limited sampling strategy for tacrolimus should consist of two or three time concentration points within a short time post-dose (&#x2264;4&#xA0;h) including a trough level. We selected 24 LLS from the literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Eighteen of these strategies were based on regression analysis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>], and six other strategies were based on Bayesian fitting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Also strategies based on the tacrolimus C<sub>0</sub> and C<sub>12</sub> concentrations were developed for our own renal transplant patient population and compared with above-mentioned LSS.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Pharmacokinetics and statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The area under the tacrolimus time concentration curve (AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>) was calculated from the time versus tacrolimus concentration plot using the linear trapezoidal rule in MWPharm 3.50 (Mediware, Groningen, The Netherlands). The predicted AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> (AUC<sub>pred</sub>), calculated with the 24 different LSS, were validated by determining the predictive performance as described by Sheiner and Beal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The percentage of the prediction error (PE) and the percentage of the absolute prediction error (APE) are parameters often used for validation in LSS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Given the high pharmacokinetic variability, an APE of less than 15% was considered clinically acceptable [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p>
        <p>Prediction bias was measured as a percentage of the prediction error [PE (%)] using the following formula:
<disp-formula id="Equa"><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ {\text{PE}}{\left( \%  \right)} = 100 \times {{\left( {{\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{pred}}}}  - {\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{actual}}}} } \right)}} \mathord{\left/  {\vphantom {{{\left( {{\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{pred}}}}  - {\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{actual}}}} } \right)}} {{\text{AUC}}}}} \right.  \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} {{\text{AUC}}}_{{{\text{actual}}}}  $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Prediction precision was measured as a percentage of the APE using the following formula:
<disp-formula id="Equb"><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ {\text{APE}}{\left( \%  \right)} = 100 \times {{\left| {{\left( {{\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{pred}}}}  - {\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{actual}}}} } \right)}} \right|}} \mathord{\left/  {\vphantom {{{\left| {{\left( {{\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{pred}}}}  - {\text{AUC}}_{{{\text{actual}}}} } \right)}} \right|}} {{\text{AUC}}}}} \right.  \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} {{\text{AUC}}}_{{{\text{actual}}}}  $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The variance in the strength of association between the AUC<sub>pred</sub> and the AUC<sub>actual</sub> was reflected by the linear regression coefficient of multiple determination (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>). All values are expressed as mean&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;SD. All statistical analyses were performed with use of SPSS 12.0 software for windows (Chicago, IL, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Evaluation of predictive performances of the limited sampling strategies</title>
        <p>Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> shows an overview of the studies describing the LSS evaluated in the present study. The regression equations and the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup> found by the investigators for the evaluated LSS are summarised in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref> describes the <italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>, which represents the association between AUC<sub>pred</sub> and AUC<sub>actual</sub> and the calculated PE and APE of the 24 evaluated LSS for our 37 pharmacokinetic profiles. Thirteen of the 18 LSS (72%) based on regression analysis had a predictivity of &gt;90%. Additionally, all except three of the LSS examined gave a better prediction of the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> in comparison with LSS based on a trough concentration C<sub>0</sub> and C<sub>12</sub> (mean 62%). Predictivity of all six LSS based on Bayesian fitting was &lt;90% (mean 66.8%). Additionally, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> illustrates an overview of the performances of the 26 LSS evaluated in our well-characterized population of renal transplant recipients.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Overview of the characteristics of transplant patients included in the studies that described limited sampling strategies</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Study</th><th>Transplanted organ</th><th>Number of patients<sup>a</sup></th><th>Number of AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> curves for validation (I<sup>b</sup>/NI<sup>c</sup>)</th><th>Analytical method<sup>d</sup></th><th>Time since transplantation<sup>e</sup></th><th>Inclusion criteria<sup>f</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Wong et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td><td>Kidney</td><td>18</td><td>0/18</td><td>Imx II</td><td>2.5&#xA0;years</td><td>1,2</td></tr><tr><td>Aumente Rubio et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td><td>Heart</td><td>22</td><td>0/25</td><td>Imx</td><td>&lt;1&#xA0;year</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td>Pisitkun et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td><td>Kidney</td><td>15</td><td>0/15</td><td>Imx II</td><td>8.7&#xA0;months</td><td>1,2,3</td></tr><tr><td>Armendariz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td><td>Kidney</td><td>22</td><td>13/14</td><td>Imx</td><td>Unknown</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr><tr><td>Scholten et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td><td>Kidney</td><td>43</td><td>64/20</td><td>Imx</td><td>Differs<sup>g</sup></td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Ragette et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td><td>Lung</td><td>15</td><td>0/31</td><td>Imx</td><td>7.3&#xA0;months</td><td>&#x2013;</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Number of transplant patients used in the included study for both developing and validating the limited sampling strategies.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Number of AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> used for developing the limited sampling strategies.</p><p><sup>c</sup>Number of independent (I) and dependent (NI) AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> used in the study to validate the created limited sampling strategies.</p><p><sup>d</sup>The analytical method used to determine the whole blood tacrolimus concentration.</p><p><sup>e</sup>The mean time after transplantation.</p><p><sup>f</sup>The inclusion criteria used for the transplant patients in the different studies.<italic> 1</italic> Tacrolimus administrated when patients were in the fasting state,<italic> 2</italic> patients selected for using no interfering medication with tacrolimus,<italic> 3</italic> patients selected with a normal liver function test.</p><p><sup>g</sup>Twenty-two pharmacokinetic profiles were obtained within 2&#xA0;weeks after transplantation, and 42 pharmacokinetic profiles were obtained between 6 and 52&#xA0;weeks after transplantation.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Overview of limited sampling strategies and their reported coefficients of correlation (<italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup>) with the complete tacrolimus AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Equation</th><th>Time points</th><th>Regression equations</th><th><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th>Ref</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>1.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq1"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq1.gif --><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$14.550 + 13.387 \times {\text{C}}_{0} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.54</td><td/></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>C<sub>12</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq2"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq2.gif --><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$15.892 + 17.852 \times {\text{C}}_{{12}} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.79</td><td/></tr><tr><td>3.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq3"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq3.gif --><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$13.3 + 1.2 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 2.4 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 5.6 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.93</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>4.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq4"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq4.gif --><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$16.2 + 2.4 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 5.9 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.93</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>5.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq5"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq5.gif --><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$0.98 + 4.17 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 2.29 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 5.3 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq6"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq6.gif --><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$3.75 + 5.52 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 6.97 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.95</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>7.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>2</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq7"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq7.gif --><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ - 5.496 + 7.189 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 2.357 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 2.131 \times {\text{C}}_{2} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.93</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>8.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq8"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq8.gif --><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$3.85 + 3.688 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 1.355 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 6.649 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>9.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq9"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq9.gif --><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ - 6.103 + 2.383 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 1.911 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 7.582 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>10.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq10"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq10.gif --><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$1.304 + 0.465 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 1.636 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 8.256 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>11.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq11"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq11.gif --><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$9.345 + 8.408 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 3.23 \times {\text{C}}_{1} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.91</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>12.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq12"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq12.gif --><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$8.231 + 2.316 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 9.636 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.95</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>13.<sup>a </sup></td><td>C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq13"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq13.gif --><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$13.114 + 0.873 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 9.291 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.95</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>14.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq14"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq14.gif --><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ - 0.192 + 1.888 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 8.783 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>15.<sup>a,b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq15"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq15.gif --><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$4.5 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 2 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 5.5 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>16.<sup>a,b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq16"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq16.gif --><tex-math id="M18">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$5 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 2 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 5 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>17.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq17"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq17.gif --><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$8.90 + 4.0 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 1.77 \times {\text{C}}_{1}  + 5.47 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>18.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>19.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>20.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.97</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>21.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.94</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>22.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>23.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub></td><td>0.95</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>24.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq18"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq18.gif --><tex-math id="M20">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$5.87 + 4.50 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 1.05 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 5.87 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.98</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>25.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq19"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq19.gif --><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$1.16 + 4.41 \times {\text{C}}_{0}  + 7.71 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.96</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td></tr><tr><td>26.<sup>a</sup></td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td><inline-formula id="IEq20"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 228_2007_354_Article_IEq20.gif --><tex-math id="M22">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$24.36 + 0.97 \times {\text{C}}_{2}  + 7.94 \times {\text{C}}_{4} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></td><td>0.94</td><td>[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Limited sample strategies derived from the linear trapezoidal rule and the complete 12-h AUC.</p><p><sup>a</sup>Limited sampling strategies that are able to predict 90% of complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> of the renal transplant recipients within the absolute prediction error (APE) of 15%.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Limited sample strategies derived from the linear trapezoidal rule and the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Evaluation of predictive performance of limited sampling strategies to estimate the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> in the 37 renal transplant recipients</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Equation</th><th>Time points</th><th><italic>R</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th>Mean PE (%)</th><th>Mean APE (%)</th><th>&#x2264;15%<sup>a</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>23.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.760</td><td>&#x2212;14.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.8 (&#x2212;46.0&#x2013;33.2)</td><td>17.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.43 (1.12&#x2013;46.0)</td><td>13 (35%)</td></tr><tr><td>22.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.779</td><td>&#x2212;11.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.0 (&#x2212;41.9 to 33.1)</td><td>15.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.83 (2.0&#x2013;41.9)</td><td>21 (57%)</td></tr><tr><td>1.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub></td><td>0.536</td><td>2.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.8 (&#x2212;27.1 to 24.4)</td><td>12.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.22 (0.7&#x2013;27.1)</td><td>22 (59%)</td></tr><tr><td>11.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub></td><td>0.703</td><td>6.58&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.8 (&#x2212;26.5 to 43.7)</td><td>12.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.1 (0.1&#x2013;43.7)</td><td>24 (65%)</td></tr><tr><td>2.</td><td>C<sub>12</sub></td><td>0.80</td><td>9.56&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.6 (&#x2212;12.7 to 29.9)</td><td>12.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.97 (0.3&#x2013;29.9)</td><td>24 (65%)</td></tr><tr><td>19.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.502</td><td>&#x2212;4.44&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;17.4 (&#x2212;45.3 to 50.6)</td><td>13.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.4 (0.4&#x2013;50.6)</td><td>25 (68%)</td></tr><tr><td>20.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.537</td><td>&#x2212;5.11&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;16.3 (&#x2212;43.1 to 50.3)</td><td>12.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.4 (0.2&#x2013;50.3)</td><td>28 (76%)</td></tr><tr><td>18.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>3</sub></td><td>0.525</td><td>9.95&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;19.4 (&#x2212;29.7 to 88.8)</td><td>13.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;17.4 (0.4&#x2013;88.8)</td><td>30 (81%)</td></tr><tr><td>25.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.911</td><td>&#x2212;7.83&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.36 (&#x2212;21.3 to 2.4)</td><td>8.08&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.02 (0.1&#x2013;21.3)</td><td>30 (81%)</td></tr><tr><td>7.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>2</sub></td><td>0.869</td><td>2.35&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.96 (&#x2212;17.2 to 27.3)</td><td>8.03&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.22 (0.0&#x2013;27.3)</td><td>31 (84%)</td></tr><tr><td>6.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.896</td><td>&#x2212;5.97&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.71 (&#x2212;20.1 to 4.7)</td><td>6.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.04 (0.6&#x2013;20.1)</td><td>31 (84%)</td></tr><tr><td>21.<sup>b</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub></td><td>0.802</td><td>&#x2212;3.69&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.2 (&#x2212;19.6 to 18.6)</td><td>9.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.67 (0.4&#x2013;19.6)</td><td>31 (84%)</td></tr><tr><td>17.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.943</td><td>5.91&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.06 (&#x2212;8.8 to 26.3)</td><td>7.02&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.93 (0.2&#x2013;26.3)</td><td>33 (89%)</td></tr><tr><td>15.<sup>c</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.934</td><td>5.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.28 (&#x2212;9.8 to 25.8)</td><td>6.81&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.57 (0.2&#x2013;25.8)</td><td>34 (92%)</td></tr><tr><td>14.</td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.964</td><td>2.28&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.58 (&#x2212;17.1 to 16.1)</td><td>5.45&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.24 (0.7&#x2013;17.1)</td><td>35 (95%)</td></tr><tr><td>24.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.941</td><td>&#x2212;4.81&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.26 (&#x2212;17.3 to 2.8)</td><td>5.32&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.73 (0.1&#x2013;17.3)</td><td>35 (95%)</td></tr><tr><td>13.</td><td>C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.973</td><td>6.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.84 (&#x2212;5.9 to 17.8)</td><td>6.68&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.28 (0.3&#x2013;17.8)</td><td>36 (97%)</td></tr><tr><td>8.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.967</td><td>3.37&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.21 (&#x2212;5.2 to 17.7)</td><td>4.87&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.80 (0.2&#x2013;17.7)</td><td>36 (97%)</td></tr><tr><td>9.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.962</td><td>0.10&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.37 (&#x2212;16.7 to 14.7)</td><td>4.71&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.22 (0.3&#x2013;16.7)</td><td>36 (97%)</td></tr><tr><td>26.</td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.959</td><td>3.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.24 (&#x2212;7.6 to 15.5)</td><td>5.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.37 (0.0&#x2013;15.5)</td><td>36 (97%)</td></tr><tr><td>10.</td><td>C<sub>1</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.976</td><td>3.07&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.40 (&#x2212;14.9 to 13.2)</td><td>4.99&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.64 (0.1&#x2013;14.9)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>16.<sup>c</sup></td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.953</td><td>&#x2212;1.58&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.29 (&#x2212;14.9 to 10.1)</td><td>4.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.75 (0.0&#x2013;14.9)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>12.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.930</td><td>3.55&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.30 (&#x2212;9.8 to 14.3)</td><td>6.29&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.46 (0.1&#x2013;14.3)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>4.</td><td>C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.963</td><td>&#x2212;1.66&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.99 (&#x2212;12.0 to 14.3)</td><td>4.13&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.20 (0.2&#x2013;14.3)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>5.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.959</td><td>1.33&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.24 (&#x2212;11.8 to 14.0)</td><td>4.22&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.32 (0.5&#x2013;14.0)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>3.</td><td>C<sub>0</sub>, C<sub>2</sub>, C<sub>4</sub></td><td>0.965</td><td>&#x2212;0.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.79 (&#x2212;10.4 to 13.7)</td><td>3.64&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.06 (0.2&#x2013;13.7)</td><td>37 (100%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Number and percentage of calculated AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> with a prediction error within 15%.</p><p><sup>b</sup>Bayesian estimation of the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>.</p><p><sup>c</sup>Limited sample strategies derived from the linear trapezoidal rule and the actual AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub>.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>An overview of the predictive performances of the limited sampling strategies published using 37 different pharmacokinetic profiles recorded in our renal transplant recipients. The number of limited sampling strategies categorized into the percentage of AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> within a prediction error of &lt;15% is plotted on the <italic>x</italic>-axis, the number of limited sampling strategies is plotted on the <italic>y</italic>-axis </p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="228_2007_354_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our results confirm the results of several other studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] that trough concentrations C<sub>0</sub> and C<sub>12</sub> have a lower predictive value for the complete 12-h AUC than almost all other studied LSS. The predictivity of LSS based on Bayesian estimation of the AUC<sub>actual</sub> was lower than the LSS based on regression analysis. Therefore a trough level and one or two time points in the early phase (&#x2264;4&#xA0;h) post-dose seem not to be sufficient for a Bayesian estimation strategy to fit correctly most of the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> and thus predict the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> reliably. The differences in variability and shape between the curves of post-transplant recipients combined with just two or three sample points might have been caused by the large differences found between the AUC<sub>pred</sub> calculated according to the Bayesian estimation strategy and the complete AUC<sub>actual</sub>.</p>
      <p>In contrast to most studies that describe LSS for tacrolimus in literature, we used an HPLC-MS/MS assay to determine the tacrolimus concentration. Because there seems to be a fixed difference of about 15% between the immunoassay and the HPLC-MS/MS, the prediction will change proportionally, and the predictivity of the LSS will be the same. Also potential interfering drug-drug interactions will have an equal influence on the different tacrolimus concentrations, which consequently has no effect on the predictivity of the different LSS.</p>
      <p>Ting et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] recently suggested that LSS should only be applied on transplant patient populations that are comparable with the transplant patient population that was used to develop the LSS. However, the renal transplant patient group examined in the present study was not exactly comparable with the transplant patient populations in which the equations for the LSS were developed. For example Aumente Rubio et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] and Ragette et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] used heart and lung transplant recipients respectively to develop and validate their LSS. Despite the fact that the LSS were developed with the pharmacokinetic profiles of patients who underwent a different kind of transplantation, Eqs. (5), (24) and (26) were able to predict at least 90% of the AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> within an APE of 15%, which suggests that these LSS are more robust than expected by Ting et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Even though LSS gave a better reflection of the tacrolimus exposure, they are currently not often applied by clinical transplant practioners, possibly for logistical and financial reasons.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, after validating several LSS from the literature, the present study indicates that all but three LSS gave a better prediction of the complete AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> than the trough concentrations C<sub>0</sub> or C<sub>12</sub>. Moreover, LSS could produce satisfactory predictions for AUC<sub>0&#x2013;12</sub> recorded in an independent renal transplant patient population, although further evaluation of their reliability is necessary.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We would like to thank Mrs Monique Mullens and Mr John Dackus (Department of Internal Medicine, University Hospital Maastricht, the Netherlands) for their excellent work regarding the extensive blood sample collection required to record a pharmacokinetic profile for each renal transplant patient.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mahalati</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kahan</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacological surrogates of allograft outcome</article-title>
          <source>Ann Transplant</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>14</fpage>
          <lpage>23</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mahalati K, Kahan BD (2000) Pharmacological surrogates of allograft outcome. Ann Transplant 5(2):14&#x2013;23 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11217202</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winkler</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christians</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A risk-benefit assessment of tacrolimus in transplantation</article-title>
          <source>Drug Saf</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>348</fpage>
          <lpage>357</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Winkler M, Christians U (1995) A risk-benefit assessment of tacrolimus in transplantation. Drug Saf 12(5):348&#x2013;357 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7545405</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McMaster</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mirza</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ismail</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vennarecci</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Patapis</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayer</surname>
              <given-names>AD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Therapeutic drug monitoring of tacrolimus in clinical transplantation</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>602</fpage>
          <lpage>605</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007691-199512000-00010</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McMaster P, Mirza DF, Ismail T, Vennarecci G, Patapis P, Mayer AD (1995) Therapeutic drug monitoring of tacrolimus in clinical transplantation. Ther Drug Monit 17(6):602&#x2013;605 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8588228</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Staatz</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tett</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of tacrolimus in solid organ transplantation</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>623</fpage>
          <lpage>653</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003088-200443100-00001</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Staatz CE, Tett SE (2004) Clinical pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics of tacrolimus in solid organ transplantation. Clin Pharmacokinet 43(10):623&#x2013;653 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15244495</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Laskow</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vincenti</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Neylan</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mendez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matas</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An open-label, concentration-ranging trial of FK506 in primary kidney transplantation: a report of the United States Multicenter FK506 Kidney Transplant Group</article-title>
          <source>Transplantation</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>900</fpage>
          <lpage>905</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007890-199610150-00005</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Laskow DA, Vincenti F, Neylan JF, Mendez R, Matas AJ (1996) An open-label, concentration-ranging trial of FK506 in primary kidney transplantation: a report of the United States Multicenter FK506 Kidney Transplant Group. Transplantation 62(7):900&#x2013;905 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8878381</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kershner</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fitzsimmons</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship of FK506 whole blood concentrations and efficacy and toxicity after liver and kidney transplantation</article-title>
          <source>Transplantation</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>62</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>920</fpage>
          <lpage>926</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007890-199610150-00009</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kershner RP, Fitzsimmons WE (1996) Relationship of FK506 whole blood concentrations and efficacy and toxicity after liver and kidney transplantation. Transplantation 62(7):920&#x2013;926 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8878385</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Undre</surname>
              <given-names>NA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hooff</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christiaans</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanrenterghem</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Donck</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heeman</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low systemic exposure to tacrolimus correlates with acute rejection</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <issue>1&#x2013;2</issue>
          <fpage>296</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(98)01633-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Undre NA, van Hooff J, Christiaans M, Vanrenterghem Y, Donck J, Heeman U et al (1999) Low systemic exposure to tacrolimus correlates with acute rejection. Transplant Proc 31(1&#x2013;2):296&#x2013;298 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10083114</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schutz</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Talaulicar</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grupp</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Undre</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacokinetics of tacrolimus primary immunosuppression in kidney transplant recipients</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>2127</fpage>
          <lpage>2128</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(01)01970-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Braun F, Schutz E, Peters B, Talaulicar R, Grupp C, Undre N et al (2001) Pharmacokinetics of tacrolimus primary immunosuppression in kidney transplant recipients. Transplant Proc 33(3):2127&#x2013;2128 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11377473</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Backman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levy</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Distant</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eisenstein</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Renard</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Whole blood and plasma levels of FK 506 after liver transplantation: correlation with toxicity</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>1804</fpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Backman L, Nicar M, Levy M, Distant D, Eisenstein C, Renard T et al (1994) Whole blood and plasma levels of FK 506 after liver transplantation: correlation with toxicity. Transplant Proc 26(3):1804 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7518160</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takahara</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kokado</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kameoka</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takano</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moutabarrik</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Monitoring of FK 506 blood levels in kidney transplant recipients</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>2106</fpage>
          <lpage>2108</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Takahara S, Kokado Y, Kameoka H, Takano Y, Jiang H, Moutabarrik A et al (1994) Monitoring of FK 506 blood levels in kidney transplant recipients. Transplant Proc 26(4):2106&#x2013;2108 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7520623</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winkler</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ringe</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rodeck</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melter</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stoll</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baumann</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The use of plasma levels for FK 506 dosing in liver-grafted patients</article-title>
          <source>Transpl Int</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>333</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00336707</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Winkler M, Ringe B, Rodeck B, Melter M, Stoll K, Baumann J et al (1994) The use of plasma levels for FK 506 dosing in liver-grafted patients. Transpl Int 7(5):329&#x2013;333 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7527638</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Armendariz</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pou</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantarell</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perello</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Capdevila</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of a limited sampling strategy to estimate area under the curve of tacrolimus in adult renal transplant patients</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>431</fpage>
          <lpage>434</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ftd.0000158080.61201.65</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Armendariz Y, Pou L, Cantarell C, Lopez R, Perello M, Capdevila L (2005) Evaluation of a limited sampling strategy to estimate area under the curve of tacrolimus in adult renal transplant patients. Ther Drug Monit 27(4):431&#x2013;434 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16044098</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balbontin</surname>
              <given-names>FG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiberd</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Squires</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Singh</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraser</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belitsky</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tacrolimus monitoring by simplified sparse sampling under the concentration time curve</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>2445</fpage>
          <lpage>2448</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.transproceed.2003.08.020</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Balbontin FG, Kiberd B, Squires J, Singh D, Fraser A, Belitsky P et al (2003) Tacrolimus monitoring by simplified sparse sampling under the concentration time curve. Transplant Proc 35(7):2445&#x2013;2448 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14611982</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kuypers</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claes</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Evenepoel</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maes</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coosemans</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pirenne</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Time-related clinical determinants of long-term tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in combination therapy with mycophenolic acid and corticosteroids: a prospective study in one hundred de novo renal transplant recipients</article-title>
          <source>Clin Pharmacokinet</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>741</fpage>
          <lpage>762</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2165/00003088-200443110-00005</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kuypers DR, Claes K, Evenepoel P, Maes B, Coosemans W, Pirenne J et al (2004) Time-related clinical determinants of long-term tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in combination therapy with mycophenolic acid and corticosteroids: a prospective study in one hundred de novo renal transplant recipients. Clin Pharmacokinet 43(11):741&#x2013;762 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15301578</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scholten</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cremers</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoemaker</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rowshani</surname>
              <given-names>AT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kan</surname>
              <given-names>EJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hartigh</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>AUC-guided dosing of tacrolimus prevents progressive systemic overexposure in renal transplant recipients</article-title>
          <source>Kidney Int</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>2440</fpage>
          <lpage>2447</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1755.2005.00352.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Scholten EM, Cremers SC, Schoemaker RC, Rowshani AT, van Kan EJ, den Hartigh J et al (2005) AUC-guided dosing of tacrolimus prevents progressive systemic overexposure in renal transplant recipients. Kidney Int 67(6):2440&#x2013;2447 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15882290</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>KM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shek</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chau</surname>
              <given-names>KF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Abbreviated tacrolimus area-under-the-curve monitoring for renal transplant recipients</article-title>
          <source>Am J Kidney Dis</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>660</fpage>
          <lpage>666</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wong KM, Shek CC, Chau KF, Li CS (2000) Abbreviated tacrolimus area-under-the-curve monitoring for renal transplant recipients. Am J Kidney Dis 35(4):660&#x2013;666 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10739787</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stolk</surname>
              <given-names>LM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Duijnhoven</surname>
              <given-names>EM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Christiaans</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hooff</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trough levels of tacrolimus</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>573</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007691-200208000-00019</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stolk LM, Van Duijnhoven EM, Christiaans MH, van Hooff JP (2002) Trough levels of tacrolimus. Ther Drug Monit 24(4):573; author reply, 4 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12142646</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pisitkun</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eiam-Ong</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chusil</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Praditpornsilpa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pansin</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tungsanga</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The roles of C4 and AUC0-4 in monitoring of tacrolimus in stable kidney transplant patients</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>8</issue>
          <fpage>3173</fpage>
          <lpage>3175</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(02)03684-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pisitkun T, Eiam-Ong S, Chusil S, Praditpornsilpa K, Pansin P, Tungsanga K (2002) The roles of C4 and AUC0-4 in monitoring of tacrolimus in stable kidney transplant patients. Transplant Proc 34(8):3173&#x2013;3175 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12493410</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ku</surname>
              <given-names>YM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Min</surname>
              <given-names>DI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An abbreviated area-under-the-curve monitoring for tacrolimus in patients with liver transplants</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007691-199804000-00014</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ku YM, Min DI (1998) An abbreviated area-under-the-curve monitoring for tacrolimus in patients with liver transplants. Ther Drug Monit 20(2):219&#x2013;223 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9558138</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aumente Rubio</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arizon del Prado</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez Malo de Molina</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cardenas Aranzana</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Segura Saint-Gerons</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez Granados</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical pharmacokinetics of tacrolimus in heart transplantation: new strategies of monitoring</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>1988</fpage>
          <lpage>1991</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(03)00656-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aumente Rubio MD, Arizon del Prado JM, Lopez Malo de Molina MD, Cardenas Aranzana M, Segura Saint-Gerons J, Lopez Granados A et al (2003) Clinical pharmacokinetics of tacrolimus in heart transplantation: new strategies of monitoring. Transplant Proc 35(5):1988&#x2013;1991 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12962871</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sgrosso</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Araujo</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vazquez</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in heart transplant</article-title>
          <source>Transplant Proc</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>142</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0041-1345(01)02706-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sgrosso JL, Araujo GL, Vazquez MC (2002) Tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in heart transplant. Transplant Proc 34(1):142&#x2013;143 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11959225</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ragette</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamler</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weinreich</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Teschler</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jakob</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in lung transplantation: new strategies for monitoring</article-title>
          <source>J Heart Lung Transplant</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>1315</fpage>
          <lpage>1319</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.healun.2004.09.001</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ragette R, Kamler M, Weinreich G, Teschler H, Jakob H (2005) Tacrolimus pharmacokinetics in lung transplantation: new strategies for monitoring. J Heart Lung Transplant 24(9):1315&#x2013;1319 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16143250</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ting</surname>
              <given-names>LS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villeneuve</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ensom</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Beyond cyclosporine: a systematic review of limited sampling strategies for other immunosuppressants</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>419</fpage>
          <lpage>430</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ftd.0000211810.19935.44</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ting LS, Villeneuve E, Ensom MH (2006) Beyond cyclosporine: a systematic review of limited sampling strategies for other immunosuppressants. Ther Drug Monit 28(3):419&#x2013;430 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16778729</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sheiner</surname>
              <given-names>LB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Beal</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Some suggestions for measuring predictive performance</article-title>
          <source>J Pharmacokinet Biopharm</source>
          <year>1981</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>503</fpage>
          <lpage>512</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01060893</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sheiner LB, Beal SL (1981) Some suggestions for measuring predictive performance. J Pharmacokinet Biopharm 9(4):503&#x2013;512 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7310648</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meier-Kriesche</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaplan</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brannan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kahan</surname>
              <given-names>BD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Portman</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A limited sampling strategy for the estimation of eight-hour neoral areas under the curve in renal transplantation</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>407</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007691-199808000-00009</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Meier-Kriesche HU, Kaplan B, Brannan P, Kahan BD, Portman RJ (1998) A limited sampling strategy for the estimation of eight-hour neoral areas under the curve in renal transplantation. Ther Drug Monit 20(4):401&#x2013;407 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9712465</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>David</surname>
              <given-names>OJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnston</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Limited sampling strategies for estimating cyclosporin area under the concentration-time curve: review of current algorithms</article-title>
          <source>Ther Drug Monit</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>100</fpage>
          <lpage>114</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00007691-200104000-00003</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">David OJ, Johnston A (2001) Limited sampling strategies for estimating cyclosporin area under the concentration-time curve: review of current algorithms. Ther Drug Monit 23(2):100&#x2013;114 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11294509</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>