<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>European Archives of Oto-Rhino-Laryngology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0937-4477</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1434-4726</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17657505</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2099162</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">402</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00405-007-0402-1</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Tonsillar metastasis of oesophageal adenocarcinoma</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Struijs</surname>
            <given-names>Bram</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>de Bree</surname>
            <given-names>Remco</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-20-4443690</phone>
            <fax>+31-20-4443688</fax>
            <email>r.bree@vumc.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van Groeningen</surname>
            <given-names>Cornelis J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mooi</surname>
            <given-names>Wolter J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ren&#xE9; Leemans</surname>
            <given-names>C.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Otolaryngology and Head and Neck Surgery, VU University Medical Center, De Boelelaan 1117, 1081 HV Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Medical Oncology, VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Pathology, VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>27</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>265</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>127</fpage>
      <lpage>129</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In the literature less than 100 cases of metastatic carcinoma of the palatine tonsil have been reported. Tonsillar metastasis of adenocarcinoma of the oesophagus has not been reported previously. We report a case of a 57-year-old male with a primary adenocarcinoma of the distal esophagus with a metastasis in the right palatine tonsil. Metastatic tumour involving the palatine tonsil is rare. The route of dissemination remains unclear. Hypothetically the dissemination of tumour cells could be lymphogenic or secondary by transportation due to vomiting or at the time of endoscopy, but most likely represents haematogenous spread.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Tonsil</kwd>
        <kwd>Metastasis</kwd>
        <kwd>Adenocarcinoma</kwd>
        <kwd>Oesophagus</kwd>
        <kwd>Head and neck</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The vast majority of cancers in the head and neck region are of epithelial origin. Lymphoma is the next most common malignancy in this area. Metastases in the head and neck other than lymph node metastases are rare.</p>
      <p>The occurrence of tonsillar metastases from non-haematological malignant neoplasms is very rare [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. We present a patient with metastasis in the right tonsil of a primary adenocarcinoma of the distal oesophagus.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case report</title>
      <p>A 57-year-old man was referred to our department of otolaryngology and head and neck surgery, because of dysphagia, pain and swelling of the right palatine tonsil. He also complained of frequent vomiting. Five months previously, an adenocarcinoma of the distal oesophagus with lymph node and liver metastases had been diagnosed. He received chemotherapy with combined capecitabine and oxaliplatin, which was stopped after two cycles because of disease progression. On physical examination an enlarged and ulcerating right palatine tonsil was seen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). A suspicious ipsilateral cervical lymph node of 2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;4&#xA0;cm was found at level II. A biopsy of the tonsillar tumour was performed and revealed intestinal-type adenocarcinoma. The histopathological picture corresponded with that of the oesophageal tumour (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Tonsillectomy was not performed because of severe clotting disorders attributed to liver metastases. The patient died 4&#xA0;weeks after his first visit to our department.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Enlarged right palatine tonsil with ulceration</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="405_2007_402_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Biopsy right tonsil: adenocarcinoma (intestinal type)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="405_2007_402_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Second primary tumours relatively often involve the head and neck region. These tumours develop in head and neck cancer patients due to their common factors in carcinogenesis, e.g., tobacco, alcohol and, probably, genetic susceptibility [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. However, this common aetiology applies for squamous cell carcinoma and not for adenocarcinoma. Simultaneous primary adenocarcinomas are not frequently found. In our patient the corresponding histopathology indicates a common origin, suggesting metastatic disease.</p>
      <p>Primary oesophageal adenocarcinoma is a relatively uncommon tumour in western countries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. The pattern of metastasis of oesophageal adenocarcinoma can be lymphogenic, haematogenic and by transportation of tumour cells by regurgitation or endoscopes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">10</xref>]. Lymphogenic spread of distal oesophageal adenocarcinoma generally involves the regional nodes in the lower posterior mediastinum, the paracardiac region, along the lesser curvature and the left gastric artery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. In case of extensive lymphogenic spread, lymph-node metastases can be found in the tracheal bifurcation region, the proximal mediastinum, coeliac axis and supra-clavicular region [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Lymphogenic spread of adenocarcinoma of the distal oesophagus and the gastro-oesophageal junction is present in 70% of the patients at the time of diagnosis of the primary tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Haematogenous dissemination occurs at a later stage and is less frequent. Liver and lung are the most common organs involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
      <p>Metastatic tumour involving the palatine tonsil is distinctly rare. These metastases represent only 0.8% of all tonsillar tumours [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Bilateral metastases of gastric carcinoma to the tonsils have been described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Less than 100 cases of metastatic carcinoma of the palatine tonsil have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">7</xref>]. The most frequent tumours metastasizing to the tonsil are melanoma, lung carcinoma, breast carcinoma and renal cell carcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Eleven cases were associated with gastric adenocarcinoma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Tonsillar metastasis of adenocarcinoma of the esophagus has not been reported previously. The occurrence of a tonsillar metastasis as the first manifestation of an occult neoplasm is very unusual [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. In the majority of cases the occurrence of a tonsillar metastasis becomes manifest after the diagnosis of the primary tumour and is generally part of a widespread systemic disease [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Therefore, mean survival time for patients with tonsillar metastases is short, with a mean of 9&#xA0;months, irrespective of the histological type of primary tumour [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>In this case there are four hypothetical pathways for metastatic spread to the tonsils: Haematogenous dissemination of tumour from an esophageal carcinoma may occur via the portal circulation, the liver, the pulmonary circulation and systemic arterial vessels, thus reaching the palatine tonsil. A second haematogenous route may be through the paravertebral plexus of Batson, bypassing the lungs [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Retrograde flow via this valveless plexus occurs during elevated intra-abdominal and intrathoracic pressure, as is brought about by straining, coughing or as in this case, vomiting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. A third route of metastasis may be through the thoracic duct followed by retrograde cervical lymphatic spread to the tonsil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. This route of dissemination is very rare and is mostly seen in cases of seminomas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Finally, some authors believe the possibility of metastasis by direct translumenal implantation, which might be favoured by a previous lesion in the mucosa of the tonsil [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The tumour cells would be transported secondary to regurgitation from the oesophagus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>], or as in this case possibly because of frequent vomiting, or at the time of endoscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>In conclusion, when finding a tumour of the tonsil a metastasis from a distant primary malignancy should be considered, although this is very rare. The route of dissemination eventually remains unclear.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Batson</surname>
              <given-names>OV</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The role of the vertebral veins in metastatic process</article-title>
          <source>Ann Intern Med</source>
          <year>1942</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Batson OV (1942) The role of the vertebral veins in metastatic process. Ann Intern Med 16:38&#x2013;45 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Benito</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alvarez-gago</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morais</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tonsillar metastasis from adenocarcinoma of the stomach</article-title>
          <source>J laryngol Otol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>291</fpage>
          <lpage>293</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Benito I, Alvarez-gago T, Morais D (1996) Tonsillar metastasis from adenocarcinoma of the stomach. J laryngol Otol 110:291&#x2013;293 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8730375</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brownson</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jaques</surname>
              <given-names>WE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lamonte</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zollinger</surname>
              <given-names>WK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypernephroma metastatic to the palatine tonsils</article-title>
          <source>Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>235</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brownson RJ, Jaques WE, Lamonte SE, Zollinger WK (1979) Hypernephroma metastatic to the palatine tonsils. Ann Otol Rhinol Laryngol 88:235&#x2013;240 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">443718</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cloos</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spitz</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schantz</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Genetic susceptibility to head and neck squamous cell carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>J Natl Cancer Inst</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>530</fpage>
          <lpage>535</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jnci/88.8.530</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cloos J, Spitz MR, Schantz SP et al (1996) Genetic susceptibility to head and neck squamous cell carcinoma. J Natl Cancer Inst 88:530&#x2013;535 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8606381</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crawford</surname>
              <given-names>BE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Callihan</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corio</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hyams</surname>
              <given-names>VJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karnei</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Symposium on malignant disease of the oral cavity and related structures</article-title>
          <source>Otolaryngol Clin North Am</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>29</fpage>
          <lpage>43</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Crawford BE, Callihan MD, Corio RL, Hyams VJ, Karnei RF (1979) Symposium on malignant disease of the oral cavity and related structures. Otolaryngol Clin North Am 12:29&#x2013;43 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">220581</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Feith</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stein</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siewert</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pattern of lymphatic spread of Barrett&#x2019;s cancer</article-title>
          <source>World J Surg</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>1052</fpage>
          <lpage>1057</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00268-003-7060-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Feith M, Stein HJ, Siewert JR (2003) Pattern of lymphatic spread of Barrett&#x2019;s cancer. World J Surg 27:1052&#x2013;1057 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12917758</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gallo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pescarmona</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crupi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Corsetti</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vincentiis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bilateral tonsillar metastasis of gastric adenocarcinomas</article-title>
          <source>Head Neck Surg</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>57</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/hed.2880140112</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gallo A, Pescarmona E, Crupi J, Corsetti GL, De Vincentiis M (1992) Bilateral tonsillar metastasis of gastric adenocarcinomas. Head Neck Surg 14:55&#x2013;57 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hurlstone</surname>
              <given-names>DP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sanders</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>RB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slater</surname>
              <given-names>DN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bardhan</surname>
              <given-names>KD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tonsillar metastasis: a rare presentation of gastric carcinoma</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Surg Oncol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>328</fpage>
          <lpage>330</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/ejso.2000.1042</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hurlstone DP, Sanders DS, Smith A, Jones RB, Slater DN, Bardhan KD (2001) Tonsillar metastasis: a rare presentation of gastric carcinoma. Eur J Surg Oncol 27(3):328&#x2013;330 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11373114</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Juan S&#xE1;nchez Jim&#xE9;nez et al (2005) Metastatic tumours in upper maxillary bone of esophageal adenocarcinoma. A case report. Med Oral Patol Oral Cir Bucal 10:252&#x2013;257</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kleinschmidt</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tonsillen Metastasen bei primaren Bronchial- und Magenkarzinom</article-title>
          <source>Z Laryngol Rhinol Otol</source>
          <year>1966</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>394</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kleinschmidt HJ (1966) Tonsillen Metastasen bei primaren Bronchial- und Magenkarzinom. Z Laryngol Rhinol Otol 45:389&#x2013;394 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5985937</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>