<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>European Radiology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0938-7994</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1084</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17562048</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2039819</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">681</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-007-0681-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Cardiac</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Coronary fly-through or virtual angioscopy using dual-source MDCT data</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van Ooijen</surname>
            <given-names>Peter M. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-50-3612286</phone>
            <email>p.m.a.van.ooijen@rad.umcg.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>de Jonge</surname>
            <given-names>Gonda</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Oudkerk</surname>
            <given-names>Matthijs</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Radiology, University Medical Center Groningen, University of Groningen, Hanzeplein 1, 9700 RB Groningen, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>11</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <issue>11</issue>
      <fpage>2852</fpage>
      <lpage>2859</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>23</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Coronary fly-through or virtual angioscopy (VA) has been studied ever since its invention in 2000. However, application was limited because it requires an optimal computed tomography (CT) scan and time-consuming post-processing. Recent advances in post-processing software facilitate easy construction of VA, but until now image quality was insufficient in most patients. The introduction of dual-source multidetector CT (MDCT) could enable VA in all patients. Twenty patients were scanned using a dual-source MDCT (Definition, Siemens, Forchheim, Germany) using a standard coronary artery protocol. Post-processing was performed on an Aquarius Workstation (TeraRecon, San Mateo, Calif.). Length travelled per major branch was recorded in millimetres, together with the time required in minutes. VA could be performed in every patient for each of the major coronary arteries. The mean (range) length of the automated fly-through was 80 (32&#x2013;107) mm for the left anterior descending (LAD), 75 (21&#x2013;116) mm for the left circumflex artery (LCx), and 109 (21&#x2013;190) mm for the right coronary artery (RCA). Calcifications and stenoses were visualised, as well as most side branches. The mean time required was 3&#xA0;min for LAD, 2.5&#xA0;min for LCx, and 2&#xA0;min for the RCA. Dual-source MDCT allows for high quality visualisation of the coronary arteries in every patient because scanning with this machine is independent of the heart rate. This is clearly shown by the successful VA in all patients. Potential clinical value of VA should be determined in the near future.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Virtual angioscopy</kwd>
        <kwd>Coronary arteries</kwd>
        <kwd>Coronary fly-through</kwd>
        <kwd>Post-processing</kwd>
        <kwd>Dual-source CT</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; European Society of Radiology 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Coronary fly-through or virtual angioscopy (VA) using various generations of computed tomography (CT) devices has been reported in a number of publications since its first mention in 2000 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Main reason for the minimal research on this topic was the limited application because of the requirements for an optimal CT scan and time consuming post-processing. Recent advances in post-processing software facilitate easy construction of VA, but until now image quality of coronary CT was insufficient in most patients. The introduction of dual-source multidetector CT (MDCT) has shown a more stable quality of data in all patients because of higher temporal resolutions, which could prove to enable VA in all patients and allow investigation of the clinical value of this visualisation technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <p>Twenty patients (13 male, mean age 60&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13&#xA0;years old) were selected at random from patients scanned for coronary artery disease using a standard coronary artery protocol on a dual source MDCT (Definition, Siemens, Forchheim, Germany).</p>
      <p>Post-processing was performed on an Aquarius Workstation (TeraRecon, San Mateo, Calif.). The software allows an automatic vessel fly-through, which provides inside front and rear views, together with a view of the path and location on the surface of the heart (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Besides this, three multiplanar reformation planes (sagittal, coronal and axial) are shown for the location of the camera. Length travelled per major branch was recorded in millimetres, together with the time required in minutes to perform the evaluation per major branch. Ostia of side branches were visualised, but no fly-through of those side branches was performed.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Large trajectory visualisation of the right coronary artery (RCA)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>VA could be performed semi-automatically with minor user interaction in every patient for each of the major coronary arteries using dual-source CT (DSCT).</p>
      <p>The mean (range) length of the automated fly-through was 80 (32&#x2013;107) mm for the left anterior descending (LAD), 75 (21&#x2013;116) mm for the left circumflex artery (LCx), and 109 (21&#x2013;190) mm for the RCA.</p>
      <p>Calcifications were clearly visualised as white structures floating inside the lumen. Stenoses were visualised when present by indentations of the lumen wall (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Visibility of the actual size of the stent lumen was still limited, but fly-through was possible in the stents we found (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Visibility of a stenotic lesion</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Stent visibility</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>The major side branches of the main coronary arteries could be detected during the fly-through (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). No fly-through was performed through those side branches.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Visibility of major side branches</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>The mean time required was 3&#xA0;min for LAD, 2.5&#xA0;min for LCx, and 2&#xA0;min for the RCA.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The introduction of DSCT enables 100% visualisation of all major arteries and thus demonstrates a major gain in image quality compared with electron beam CT (EBCT) and MDCT, with only 76% and 84% assessable, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>].</p>
      <p>Furthermore, the time required for processing the data decreased to about 2.5&#xA0;min compared with the 6-13&#xA0;min required in 2002 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Notice that the times shown in the table for EBCT and MDCT do not include the actual computing time, which could be hours with the hard- and software at that time. Currently, all computation and visualisation is in real time and thus included in the 2.5&#xA0;min required for a coronary fly-through of a major branch using DSCT data. 
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Results of an earlier study using EBCT and four-slice MDCT (<italic>4-MDCT</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] in comparison with the DSCT results of the current study</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>&#xA0;</th><th>EBCT (2002)</th><th>4-MDCT (2002)</th><th>DSCT (2006)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>LAD</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Percentage assessable</td><td>14/15 (93%)</td><td>14/15 (93%)</td><td>20/20 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean preparation time (min)</td><td>12</td><td>13</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean number of key frames</td><td>13</td><td>16</td><td><italic>n.a.</italic></td></tr><tr><td>LC</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Percentage assessable</td><td>11/15 (73%)</td><td>10/15 (67%)</td><td>20/20 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean preparation time (min)</td><td>7</td><td>10</td><td>2.5</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean number of key frames</td><td>9</td><td>13<sup>*</sup></td><td><italic>n.a.</italic></td></tr><tr><td>RCA</td><td/><td/><td/></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Percentage assessable</td><td>9/15 (60%)</td><td>14/15 (95%)</td><td>20/20 (100%)</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean preparation time (min)</td><td>6</td><td>10</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Mean number of key frames</td><td>8</td><td>14</td><td><italic>n.a.</italic></td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Total percentage assessable</td><td>34/45 (76%)</td><td>38/45 (84%)</td><td>60/60 (100%)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The number of key frames is no longer applicable (<italic>n.a.</italic>) for the current software tools that can perform the coronary fly-through in real time</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Different artefacts still hamper the fly-through. First, non-optimal reconstruction will present itself as a sudden change in the form of the vessel wall. The effects are shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, and it will be clear that these artefacts can be easily recognised because of the non-natural shape of the wall. A more difficult artefact is cause by motion. Here, the artefact can be easily appreciated on the three-dimensional view, but in the fly-through it presents as a apparent stenosis (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>).
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Problems with artefacts in non-optimal reconstructed datasets</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Problems with motion artefacts causing apparent stenoses</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      <p>Finally, surgical clips in bypasses still pose a problem as already shown an earlier publication using EBCT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>Visualisation is hampered by presence of surgical clips in a bypass graft</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_681_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
      <p>All three articles that (to our best knowledge) are available on this topic conclude with similar remarks [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. They all state that the coronary fly-through or virtual coronary angioscopy (VCA) is a promising technique that, however, requires higher quality of the datasets and better image processing software.</p>
      <p>A shortcoming of our study was the lack of a &#x201C;gold standard&#x201D; to confirm the findings of the coronary fly-through.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Dual-source MDCT provides a high quality visualisation of the coronary artery tree, independently of the heart rate. This is clearly shown by the successful VCA in all 20 patients in this study. With recent advancements of image processing software and CT acquisition techniques, the conditions have been met for providing the technical basis for the clinical validation of VCA and the potential clinical value of VCA should be determined in the near future.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ooijen</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oudkerk</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geuns</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rensing</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feyter</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Coronary artery fly-through using electron beam computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>E6</fpage>
          <lpage>E10</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Ooijen PM, Oudkerk M, van Geuns RJ, Rensing BJ, de Feyter PJ (2000) Coronary artery fly-through using electron beam computed tomography. Circulation 102(1):E6&#x2013;E10 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10880428</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schroeder</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kopp</surname>
              <given-names>AF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohnesorge</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Loke-Gie</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuettner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baumbach</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Herdeg</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Claussen</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karsch</surname>
              <given-names>KR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Virtual coronary angioscopy using multislice computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Heart</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>209</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1136/heart.87.3.205</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schroeder S, Kopp AF, Ohnesorge B, Loke-Gie H, Kuettner A, Baumbach A, Herdeg C, Claussen CD, Karsch KR (2002) Virtual coronary angioscopy using multislice computed tomography. Heart 87(3):205&#x2013;209 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11847152</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ooijen</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nieman</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feyter</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oudkerk</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Noninvasive coronary angioscopy using electron beam computed tomography and multidetector computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Am J Cardiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>998</fpage>
          <lpage>1002</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0002-9149(02)02686-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Ooijen PM, Nieman K, de Feyter PJ, Oudkerk M (2002) Noninvasive coronary angioscopy using electron beam computed tomography and multidetector computed tomography. Am J Cardiol 90(9):998&#x2013;1002 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12398971</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scheffel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alkadhi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Plass</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vachenauer</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Desbiolles</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gaemperli</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schepis</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frauenfelder</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schertler</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Husmann</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grunenfelder</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Genoni</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaufmann</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marincek</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leschka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accuracy of dual-source CT coronary angiography: First experience in a high pre-test probability population without heart rate control</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>12</issue>
          <fpage>2739</fpage>
          <lpage>2747</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-006-0474-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Scheffel H, Alkadhi H, Plass A, Vachenauer R, Desbiolles L, Gaemperli O, Schepis T, Frauenfelder T, Schertler T, Husmann L, Grunenfelder J, Genoni M, Kaufmann PA, Marincek B, Leschka S (2006) Accuracy of dual-source CT coronary angiography: First experience in a high pre-test probability population without heart rate control. Eur Radiol 16(12):2739&#x2013;2747 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17031451</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nikolaou</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wintersperger</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leber</surname>
              <given-names>AW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ziegler</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rist</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buhmann</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knez</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reiser</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dual-source CT cardiac imaging: initial experience</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1409</fpage>
          <lpage>1415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-006-0298-y</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Johnson TR, Nikolaou K, Wintersperger BJ, Leber AW, von Ziegler F, Rist C, Buhmann S, Knez A, Reiser MF, Becker CR (2006) Dual-source CT cardiac imaging: initial experience. Eur Radiol 16(7):1409&#x2013;1415 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770652</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flohr</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCollough</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruder</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Petersilka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gruber</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suss</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grasruck</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stierstorfer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krauss</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raupach</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Primak</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuttner</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Achenbach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kopp</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohnesorge</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First performance evaluation of a dual-source CT (DSCT) system</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-005-2919-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Flohr TG, McCollough CH, Bruder H, Petersilka M, Gruber K, Suss C, Grasruck M, Stierstorfer K, Krauss B, Raupach R, Primak AN, Kuttner A, Achenbach S, Becker C, Kopp A, Ohnesorge BM (2006) First performance evaluation of a dual-source CT (DSCT) system. Eur Radiol 16(2):256&#x2013;268 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16341833</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>This work was presented as posters at the NASCI 2006 and the ESCR 2006</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>