<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="case-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Spine J</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="iso-abbrev">Eur Spine J</journal-id>
      <journal-title-group>
        <journal-title>European Spine Journal</journal-title>
      </journal-title-group>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0940-6719</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-0932</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16858595</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1602199</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">182</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00586-006-0182-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Case Report</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Endovascular treatment of an open cervical fracture with carotid artery tear</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Witz</surname>
            <given-names>Misha</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gepstein</surname>
            <given-names>Reuven</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Paran</surname>
            <given-names>Haim</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Shnaker</surname>
            <given-names>Ali</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Lehmann</surname>
            <given-names>Jonathan</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Gryton</surname>
            <given-names>Igal</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name>
            <surname>Shabat</surname>
            <given-names>Shay</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+972-9-7472642</phone>
            <fax>+972-9-7410596</fax>
            <email>drshabat@hotmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Vascular Surgery Unit, Sapir Medical Center, Kfar-Saba, Israel </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Spinal Care Unit, Sapir Medical Center, Kfar-Saba, Israel </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of General Surgery A, Sapir Medical Center, Kfar-Saba, Israel </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Department of Radiology, Unit of Invasive Radiology, Sapir Medical Center, Kfar-Saba, Israel </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>21</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>Suppl 5</issue>
      <fpage>650</fpage>
      <lpage>652</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>5</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2006</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract id="Abs1">
        <p>The dilemma of how to treat penetrating wound injuries to the neck, which involve a combination of a common carotid artery rupture and a cervical spinal fracture, is presented in this case report.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group xml:lang="en">
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Carotid artery tear</kwd>
        <kwd>Penetrating injury</kwd>
        <kwd>Cervical fracture</kwd>
        <kwd>Endovascular treatment</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-group>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2006</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Penetrating injuries of the carotid artery can pose a significant challenge to the vascular surgeon. This type of vascular trauma accounts for only 3% of patients studied retrospectively in most trauma centers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. The severity of injury varies from complete transection to formation of a pseudoaneurysm or initimal flap formation with or without occlusion. Traditionally, the treatment of these lesions has been surgical. However, limitations to obtain satisfactory vascular control led to the search for other alternative treatment options [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Recently, the management armamentarium has expanded with the advent of more sophisticated endovascular techniques [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Pseudoaneurysm of the common carotid artery after gunshot injury is a relatively infrequent finding. We present a case of a common carotid artery pseudoaneurysm managed by a commercially flexible covered stent.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Case history</title>
      <p>A 16-year-old adolescent was transferred to our institution from a different hospital for stabilization of a cervical spinal fracture. Six hours prior to his transfer he had sustained an isolated gunshot wound to his neck. He was quadraplegic and unconscious on his admission to the referring hospital and was therefore intubated and ventilated. CT scan of the cervical spine showed a blow-out fracture of the body of C6 with involvement of the left vertebral foramen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). CT scans of the brain and chest were within normal limits.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>CT scan at the C6 level demonstrating a vertebral body fracture extending into the left vertebral foramen</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="586_2006_182_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Upon admission to our institution his hemodynamic condition was stable with a blood pressure of 115/70&#xA0;mmHg and pulse of 60&#xA0;beats/minute. He was ventilated and had a SaO2 of 100% with FiO2 of 0.4. Physical examination of his neck area demonstrated an entry wound in the posterior neck to the left of the midline and an exit wound in the left side of his neck. A large hematoma on the left side of the neck was demonstrated and palpated. A duplex scan of the left carotid artery was performed and was interpreted as a probable false aneurysm of common carotid artery. CT angiogram of the neck demonstrated anterior and posterior leak of contrast from the common carotid artery, 1&#xA0;cm proximal to the bifurcation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The left vertebral artery was shown to be intact. The left internal jugular vein was compressed by the hematoma. The patient was transferred to the angiography suite and the presence of false aneurysms was confirmed. Under local anesthesia, through a transfemoral approach a catheter was inserted into the aneurysmatic area. The aneurysms were treated by the insertion of a covered stent (Jostent 8&#xA0;(&#xD7;&#xA0;38&#xA0;mm<sup>2</sup>), which also occluded the origin of the external carotid artery (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). No change in his neurological status after the insertion of the stent was seen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). No anticoagulation was given. His neck fracture was stabilized by an external fixation device and he was transferred back to the referring hospital.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Selective left common carotid artery angiography shows traumatic pseudoaneurysm 1&#xA0;cm below bifurcation</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="586_2006_182_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Selective common carotid artery angiography demonstrates endovascular stent&#x2014;extending proximal and distal to the borders of pseudoaneurysm with complete exclusion of pseudoaneurysm and external carotid artery</p></caption><graphic xlink:href="586_2006_182_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
      <p>One year later, duplex US follow-up showed good hemodynamics without stenosis. Clinically, no cranial lesions were found.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The use of endovascular stent-grafts to address arterial tears was first introduced by Dotter in 1969 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Over the past decade, endovascular grafting has been evaluated as an alternative to conventional surgical repair in the management of aneurysms and other vascular lesions. The application of this form of therapy to the management of vascular trauma offers many potential advantages. Angiography assists with the diagnosis of traumatic lesions such as intimal dissections [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. In addition, endovascular techniques can be utilized to help with vascular control, as an adjunct to surgery in regions where obtaining proximal or distal control is technically difficult. The use of endovascular stent-grafting for the definitive repair of traumatic lesions has been shown to be associated with a decrease in anesthetic requirement, blood loss and extent of dissection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. High-velocity missiles can produce a significant amount of tissue damage, even if not suspected on initial examination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The inherent problems of graft placement in the setting of severe tissue damage, gross contamination and scar tissue formation make the use of a remote insertion site particularly advantageous in the trauma patient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].</p>
      <p>Injury to the carotid artery constitutes only 3% of all arterial injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. In spite of the rarity of carotid injuries, this trauma presents significant challenges to the vascular surgeon. Gunshot wounds account for approximately half the injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Injury of the carotid artery is frequently associated with other organ injuries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Clinical examination may be unreliable due to confounding factors such as destructive injuries of spine, chest, abdomen, fractures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Therefore, imaging evaluation is essential for the identification and localization of carotid trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>In contrast to blunt carotid injury, treatment of penetrating injuries of the carotid artery has been primarily surgical [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Depending on the described clinical scenario the surgeon is left with several options, which are observation, anticoagulation, ligation of the carotid artery, balloon occlusion of the artery, resection with graft interposition or bypass procedure. However, the best definitive management remains controversial, as no prospective studies regarding the management of penetrating carotid injuries have been reported [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Only few case reports on internal carotid artery aneurysm and pseudoaneurysm treated with endovascular stent and coiling procedure have been published [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. In case of carotid trauma, surgical treatment would be difficult because of problems of exposing the bleeding carotid and to get enough vascular access.</p>
      <p>The combined evidences from all cases published in the medical literature support endovascular intervention for pseudoaneurysm of the carotid artery as a good clinical treatment choice. In our patient, we chose to use device graft to ensure complete exclusion of the pseudoaneurysm and external carotid artery without the need for endovascular coil placement. Further studies to investigate the role of endovascular treatment for penetrating carotid artery injury are indicated.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Biffe</surname>
              <given-names>WL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryn</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The unrecognized epidemic of blunt carotid arterial injuries. Early diagnosis improves neurologic outcome</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>228</volume>
          <fpage>462</fpage>
          <lpage>470</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-199810000-00003</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9790336</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dotter</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transluminally-placed coilspring endarterial tube grafts. Long-term patency in canine popliteal artery</article-title>
          <source>Invest Radiol</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>332</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00004424-196909000-00008</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5346893</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>du Toit</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strauss</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blaszczyk</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villiers</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warren</surname>
              <given-names>BL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endovascular treatment of penetrating thoracic outlet arterial injuries</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Vasc Endovasc Surg</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>489</fpage>
          <lpage>495</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/ejvs.1999.1050</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10828229</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khoury</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hajj</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khoury</surname>
              <given-names>SI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Basil</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Speir</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Penetrating trauma of the carotid vessels</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>607</fpage>
          <lpage>610</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0950-821X(05)80816-3</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2279571</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kramer</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pamler</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seifarth</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brambs</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sunder-Plassmann</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gorich</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Endovascular grafting of traumatic aortic aneurysms in contaminated fields</article-title>
          <source>J Endovasc Ther</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>262</fpage>
          <lpage>267</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1583/1545-1550(2001)008&lt;0262:EGOTAA&gt;2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11491260</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liekweg</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greenfield</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Management of penetrating carotid arterial injury</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>188</volume>
          <fpage>587</fpage>
          <lpage>592</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00000658-197811000-00001</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">718284</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veith</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transluminally-placed endovascular stented graft repair for arterial trauma</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>466</fpage>
          <lpage>473</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8084041</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martin</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Veith</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Panneta</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Percutaneous transfemoral insertion of a stented graft to repair a traumatic femoral arteriovenous fistula</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>302</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mva.1993.48841</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8350439</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McNeil</surname>
              <given-names>ID</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chion</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gunlock</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grayson</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Soares</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hagiuo</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Successful endovascular therapy of penetrating zone III internal carotid injury</article-title>
          <source>J Vasc Surg</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>190</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mva.2002.125020</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12096279</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Padberg</surname>
              <given-names>FT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hobson</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jeager</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lynch</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Penetrating carotidarterial trauma</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>50</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>282</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="other">Perry MO (1994) Vascular injuries in the neck and thoracic outlet. In: Veith FJ, Hobson RW, Williams RA (eds) Vascular surgery: principles and practice, 2nd edn. McGraw-Hill, New York, pp 967&#x2013;975</mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Soalea</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solafani</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interventional techniques in vascular trauma</article-title>
          <source>Surg Clin North Am</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0039-6109(05)70270-X</pub-id>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11218157</pub-id>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <mixed-citation publication-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Temberlake</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rice</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kerstein</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rush</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McSwain</surname>
              <given-names>NE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Penetrating injury to the carotid artery: a reappraisal of management</article-title>
          <source>Ann Surg</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>154</fpage>
          <lpage>157</lpage>
        </mixed-citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>