<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Eur Radiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>European Radiology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0938-7994</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1084</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17851666</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2077913</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">724</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-007-0724-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Cardiac</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Dual-source computed tomography in patients with acute chest pain: feasibility and image quality</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schertler</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Scheffel</surname>
            <given-names>Hans</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Frauenfelder</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Desbiolles</surname>
            <given-names>Lotus</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Leschka</surname>
            <given-names>Sebastian</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stolzmann</surname>
            <given-names>Paul</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Seifert</surname>
            <given-names>Burkhardt</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Flohr</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Marincek</surname>
            <given-names>Borut</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Alkadhi</surname>
            <given-names>Hatem</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>hatem.alkadhi@usz.ch</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Medical Radiology, Institute of Diagnostic Radiology, University Hospital Zurich, Raemistrasse 100CH-8091, Zurich, Switzerland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Biostatistics, University of Zurich, Zurich, Switzerland </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Siemens Medical Solutions, Computed Tomography CTE PA, Forchheim, Germany </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>13</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>17</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <fpage>3179</fpage>
      <lpage>3188</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>22</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The aim of this study was to determine the feasibility and image quality of dual-source computed tomography angiography (DSCTA) in patients with acute chest pain for the assessment of the lung, thoracic aorta, and for pulmonary and coronary arteries. Sixty consecutive patients (32 female, 28 male, mean age 58.1&#xB1;16.3&#xA0;years) with acute chest pain underwent contrast-enhanced electrocardiography-gated DSCTA without prior beta-blocker administration. Vessel attenuation of different thoracic vascular territories was measured, and image quality was semi-quantitatively analyzed by two independent readers. Image quality of the thoracic aorta was diagnostic in all 60 patients, image quality of pulmonary arteries was diagnostic in 59, and image quality of coronary arteries was diagnostic in 58 patients. Pairwise intraindividual comparisons of attenuation values were small and ranged between 1&#xB1;6&#xA0;HU comparing right and left coronary artery and 56&#xB1;9&#xA0;HU comparing the pulmonary trunk and left ventricle. Mean attenuation was 291&#xB1;65&#xA0;HU in the ascending aorta, 334&#xB1;93&#xA0;HU in the pulmonary trunk, and 285&#xB1;66&#xA0;HU and 268&#xB1;67&#xA0;HU in the right and left coronary artery, respectively. DSCTA is feasible and provides diagnostic image quality of the thoracic aorta, pulmonary and coronary arteries in patients with acute chest pain.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Acute chest pain</kwd>
        <kwd>Dual-source CT</kwd>
        <kwd>Coronary angiography</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; European Society of Radiology 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Acute chest pain represents one of the most difficult diagnostic challenges in emergency medicine. Chest pain history alone often cannot identify a group of patients who could be treated without further diagnostic testing [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>], and triage decisions based on initial cardiac enzyme levels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and electrocardiography (ECG) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] are often insufficient. Imaging may improve patient triage by decreasing delay in diagnosis and treatment and thus morbidity and mortality [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Most studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] have focused on patients being suspected of having acute coronary syndrome, but did not include additional differential diagnoses such as aortic dissection or pulmonary embolism, conditions that may clinically mimic coronary syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      <p>Multi-detector row computed tomography (CT) angiography is widely accepted and routinely used as a primary tool in the emergency assessment of pulmonary embolism [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>] and aortic dissection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. In addition, 64-slice CT coronary angiography has demonstrated the capability to diagnose and to rule-out coronary artery disease (CAD) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. Some recent studies have shown that ECG-gated multi-detector row CT is logistically feasible [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] and yields promising results as a modality for evaluating chest pain patients with cardiac and non-cardiac disease in the emergency setting [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. Even though using 64-slice CT scanner technology, however, patients with elevated heart rates require medical heart rate control prior to CT coronary angiography by administering beta-blockers and/or benzodiazepines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
      <p>Dual-source CT (DSCT) represents the most recent scanner technology and is characterized by two tubes and two detectors that are mounted in orthogonal orientation onto the gantry. As compared to 64-slice CT, this scanner configuration maintains a consistently high spatial resolution while enabling ECG-gated imaging with an increased temporal resolution of 83&#xA0;ms [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. First studies have shown robust results of DSCT angiography (DSCTA) regarding image quality of cardiac structures even at high heart rates [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>].</p>
      <p>The purpose of this study was to investigate the feasibility and image quality of ECG-gated DSCTA of the chest as a tool to evaluate cardiac and non-cardiac causes of acute chest pain in patients presenting to the emergency department.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Patient population</title>
        <p>Sixty consecutive patients (32 females, 28 males, mean age 58.1&#xB1;16.3&#xA0;years, age range 26&#x2013;84&#xA0;years) were prospectively included in this study. Intake was performed on weekdays from 7&#xA0;am to 7&#xA0;pm from August to October 2006. All patients suffered from acute chest pain and were referred to our department to diagnose or to rule out pulmonary embolism (n=56) or aortic dissection (n=4). Inclusion criteria were acute chest pain &gt;5&#xA0;min within the previous 24&#xA0;h and/or elevated serum D-dimer levels. Dyspnea and hemodynamic instability were not considered exclusion criteria. Similarly, all patients irrespective of their mean or regularity of heart rate and irrespective of their ability to perform breath-hold were included. Exclusion criteria included pregnancy, previous adverse reaction to iodinated contrast agent, nephropathy (serum creatinine &gt;1.3&#xA0;mg/dl), elevated troponine-I or creatine kinase-MB level in the initial blood sample, initial diagnostic ECG changes indicating an acute coronary syndrome (i.e., ST elevation or depression &gt;1&#xA0;mm, T-wave inversion &gt;4&#xA0;mm in &gt;2 anatomically contagious leads), and interference with standard clinical care of patients. The study was approved by the local ethics committee; informed consent was obtained.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Scan protocol and data reconstruction</title>
        <p>All CT examinations were performed on a DSCT scanner (Somatom Definition, Siemens Medical Solutions, Forchheim, Germany). First, a single non-enhanced low-dose scan at the level of the aortic root was obtained. In this slice, a region of interest (ROI) was set in the lumen of the aorta for monitoring intraluminal contrast enhancement. The delay from start of contrast material injection to start of scanning was planned using the bolus-tracking technique. A total of 110&#xA0;ml iodinated contrast material (iodixanol, Visipaque 320; 320&#xA0;mg/ml, GE Healthcare, Buckinghamshire, UK) was administered at a flow rate of 4&#xA0;ml/s via an 18-gauge needle placed into a superficial vein in the left antecubital fossa, followed by 30&#xA0;ml saline solution at the same flow rate (4&#xA0;ml/s). After reaching the preset contrast enhancement level of 80 Hounsfield Units (HU) in the ROI, a breath-hold signal was given and the scan was initiated automatically after a delay of 6 s. A topogram was used for planning the examination and determining the scan range. Data acquisition was performed using a dedicated biphasic chest pain protocol. As illustrated in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>, the lower chest including the heart was scanned with a tube current time of 320&#xA0;mAs while the upper chest was scanned with a tube current time product of 160&#xA0;mAs. The borderline between upper and lower scan range was set at approximately 2&#xA0;cm below the carina. Data acquisition was performed in a cranio-caudal direction. Acquisition parameters were as follows: detector collimation 2&#xD7;32&#xD7;0.6&#xA0;mm by using a z-flying focal spot for the simultaneous acquisition of 2&#xD7;64 overlapping 0.6-mm slices, gantry rotation time 330&#xA0;ms, and tube potential 120&#xA0;kV. The pitch varied according to the patient's heart rate and ranged from 0.2&#x2013;0.43, with higher pitch at higher heart rates. ECG-pulsing for radiation dose reduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] was applied in all patients. At mean heart rates below 60&#xA0;bpm, full tube current was applied from 60 to 70%, at 61&#x2013;70&#xA0;bpm from 50 to 80%, and at heart rates above 70 from 30 to 80% of the R-R interval.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Scan topogram illustrating planning of the chest pain protocol. The scan range covered the entire chest (red box). Premonitoring for bolus tracking was performed at the level of the aortic root (white line). The border for full tube current for the heart and half tube current for the upper lung is set approximately 2&#xA0;cm below the tracheal bifurcation. It is delimited by a virtual horizontal line connecting the upper ends of the blue boxes on both sides</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>Retrospective ECG-gating for phase synchronization was used. For the heart, CT data sets were reconstructed at 70% of the R-R interval with a slice thickness of 0.75&#xA0;mm (increment 0.5&#xA0;mm) by using a medium soft-tissue convolution kernel (B26f) (mean field of view, FoV: 151&#xB1;17&#xA0;mm, image matrix 512&#xD7;512). If considered necessary, additional images were reconstructed in 5% steps using the same parameters within the time window of full tube current. Images of the mediastinum (mean FoV: 293&#xB1;43&#xA0;mm) including the aorta and pulmonary arteries were reconstructed with a slice thickness of 1&#xA0;mm (increment 0.8&#xA0;mm) by using a medium soft-tissue convolution kernel (B30f), and images of the lung were reconstructed with a slice thickness of 2&#xA0;mm (increment 1.5&#xA0;mm) by using a sharp convolution kernel (B60f, same FoV as for the mediastinum). All images were transferred to a second Wizard (Siemens) equipped with cardiac post-processing software (Syngo Circulation, Siemens).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>All data were qualitatively evaluated regarding image quality and artifacts of different thoracic structures by two independent readers who are both experienced in cardiovascular radiology. This evaluation was performed on transverse source images, multi-planar reformations (MPR), curved MPR, and thin-slab maximum intensity projections.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Image quality and artifacts-lung parenchyma</title>
        <p>Image quality of lung parenchyma was independently rated using a two-point scale, adapted from a previous publication [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Lung parenchyma allowing diagnostic assessment due to distinct anatomic details of bronchial and parenchymal structures without significant artifacts and noise was rated with a score of 1 (diagnostic). Lung parenchyma with artifacts or noise causing reduction of image quality and diagnostic value was rated with a score of 2 (non-diagnostic).</p>
        <p>Artifacts were rated to quantify the cranio-caudal distribution of artifacts within the lung parenchyma for the right and left lung separately in coronal MPR. Because of the different tube current at upper and lower parts along the z-axis (see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>), the following scores were separately applied for the apex and the basis of the lung, respectively: 1=&#x2009;no artifacts, 2=&#x2009;breathing artifacts (stair step artifacts), 3=&#x2009;ECG-gating (i.e., synchronization or interpolation artifacts), and 4=&#x2009;noise artifacts. If breathing and ECG-gating artifacts appeared at the same time in one patient, the artifact with the worst impact on image quality was noted.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Image quality and artifacts-vascular structures</title>
        <p>Image quality of thoracic vascular structures was independently rated using the same two-point scale [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] as used for the rating of the lung parenchyma. Regarding the thoracic aorta, a score of 1 (diagnostic) indicated confident evaluation of the ascending aorta, the aortic arch, and descending aorta. Regarding pulmonary arteries, a score of 1 indicated confident evaluation of central, lobar, segmental, or subsegmental pulmonary arteries. Regarding coronary arteries, a score of 1 represented confident depiction (homogenous attenuation; no artifacts decreasing coronary analysis) of the right coronary artery (RCA), left main artery (LMA), left anterior descending artery (LAD), left circumflex artery (LCX), and their side branches. A score of 2 indicated decreased image quality of thoracic vascular structures with severe impairment of diagnostic value (non-diagnostic) due to breathing, motion, or ECG-gating artifacts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Image noise and attenuation-vascular structures</title>
        <p>Image noise was determined as the standard deviation of attenuation in a ROI placed in the ascending aorta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Contrast attenuation was measured in each patient in the ascending aorta, pulmonary trunk, LMA, proximal segment of the RCA, and right and left ventricle. Image noise and contrast attenuation were assessed using a circular ROI positioned exactly within the vessel or ventricular lumen while avoiding superimposition or partial volume effects from the vessel wall or myocardium. Measurements of the ascending aorta and pulmonary trunk as well as of the right and left ventricle were performed on the same transverse image, while the ROI in the coronary arteries was individually placed on separate transverse images.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Imaging findings</title>
        <p>Imaging findings indicating the possible underlying cause of acute chest pain were documented in each patient by both readers in consensus.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Statistical analysis was performed using commercially available software (SPSS 11.5, SPSS Inc., Il). Quantitative variables are expressed as mean &#xB1; standard deviation (SD) including 95% confidence intervals (CI) or range when appropriate. Categorical data were expressed as frequencies or percentages. Inter-observer agreement (kappa statistics) for image quality ratings was calculated. Two-tailed Student's <italic>t</italic> test for paired samples was used to explore significant differences in vessel attenuation among the ascending aorta, RCA, LMA, pulmonary trunk, and right and left ventricle. Intra-individual differences regarding vessel attenuation among the different vascular territories were performed using pairwise comparisons. Bonferroni correction for multiple comparisons was made, and a <italic>P</italic>-value &lt;0.003 was considered statistically significant.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec11" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>All CT scans were well tolerated and were successfully performed in all 60 patients without complications. All patients had a sinus rhythm, and the average heart rate during data acquisition was 74.9&#xB1;19.0 beats per minute (bpm) (range 45-130&#xA0;bpm). No beta receptor antagonists or benzodiazepines were administered prior to CT; 13 patients (22%) took oral beta blockers as part of their baseline medication at the time of the scan. Mean scan time was 12.2&#xB1;2.3&#xA0;s (range 9.7&#x2013;17.5&#xA0;s) and mean scan length was 24.1&#xB1;2.1&#xA0;cm (range 19.3&#x2013;29.7&#xA0;cm). The reconstruction interval used for image reading was 70% of the R-R interval. In seven patients it was considered necessary to reconstruct additional data sets in 5% intervals within the window of full tube current to obtain images with diagnostic quality.</p>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Image quality and artifacts-lung parenchyma</title>
        <p>Image quality of lung parenchyma was rated as being diagnostic (score 1) by both readers in all 60 patients (100%; excellent inter-observer agreement, kappa&#x2009;=1.0), and pathology both at upper and lower lung parts could be diagnosed or excluded in all 60 patients.</p>
        <p>Lung parenchyma was rated by both readers as being artifact-free in 42 patients (70%). Breathing artifacts causing stair-step artifacts were encountered in nine patients (15%) by one reader and eight (13%) of these nine patients by the other reader (excellent inter-observer agreement, kappa&#x2009;=0.93). Breathing artifacts were exclusively found at the lung base, i.e., at the end of the breath-hold period. ECG-gating-related artifacts were found in ten patients (17%) by one reader, and in nine (15%) of these ten patients by the other reader (excellent inter-observer agreement, kappa&#x2009;=0.84). The two types of artifacts were not encountered in the same patient, and image quality was diagnostic despite the artifacts.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>Image quality and artifacts-vascular structures</title>
        <p>Image quality of the thoracic aorta was rated by both readers as being diagnostic (score 1) in all 60 patients (100%; excellent inter-observer agreement, kappa&#x2009;=1.0), and pathologies of the thoracic aorta could be diagnosed or excluded by both readers in all 60 patients. Both readers rated image quality of the pulmonary arteries in the one (i.e., the same) patient (2%) as being non-diagnostic (score 2) due to insufficient attenuation of segmental and subsegmental pulmonary arteries. In this patient, attenuation did not allow excluding segmental or subsegmental pulmonary embolism, while attenuation in the pulmonary trunk and right and left lobar artery was considered sufficient for diagnosis or exclusion of central and lobar pulmonary embolism. In this patient, image quality of the coronary arteries was considered as being diagnostic by both readers. Image quality of coronary arteries was rated by both readers as being diagnostic (score 1) in the same 58 patients (97%; excellent inter-observer agreement, kappa&#x2009;=1.0). In the remaining two patients (3%), image quality of the coronary arteries was considered by both readers as being non-diagnostic (score 2) due to ECG-gating-related artifacts (mean heart rate 71&#xA0;bpm, ranging from 50 to 84&#xA0;bpm during scanning) in one and severe image noise due to obesity (body mass index 40.4&#xA0;kg/m<sup>2</sup>) in the other. In both patients, both readers rated image quality of the pulmonary arteries as being diagnostic.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Image noise and attenuation-vascular structures</title>
        <p>Mean image noise in the ascending aorta (mean ROI size 3.6&#xB1;0.2&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) was 29.8&#xB1;5.6.</p>
        <p>Mean attenuation in the ascending aorta (same ROI and same ROI size as for measurements of image noise) was 291&#xB1;65&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 274&#x2013;308&#xA0;HU), mean attenuation in the pulmonary trunk (mean ROI size 2.4&#xB1;0.2&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) was 334&#xB1;93&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 310&#x2013;358&#xA0;HU), mean attenuation in the proximal RCA (mean ROI size 0.14&#xB1;0.02&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) was 285&#xB1;66&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 268&#x2013;302&#xA0;HU), and mean attenuation in the LMA (mean ROI size 0.12&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>&#xB1;0.01) was 286&#xB1;67&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 269&#x2013;304&#xA0;HU). Mean attenuation in the right ventricle (mean ROI size 2.6&#xB1;0.2&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) was 313&#xB1;89&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 290&#x2013;336&#xA0;HU) and mean attenuation in the left ventricle (mean ROI size 2.6&#xB1;0.2&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) was 277&#xB1;66&#xA0;HU (95% CI: 260&#x2013;294&#xA0;HU) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Mean attenuation values (HU) within different vessels indicating a relatively homogenous contrast distribution between the different thoracic vascular territories. RCA&#x2009;=&#x2009;right coronary artery; LMA&#x2009;=&#x2009;left main coronary artery</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>No significant differences regarding attenuation were found between the RCA and LMA (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.), and between the ascending aorta and both coronary arteries (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.). No significant differences in attenuation were present between the right and left ventricle (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.), between the right ventricle and ascending aorta (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.), between the right ventricle and pulmonary trunk (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.), and between the right ventricle and the RCA (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.) and LMA (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.). Similarly, there were no significant differences in attenuation between the left ventricle and ascending aorta (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.), and between left ventricle and LMA (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.) and RCA (<italic>P</italic>=n.s.). Significant differences were only found between the pulmonary trunk and ascending aorta (P&#x2009;&lt;0.003), between the pulmonary trunk and the RCA and LMA (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.003), respectively, and between the left ventricle and pulmonary trunk (<italic>P</italic>&lt;0.003).</p>
        <p>Pairwise comparisons of mean intra-individual differences regarding vessel attenuation were small and ranged between 1.18&#xB1;5.86&#xA0;HU comparing the right and left coronary artery and 56.45&#xB1;8.96&#xA0;HU comparing the pulmonary trunk and left ventricle (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). 
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Pairwise intra-individual comparisons between different thoracic vascular territories</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="2">&#xA0;</th><th rowspan="2">Mean difference</th><th rowspan="2">Standard deviation</th><th colspan="2">95% confidence interval</th></tr><tr><th>Lower boundary</th><th>Upper boundary</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>Aorta</td><td>Pulmonary trunk</td><td>-43</td><td>11</td><td>-75</td><td>-11</td></tr><tr><td>Aorta</td><td>RCA</td><td>6</td><td>5</td><td>-10</td><td>22</td></tr><tr><td>Aorta</td><td>LCA</td><td>5</td><td>4</td><td>-8</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>Aorta</td><td>Right ventricle</td><td>-23</td><td>13</td><td>-63</td><td>18</td></tr><tr><td>Aorta</td><td>Left ventricle</td><td>14</td><td>5</td><td>-3</td><td>30</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary trunk</td><td>RCA</td><td>49</td><td>11</td><td>16</td><td>82</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary trunk</td><td>LCA</td><td>47</td><td>12</td><td>12</td><td>83</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary trunk</td><td>Right ventricle</td><td>20</td><td>12</td><td>-16</td><td>57</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary trunk</td><td>Left ventricle</td><td>57</td><td>9</td><td>29</td><td>84</td></tr><tr><td>RCA</td><td>LCA</td><td>-1</td><td>6</td><td>-19</td><td>17</td></tr><tr><td>RCA</td><td>Right ventricle</td><td>-28</td><td>13</td><td>-69</td><td>13</td></tr><tr><td>RCA</td><td>Left ventricle</td><td>8</td><td>5</td><td>-8</td><td>24</td></tr><tr><td>LCA</td><td>Right ventricle</td><td>-27</td><td>14</td><td>-70</td><td>15</td></tr><tr><td>LCA</td><td>Left ventricle</td><td>9</td><td>6</td><td>-10</td><td>28</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>RCA&#x2009;=&#x2009;right coronary artery; LCA&#x2009;=&#x2009;left coronary artery</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Imaging findings</title>
        <p>No pathologic findings were found in 33 patients (55%), whereas various pathologies of the aorta, pulmonary and coronary arteries, lung, and mediastinum were present in 27 patients (45%) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). 
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Imaging findings in the study population</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Diagnosis</th><th>Number of patients (n=60)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>No pathology</td><td>33</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary embolism</td><td>11</td></tr><tr><td>Aortic pathology, total</td><td>5</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Dissection type B</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Pseudoaneurysm of the aortic arch</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Plaque rupture</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Coronary pathology, total</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Significant stenosis of the LAD</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>&#xA0;Occlusion of the RCA</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Pulmonary consolidation</td><td>3</td></tr><tr><td>Pericarditis/pericardial effusion</td><td>2</td></tr><tr><td>Seropneumothorax</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Non-small cell lung cancer</td><td>1</td></tr><tr><td>Synovial cell carcinoma</td><td>1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>LAD, left anterior descending artery; RCA, right coronary artery</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>A 63-year-old female patient admitted to the emergency department with acute chest pain. (<bold>a</bold>) Curved multiplanar reformations along the centerline of the right coronary (RCA), left anterior descending (LAD), and the left circumflex artery (RCX) allow excluding significant coronary stenosis in this patient. Mean heart rate during DSCTA was 71&#xA0;bpm. (<bold>b</bold>) Thin-slab transverse maximum intensity projection shows no evidence of pulmonary embolism. (<bold>c</bold>) Transverse image at the level of the pulmonary trunk demonstrates acute aortic dissection type B (arrow) with mild left-sided pleural effusion</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>A 58-year-old female patient admitted to the emergency department with acute chest pain. (<bold>a</bold>) Curved multiplanar reformations along the centerline of the right coronary (RCA), left anterior descending (LAD), and the left circumflex artery (LCX) demonstrate normal coronary arteries and no evidence of stenosis. Mean heart rate during DSCTA was 63&#xA0;bpm. (<bold>b</bold>) Thin-slab transverse maximum intensity projection show bilateral pulmonary embolism (arrows). (<bold>c</bold>) Oblique-sagittal thin-slab maximum intensity projection demonstrates the thoracic aorta without evidence of disease</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>A 71-year-old male patient admitted to the emergency department with acute chest pain. (<bold>a</bold>) Curved multiplanar reformations along the centerline of the right coronary (RCA), left anterior descending (LAD), and the left circumflex artery (LCX) show occlusion of the proximal RCA (long arrow) and vessel wall calcifications without significant stenosis in the proximal and middle segment of the LAD and LCX (short arrows). Mean heart rate during DSCTA was 73&#xA0;bpm. (<bold>b</bold>) Thin-slab transverse maximum intensity projection demonstrates normal opacification of pulmonary arteries with no evidence of embolism. (<bold>c</bold>) Oblique-sagittal thin-slab maximum intensity projection demonstrates the thoracic aorta with minimal atherosclerotic wall changes, but with no evidence of potential causes for acute chest pain</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our study demonstrates that DSCT allows performing an ECG-gated chest examination for visualizing the different thoracic vascular territories at the same time-by employing an adjusted contrast media protocol-within a reasonable breath-hold period, and thus provides a diagnostic image quality in almost all patients. One of the most important findings of this study is that diagnostic data of coronary arteries could be obtained without foregoing heart rate control.</p>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Contrast media protocol and scan time</title>
        <p>With increasing gantry rotation times and faster volume coverage of newer CT scanners, scan times successively shorten and higher injection rates are required to achieve sufficient contrast in the vascular territory of interest. Similar to a previous 64-slice CT study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>], we have set the ROI for bolus tracking in the ascending aorta. With a relatively low threshold of 80&#xA0;HU above which the scan was initiated, a homogenous attenuation in both aortic/coronary and pulmonary arteries could be achieved. By doing so, we aimed at the time interval where the contrast enhancement curve of the pulmonary circulation overlaps with enhancement of the aorta [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. This has also resulted in comparable attenuation in left and right cardiac cavities. Recommended mean attenuation values for diagnostic image quality are approximately 300&#xA0;HU for the pulmonary arteries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] and 250&#x2013;350&#xA0;HU in the ascending aorta and coronary arteries [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. We obtained a mean attenuation of 291&#xA0;HU in the ascending aorta, 334&#xA0;HU in the pulmonary trunk, 285&#xA0;HU in the RCA, and 286&#xA0;HU in the LMA with only small intra- and inter-individual variations. These attenuation values were considered diagnostic in 98% of our patients and are comparable to previously published data [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. We encountered only one patient with non-diagnostic attenuation of segmental and subsegmental pulmonary arteries. However, this may have been also caused by other reasons negatively affecting contrast attenuation in pulmonary arteries such as Valsalva maneuver [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
        <p>The other major issue for CT in acute chest pain represents the issue of scan duration. As ECG-gated CT requires low pitch [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>], scan time is increased as compared to non-gated chest CT examinations. This, however, negatively affects image quality by making examinations more prone to breathing artifacts. This holds particularly true for patients with acute chest pain who often suffer from dyspnea. In our study, mean scan time was approximately 12 s, which represents a further improvement as compared to a mean scan time of 21 s with 64-slice CT [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Role of CT in the diagnostic pathway of acute chest pain</title>
        <p>Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> represents a simplified flow-chart of a generally accepted clinical pathway for patients with cardiac and non-cardiac causes of acute chest pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. While CT is the accepted reference modality for the diagnosis and exclusion of pulmonary embolism and aortic dissection [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], the role of CT in patients with a suspected cardiac cause for chest pain is currently under investigation. Gallagher and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] have shown that 64-slice CT has accuracy that is comparable to that of stress nuclear imaging for the detection of acute coronary syndrome in low-risk patients with negative serial ECG and biomarker results. Hoffmann and coworkers [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] have demonstrated that 64-slice CT has good performance characteristics for ruling out acute coronary syndromes in patients presenting to the emergency department with acute chest pain. The authors demonstrated in patients in whom initial triage was inconclusive that the absence of coronary artery plaque or significant stenosis on CT angiography had an excellent negative predictive value for the subsequent diagnosis of acute coronary syndrome. Furthermore, in those patients with CAD on CT, the extent of coronary atherosclerotic plaque provided incremental information to standard baseline patient variables and clinical risk assessment. Goldstein and colleagues [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] have shown that 64-slice CT coronary angiography is able to definitely establish or exclude CAD as the cause of acute chest pain. The high negative predictive value of the studies suggests that CT coronary angiography may be useful for facilitating and optimizing triage of patients with acute chest pain and/or inconclusive initial emergency department evaluation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>].
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Flow chart of a generally accepted clinical pathway for patients with cardiac and non-cardiac causes of acute chest pain. CT represents the standard of reference in patients with suspicion of acute aortic syndromes or pulmonary embolism (light gray boxes). The added value of CT in the evaluation of acute coronary syndrome has been already demonstrated [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] (moderate gray box). The potential future role of CT in patients with acute chest pain might be at an even earlier point of diagnostic work-up (dark gray boxes) to rule out life-threatening coronary, pulmonary, and aortic disease and to guide adequate therapeutic interventions</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="330_2007_724_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Study limitations</title>
        <p>We included only a relatively small number of patients and thus a small number of pathologies. Second, our study lacks a standard end-point to assess the final diagnosis and misses comparison with the reference standard invasive coronary angiography for investigating CAD for which diagnostic accuracy could be calculated. However, only a minority of our patients underwent invasive coronary angiography because in our emergency department standard management in patients with suspected acute coronary syndrome directly undergoing invasive coronary angiography without prior CT. That is in line with most studies involving patients referred to the emergency department [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Third, we did not investigate the optimal contrast media technique for obtaining homogenous contrast attenuation of different thoracic vascular territories. It remains to be determined if the use of the test bolus technique would yield better results with regard to vessel opacification. Finally, it needs to be assessed whether caudo-cranial or caudo-cranial scan direction will result in better image quality.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec20" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>First experience indicates that DSCTA is feasible in patients with acute chest pain and provides diagnostic image quality of the aorta, pulmonary arteries, and coronary artery system as well as of the lung parenchyma and mediastinum in a patient population without foregoing heart rate control. A dedicated contrast media protocol allows for homogenous attenuation of the different thoracic vascular territories.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>This study has been supported by the National Center of Competence in Research, Computer-Aided and Image-Guided Medical Interventions of the Swiss National Science Foundation.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Swap</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nagurney</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Value and limitations of chest pain history in the evaluation of patients with suspected acute coronary syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Jama</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>294</volume>
          <fpage>2623</fpage>
          <lpage>2629</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.294.20.2623</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Swap CJ, Nagurney JT (2005) Value and limitations of chest pain history in the evaluation of patients with suspected acute coronary syndromes. Jama 294:2623&#x2013;2629 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16304077</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zimmerman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic marker cooperative study for the diagnosis of myocardial infarction</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>1671</fpage>
          <lpage>1677</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zimmerman J et al (1999) Diagnostic marker cooperative study for the diagnosis of myocardial infarction. Circulation 99:1671&#x2013;1677 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10190875</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fesmire</surname>
              <given-names>FM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The Erlanger chest pain evaluation protocol: a one-year experience with serial 12-lead ECG monitoring, two-hour delta serum marker measurements, and selective nuclear stress testing to identify and exclude acute coronary syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>584</fpage>
          <lpage>594</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mem.2002.129506</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fesmire FM et al (2002) The Erlanger chest pain evaluation protocol: a one-year experience with serial 12-lead ECG monitoring, two-hour delta serum marker measurements, and selective nuclear stress testing to identify and exclude acute coronary syndromes. Ann Emerg Med 40:584&#x2013;594 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12447334</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MDCT in early triage of patients with acute chest pain</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>187</volume>
          <fpage>1240</fpage>
          <lpage>1247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2214/AJR.05.2240</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hoffmann U et al (2006) MDCT in early triage of patients with acute chest pain. AJR Am J Roentgenol 187:1240&#x2013;1247 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17056911</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Efficacy of multislice computed tomography for the detection of acute coronary syndrome in the emergency department</article-title>
          <source>Circ J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>1047</fpage>
          <lpage>1051</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1253/circj.69.1047</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sato Y et al (2005) Efficacy of multislice computed tomography for the detection of acute coronary syndrome in the emergency department. Circ J 69:1047&#x2013;1051 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16127184</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gallagher</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raff</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neill</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neil</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The diagnostic accuracy of 64-slice computed tomography coronary angiography compared with stress nuclear imaging in emergency department low-risk chest pain patients</article-title>
          <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>136</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.annemergmed.2006.06.043</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gallagher MJ, Ross MA, Raff GL, Goldstein JA, O&#x2019;Neill WW, O&#x2019;Neil B (2007) The diagnostic accuracy of 64-slice computed tomography coronary angiography compared with stress nuclear imaging in emergency department low-risk chest pain patients. Ann Emerg Med 49:125&#x2013;136 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16978738</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallagher</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neill</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neil</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raff</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A randomized controlled trial of multi-slice coronary computed tomography for evaluation of acute chest pain</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>863</fpage>
          <lpage>871</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2006.08.064</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Goldstein JA, Gallagher MJ, O&#x2019;Neill WW, Ross MA, O&#x2019;Neil B, Raff GL (2007) A randomized controlled trial of multi-slice coronary computed tomography for evaluation of acute chest pain. J Am Coll Cardiol 49:863&#x2013;871 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17320744</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Coronary multidetector computed tomography in the assessment of patients with acute chest pain</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>2251</fpage>
          <lpage>2260</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.106.634808</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hoffmann U et al (2006) Coronary multidetector computed tomography in the assessment of patients with acute chest pain. Circulation 114:2251&#x2013;2260 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17075011</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Erhardt</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Task force on the management of chest pain</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>1153</fpage>
          <lpage>1176</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1053/euhj.2002.3194</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Erhardt L et al (2002) Task force on the management of chest pain. Eur Heart J 23:1153&#x2013;1176 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12206127</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quiroz</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clinical validity of a negative computed tomography scan in patients with suspected pulmonary embolism: a systematic review</article-title>
          <source>Jama</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>293</volume>
          <fpage>2012</fpage>
          <lpage>2017</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.293.16.2012</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Quiroz R et al (2005) Clinical validity of a negative computed tomography scan in patients with suspected pulmonary embolism: a systematic review. Jama 293:2012&#x2013;2017 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15855435</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hayter</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rhea</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Small</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tafazoli</surname>
              <given-names>FS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novelline</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Suspected aortic dissection and other aortic disorders: multi-detector row CT in 373 cases in the emergency setting</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>238</volume>
          <fpage>841</fpage>
          <lpage>852</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2383041528</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hayter RG, Rhea JT, Small A, Tafazoli FS, Novelline RA (2006) Suspected aortic dissection and other aortic disorders: multi-detector row CT in 373 cases in the emergency setting. Radiology 238:841&#x2013;852 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16452396</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Leschka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accuracy of MSCT coronary angiography with 64-slice technology: first experience</article-title>
          <source>Eur Heart J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1482</fpage>
          <lpage>1487</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/eurheartj/ehi261</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Leschka S et al (2005) Accuracy of MSCT coronary angiography with 64-slice technology: first experience. Eur Heart J 26:1482&#x2013;1487 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15840624</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raff</surname>
              <given-names>GL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gallagher</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Neill</surname>
              <given-names>WW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldstein</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diagnostic accuracy of noninvasive coronary angiography using 64-slice spiral computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>552</fpage>
          <lpage>557</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jacc.2005.05.056</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Raff GL, Gallagher MJ, O&#x2019;Neill WW, Goldstein JA (2005) Diagnostic accuracy of noninvasive coronary angiography using 64-slice spiral computed tomography. J Am Coll Cardiol 46:552&#x2013;557 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16053973</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schertler</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glucker</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wildermuth</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jungius</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marincek</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boehm</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of retrospectively ECG-gated and nongated MDCT of the chest in an emergency setting regarding workflow, image quality, and diagnostic certainty</article-title>
          <source>Emerg Radiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>29</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10140-005-0435-y</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schertler T, Glucker T, Wildermuth S, Jungius KP, Marincek B, Boehm T (2005) Comparison of retrospectively ECG-gated and nongated MDCT of the chest in an emergency setting regarding workflow, image quality, and diagnostic certainty. Emerg Radiol 12:19&#x2013;29 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16283221</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ECG-gated 64-MDCT angiography in the differential diagnosis of acute chest pain</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>188</volume>
          <fpage>76</fpage>
          <lpage>82</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2214/AJR.05.1153</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Johnson TR et al (2007) ECG-gated 64-MDCT angiography in the differential diagnosis of acute chest pain. AJR Am J Roentgenol 188:76&#x2013;82 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17179348</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Read</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuo</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Assessment of chest pain in the emergency room: what is the role of multidetector CT?</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>368</fpage>
          <lpage>372</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrad.2005.12.022</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">White C, Read K, Kuo D (2006) Assessment of chest pain in the emergency room: what is the role of multidetector CT? Eur J Radiol 57:368&#x2013;372 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16434159</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mollet</surname>
              <given-names>NR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>High-resolution spiral computed tomography coronary angiography in patients referred for diagnostic conventional coronary angiography</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>2318</fpage>
          <lpage>2323</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.105.533471</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mollet NR et al (2005) High-resolution spiral computed tomography coronary angiography in patients referred for diagnostic conventional coronary angiography. Circulation 112:2318&#x2013;2323 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16203914</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Flohr</surname>
              <given-names>TG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>First performance evaluation of a dual-source CT (DSCT) system</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>256</fpage>
          <lpage>268</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-005-2919-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Flohr TG et al (2006) First performance evaluation of a dual-source CT (DSCT) system. Eur Radiol 16:256&#x2013;268 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16341833</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Achenbach</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contrast-enhanced coronary artery visualization by dual-source computed tomography&#x2013;initial experience</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>57</volume>
          <fpage>331</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ejrad.2005.12.017</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Achenbach S et al (2006) Contrast-enhanced coronary artery visualization by dual-source computed tomography&#x2013;initial experience. Eur J Radiol 57:331&#x2013;335 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16426789</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>TR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dual-source CT cardiac imaging: initial experience</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1409</fpage>
          <lpage>1415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-006-0298-y</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Johnson TR et al (2006) Dual-source CT cardiac imaging: initial experience. Eur Radiol 16:1409&#x2013;1415 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16770652</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Scheffel</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accuracy of dual-source CT coronary angiography: First experience in a high pre-test probability population without heart rate control</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>2739</fpage>
          <lpage>2747</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-006-0474-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Scheffel H et al (2006) Accuracy of dual-source CT coronary angiography: First experience in a high pre-test probability population without heart rate control. Eur Radiol 16:2739&#x2013;2747 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17031451</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jakobs</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multislice helical CT of the heart with retrospective ECG gating: reduction of radiation exposure by ECG-controlled tube current modulation</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1081</fpage>
          <lpage>1086</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-001-1278-x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jakobs TF et al (2002) Multislice helical CT of the heart with retrospective ECG gating: reduction of radiation exposure by ECG-controlled tube current modulation. Eur Radiol 12:1081&#x2013;1086 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11976849</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>d&#x2019;Agostino</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low-dose ECG-gated 64-slices helical CT angiography of the chest: evaluation of image quality in 105 patients</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>2137</fpage>
          <lpage>2146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-006-0218-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">d&#x2019;Agostino AG et al (2006) Low-dose ECG-gated 64-slices helical CT angiography of the chest: evaluation of image quality in 105 patients. Eur Radiol 16:2137&#x2013;2146 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16609862</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lembcke</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Image quality of noninvasive coronary angiography using multislice spiral computed tomography and electron-beam computed tomography: intraindividual comparison in an animal model</article-title>
          <source>Invest Radiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>357</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.rli.0000123316.10765.6c</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lembcke A et al (2004) Image quality of noninvasive coronary angiography using multislice spiral computed tomography and electron-beam computed tomography: intraindividual comparison in an animal model. Invest Radiol 39:357&#x2013;364 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15167102</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Determination of optimal timing window for pulmonary artery MDCT angiography</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>188</volume>
          <fpage>313</fpage>
          <lpage>317</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2214/AJR.06.0078</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lee CH et al (2007) Determination of optimal timing window for pulmonary artery MDCT angiography. AJR Am J Roentgenol 188:313&#x2013;317 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17242236</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Prokop</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multislice CT angiography</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Radiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>36</volume>
          <fpage>86</fpage>
          <lpage>96</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0720-048X(00)00271-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Prokop M (2000) Multislice CT angiography. Eur J Radiol 36:86&#x2013;96 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11116172</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optimal contrast application for cardiac 4-detector-row computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Invest Radiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <fpage>690</fpage>
          <lpage>694</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.rli.0000084886.44676.e4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Becker CR et al (2003) Optimal contrast application for cardiac 4-detector-row computed tomography. Invest Radiol 38:690&#x2013;694 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14566178</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Husmann</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Influence of cardiac hemodynamic parameters on coronary artery opacification with 64-slice computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Eur Radiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1111</fpage>
          <lpage>1116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00330-005-0110-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Husmann L et al (2006) Influence of cardiac hemodynamic parameters on coronary artery opacification with 64-slice computed tomography. Eur Radiol 16:1111&#x2013;1116 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16607499</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raptopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>VD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>MDCT angiography of acute chest pain: evaluation of ECG-gated and nongated techniques</article-title>
          <source>AJR Am J Roentgenol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>186</volume>
          <fpage>S346</fpage>
          <lpage>S356</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2214/AJR.04.1882</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Raptopoulos VD et al (2006) MDCT angiography of acute chest pain: evaluation of ECG-gated and nongated techniques. AJR Am J Roentgenol 186:S346&#x2013;S356 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16714608</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wittram</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pulmonary artery enhancement at CT pulmonary angiography</article-title>
          <source>Radiology</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>229</volume>
          <fpage>932</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/radiol.2293030474</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wittram C (2003) Pulmonary artery enhancement at CT pulmonary angiography. Radiology 229:932; author reply 932&#x2013;933 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14657327</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Primak</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McCollough</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruesewitz</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fletcher</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between noise, dose, and pitch in cardiac multi-detector row CT</article-title>
          <source>Radiographics</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1785</fpage>
          <lpage>1794</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1148/rg.266065063</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Primak AN, McCollough CH, Bruesewitz MR, Zhang J, Fletcher JG (2006) Relationship between noise, dose, and pitch in cardiac multi-detector row CT. Radiographics 26:1785&#x2013;1794 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17102050</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>TH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goldman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of the patient with acute chest pain</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>342</volume>
          <fpage>1187</fpage>
          <lpage>1195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM200004203421607</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lee TH, Goldman L (2000) Evaluation of the patient with acute chest pain. N Engl J Med 342:1187&#x2013;1195 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10770985</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Belle</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effectiveness of managing suspected pulmonary embolism using an algorithm combining clinical probability, D-dimer testing, and computed tomography</article-title>
          <source>Jama</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>295</volume>
          <fpage>172</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.295.2.172</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Belle A et al (2006) Effectiveness of managing suspected pulmonary embolism using an algorithm combining clinical probability, D-dimer testing, and computed tomography. Jama 295:172&#x2013;179 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16403929</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ioannidis</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salem</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chew</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Accuracy of imaging technologies in the diagnosis of acute cardiac ischemia in the emergency department: a meta-analysis</article-title>
          <source>Ann Emerg Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>471</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1067/mem.2001.114901</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ioannidis JP, Salem D, Chew PW, Lau J (2001) Accuracy of imaging technologies in the diagnosis of acute cardiac ischemia in the emergency department: a meta-analysis. Ann Emerg Med 37:471&#x2013;477 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11326183</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>