<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Int Urol Nephrol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>International Urology and Nephrology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0301-1623</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-2584</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18193489</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2268719</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9300</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11255-007-9300-0</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Magnesium carbonate for phosphate control in patients on hemodialysis. A randomized controlled trial</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Tzanakis</surname>
            <given-names>Ioannis P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+30-28210-43140</phone>
            <fax>+30-28210-22109</fax>
            <email>ioatza@otenet.gr</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Papadaki</surname>
            <given-names>Antonia N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wei</surname>
            <given-names>Mingxin</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kagia</surname>
            <given-names>Stella</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Spadidakis</surname>
            <given-names>Vlassios V.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kallivretakis</surname>
            <given-names>Nikolaos E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Oreopoulos</surname>
            <given-names>Dimitrios G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Nephrology, General Hospital of Chania, 18, Michali Mefa St, Chania-Crete, PC 73100 Greece </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Liwan Hospital,  Guangzhou Medical College, Guangzhou, Guangdong Province P.R. China </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Toronto Western Hospital,  Toronto, Ontario Canada </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>10</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>40</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>193</fpage>
      <lpage>201</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>29</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>19</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Magnesium salts bind dietary phosphorus, but their use in renal patients is limited due to their potential for causing side effects. The aim of this study was to evaluate the efficacy and safety of magnesium carbonate (MgCO<sub>3</sub>) as a phosphate-binder in hemodialysis patients.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>Forty-six stable hemodialysis patients were randomly allocated to receive either MgCO<sub>3</sub> (<italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;25) or calcium carbonate (CaCO<sub>3</sub>), (<italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;21) for 6&#xA0;months. The concentration of Mg in the dialysate bath was 0.30&#xA0;mmol/l in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 0.48&#xA0;mmol/l in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Only two of 25 patients (8%) discontinued ingestion of MgCO<sub>3</sub> due to complications: one (4%) because of persistent diarrhea, and the other (4%) because of recurrent hypermagnesemia. In the MgCO<sub>3</sub> and CaCO<sub>3</sub> groups, respectively, time-averaged (months 1&#x2013;6) serum concentrations were: phosphate (P), 5.47 vs. 5.29&#xA0;mg/dl, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; Ca, 9.13 vs. 9.60&#xA0;mg/dl, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001; Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product, 50.35 vs. 50.70 (mg/dl)<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; Mg, 2.57 vs. 2.41&#xA0;mg/dl, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; intact parathyroid hormone (iPTH), 285 vs. 235&#xA0;pg/ml, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01. At month 6, iPTH levels did not differ between groups: 251 vs. 212&#xA0;pg/ml, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns. At month 6 the percentages of patients with serum levels of phosphate, Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product and iPTH that fell within the Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative (K/DOQI) guidelines were similar in both groups, whereas more patients in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group (17/23; 73.91%) than in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (5/20, 25%) had serum Ca levels that fell within these guidelines, with the difference being significant at <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusion</title>
          <p>Our study shows that MgCO<sub>3</sub> administered for a period of 6&#xA0;months is an effective and inexpensive agent to control serum phosphate levels in hemodialysis patients. The administration of MgCO<sub>3</sub> in combination with a low dialysate Mg concentration avoids the risk of severe hypermagnesemia.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>End-stage renal disease</kwd>
        <kwd>Hemodialysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Magnesium carbonate</kwd>
        <kwd>Phosphate-binders</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, B.V. 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction </title>
      <p>Normalization of the serum phosphate level is the cornerstone of medical protocols aimed at preventing and treating secondary hyperparathyroidism. Moreover, it has been shown that elevated serum levels of phosphate and the calcium&#x2013;phosphate product (Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P) play an important role in the development of extraosseous calcifications and are associated with increased mortality in hemodialysis patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. The ingestion of phosphate-binding agents in conjunction with dietary phosphate restriction and its adequate removal by dialysis are the cornerstones of serum phosphate control in end-stage renal disease (ESRD) patients. However, four decades after the introduction of chronic hemodialysis in early 1960s, we have not yet found the ideal phosphate binder(s) in terms of combined efficacy, safety and low cost. Aluminum and calcium salts and non-aluminum and non-calcium agents, such as sevelamer and lanthanum carbonate, all have advantages and disadvantages [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. Magnesium-containing agents are aluminum- and calcium-free and are inexpensive phosphate-binders and, to date, their potential has not been explored extensively. In studies involving small series of both hemodialysis and peritoneal dialysis patients, magnesium carbonate (MgCO<sub>3</sub>) and magnesium hydroxide [Mg(OH)<sub>2</sub>] have been administered either alone or in combination with calcium salts with good results [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. However, these compounds are not widely used in ESRD patients because nephrologists have an inordinate fear of hypermagnesemia and the belief that Mg administration frequently is accompanied by gastrointestinal disorders.</p>
      <p>We carried out this study in hemodialysis patients to evaluate the efficacy and safety of MgCO<sub>3</sub> as a phosphate-binder when given with a concurrent low dialysate magnesium solution. The control of serum phosphate in the two groups of patients was the primary outcome, while secondary outcomes were changes in serum calcium, magnesium, Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P and PTH levels and changes in bowel movements.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>Subjects and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Patients and study design</title>
        <p>Stable ESRD patients on maintenance hemodialysis in our renal unit participated in the study. The protocol of this project was approved by the Ethics Committee of the hospital. Exclusion criteria were: age &lt;18&#xA0;years, hemodialysis for less than 6&#xA0;months, psychiatric or other disorders leading to non-compliance, unlikeliness to continue hemodialysis for more than 6&#xA0;months in the same facility, critical illness at the time of recruitment, previous parathyroidectomy, severe hyperparathyroidism [serum intact parathyroid hormone (iPTH) &gt; 500&#xA0;pg/ml], normal serum phosphate (&lt;5.5&#xA0;mg/dl) without phosphate-binders, diseases resulting in diarrhea and the lack of informed consent. A total of 54 patients met the criteria and were approached for enrolment. The inclusion period lasted 2&#xA0;months, between March 2 and April 29, 2006. Enrolled patients signed an informed consent and thereafter entered a 4-week washout period during which we withdrew all phosphate-binders as well as vitamin D medications. After the washout phase, three patients were removed because they had serum phosphate levels lower than 5.8&#xA0;mg/dl; the remaining 51 patients were allocated to receive either MgCO<sub>3</sub> tablets (MgCO<sub>3</sub> group) or calcium carbonate tablets (CaCO<sub>3</sub> group) for 6&#xA0;months. We chose CaCO<sub>3</sub> instead of calcium acetate because the latter is not commercially available in Greece. Four patients did not agree to consume MgCO<sub>3</sub> but did agree to participate by taking their standard binder of CaCO<sub>3</sub>; we allocated these patients to the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group, whereas the remainder of the patients were randomly allocated with a ratio 1:1 to either the CaCO<sub>3</sub> (21 randomly assigned patients plus 4 = 25 patients) or to the MgCO<sub>3</sub> (26) group. Each MgCO<sub>3</sub> tablet contained 250&#xA0;mg MgCO<sub>3</sub>, which is equivalent to 71&#xA0;mg of elemental magnesium, and each CaCO<sub>3</sub> tablet contained 420&#xA0;mg of  CaCO<sub>3</sub> equivalent to 168&#xA0;mg of elemental calcium. All patients were on the same standard dialysis schedule (three times weekly&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;4 h), and in all of the patients the delivered dose of hemodialysis, as calculated by applying the single pool Kt/V<sub>urea</sub> index using the second-generation formula of Daugirdas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>],<sub>,</sub> was &#x2265;1.35. In both groups, calcium concentration in the dialysate bath was 1.50&#xA0;mmol/l, whereas magnesium concentration was 0.48&#xA0;mmol/l in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group and 0.30&#xA0;mmol/l in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group. The National Kidney Foundation (NKF) suggests a bath calcium dialysate concentration of 1.25&#xA0;mmol/l (based on opinion, not on evidence). We used a bath concentration 1.50&#xA0;mmol/l because we wanted to avoid episodes of hypocalcemia, particularly in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group. The patients should be more susceptible to manifest hypocalcemia since they did not receive vitamin D. The starting dose of both phosphate-binders were three tablets of MgCO<sub>3</sub> or CaCO<sub>3</sub> daily; the dose was adjusted thereafter according to the serum phosphate values: weekly for the first month and then monthly. The dosage of the study drug was increased to one or two tablets per meal as required to achieve the target of serum phosphate level &#x2264;5.5&#xA0;mg/dl. Based on our clinical experience, to achieve adequate control of serum phosphate we set the maximum daily dose of CaCO<sub>3</sub> to 3780&#xA0;mg (nine tablets), which is equivalent to 1512&#xA0;mg of elemental calcium, and the maximum daily dose of MgCO<sub>3</sub> to 2250&#xA0;mg (nine tablets), which is equivalent to 639&#xA0;mg of elemental magnesium. Each patient&#x2019;s full biochemical profile was obtained at baseline, then weekly during the first month and monthly thereafter. Parathyroid hormone was measured at baseline and then at monthly intervals. If a patient developed hypercalcemia (serum Ca&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;10.5&#xA0;mg/dl), the daily dose of CaCO<sub>3</sub> was reduced by one or two tablets. The same was done in patients with severe hypermagnesemia, which is defined as a serum magnesium level &gt;3.5&#xA0;mg/dl. If severe hypermagnesemia persisted for more than 3 weeks, the administration of MgCO<sub>3</sub> was stopped, and the patient was dropped from the study. No patient received vitamin D or a calcimimetic agent during the study. Serum total calcium values were corrected to the serum albumin values.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>The laboratory values were expressed as mean&#xA0;[&#xB1; one standard deviation (SD)].</p>
        <p>Student&#x2019;s two-tailed unpaired <italic>t</italic> test was used to compare values between the two groups of patients at baseline and at 6&#xA0;months. We used repeated measures of analysis of variance (repeated ANOVA method) to test for differences between the two treatment groups in average values of calcium, phosphate, Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P, magnesium, alkaline phosphatase (ALP) and PTH over time (time-averaged mean value differences). The chi-square test was applied to determine differences in the prevalence of laboratory data. Significance was set at a <italic>P</italic> level of &lt;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>Of the 26 patients enrolled in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group, one dropped out due to non-compliance. Of the remaining 25 patients, two (8%) discontinued ingestion of MgCO<sub>3</sub> and dropped out: one (4%) because of persistent diarrhea, and one (4%) because of recurrent hypermagnesemia. Of the 25 patients in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group; five were removed from the study (two received a kidney transplant, one died (pneumonia), one suffered a stroke and was unable to swallow tablets and one moved to another hospital). The use of phosphate-binders and vitamin D by the patients before the washout period is given in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. Patients&#x2019; mean serum values at baseline and at the end of the follow-up period are shown in Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>. The monthly follow-up of the mean biochemical parameters are shown in Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. The mean Kt/V<sub>urea</sub> was 1.379&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.026 in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> and 1.381&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.027 in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Patients&#x2019; data in terms of the use of phosphate-binders and vitamin D before the washout period</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">MgCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>n</italic> = 25)</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>n</italic> = 21)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Vitamin D</td><td align="left">11/25</td><td align="left">8/21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphate binders</td><td align="left">25/25</td><td align="left">21/21</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;</italic>CaCO<sub>3</sub></td><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Sevelamer</td><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">4</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;CaCO3&#xA0;+&#xA0;sevelamer</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Mean serum values at baseline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">MgCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Age (years)</td><td char="." align="char">63.23</td><td char="." align="char">65.32</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">12.19</td><td char="." align="char">11.68</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Calcium (mg/dl)<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">9.42</td><td char="." align="char">9.14</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.54</td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphorous (mg/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">6.63</td><td char="." align="char">6.58</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.86</td><td char="." align="char">0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product (mg/dl)<sup>2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">62.62</td><td char="." align="char">60.08</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">10.36</td><td char="." align="char">8.35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnesium (mg/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">2.38</td><td char="." align="char">2.36</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.28</td><td char="." align="char">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALP (IU/l)</td><td char="." align="char">76</td><td char="." align="char">86</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">37</td><td char="." align="char">35</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intact PTH (pg/ml)</td><td char="." align="char">316</td><td char="." align="char">296</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">182</td><td char="." align="char">157</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>SD,&#xA0;Standard deviation; ALP, alkaline phosphatase; PTH, parathyroid hormone; ns, not significant</p><p><sup>a</sup>Serum total calcium level corrected to serum albumin</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Mean values at 6 months</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">MgCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Calcium (mg/dl)<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">8.97</td><td char="." align="char">9.72</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;2.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.57</td><td char="." align="char">0.42</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphorous (mg/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">5.12</td><td char="." align="char">5.28</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product (mg/dl)<sup>2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">46.04</td><td char="." align="char">51.38</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">7.65</td><td char="." align="char">7.75</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnesium (mg/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">2.59</td><td char="." align="char">2.40</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALP (IU/l)</td><td char="." align="char">89</td><td char="." align="char">84</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.46</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">28</td><td char="." align="char">26</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;NS</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intact PTH (pg/ml)</td><td char="." align="char">251</td><td char="." align="char">212</td><td align="left"><italic>t</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">118</td><td char="." align="char">198</td><td align="left"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;NS</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Serum total calcium corrected to serum albumin</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Monthly follow-up of serum phosphate (<italic>sP</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11255_2007_9300_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Monthly follow-up of serum calcium (<italic>sCa</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11255_2007_9300_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Monthly follow-up of serum Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product (<italic>SCa &#xD7;&#xA0;P</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11255_2007_9300_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Monthly follow-up of serum PTH (<italic>siPTH</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11255_2007_9300_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      <p>The mean daily dose of CaCO<sub>3</sub> was 6.76 tablets (range 3&#x2013;9) containing a total of 2839&#xA0;mg (range 1260&#x2013;3780) of CaCO<sub>3</sub>, which is equivalent to 1136&#xA0;mg of elemental calcium (range 504&#x2013;1512&#xA0;mg) The mean daily dose of MgCO<sub>3</sub> was 6.21 tablets (range 3&#x2013;9) containing a total of 1552&#xA0;mg (range 750&#x2013;2,250) of MgCO<sub>3</sub>, which is equivalent to 441&#xA0;mg of elemental magnesium (range 213&#x2013;639&#xA0;mg). A Shapiro&#x2013;Wilk test did not indicate any evidence against the normality assumption for the distribution of calcium, phosphate, Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P, magnesium, ALP and PTH levels within the two groups (CaCO<sub>3</sub> and MgCO<sub>3</sub>) at any time period during the follow-up. The significance level for the normality tests was set to <italic>a</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.001.</p>
      <p>Average values of the biochemical data during months 1&#x2013;6 are shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The initial mean serum phosphate levels were 6.63&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 6.58&#xA0;mg/dl in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns), while at the end of the study serum phosphate values were 5.13 and 5.26&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> and CaCO<sub>3</sub> groups respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Time-averaged mean serum phosphate values were 5.47&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 5.29&#xA0;mg/dl in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Serum phosphate levels decreased by 23% in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and by 19% in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns). At the end of the study 17 of 23 (74%) patients in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> and 13 of 20 (65%) of the CaCO3 group, (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.10, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) had serum phosphate values within the range recommended by the Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative (K/DOQI) guidelines (upper threshold of 5.5&#xA0;mg/dl) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Average serum values during months 1&#x2013;6 of the follow-up period</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">MgCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub> group</th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic> value (<italic>t</italic> test)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Calcium (mg/dl)<sup>a</sup></td><td char="." align="char">9.13</td><td char="." align="char">9.60</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.53</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphorous (mg/dl)</td><td char="." align="char">5.47</td><td char="." align="char">5.29</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.81</td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product (mg/dl)<sup>2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">50.35</td><td char="." align="char">50.70</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">7.75</td><td char="." align="char">8.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Magnesium (mg/dl)<sup>2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">2.57</td><td char="." align="char">2.41</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">0.41</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">ALP (IU/l)</td><td char="." align="char">88</td><td char="." align="char">80</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">32</td><td char="." align="char">27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Intact PTH (pg/ml)</td><td char="." align="char">285</td><td char="." align="char">231</td><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">SD</td><td char="." align="char">161</td><td char="." align="char">177</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Serum total calcium corrected to serum albumin</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Patients with laboratory values within the Kidney Disease Outcomes Quality Initiative (K/DOQI) guideline range at 6 months</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">MgCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>n</italic>, %)</th><th align="left">CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>n</italic>, %)</th><th align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>, <italic>P</italic> value</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Calcium </td><td char="(" align="char">17/23 (73.91)</td><td char="(" align="char">5/20 (25)</td><td align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;8.42, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Phosphorous</td><td char="(" align="char">17/23 (73.91)</td><td char="(" align="char">13/20 (65)</td><td align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.10, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product</td><td char="(" align="char">20/23 (86.95)</td><td char="(" align="char">14/20 (70)</td><td align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.99, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr><tr><td align="left">PTH</td><td char="(" align="char">11/23 (47.82)</td><td char="(" align="char">8/20 (40)</td><td align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.79, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Mean serum Ca values at baseline were 9.42&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 9.14&#xA0;mg/dl in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Time-averaged mean serum values were 9.13&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 9.60 in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P </italic>&lt; 0.001) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). At 6&#xA0;months, these values were 8.97 and 9.72&#xA0;mg/dl, respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Seventeen patients (17/23; 74%) who received MgCO<sub>3</sub> and only 5/20 (25%) of those on CaCO<sub>3</sub> had serum Ca values within the K/DQOI guidelines ( &#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;8.42, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>). We encountered six episodes of hypercalcemia, defined as a serum calcium level &gt;10.5&#xA0;mg/dl, in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group in comparison to one episode in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group.</p>
      <p>The two groups of patients had nearly equal values of serum Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product at the beginning, at the end as well as during the period study (Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>), with the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group having 62.6&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2</sup> and the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group having 60.1&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2</sup> (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Mean levels of Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P during months 1&#x2013;6 of the follow-up were similar &#x2013; 50.35&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2</sup> in the MgCo<sub>3</sub> group and 50.70&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2 </sup>in the CaCo<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>); at the end of the study, the corresponding values were 46.0 and 51.4&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2</sup> (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>), whereas 20/23 (87%) and 14/20 (70%) patients, respectively, had Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product below the upper limits of K/DQOI recommendations (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p>
      <p>Starting mean levels of serum iPTH were similar in both groups &#x2013; 316&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;182&#xA0;pg/ml in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 296&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;157&#xA0;pg/ml in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (normal range 10&#x2013;65&#xA0;pg/ml) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). During the 6-month follow-up period, average iPTH levels were significantly higher in the MgCO<sub>3</sub>-treated patients (285&#xA0;pg/ml) than in those treated with CaCO<sub>3</sub> (231&#xA0;pg/ml) (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). However, at the end of the study, those levels did not differ significantly &#x2013; 251&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;118 and 212&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;198&#xA0;pg/ml, respectively (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). In terms of PTH levels, there was no statistically significant difference between the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group and the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group &#x2013; 29 versus 21%, respectively  (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.11, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns). Moreover, ten of 23 (43%) patients in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and nine of 20 (45%) in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group had initial levels of iPTH above 300&#xA0;pg/ml; in three of these ten patients (30%) of the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and five of the nine (56%) of the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group, the iPTH decreased below 300&#xA0;pg/ml [&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.38, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns; 11/23 (48%)]. Eight of 20 patients (40%) in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group and six of 23 patients (26%) in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) had final values of iPTH below 150&#xA0;pg/ml. The number of patients of both groups, patients who received MgCO<sub>3</sub>, and eight of 20 (40%) patients who received CaCO<sub>3</sub> who had serum phosphorus, calcium, Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product and iPTH values at 6&#xA0;months that fell within the range recommended by the K/DOQI guidelines are shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref> (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.79, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns).</p>
      <p>During the follow-up period the average serum Mg levels were slightly &#x2013; but not significantly &#x2013; higher in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group than in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group: 2.57 vs. 2.41&#xA0;mg/dl (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Similarly, at 6&#xA0;months, these values were 2.59 and 2.40&#xA0;mg/dl (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;ns) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). One patient of the 25 (4%) stopped taking MgCO<sub>3</sub> because of recurrent high levels of serum magnesium (&gt;3.5&#xA0;mg/dl, the upper threshold according to our protocol). Two more patients manifested a transient elevation of serum magnesium &#x2013; from 3.18 to 3.36&#xA0;mg/dl. No patient in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group had a serum magnesium &gt;3&#xA0;mg/dl.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>This is the first study that compares MgCO<sub>3</sub> with only one other phosphate-binder in hemodialysis patients. Our results show that MgCO<sub>3</sub> administered for a period of 6&#xA0;months has a good phosphate-binding ability, is well tolerated by most patients and is accompanied by a low incidence of side effects.</p>
      <p>O&#x2019;Donovan et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] described 28 patients on hemodialysis who were given magnesium chloride in place of oral aluminum hydroxide. These patients were also switched from a dialysate containing 0.85&#xA0;mmol/l magnesium to one not containing any magnesium at all. After 24&#xA0;months of treatment on this regimen, serum phosphate was effectively controlled in these patients. The researchers saw no evidence of increased secondary hyperparathyroidism. Delmez et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] conducted a 10-week, prospective, randomized crossover study of 15 hemodialysis patients, who were on MgCO<sub>3</sub> with a dialysate magnesium concentration of 0.25&#xA0;mmol/l; with this regimen, these investigators were able to reduce the CaCO<sub>3</sub> dose and use a higher dose of calcitriol. Mean serum phosphate levels in the patients were similar with the MgCO<sub>3</sub>/CaCO<sub>3</sub> combination as with the CaCO<sub>3</sub> treatment alone (5.7&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.2 vs. 5.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.2&#xA0;mg/dl, respectively), and there were no adverse gastrointestinal effects. Parsons et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] described 32 continuous cycling peritoneal dialysis (CAPD) in patients who were dialyzed with magnesium-free dialysate and used a mixture of CaCO<sub>3</sub> and MgCO<sub>3</sub> as a phosphate-binder for over 1&#xA0;year. These patients achieved satisfactory control of hyperparathyroidism, with normal serum calcium, phosphorous and magnesium concentrations. Other investigators have also shown that the use of magnesium-containing agents as phosphate-binders can provide effective control of serum phosphate and hyperparathyroidism and that serum magnesium levels remain within acceptable ranges [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. Spiegel et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] recently compared a regimen of MgCO<sub>3</sub> and CaCO<sub>3</sub> versus one with calcium acetate and found that the two were equally effective as phosphate-binders.</p>
      <p>In our study, MgCO<sub>3</sub> was well tolerated by most of our patients &#x2013; only two of the 25 patients (8%) of this group were removed from the study, one for diarrhea and the other for hypermagnesemia. A third patient complained initially of mild diarrhea and abdominal discomfort, but this resolved after the first week. In comparison, five patients in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> arm complained of constipation, but none dropped out of the study.</p>
      <p>Serum phosphate levels after the 4-week wash-out period were 6.63&#xA0;mg/dl in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group and 6.58&#xA0;mg/dl in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group. These values are lower than those reported by other investigators: 7.7&#xA0;mg/dl by Qunibi et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] in the CARE study, 7.4&#x2013;7.7&#xA0;mg/dl by Chertow et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] in the Treat to Goal study and 6.6&#x2013;7.2&#xA0;mg/dl by Asmus et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. However, in the recently presented preliminary results of the CARE 2 study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], patients&#x2019; mean serum phosphate values were 6.5&#x2013;6.6&#xA0;mg/dl. Our values may have been lower because our patients adhered more closely to their diet, they were receiving an adequate dose of hemodialysis or they had neither marked hyperparathyroidism (siPTH &lt;500&#xA0;pg/ml) nor did they receive vitamin D. The Mediterranean type of diet consumed by our population on the island of Crete is less likely to cause hyperphosphatemia.</p>
      <p>The serum phosphate level was reduced equally in both groups, and after the second month of treatment the mean values of serum phosphate in the two groups were comparable. (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>In terms of the biochemical findings, the main difference between the two groups was the levels of serum calcium. Hypercalcemia is the price one has to pay for adequate phosphate-binding control with calcium-containing binders; the absence of hypercalcemia is the major advantage of magnesium-based phosphate-binders.</p>
      <p>We observed that patients receiving MgCO<sub>3</sub> were more likely to have serum calcium levels within the K/DQOI guidelines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] than those on CaCO<sub>3</sub>. Both groups of patients achieved a mean serum Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product of &lt;55&#xA0;mg<sup>2</sup>/dl<sup>2</sup> (Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Consequently, a significant proportion of patients had a Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product within the K/DQOI recommendations (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>).</p>
      <p>The risk of severe hypermagnesemia is a major concern when magnesium salts are administered to hemodialysis patients. In such patients serum magnesium levels depend chiefly on the dialysate concentration of this ion, which standardly ranges between 0.45 and 0.50&#xA0;mmol/l. In the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group we used a low magnesium dialysate, 0.30&#xA0;mmol/l, and this enabled us to avoid extreme hypermagnesemia and keep serum magnesium levels within acceptable ranges.</p>
      <p>Clinical symptoms and ECG disorders due to hypermagnesemia appear only when the level of serum magnesium &gt;4&#xA0;mg/dl [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. The ionized fraction that represents approximately 60% of the total serum magnesium is the biologically active form of this element. Truttmann et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] and Saha et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] recently demonstrated that the ionized fraction of magnesium lower in HD patients than in individuals with normal renal function; therefore, the incidence of &#x2018;real hypermagnesemia&#x2019; may be overestimated in these patients. Of note is that serum magnesium accounts for approximately 1% of the total body magnesium since it is mainly an intracellular cation. Estimation of total body magnesium is based on the determination of intracellular magnesium (IcMg) levels in skeletal muscles or in peripheral lymphocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Calculations on the levels of magnesium in these tissues in uremic patients have produced conflicting results, with positive or neutral or even a negative correlation with serum magnesium being found [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
      <p>Although we did not examine the consequences of hypomagnesemia and high serum magnesium levels, various studies have shown that hypomagnesemia plays a significant role in the pathogenesis of cardiovascular diseases and that a high serum magnesium level may retard the development and/or acceleration of arterial atherosclerosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Meema et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] first showed that &#x2018;hypermagnesemia might be associated with retardation or improvement of arterial calcifications in peritoneal dialysis patients&#x2019;. Izawa et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>] described a hemodialysis patient in whom soft-tissue calcifications resolved after treatment with a dialysate with a  high concentration of magnesium. Two studies by our team [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] clearly demonstrated that the absence of mitral annular calcifications and a thinner carotid intima media thickness in hemodialysis patients both correlated with higher levels of serum and intracellular magnesium. In a previous study, we showed that both intracellular and serum magnesium concentrations were directly associated with 5-year survival in 94 hemodialysis patients of our unit [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
      <p>One of the secondary objectives of the study was to investigate if MgCO<sub>3</sub> effectively controls serum iPTH. Calcium carbonate was more effective than MgCO<sub>3</sub> in decreasing serum iPTH. In the MgCO<sub>3</sub>-treated patients time-average mean values of iPTH during months 1&#x2013;6 were significantly higher than in those treated with CaCO<sub>3</sub> (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). However, the final levels of serum iPTH at 6&#xA0;months did not differ significantly between the two groups. Furthermore, at the end of 6&#xA0;months, a slightly higher number of patients (48%) in the MgCO<sub>3</sub> group than in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> (40%) group achieved serum iPTH values in the range of 150&#x2013;300&#xA0;pg/ml.</p>
      <p>In the presence of almost equal serum <italic>P</italic> values in the two groups, we hypothesize that the relatively higher PTH reduction in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group was due to the significant higher concentration of serum calcium in this group. On the other hand, high levels of serum magnesium have a similar, but weaker, action in suppressing PTH secretion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>, which shows the monthly follow-up of serum iPTH levels, shows that the curve of the change in mean iPTH values is different in the MgCO<sub>3</sub>-treated patients in that the mean values increase during the first month of the treatment, subsequently falling (but slower than in the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group) and finally, in the sixth month, they approach the mean iPTH values of the CaCO<sub>3</sub> group. We speculate that the shape of this curve indicates that suppressive action of serum magnesium on the parathyroid glands is weaker but delayed compared to that of serum calcium. The number of patient who had final serum iPTH values of &lt;150&#xA0;pg/ml, which could be associated with adynamic bone disease, did not differ in the two groups. However, the impact of the two regimens on the patients&#x2019; bone turn over was not included in the objectives of the study, so we did not obtain data associated with bone metabolism markers.</p>
      <p>Our experience suggests that a significant proportion of hemodialysis patients need more than one agent to achieve a satisfactory phosphate-binding. In such cases, MgCO<sub>3</sub> could be if not the primary at least the second constituent of the phosphate-binding regimen, combined ideally with a calcium-containing salt<italic>.</italic> An additional advantage is that MgCO<sub>3</sub> is much less expensive than the newest sevelamer HCL and lanthanum carbonate.</p>
      <p>The limitations of our study are: (1) it is a single-center study, although this has also a number of advantages; (2) the number of the participant patients was not large, although it is one of the largest groups reported to date; (3) the allocation of the patients to the two regimens was only partially random; (4) the relatively low starting serum phosphate level in conjunction with the no vitamin D use means that the patients were not typical of most HD patients; (5) we did not obtain data on the patients&#x2019; bone metabolism markers.</p>
      <p>In conclusion, our study showed that MgCO<sub>3</sub> administered for a period of 6&#xA0;months is an effective and inexpensive agent to control serum P levels in hemodialysis patients. Gastrointestinal disorders due to its use were minor, while its administration in combination with a low dialysate magnesium concentration reduces the risk of severe hypermagnesemia. Patients treated with MgCO<sub>3</sub> had a mild suppression of PTH, an optimum regulation of Ca&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;P product, relatively low serum calcium and no episodes of hypercalcemia. We believe that this demonstration of the effectiveness of MgCO<sub>3</sub> to bind phosphate warrants further investigation in a larger group of patients.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Open Access</title>
      <p>This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Block</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klassen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lazarus</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ofsthum</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lowrie</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chertow</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mineral metabolism, mortality, and morbidity in maintenance hemodialysis</article-title>
          <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>2208</fpage>
          <lpage>2218</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/01.ASN.0000133041.27682.A2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Block GA, Klassen PS, Lazarus JM, Ofsthum N, Lowrie EG, Chertow GM (2004) Mineral metabolism, mortality, and morbidity in maintenance hemodialysis. J Am Soc Nephrol 15:2208&#x2013;2218 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15284307</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Drueke T, Foley RN (2006) Improving outcomes in chronic kidney disease. Kidney Int Suppl 105:S1&#x2013;S4</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Salusky IB (2006) A new era in phosphate binder therapy. What are the options? Kidney Int Suppl 105:S10&#x2013;S15</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Donovan</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hammer</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moniz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parsons</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Substitution of aluminium salts by magnesium salts in control of dialysis hyperphosphatemia</article-title>
          <source>Lancet</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>880</fpage>
          <lpage>882</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">O&#x2019;Donovan R, Baldwin D, Hammer M, Moniz C, Parsons V (1980) Substitution of aluminium salts by magnesium salts in control of dialysis hyperphosphatemia. Lancet 1:880&#x2013;882 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Delmez</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kelber</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norword</surname>
              <given-names>KY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Slatopolsky</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnesium carbonate as a phosphate binder: a prospective, controlled, crossover study</article-title>
          <source>Kidney Int</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>163</fpage>
          <lpage>167</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ki.1996.22</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Delmez JA, Kelber J, Norword KY, Slatopolsky E (1996) Magnesium carbonate as a phosphate binder: a prospective, controlled, crossover study. Kidney Int 49:163&#x2013;167 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8770963</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Parsons</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papapoulos</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weston</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomlinson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Riordan</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The long-term effect of lowering dialysate magnesium on circulating parathyroid hormone in patients on regular haemodialysis therapy</article-title>
          <source>Acta Endocrinol (Copenh)</source>
          <year>1980</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <fpage>455</fpage>
          <lpage>460</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Parsons V, Papapoulos SE, Weston MJ, Tomlinson S, O&#x2019;Riordan JL (1980) The long-term effect of lowering dialysate magnesium on circulating parathyroid hormone in patients on regular haemodialysis therapy. Acta Endocrinol (Copenh) 93:455&#x2013;460 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7386116</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winer</surname>
              <given-names>RL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cutler</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arief</surname>
              <given-names>AI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lacher</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoenfeld</surname>
              <given-names>PY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coburn</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horowitz</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of a magnesium-free dialysate on magnesium metabolism during continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis</article-title>
          <source>Am J Kidney Dis</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>268</fpage>
          <lpage>275</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Shah GM, Winer RL, Cutler RE, Arief AI, Goodman WG, Lacher JW, Schoenfeld PY, Coburn JW, Horowitz AM (1987) Effects of a magnesium-free dialysate on magnesium metabolism during continuous ambulatory peritoneal dialysis. Am J Kidney Dis 10:268&#x2013;275 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3661548</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roujouleh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lavaud</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toupance</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melin</surname>
              <given-names>GP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chanard</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnesium hydroxide treatment of hyperphosphatemia in chronic hemodialysis patients with an aluminum overload</article-title>
          <source>Nephrology</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>50</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Roujouleh H, Lavaud S, Toupance O, Melin GP, Chanard G (1987) Magnesium hydroxide treatment of hyperphosphatemia in chronic hemodialysis patients with an aluminum overload. Nephrology 8:45&#x2013;50 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Guillot</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hood</surname>
              <given-names>VL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Runge</surname>
              <given-names>CF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gennari</surname>
              <given-names>FJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The use of magnesium-containing in patients with end-stage renal disease on maintenance hemodialysis</article-title>
          <source>Nephron</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>30</volume>
          <fpage>114</fpage>
          <lpage>117</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Guillot AP, Hood VL, Runge CF, Gennari FJ (1982) The use of magnesium-containing in patients with end-stage renal disease on maintenance hemodialysis. Nephron 30:114&#x2013;117 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7099318</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moriniere</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vinatier</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westeel</surname>
              <given-names>PF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cohemsolal</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belbrik</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abdulmassih</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hocine</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marie</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leflon</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roche</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnesium hydroxide as a complementary aluminium-free phosphate binder to moderate doses of oral calcium in uremic patients on chronic haemodialysis: lack of deleterious effect on bone mineralization</article-title>
          <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>651</fpage>
          <lpage>656</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moriniere P, Vinatier I, Westeel PF, Cohemsolal M, Belbrik S, Abdulmassih Z, Hocine C, Marie A, Leflon P, Roche C (1988) Magnesium hydroxide as a complementary aluminium-free phosphate binder to moderate doses of oral calcium in uremic patients on chronic haemodialysis: lack of deleterious effect on bone mineralization. Nephrol Dial Transplant 3:651&#x2013;656 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3146723</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Daugirdas</surname>
              <given-names>JT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Second generation logarithmic estimates of single pool variable volume Kt/V: an analysis of error</article-title>
          <source>J Am Soc Nephrol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>1205</fpage>
          <lpage>1213</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Daugirdas JT (1993) Second generation logarithmic estimates of single pool variable volume Kt/V: an analysis of error. J Am Soc Nephrol 4:1205&#x2013;1213 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8305648</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Spiegel DM, Farmer B, Chonhol M (2006) Magnesium carbonate is an effective phosphate binder. National Kidney Foundation, Spring Clinical Meeting 2006, Chicago</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Quinibi</surname>
              <given-names>WY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hootkins</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McDowell</surname>
              <given-names>LL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyer</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garza</surname>
              <given-names>RO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pelham</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cleveland</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Muenz</surname>
              <given-names>LR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>DY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nolan</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Treatment of hyperphosphatemia in hemodialysis patients: the Calcium Acetate Renagel Evaluation (CARE STUDY)</article-title>
          <source>Kidney Int</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>1914</fpage>
          <lpage>1926</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1523-1755.2004.00590.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Quinibi WY, Hootkins RE, McDowell LL, Meyer MS, Simon M, Garza RO, Pelham RW, Cleveland MV, Muenz LR, He DY, Nolan CR (2004) Treatment of hyperphosphatemia in hemodialysis patients: the Calcium Acetate Renagel Evaluation (CARE STUDY). Kidney Int 65:1914&#x2013;1926 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15086935</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Chertow GM, Burke SK, Raggi P, Treat to Goal Working Group (2002) Sevelamer attenuates the progression of coronary and aortic calcification in hemodialysis patients. Kidney Int 62:245&#x2013;252</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Asmus</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Braun</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krause</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two year comparison of sevelamer and calcium carbonate on cardiovascular calcification and bone density</article-title>
          <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1653</fpage>
          <lpage>1661</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/ndt/gfh894</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Asmus HG, Braun J, Krause R et al. (2005) Two year comparison of sevelamer and calcium carbonate on cardiovascular calcification and bone density. Nephrol Dial Transplant 20:1653&#x2013;1661 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15930018</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Quinibi W, Moustafa M. Kessler P, Muenz L, Budoff M (2006) Coronary artery calcification in hemodialysis patients. Preliminary results from the Calcium Acetate Renagel Evaluation-2 (CARE-2) study. Poster presented at the 39th ASN Congress, San-Diego, CA</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">National Kidney Foundation (2003) K/DOQI clinical practice guidelines for bone metabolism and disease in chronic kidney disease patients. Am J Kidney Dis 42[Suppl 3]:S1&#x2013;S202</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agus</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moral</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modulation of cardiac ion channels by magnesium</article-title>
          <source>Ainu Rev Physiol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>299</fpage>
          <lpage>307</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.ph.53.030191.001503</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agus ZS, Moral M (1991) Modulation of cardiac ion channels by magnesium. Ainu Rev Physiol 53:299&#x2013;307 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Truttmann</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farina</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vizier</surname>
              <given-names>RO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niftier</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pfister</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bianchetti</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Maintenance hemodialysis and circulating ionized magnesium</article-title>
          <source>Nephron</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>616</fpage>
          <lpage>621</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000064109</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Truttmann AC, Farina R, Vizier RO, Niftier JM, Pfister R, Bianchetti MG (2002) Maintenance hemodialysis and circulating ionized magnesium. Nephron 92:616&#x2013;621 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12372946</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saha</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harmoinen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nisula</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pasternack</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Serum ionized versus total magnesium in patients with chronic renal disease</article-title>
          <source>Nephron</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>149</fpage>
          <lpage>152</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1159/000045158</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Saha H, Harmoinen A, Nisula M, Pasternack A (1998) Serum ionized versus total magnesium in patients with chronic renal disease. Nephron 80:149&#x2013;152 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9736811</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kelepouris</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agus</surname>
              <given-names>ZS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Hypomagnesaemia: renal magnesium handling</article-title>
          <source>Semin Nephrol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>58</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kelepouris E, Agus ZS (1998) Hypomagnesaemia: renal magnesium handling. Semin Nephrol 18:58&#x2013;73 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9459289</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hutchison</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Serum magnesium and end-stage renal disease</article-title>
          <source>Perit Dial Int</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>327</fpage>
          <lpage>329</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hutchison AJ (1997) Serum magnesium and end-stage renal disease. Perit Dial Int 17:327&#x2013;329 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9284456</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mountokalakis</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnesium metabolism in chronic renal failure</article-title>
          <source>Magnes Res</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>121</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mountokalakis TD (1990) Magnesium metabolism in chronic renal failure. Magnes Res 3:121&#x2013;127 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2133626</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maier</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Low magnesium and atherosclerosis: an evidence-based link</article-title>
          <source>Mol Aspects Med</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>137</fpage>
          <lpage>146</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0098-2997(02)00095-X</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Maier J (2003) Low magnesium and atherosclerosis: an evidence-based link. Mol Aspects Med 24:137&#x2013;146 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12537993</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ueshima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Magnesium and ischemic heart disease: a review of epidemiological, experimental, and clinical evidences</article-title>
          <source>Magnes Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>275</fpage>
          <lpage>284</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ueshima K (2005) Magnesium and ischemic heart disease: a review of epidemiological, experimental, and clinical evidences. Magnes Res 18:275&#x2013;284 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16548143</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meema</surname>
              <given-names>HE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oreopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>DG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rapaport</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Serum magnesium level and calcification in end-stage renal disease</article-title>
          <source>Kidney Int</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>388</fpage>
          <lpage>394</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/ki.1987.222</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Meema HE, Oreopoulos DG, Rapaport A (1987) Serum magnesium level and calcification in end-stage renal disease. Kidney Int 32:388&#x2013;394 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3669498</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Izawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imura</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuroda</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takeda</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of magnesium on secondary hyperparathyroidism in chronic hemodialysis: a case with soft tissue calcification improved by high Mg dialysate</article-title>
          <source>Calcif Tissue Res</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>162</fpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Izawa H, Imura M, Kuroda M, Takeda R (1974) Effect of magnesium on secondary hyperparathyroidism in chronic hemodialysis: a case with soft tissue calcification improved by high Mg dialysate. Calcif Tissue Res 15:162 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4844404</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tzanakis</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pras</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kounali</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mamali</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kartsonakis</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mayopoulou-Symvoulidou</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kallivretakis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mitral annular calcification in hemodialysis patients: a possible protective role of magnesium</article-title>
          <source>Nephrol Dial Transplant</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>2036</fpage>
          <lpage>2037</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tzanakis I, Pras A, Kounali D, Mamali V, Kartsonakis V, Mayopoulou-Symvoulidou D, Kallivretakis N (1987) Mitral annular calcification in hemodialysis patients: a possible protective role of magnesium. Nephrol Dial Transplant 12:2036&#x2013;2037 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9306378</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tzanakis</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virvidakis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsomi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mantakas</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Girousis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karefylakis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Papadaki</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kallivretakis</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mountokalakis</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intra- and extracellular magnesium levels and atheromatosis in haemodialysis patients</article-title>
          <source>Magnes Res</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>102</fpage>
          <lpage>108</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tzanakis I, Virvidakis K, Tsomi A, Mantakas E, Girousis N, Karefylakis N, Papadaki A, Kallivretakis N, Mountokalakis T (2004) Intra- and extracellular magnesium levels and atheromatosis in haemodialysis patients. Magnes Res 17:102&#x2013;108 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15319142</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Tzanakis I, Tsomi A, Papadaki A, Mantakas E, Kallivretakis N (2006) The higher intracellular magnesium, the better long-term survival on hemodialysis. Poster presented at the 39th ASN Congress, San Diego, CA</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Esbaei</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bargman</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oreopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationship between serum magnesium, parathyroid hormone, and vascular calcification in patients on dialysis: a literature review</article-title>
          <source>Perit Dial Int</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>366</fpage>
          <lpage>373</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wei M, Esbaei K, Bargman J, Oreopoulos D (2006) Relationship between serum magnesium, parathyroid hormone, and vascular calcification in patients on dialysis: a literature review. Perit Dial Int 26:366&#x2013;373 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16722031</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>