<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xmlns:mml="http://www.w3.org/1998/Math/MathML" article-type="research-article" xml:lang="EN">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Antimicrob Chemother</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="publisher-id">jac</journal-id>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="hwp">jac</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Antimicrobial Chemotherapy</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0305-7453</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1460-2091</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18359757</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2386081</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/jac/dkn122</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">dkn122</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Research</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Microbiological evaluation of a new growth-based approach for rapid detection of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic></article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>von Eiff</surname>
            <given-names>Christof</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="corresp" rid="cor1">*</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Maas</surname>
            <given-names>Dominik</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Sander</surname>
            <given-names>Gunnar</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Friedrich</surname>
            <given-names>Alexander W.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Peters</surname>
            <given-names>Georg</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name>
            <surname>Becker</surname>
            <given-names>Karsten</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="af1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
      </contrib-group>
      <aff id="af1"><label>1</label><institution>Institute of Medical Microbiology, University Hospital of M&#xFC;nster</institution>, <addr-line>Domagkstr. 10, 48149 M&#xFC;nster</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
      <aff id="af2"><label>2</label><institution>Institute for Hygiene, University Hospital of M&#xFC;nster</institution>, <addr-line>Robert-Koch-Str. 41, 48149 M&#xFC;nster</addr-line>, <country>Germany</country></aff>
      <author-notes>
        <corresp id="cor1"><label>*</label>Corresponding author. Tel: <phone>+49-251-83-55360</phone>; Fax: <fax>+49-251-83-55350</fax>; E-mail: <email>eiffc@uni-muenster.de</email></corresp>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>6</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="pmc-release">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>61</volume>
      <issue>6</issue>
      <fpage>1277</fpage>
      <lpage>1280</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-request">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author 2008. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</copyright-statement>
      <copyright-year>2008</copyright-year>
      <license license-type="creative-commons" xlink:href="http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/">
        <p>The online version of this article has been published under an open access model. Users are entitled to use, reproduce, disseminate, or display the open access version of this article for non-commercial purposes provided that: the original authorship is properly and fully attributed; the Journal and Oxford University Press are attributed as the original place of publication with the correct citation details given; if an article is subsequently reproduced or disseminated not in its entirety but only in part or as a derivative work this must be clearly indicated. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org</p>
      </license>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Objectives</title>
          <p>Recently, a rapid screening tool for methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) has been introduced that applies a novel detection technology allowing the rapid presence or absence of MRSA to be determined from an enrichment broth after only a few hours of incubation. To evaluate the reliability of this new assay to successfully detect MRSA strains of different origin and clonality, well-characterized <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strains were tested in this study.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec sec-type="methods">
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>More than 700 methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant strains covering &gt;90% of all registered European MRSA <italic>spa</italic> types within the SeqNet network were studied.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>All 513 MRSA strains tested were recognized as methicillin-resistant: among these, 96 MRSA strains were from an institutional collection, each presenting a unique <italic>spa</italic> type. None of the 211 methicillin-susceptible strains were detected as positive.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>The new growth-based rapid MRSA assay was shown to detect without exception all MRSA strains of large collections of strains comprising highly diverse genetic backgrounds, indicating that such a phenotypic test might be potentially more likely to cope with new strains.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>staphylococci</kwd>
        <kwd>MRSA</kwd>
        <kwd>infection control</kwd>
        <kwd><italic>spa</italic> typing</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="s1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The increasing numbers of multidrug-resistant Gram-positive pathogens have generated worldwide concern in the medical community. In particular, methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) is a major cause of disease and healthcare expenditures in almost every continent. The emergence and spread of MRSA has been shown to be associated with both hospital- and community-acquired infections. Effective treatment options for these infections are limited and the situation may become more severe soon. For these reasons, a proactive management of MRSA in healthcare facilities is needed.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C2">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Active screening and compliance to appropriate infection control activities have been shown to play an important role in the control of MRSA.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C1">1</xref></sup> Rapid diagnostic tests have the potential to make efforts even more effective. Thus, infection prevention has taken a step forward with the introduction of various tests for rapid identification of MRSA carriers.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C1">1</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C2">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In 2006, a new rapid method based on a novel bioluminescence detection technology for the rapid detection of MRSA directly from specimens was published.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C3">3</xref></sup> An improved version of this assay, the 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test (3M Company, Maplewood, MN, USA), was recently introduced, which allows the presence or absence of MRSA to be determined within 5 h. Although the clinical performance has been previously analysed,<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C5">5</xref></sup> so far no data are available on the detection of MRSA strains with highly diverse genetic backgrounds.</p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to assess the reliability of this assay to successfully detect MRSA strains circulating currently in Germany and other parts of Europe on the basis of several well-characterized <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strain collections. For this purpose, <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strains of different origin and clonality comprising 724 methicillin-susceptible and methicillin-resistant strains comprising &gt;90% of all registered European MRSA <italic>spa</italic> types within the SeqNet network (<uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.SeqNet.org">www.SeqNet.org</uri>) were tested in this study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec sec-type="materials|methods" id="s2">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <p>All staphylococcal strains were freshly isolated from clinical material at the University of M&#xFC;nster or during the course of various multicenter studies. One hundred and sixty-four strains isolated from patients with <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> bacteraemia (including 12 MRSA strains) as well as 50 isolates from the anterior nares of patients who did not subsequently develop <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> bacteraemia in a subsequent observation period (4 MRSA strains), were included into this study. Apart from 28 isolates from 14 patients (<italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> first recovered from the anterior nares and subsequently from blood, one infected with MRSA), only one isolate per patient was tested. In addition, 96 MRSA strains, each presenting a unique <italic>spa</italic> type, were selected from our institutional collection (Table&#xA0;<xref ref-type="table" rid="DKN122TB1">1</xref>). Furthermore, four hundred MRSA isolates were collected during the course of a recent multicenter study, also including community-acquired MRSA. In total, the 724 <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strains tested comprised 211 methicillin-susceptible <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> (MSSA) and 513 MRSA strains.</p>
      <table-wrap id="DKN122TB1" position="float">
        <label>Table&#xA0;1</label>
        <caption>
          <p>Grouping of <italic>spa</italic> types tested in this study into <italic>spa</italic> clonal complexes (<italic>spa</italic>-CCs)</p>
        </caption>
        <table frame="hsides" rules="groups">
          <colgroup span="1">
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
            <col align="left" span="1"/>
          </colgroup>
          <thead>
            <tr>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>spa</italic>-CC<sup>a</sup></th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1"><italic>spa</italic> types<sup>b</sup></th>
              <th align="left" rowspan="1" colspan="1">Putative MLST types<sup>c</sup></th>
            </tr>
          </thead>
          <tbody>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">001</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t001, t002, t003, t010, t035, t039, t041, t045, t055, t057, t066, t105, t106, t109, t110, t143, t149, t151, t264, t265, t422, t820, t892, t1018</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-5, ST-45, ST-46, ST-222, ST-225, ST-228, ST-231, ST-111, ST-228</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">004</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t004, t028, t029, t033, t040, t043, t061, t065, t141, t142, t266, t911</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-45, ST-45, ST-46</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">015</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t015, t031, t069, t073, t102, t116, t133</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-45</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">024</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t008, t009, t024, t036, t051, t052, t068, t113, t115, t139, t146, t243, t305</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-8, ST-235, ST-247, ST-250, ST-254, ST-247, ST-250</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">032</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t005, t022, t032, t107, t290, t379, t432, t794</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-22, ST-23, ST-60</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">037</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t011, t030, t037, t047, t108, t135, t137, t138</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-30, ST-239, ST-240, ST-241, ST-246</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">038</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t038, t161, t247</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-45</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">044</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t042, t044, t131</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-80</td>
            </tr>
            <tr>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">Singletons</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">t012, t091, t101, t104, t163, t321, t372, t417, t431, t907</td>
              <td rowspan="1" colspan="1">ST-7, ST-30, ST-22</td>
            </tr>
          </tbody>
        </table>
        <table-wrap-foot>
          <fn>
            <p><sup>a</sup>Naming of <italic>spa</italic>-CC was derived from the group founder.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn>
            <p><sup>b</sup>t026, t103, t111, t132, t145, t282, t322 and t1007 were excluded from determination of the <italic>spa</italic>-CCs due to low number of repeats.</p>
          </fn>
          <fn>
            <p><sup>c</sup>Putative MLST types were taken from the public SeqNet.org <italic>spa</italic> server database.</p>
          </fn>
        </table-wrap-foot>
      </table-wrap>
      <p>If the biochemical identification of staphylococcal isolates using the ATB 32 Staph gallery (bioM&#xE9;rieux, Marcy l&#x2019;&#xC9;toile, France) was ambiguous or categorized as unacceptable, partial 16S rRNA gene and RNA polymerase B (<italic>rpoB</italic>) gene sequencing was performed as described previously.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C6">6</xref></sup> Isolates were confirmed to be methicillin-resistant by detection of the <italic>mecA</italic> gene.</p>
      <p>To determine the clonal lineages of MRSA strains, the x region of the <italic>spa</italic> gene was amplified by PCR with primers 1095F (5&#x2032;-AGACGATCCTTCGGTGAGC-3&#x2032;) and 1517R (5&#x2032;-GCTTTTGCAATGTCATTTACTG-3&#x2032;). DNA sequences were obtained with an ABI 377 sequencer (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA, USA). <italic>spa</italic> types were determined using the Ridom StaphType software version 1.3 (Ridom GmbH, W&#xFC;rzburg, Germany), and <italic>spa</italic> clonal complexes (<italic>spa</italic>-CCs) were assigned by using the BURP algorithm.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C7">7</xref></sup></p>
      <p>The 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test is a novel culture-based test for the detection of MRSA performed on a semi-automated system comprising a sample processor and a luminometer. The assay consists of three successive selectivity steps: selective enrichment in a proprietary broth containing cefoxitin (2 mg/L) and colistin (50 mg/L), immuno-magnetic extraction using a highly specific anti-<italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> monoclonal antibody and selective lysis using lysostaphin. The selectivity steps are followed by a detection step using a highly sensitive cell marker, adenylate kinase (AK). AK is an essential enzyme found in all living cells, which regulates energy provision by catalysing the equilibrium reaction ATP + AMP = 2 ADP. By supplying a continual source of purified ADP, this assay drives the AK reaction to generate up to 40 000 ATP molecules per min. These amplified levels of ATP are measured using the luminometer supplied with the system.</p>
      <p>For the present study, test isolates were streaked on sheep blood agar plates and grown at 37&#xB0;C to confirm purity. For each isolate, one to three colonies were picked and suspended in sterile saline (0.9%) to achieve a turbidity equivalent to that of a 0.5 McFarland standard. Usually, 43 isolates were processed in each run. The 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test was performed according to the instructions of the manufacturer. In brief, 10 &#xB5;L of each prepared bacterial suspension was transferred into a vial containing 1 mL of selective enrichment broth. Vials were incubated at 37&#xB0;C for 2 h before 150 &#xB5;L aliquots of each test sample were transferred into two adjacent wells of a 96-well assay plate, each containing 20 &#xB5;L of capture reagent. MRSA cells bound to the monoclonal antibody on the capture reagent were then extracted from the sample matrix using the sample processor and concentrated in 100 &#xB5;L of broth. One well for each sample was processed automatically for a baseline signal (T0) in the BacLite luminometer. After a further incubation period of 2 h at 37&#xB0;C, the second well for each sample was processed in the same way (T2 reading). Results are expressed in relative light units and interpreted as either a positive or negative screen result by a software embedded algorithm. Positive and negative controls as well as reagent and broth controls were included in each test run. A run took &#x223C;5 h with a total hands-on time of 45&#x2013;50 min (&lt;1.5 min per tested isolate).</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s3">
      <title>Results and discussion</title>
      <p>Analysing a total of 724 <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic> strains, all 513 MRSA strains tested were recognized as MRSA, whereas none of the 211 MSSA strains was detected positive by the 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test. These results are particularly impressive as the institutional MRSA strain collection used in this study represents more than 90 different <italic>spa</italic> types covering &gt;90% of all registered European MRSA <italic>spa</italic> types within the SeqNet network (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKN122TB1">1</xref>). Beside several singletons, the MRSA enrolled in this study were grouped into eight <italic>spa</italic> clonal complexes (Table <xref ref-type="table" rid="DKN122TB1">1</xref>). Thus, a very large number of MRSA strains with different genetic backgrounds were recognized as MRSA using this novel method.</p>
      <p>Hospitals and other healthcare facilities across the world are faced with alarming rates of infections caused by MRSA. Continuous spread of these pathogens requires efficient strategies for infection control. Early identification of MRSA carriers among hospitalized patients is crucial to prevent its spread.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C1">1</xref></sup> Therefore, rapid availability of laboratory results is of utmost importance. However, conventional screening methods require prolonged incubation and confirmatory testing. During this time, MRSA-negative patients may be held in unnecessary isolation, whereas unidentified MRSA-positive individuals remain a hidden reservoir for cross-infection. A rapid negative result should allow more effective use of hospital isolation resources, whereas a rapid positive result should help reduce the spread of the infection and MRSA infection rates.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C2">2</xref></sup></p>
      <p>In the past few years, several in-house and commercial rapid MRSA assays based on molecular techniques have been introduced for the detection of this pathogen directly from the specimen, mostly from the anterior nares. The first molecular assays developed were based on the detection of an <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic>-specific sequence and the <italic>mecA</italic> gene, which encodes methicillin resistance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C8">8</xref></sup> These tests are difficult to use for the direct detection of MRSA from non-sterile specimens, such as nasal samples, because of the likely co-presence of MSSA and methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative staphylococci.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C9">9</xref></sup> In a setting of low prevalence of MRSA, a molecular test targeting the <italic>mecA</italic> and an <italic>S</italic>. <italic>aureus</italic>-specific gene in parallel applied directly to clinical specimens would result in a high number of false positives and unacceptable performance.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C9">9</xref></sup></p>
      <p>This technical limitation has been overcome in some assays, by linking detection of the presence of the <italic>mecA</italic> gene with detection of the neighbouring chromosome-borne <italic>orfX</italic> gene.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C10">10</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C11">11</xref></sup> In that approach, regions near the integration site of SCC<italic>mec</italic> were targeted as surrogate markers instead of the <italic>mecA</italic> gene itself. However, these flanking regions are known to be more heterogeneous than assumed so far.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C10">10</xref></sup> Thus, false-negative results due to variations within the primer binding sites may occur. Moreover, false-positive results due to the detection of DNA from non-viable MRSA, deletions or replacement of the <italic>mec</italic> region <italic>in vivo</italic> or &#x2018;ghost sequences&#x2019; such as partial SCC<italic>mec</italic> sequences in MSSA can occur, albeit their incidence in the routine clinical setting is as yet unclear.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C12">12</xref></sup> Despite the technical improvements in recent molecular-based assays, their high costs and relatively high operator skill requirement remain obstacles to their widespread routine use.</p>
      <p>The ability of a test to detect a broad range of MRSA clones is particularly important for an assay that may be used across a wide geographic region as tests with gaps in detection could potentially &#x2018;select out&#x2019; strains whose spread would be uncontrolled.</p>
      <p>Beside a variety of method-inherent limitations, rapid DNA-based methods amplify the nucleic acid and not the organism, which means the MRSA strain is unavailable for further characterization, such as determination of the resistance profile and strain typing. In contrast, applying the rapid growth-based assay tested here, any further examinations to characterize the respective strains will be possible from the enrichment broth.</p>
      <p>For the 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test, a diagnostic sensitivity of 94.6% and diagnostic specificity of 96.9% for nasal screening swabs and 95.9% sensitivity and 88.8% specificity for groin screening swabs, respectively, have been reported.<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C5">5</xref></sup> The analytical limit of detection of the assay was shown to be &#x2264;94 cfu (3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test, Instructions for Use).<sup><xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C4">4</xref>,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="DKN122C5">5</xref></sup></p>
      <p>Here, the new growth-based rapid MRSA assay was shown to detect without exception all MRSA strains of large collections of strains comprising highly diverse genetic backgrounds. Such a phenotypic test might be potentially more likely to cope with new strains. Further studies are warranted to evaluate this method using clinical specimens.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s4">
      <title>Funding</title>
      <p>This work was supported in part by a grant from the Bundesministerium f&#xFC;r Bildung und Forschung (BMBF), Germany (Pathogenomic Plus Network PTJ-BIO/0313801B). The device and the respective assay consumables were given to us by 3M for this study.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="s5">
      <title>Transparency declarations</title>
      <p>Two of the authors (A. W. F. and K. B.) delivered independent scientific presentations at 3M-supported symposia. C. v. E. is a member of 3M&#x2019;s Scientific Advisory Board. All other authors: none to declare.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We would like to thank A. Eggemann for excellent experimental assistance.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list>
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="DKN122C1">
        <label>1</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kluytmans</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Control of meticillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) and the value of rapid tests</article-title>
          <source>J Hosp Infect</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
          <fpage>100</fpage>
          <lpage>4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17540251</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C2">
        <label>2</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harbarth</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Masuet-Aumatell</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schrenzel</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of rapid screening and pre-emptive contact isolation for detecting and controlling methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> in critical care: an interventional cohort study</article-title>
          <source>Crit Care</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>R25</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469125</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C3">
        <label>3</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Millar</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matthews</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of BacLite Rapid MRSA, a rapid culture based screening test for the detection of ciprofloxacin and methicillin resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> (MRSA) from screening swabs</article-title>
          <source>BMC Microbiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>83</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17010192</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C4">
        <label>4</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;Hara</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gregory</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Taylor</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of the 3M&#x2122; BacLite&#x2122; Rapid MRSA Test for the direct detection of MRSA from nasal and groin surveillance specimens</article-title>
          <source>Abstracts of the Annual Meeting of the Infectious Diseases Society of America, San Diego, CA, 2007</source>
          <publisher-loc>Arlington, VA, USA</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Infectious Diseases Society of America</publisher-name>
          <comment>Abstract 540, pp. 162&#x2013;3</comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C5">
        <label>5</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bagoole</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evaluation of the 3M BacLite Rapid MRSA test for the direct detection of MRSA</article-title>
          <source>Abstracts of the Institute of Biomedical Science International Congress, Birmingham, UK, 2007</source>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Institute of Biomedical Science</publisher-name>
          <comment>
            <uri xlink:type="simple" xlink:href="www.ibms.org">www.ibms.org</uri>
          </comment>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C6">
        <label>6</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harmsen</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mellmann</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Development and evaluation of a quality-controlled ribosomal sequence database for 16S ribosomal DNA-based identification of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>4988</fpage>
          <lpage>95</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15528685</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C7">
        <label>7</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strommenger</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettlitz</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weniger</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Assignment of <italic>Staphylococcus</italic> isolates to groups by <italic>spa</italic> typing, <italic>Sma</italic>I macrorestriction analysis, and multilocus sequence typing</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>2533</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16825376</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C8">
        <label>8</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Petinaki</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arvaniti</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dimitracopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of <italic>mecA</italic>, <italic>mecR1</italic> and <italic>mecI</italic> genes among clinical isolates of methicillin-resistant staphylococci by combined polymerase chain reactions</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>297</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11222562</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C9">
        <label>9</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Becker</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pagnier</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schuhen</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Does nasal cocolonization by methicillin-resistant coagulase-negative staphylococci and methicillin-susceptible <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> strains occur frequently enough to represent a risk of false-positive methicillin-resistant <italic>S. aureus</italic> determinations by molecular methods?</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>229</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16390977</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C10">
        <label>10</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huletsky</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Giroux</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rossbach</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>New real-time PCR assay for rapid detection of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> directly from specimens containing a mixture of staphylococci</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Microbiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>1875</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15131143</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C11">
        <label>11</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cuny</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Witte</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>PCR for the identification of methicillin-resistant <italic>Staphylococcus aureus</italic> (MRSA) strains using a single primer pair specific for SCC<italic>mec</italic> elements and the neighbouring chromosome-borne <italic>orfX</italic></article-title>
          <source>Clin Microbiol Infect</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>834</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16153258</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="DKN122C12">
        <label>12</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Corkill</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anson</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Griffiths</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Detection of elements of the staphylococcal cassette chromosome (SCC) in a methicillin-susceptible (<italic>mecA</italic> gene negative) homologue of a fucidin-resistant MRSA</article-title>
          <source>J Antimicrob Chemother</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>229</fpage>
          <lpage>31</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15150163</pub-id>
        </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>