<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="brief-report">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">J Chem Ecol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Journal of Chemical Ecology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0098-0331</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-1561</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18408973</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2373414</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9464</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-008-9464-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Rapid Communication</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Defense-Inducing Volatiles: In Search of the Active Motif</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Heil</surname>
            <given-names>Martin</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>mheil@ira.cinvestav.mx</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Lion</surname>
            <given-names>Ulrich</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Boland</surname>
            <given-names>Wilhelm</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Departamento de Ingenier&#xED;a Gen&#xE9;tica, CINVESTAV, Km. 9.6 Libramiento Norte, Irapuato, CP 36821 Guanajuato M&#xE9;xico </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of General Botany, Plant Ecology, University of Duisburg-Essen, Universit&#xE4;tsstra&#xDF;e 5, 45117 Essen, Germany </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Deparment of Bioorganic Chemistry, Max-Planck-Institute for Chemical Ecology, Hans-Kn&#xF6;ll-Str. 8, 07745 Jena, Germany </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>12</day>
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>34</volume>
      <issue>5</issue>
      <fpage>601</fpage>
      <lpage>604</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>6</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>3</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Herbivore-induced volatile organic compounds (VOCs) are widely appreciated as an indirect defense mechanism since carnivorous arthropods use VOCs as cues for host localization and then attack herbivores. Another function of VOCs is plant&#x2013;plant signaling. That VOCs elicit defensive responses in neighboring plants has been reported from various species, and different compounds have been found to be active. In order to search for a structural motif that characterizes active VOCs, we used lima bean (<italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic>), which responds to VOCs released from damaged plants with an increased secretion of extrafloral nectar (EFN). We exposed lima bean to (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, a substance naturally released from damaged lima bean and known to induce EFN secretion, and to several structurally related compounds. (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate, 5-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenylisovalerate, and (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenylbutyrate all elicited significant increases in EFN secretion, demonstrating that neither the (<italic>Z</italic>)-configuration nor the position of the double-bond nor the size of the acid moiety are critical for the EFN-inducing effect. Our result is not consistent with previous concepts that postulate reactive electrophile species (Michael-acceptor-systems) for defense-induction in Arabidopsis. Instead, we postulate that physicochemical processes, including interactions with odorant binding proteins and resulting in changes in transmembrane potentials, can underlie VOCs-mediated signaling processes.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Herbivore-induced volatiles</kwd>
        <kwd>Hexenyl acetate</kwd>
        <kwd>Indirect defense</kwd>
        <kwd>Induced defense</kwd>
        <kwd>Plant-plant communication</kwd>
        <kwd>Signal</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Plants respond to herbivore damage with the release of volatile organic compounds (VOCs) that signal the presence of herbivore prey to predators and parasites and thereby serve as an indirect defense mechanism (e.g., Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2008</xref>). Research has demonstrated that these VOCs can also be perceived by neighboring plants or intact, systemic parts of the damaged plant (Baldwin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2006</xref>; Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2008</xref>). Particularly, green-leaf volatiles (GLVs) have been associated with induced resistance in intact plants (Arimura et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2000</xref>; Engelberth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>; Farag et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>; Ruther and Kleier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2005</xref>; Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>;). However, little is known about the identity of VOCs that are active in this context or about a structural motif that active VOCs might have in common. In an attempt to explain the inducing activity of such VOCs on gene expression, it has been suggested that GLVs with an &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-unsaturated carbonyl group such as (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal can trigger defense responses in Arabidopsis through their activity as reactive electrophile species (Almeras et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2003</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the present study, we used lima bean (<italic>Phaseolus lunatus</italic> L.) to search for traits that characterize defense-inducing VOCs. Lima bean responds to herbivore damage with the jasmonate-mediated production of VOCs and extrafloral nectar (EFN), an aqueous, sugar-containing secretion on nonreproductive plant organs that attracts predatory arthropods (mainly ants). The natural blend of VOCs that is released from a herbivore-damaged lima bean induces EFN secretion in intact neighboring plants (Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>) and serves as a within-plant signal (Heil and Silva Bueno <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2007</xref>). Among the quantitatively dominant VOCs that are released from induced lima bean, however, only (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate significantly induced EFN secretion when used as pure compound (Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>). In the present study, we applied different structurally related esters to lima bean plants and monitored their EFN secretion.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and Methods</title>
      <p>Plants were cultivated from seeds collected in the coastal area of Puerto Escondido, Oaxaca, M&#xE9;xico (15&#xB0;55.596 N and 097&#xB0;09.118 W, elevation 15&#xA0;m). Seedlings were cultivated under ambient conditions in 250&#xA0;ml pots filled with soil from the original growing site. The plants were watered daily and fertilized 6&#xA0;weeks after germination with commercial fertilizer: 10&#xA0;ml per plant of a solution of 3&#xA0;mg l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> of &#x201C;Fertilisante foliar de alta concentraci&#xF3;n&#x201D; (Grupo Bioqu&#xED;mico Mexicano, Aaltillo, Coah., Mexico). Experiments were conducted with plants of an age of 8&#x2013;10&#xA0;weeks. The following compounds were dissolved in Lanolin paste (all at 0.1&#xA0;&#x3BC;g &#x3BC;l<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>): (A) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (B) (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (C) (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate, (D) 5-hexenyl acetate, (E) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl isovalerate, (F) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl butyrate, (G) 2-ethylhexanol, (H) (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexanal, (I) decanal, and (K) nonanal (Lanolin paste and all compounds were purchased from Sigma Aldrich). Each 0.25&#xA0;g paste per plant was applied on green plastic stripes (MAX Bindeband) attached to the plant in order to avoid direct contact of the paste with the plant. The plants were then packed in perforated PET foil bags (Bratenschlauch, Toppits, Minden, Germany) and in nets to protect them from EFN consumers. Amounts of VOCs released from the lanolin paste into the plants&#x2019; headspace under these conditions were monitored in a parallel experiment that used a closed-loop stripping system as described previously (Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>). EFN secretion was quantified from the five youngest leaves 24&#xA0;h later. In short, EFN concentration was measured with a portable refractometer, and nectar volume was measured with glass capillaries (Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>) to calculate the total amount of soluble solids secreted, which in the case of lima bean EFN are mainly glucose, fructose, and sucrose. Leaves were then collected and dried to calculate EFN secretion as soluble solids secreted per gram leaf dry mass and per 24&#xA0;h. Plants to which Lanolin paste without any compound added had been applied served as controls (Lanolin control, LC). Per day, two groups each comprising all 11 treatments were investigated, and in total eight plants per treatment were used.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Results and Discussion</title>
      <p>Amounts of VOCs released from the lanolin paste into the plant&#x2019;s headspace resembled those released from an induced plant, i.e., all individual VOCs were present at 80&#x2013;130% of the amount of (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate that is released under comparable conditions from five induced leaves of lima bean (data not shown, for amounts of VOCs released from an induced plant see Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>). The different VOCs to which lima bean plants had been exposed affected their EFN secretion significantly (General linear model: <italic>F</italic><sub>77,10</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;10.05, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001). Compounds A&#x2013;F consisted of acyl hexenols in which the configuration and position of the double bond was systematically shifted from the polar head to the aliphatic terminus of the molecule. Moreover, the importance of the size of the acyl moiety was evaluated by using acetates, butyrate, and isovalerate of (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenol. Although only one of the tested VOCs is naturally released from lima bean, exposure to the six compounds (A&#x2013;F) elicited EFN secretions that were significantly higher than those of the controls (LSD posthoc analysis: <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05, see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). These compounds were (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate, 5-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl isovalerate, and (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl butyrate. Hence, EFN secretion by lima bean can be induced by VOCs that are not released naturally from this species, while several VOCs that are released from induced plants did not significantly change EFN secretion in previous experiments (Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>EFN secretion in &#x3BC;g soluble solids secreted per gram leaf dry mass and per 24&#xA0;h is depicted. Plants were exposed for 24&#xA0;h to (<italic>A</italic>) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>B</italic>) (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>C</italic>) (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>D</italic>) 5-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl isovalerate, (<italic>F</italic>) (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl butyrate, (<italic>G</italic>) 2-ethylhexanol, (<italic>H</italic>) (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexanal, (<italic>I</italic>) decanal, and (<italic>K</italic>) nonanal dissolved in Lanolin paste. Plants to which pure Lanolin paste had been applied served as controls (<italic>LC</italic>). Lower and upper whiskers represent the 5% and the 95% percentile, lower and upper margins of boxes the 25% and the 75% percentile, the <italic>lines within boxes</italic> indicate medians. <italic>Different letters appearing above boxes</italic> mark treatment effects that differ significantly from each other (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05 according to LSD posthoc analysis), and structures of compounds leading to a significant induction of EFN secretion as compared to the control are graphically presented. LogP values of all compounds were calculated with ChemDraw Ultra 6.0 and are given under the structures (compounds <italic>A</italic>&#x2013;<italic>F</italic>) and in the insert (<italic>G</italic>&#x2013;<italic>K</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="10886_2008_9464_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>How are VOCs perceived by plants, and via which mechanisms do they affect defense expression patterns? It has been suggested that molecules with an &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-unsaturated carbonyl group can trigger defenses in Arabidopsis through their activity as reactive electrophile species (Almeras et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2003</xref>). In principle, VOCs could also be perceived by binding to specific receptor-proteins or to odorant binding proteins with a preference for a class of compounds, similar to animal olfactory systems.</p>
      <p>Apparently, neither the configuration nor the position of the double bound is a critical factor. Compounds reported to prime or induce gene activity or phenotypic defenses in intact corn plants comprise (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexen-1-ol, (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenal, and (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate (Engelberth et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2004</xref>; Farag et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2005</xref>; Ruther and Kleier <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2005</xref>). We found that (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate, (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate, and 5-hexenyl acetate all elicited particularly high EFN secretion rates in lima bean. The majority of these substances lack an &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-unsaturated carbonyl group, which thus cannot be a generally required motif. In addition, a compound such as 5-hexenyl acetate cannot yield an electrophile such as (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal via the sequence of ester hydrolysis, oxidation, and isomerization, as it is principally possible for (<italic>E</italic> or <italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate or (<italic>E</italic> or <italic>Z</italic>)-2-hexenyl acetate. Moreover, unlike (Z)-3-hexenyl acetate the potential end product of the transformation sequence, (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexenal, had only a weak effect on the nectar flow. Similarly, the observation that (<italic>Z</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate and (<italic>E</italic>)-3-hexenyl acetate elicited almost identical EFN secretion rates contradicts the involvement of classical receptor proteins, since these usually require a specific stereochemistry of the interacting molecule. We further calculated LogP values to check for putative importance of the compound&#x2019;s lipophilicity but did not find any clear relation between the EFN-inducing activity of a compound and its octanol-water partition coefficient (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).</p>
      <p>More studies are required to understand which VOCs induce plant defenses via which mechanism. However, our results point to a new mechanism. Changes in transmembrane potentials&#x2014;occurring through modulations of ion fluxes&#x2014;are involved in early signaling events in the cellular response to stress (Maffei et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2007</xref>), and exposition to VOCs indeed changes membrane potentials in intact lima bean leaves (M. Maffei, personal communication). It is thus tempting to speculate that the dissolving of VOCs in the membranes coupled to interactions with membrane proteins, similar to the odorant binding proteins of insects (Campanacci et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2001</xref>), leads to changes in transmembrane potentials and thereby induces gene activity. This hypothesis gains support from the observation that the induction of EFN secretion by VOCs appears to be a gradual one rather than a clear &#x2018;yes-or-know&#x2019; response. Several of the compounds that are released naturally from lima bean showed a trend towards an increase in EFN secretion, although the difference was not significant: EFN secretion in response to Linalool was on average higher by 40% than in control plants, and DMNT ((3<italic>E</italic>)-4,8-dimethylnona-1,3,7-triene) increased EFN secretion by 50% (see Table 1 in Kost and Heil <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2006</xref>). Similarly, plants exposed to ethylhexanol or (<italic>E</italic>)-2-hexanal in the present study showed a trend towards higher EFN secretions than controls (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). EFN responds to a comparably wide variety of structures, and slight changes in the molecular structure gradually alter the induction effect. This observation is best explained by a comparably simple physicochemical process, whose detailed nature remains to be elucidated.</p>
      <p>How can signals evolve that apparently lack chemical specificity? The answer might be simply that plants seldom are exposed to GLVs or chemically related compounds that are not released from attacked plants. In evolutionary terms, the probability of this situation was probably too low to cause any selection towards a more specific signal perception.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Ralf Kr&#xFC;ger, Susann Schiwy, and Juan Carlos Silva Bueno for help with the experiments and plant cultivation. Financial support by the DFG (grant He3169/4&#x2013;2), CONACYT (Consejo National de Ciencias y Tecnologia) and the Max-Planck-Gesellschaft is gratefully acknowledged.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title><sc>R</sc>eferences</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Almeras</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stolz</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vollenweider</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reymond</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mene-saffrane</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farmer</surname>
              <given-names>E. E.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reactive electrophile species activate defense gene expression in Arabidopsis</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>202</fpage>
          <lpage>216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01718.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Almeras, E., Stolz, S., Vollenweider, S., Reymond, P., Mene-saffrane, L., and Farmer, E. E. 2003. Reactive electrophile species activate defense gene expression in Arabidopsis. Plant J 34:202&#x2013;216. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Arimura</surname>
              <given-names>G.-I.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozawa</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimoda</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nishioka</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boland</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takabayashi</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Herbivory-induced volatiles elicit defence genes in lima bean leaves</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>406</volume>
          <fpage>512</fpage>
          <lpage>515</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35020072</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Arimura, G.-I., Ozawa, R., Shimoda, T., Nishioka, T., Boland, W., and Takabayashi, J. 2000. Herbivory-induced volatiles elicit defence genes in lima bean leaves. Nature 406:512&#x2013;515. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10952311</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>I. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Halitschke</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Paschold</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Von dahl</surname>
              <given-names>C. C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Preston</surname>
              <given-names>C. A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Volatile signaling in plant-plant interactions: &#x201C;Talking trees&#x201D; in the genomics era</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>311</volume>
          <fpage>812</fpage>
          <lpage>815</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1118446</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Baldwin, I. T., Halitschke, R., Paschold, A., Von dahl, C. C., and Preston, C. A. 2006. Volatile signaling in plant-plant interactions: &#x201C;Talking trees&#x201D; in the genomics era. Science 311:812&#x2013;815. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16469918</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Campanacci</surname>
              <given-names>V.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krieger</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bette</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sturgis</surname>
              <given-names>J. N.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lartigue</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cambillau</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breer</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tegoni</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Revisiting the specificity of Mamestra brassicae and Antheraea polyphemus pheromone-binding proteins with a fluorescence binding assay</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>20078</fpage>
          <lpage>20084</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M100713200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Campanacci, V., Krieger, J., Bette, S., Sturgis, J. N., Lartigue, A., Cambillau, C., Breer, H., and Tegoni, M. 2001. Revisiting the specificity of Mamestra brassicae and Antheraea polyphemus pheromone-binding proteins with a fluorescence binding assay. J. Biol. Chem. 276:20078&#x2013;20084. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11274212</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Engelberth</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alborn</surname>
              <given-names>H. T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmelz</surname>
              <given-names>E. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tumlinson</surname>
              <given-names>J. H.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Airborne signals prime plants against insect herbivore attack</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>1781</fpage>
          <lpage>1785</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0308037100</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Engelberth, J., Alborn, H. T., Schmelz, E. A., and Tumlinson, J. H. 2004. Airborne signals prime plants against insect herbivore attack. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 101:1781&#x2013;1785. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14749516</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farag</surname>
              <given-names>M. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fokar</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>H. A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Allen</surname>
              <given-names>R. D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Par&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>P. W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>(Z)-3-Hexenol induces defense genes and downstream metabolites in maize</article-title>
          <source>Planta</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>220</volume>
          <fpage>900</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00425-004-1404-5</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Farag, M. A., Fokar, M., Zhang, H. A., Allen, R. D., and Par&#xE9;, P. W. 2005. (Z)-3-Hexenol induces defense genes and downstream metabolites in maize. Planta 220:900&#x2013;909. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15599762</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heil</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Indirect defence via tritrophic interactions</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>2008</year>
          <volume>178</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>61</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2007.02330.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Heil, M. 2008. Indirect defence via tritrophic interactions. New Phytol 178:41&#x2013;61. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18086230</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heil</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silva bueno</surname>
              <given-names>J. C.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Within-plant signaling by volatiles leads to induction and priming of an indirect plant defense in nature</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>5467</fpage>
          <lpage>5472</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.0610266104</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Heil, M., and Silva bueno, J. C. 2007. Within-plant signaling by volatiles leads to induction and priming of an indirect plant defense in nature. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 104:5467&#x2013;5472. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17360371</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kost</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heil</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Herbivore-induced plant volatiles induce an indirect defence in neighbouring plants</article-title>
          <source>J. Ecol.</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>619</fpage>
          <lpage>628</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2745.2006.01120.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kost, C., and Heil, M. 2006. Herbivore-induced plant volatiles induce an indirect defence in neighbouring plants. J. Ecol. 94:619&#x2013;628. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Maffei</surname>
              <given-names>M. E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mith&#xF6;fer</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boland</surname>
              <given-names>W.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Before gene expression: early events in plant-insect interaction</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci.</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>310</fpage>
          <lpage>316</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tplants.2007.06.001</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Maffei, M. E., Mith&#xF6;fer, A., and Boland, W. 2007. Before gene expression: early events in plant-insect interaction. Trends Plant Sci. 12:310&#x2013;316. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17596996</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ruther</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kleier</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant-plant signaling: Ethylene synergizes volatile emission in Zea mays induced by exposure to (Z)-3-Hexen-1-ol</article-title>
          <source>J. Chem. Ecol.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>2217</fpage>
          <lpage>2222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10886-005-6413-8</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ruther, J., and Kleier, S. 2005. Plant-plant signaling: Ethylene synergizes volatile emission in Zea mays induced by exposure to (Z)-3-Hexen-1-ol. J. Chem. Ecol. 31:2217&#x2013;2222. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16132223</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>