<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Knee Surgery, Sports Traumatology, Arthroscopy</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0942-2056</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1433-7347</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17237964</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1915597</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">275</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00167-006-0275-7</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Ankle</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The distal fascicle of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament as a cause of tibiotalar impingement syndrome: a current concepts review</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>van den Bekerom</surname>
            <given-names>Michel P. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-55-5818181</phone>
            <fax>+31-55-5818131</fax>
            <email>Bekerom@gmail.com</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Raven</surname>
            <given-names>Eric E. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Orthopaedic Surgery, Gelre Hospitals, Apeldoorn, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Department of Surgery and Traumatology, Gelre Hospitals, Location Lukas, P.O. Box 9014, 7300 Apeldoorn, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>20</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>15</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>465</fpage>
      <lpage>471</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Impingement syndromes of the ankle involve either osseous or soft tissue impingement and can be anterior, anterolateral, or posterior. Ankle impingement syndromes are painful conditions caused by the friction of joint tissues, which are both the cause and the effect of altered joint biomechanics. The distal fascicle of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament (AITFL) is possible cause of anterior impingement. The objective of this article was to review the literature concerning the anatomy, pathogenesis, symptoms and treatment of the AITFL impingement and finally to formulate treatment recommendations. The AITFL starts from the distal tibia, 5&#xA0;mm in average above the articular surface, and descends obliquely between the adjacent margins of the tibia and fibula, anterior to the syndesmosis to the anterior aspect of the lateral malleolus. The incidence of the accessory fascicle differs very widely in the several studies. The presence of the distal fascicle of the AITFL and also the contact with the anterolateral talus is probably a normal finding. It may become pathological, due to anatomical variations and/or anterolateral instability of the ankle resulting from an anterior talofibular ligament injury. When observed during an ankle arthroscopy, the surgeon should look for the criteria described to decide whether it is pathological and considering resection of the distal fascicle. The presence of the AITFL and the contact with the talus is a normal finding. An impingement of the AITFL can result from an anatomical variant or anteroposterior instability of the ankle. The diagnosis of ligamentous impingement in the anterior aspect of the ankle should be considered in patients who have chronic ankle pain in the anterolateral aspect of the ankle after an inversion injury and have a stable ankle, normal plain radiographs, and isolated point tenderness on the anterolateral aspect of the talar dome and in the anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament. The impingement syndrome can be treated arthroscopically.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>
          <bold>Keywords</bold>
        </title>
        <kwd>Ankle</kwd>
        <kwd>Impingement syndrome</kwd>
        <kwd>Anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament</kwd>
        <kwd>Accessory fascicle</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>
        <bold>Introduction</bold>
      </title>
      <p>Impingement syndromes of the ankle involve either osseous or soft tissue impingement and can be anterior, anterolateral, or posterior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Ankle impingement syndromes are painful conditions caused by the friction of joint tissues, which are both the cause and the effect of altered joint biomechanics [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The leading causes of impingement lesions are post-traumatic ankle injuries, usually ankle sprains, resulting in chronic ankle pain [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. According to the ISAKOS definition, anterior ankle impingement is a pain syndrome characterised by anterior ankle pain on activity. Recurrent dorsiflexion is often the cause. On investigation, there is pain on palpation at the antero/medial and/or anterolateral aspect of the ankle joint. Some swelling and/or limitations of dorsiflexion are present [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. The first reported impingement syndromes about the ankle have evolved osseous impingement and generally have been noted in athletes whose sports necessitated sudden acceleration, jumping, and extremes of dorsiflexion or plantar flexion. Impingement of the ankle was first described in the English language literature by Morris [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>], in 1943, in five patients who had what he called the athlete&#x2019;s ankle. This was later called footballer&#x2019;s ankle in the report of McMurray [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>].</p>
      <p>Soft tissue impingement of the ankle is a common cause of chronic ankle pain that usually arises at the lateral and/or anterolateral compartment of the ankle joint following an inversion injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. It is estimated that approximately 3% of ankle sprains may lead to anterolateral impingement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Three types of intra-articular soft tissue lesions that lead to these complaints have been described: the meniscoid lesion, synovitis, and the distal fascicle of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament (AITFL) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The formation of tibiotalar spurs due to repetitive capsule traction therefore does not seem plausible reason for anterior ankle impingement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>].</p>
      <p>Impinging soft tissue pathology in the ankle was first described by Wolin et&#xA0;al. as a &#x201C;meniscoid mass or lesion&#x201D; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. They described the lesion as a membrane shaped hyalinised scar tissue obstructing the lateral talofibular articulation in nine patients with persistent symptoms over the anterolateral corner of the ankle after an inversion trauma [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Some authors thought this lesion was formed from the torn ends of the anterior tibiofibular ligament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However there was no ligamentous tissue found on histologic examination of this lesion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Guhl thought the lesion was of synovial origin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Irritation of the joint by bleeding and a torn capsule or a torn anterior tibiofibular ligament are thought to be the underlying factors for developing post-traumatic synovitis in the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] which in unstable ankles may lead to formation of fibrosis and granulation tissue. Although synovitis and the meniscoid lesion have been referred frequently, impingement by a separated fascicle of the AITFL is a relatively new and unknown pathology. Bassett et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] were the first who reported a ligamentous etiology of impingement of the anterior aspect of the ankle. The presence of the so-called accessory AITFL, as described by Nikolopoulos was confirmed by them [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However they called this accessory ligament, the distal fascicle of the normal AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. The distal part of the fascicle rubs against the talus, and that this causes pain at the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
      <p>The objective of this article was to review the literature concerning the anatomy, pathogenesis, symptoms and treatment of the AITFL impingement and finally to formulate treatment recommendations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2">
      <title>
        <bold>Anatomy of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament</bold>
      </title>
      <p>The distal tibiofibular joint was classically described as a syndesmosis between the rough, triangular surface on the medial and distal aspect of the fibular shaft and the fibular notch of the distal end of the tibia. The tibiofibular syndesmosis is established by three ligaments: the interosseous ligament, the posterior inferior tibiofibular ligament, and the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].</p>
      <p>The AITFL is a flat band becoming thicker from superior to inferior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The ligament starts from the distal tibia, 5&#xA0;mm in average above the articular surface, and descends obliquely between the adjacent margins of the tibia and fibula, anterior to the syndesmosis to the anterior aspect of the lateral malleolus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Its length ranges from 12 to 20&#xA0;mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]; its thickness, from 1 to 3&#xA0;mm [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]; and its width ranges from 7 to 12&#xA0;mm at the fibular insertion and 9 to 22&#xA0;mm at the tibial insertion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. This ligament is the weakest of the syndesmotic ligaments and is the first to yield to forces that promote an external rotation of the fibula around its longitudinal axis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. Resection of the accessory ligament did not disturb the stability of the syndesmosis, a finding that was in accordance with the results reported by Rasmussen et&#xA0;al. which suggests that mobility is minimally influenced by isolated cutting of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
      <p>Nikolopoulos et&#xA0;al. studied 24 cadaveric ankles to describe the anatomy of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In five ankles the AITFL appeared to consist of two layers, one superficial and one deep, which were separated by a thin fibrofatty septum [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. However, the total thickness of these two layers did not exceed the average thickness of the AITFL in the rest of the specimens [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In five ankles, the articulated surfaces of the distal tibia and fibula that formed the syndesmosis were covered by articular cartilage and were surrounded by synovial bursa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. A completely separate accessory anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament was present in 22 ankles (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Nikolopoulos was the first to describe this accessory ligament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. However the results of his study were never published in English literature [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Nikolopoulos believed that this anatomical structure represents a separate ligament rather than a distal component of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The fact that there was clearly a fibrofatty septum that separates the AITFL from the accessory fascicle, similar to the one that covered the intermediate space between the interosseous and the anterior or the interosseous and the posterior tibiofibular ligaments, suggested that this fascicle could probably be considered an independent accessory ligament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Some other authors described this accessory ligament as a complete separate distal fascicle of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>].
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>The distal fascicle in relation to the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="167_2006_275_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>Ray and Kriz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] founded in 10 of the 46 specimens an accessory ligament. This ligament was parallel and distal to the AITFL. The fibres of the accessory ligament descended obliquely from the lateral, anterior, and distal borders of the tibia to the anteromedial aspect of the lateral malleolus, approximating the fibular insertion of the anterior talofibular ligament (ATFL).</p>
      <p>Its length ranges from 17 to 22&#xA0;mm, its thickness from 1 to 2&#xA0;mm, and its width from 3 to 5&#xA0;mm. The maximum, minimum, mean, and standard deviation for the length, width, gap, and angle of declination for the inferior fibre bundle are provided in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>. The ligament was not covered by synovial tissue, ran deeper than the AITFL and was described as being intra-articular, although how this was determined was not stated by the authors. The accessory ligament crossed the superior lateral margin of the ankle joint. The accessory ligament was separated from the AITFL by a distinct fibrofatty septum. The ligament could even be divided in two, three, or more fascicles, increasing in length from superior to inferior [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Characteristics of the inferior fascicle of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Maximum</th><th align="left">Minimum</th><th align="left">Mean</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Ligament length (cm)</td><td char="." align="char">3.4</td><td char="." align="char">2.1</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">2.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.3</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ligament width (cm)</td><td char="." align="char">1.3</td><td char="." align="char">0.2</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.4&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gap (cm)</td><td char="." align="char">0.5</td><td char="." align="char">0.1</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">0.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Declination angle (deg)</td><td char="." align="char">155.0</td><td char="." align="char">121.5</td><td char="&#xB1;" align="char">136.3&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;7.4</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>The incidence of the accessory fascicle differs very widely in the several studies (21&#x2013;92%) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The discrepancies in the incidence between the several studies were probably due to the different definitions of a separate fascicle. Ray and Kriz did not consider it a separate fascicle if any digitations were present between the fascicle and the main body of the AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. The incidence was up to 92%, which implied that the ligament may be considered as a normal finding. Vessels from the anterior peroneal artery penetrate through the interlaminar spaces [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. It is not uncommon to have branches from the anterior tibial artery or peroneal artery or a branch arising from the anastomosis between these two arteries pass between these fascicles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. The most inferior fibres of the ligament merged at their fibular attachment with the origin of the ATFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p>
      <p>Ray and Kriz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] studied 23 cadaveric ankles. A classification scheme was designed to categorise the anatomical variations observed in the AITFL (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>AITFL classification system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><tbody><tr><td align="left">Type 1</td><td align="left">Multiple fascicles (more than three) with or without small gaps between adjacent fascicles</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#xA0;1A</td><td align="left">The inferior fascicle is separated from the rest of the ligament by a gap and possesses its own distinct proximal and distal attachments</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#xA0;1B</td><td align="left">The inferior fascicle is not completely separated from the rest of the ligament by a gap. Either its proximal or its distal attachment is continuous with the rest of the ligament</td></tr><tr><td align="left"> &#xA0;1C</td><td align="left">Multiple fascicles without gaps intervening between them</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Type 2</td><td align="left">Three fascicles or less. A distinct inferior fascicle with both its proximal and distal attachments separate from the rest of the ligament. The inferior fascicle is separated completely from the main portion of the ligament by a gap</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Type 3</td><td align="left">Three fascicles or less. A distinct inferior fascicle with either its proximal or its distal attachment continuous with the rest of the ligament. A gap does not completely separate the inferior fascicle from the rest of the ligament</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Type 4</td><td align="left">Three fascicles or less. The lower portion of the ligament possesses an inferior fascicle with both its proximal and distal attachments for the rest of the ligament</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Type 5</td><td align="left">Three fascicles or less. A ligament with no separations or gaps within its structure. It may or may not possess a fascicular arrangement</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>
        <bold>Pathomechanism of the impingement syndrome</bold>
      </title>
      <p>It should be stressed that most studies were carried out in vitro and do not take muscular tonus and the effects of weightbearing into consideration, we performed a review of the pathomechanism of the impingement syndrome caused by the distal fascicle of the AITFL.</p>
      <p>Bassett et&#xA0;al. correlated the presence of this accessory ligament with pain from impingement in the anterolateral aspect of the ankle in patients with a history of inversion sprains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. They postulated that the post-traumatic anterolateral hyperlaxity, due to an injured ATFL, resulted in anterior extrusion of the talar dome with dorsiflexion, which now contacted the inferior fascicle of the AITFL with more pressure and friction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. This in turn might set up an environment favouring ligamentous impingement of the anterior aspect of the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>Akseki et&#xA0;al. stated that the variations in width, length, and obliquity of the fascicle may be related to the pathological behaviour of the fascicle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Mean width and length of the fascicle with bending during dorsiflexion and dorsiflexion-eversion were significantly higher than the fascicle without bending. Therefore this wider and longer fascicles had more potential to become pathological than thinner ones. They also conclude that if the fibular insertion point is far from the joint level, the fascicle has more potential to become pathological. These findings might be useful during arthroscopic procedures of the ankle.</p>
      <p>During dorsiflexion of the ankle the posterior shift of the anterior talus below the tibial plafond in ATFL intact cases was observed. Following incision of the ATFL this posterior shift of the talus was not observed; the talus remained in an anterior position and thus in contact with the fascicle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Lesion of the ATFL led to bending of the fascicle with dorsiflexion and dorsiflexion-inversion in the specimens which the bending sign was negative. Lesion of the ATFL led also to contact between the talus and the fascicle in the ankles which showed no contact previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. After sectioning the ATFL the anteroposterior laxity of the ankle increases especially in dorsiflexion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>].</p>
      <p>In 89.3% of the cases contact was observed between the ATFL and the anterolateral corner of the talus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This contact may be normal in some of the cases. Contact was observed at an average of 12&#xB0; of dorsiflexion of the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Bending of the accessory ligament, indicating further tensioning of its ligamentous bands caused by impingement of the talus, this was noted in an extent of dorsiflexion that varied from 5&#xB0; to 10&#xB0; (average 7&#xB0;) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. Maximum dorsiflexion of the foot relieved the contact between the ligament and the superolateral corner of the talus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In other studies the contact was also observed in neutral position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>].</p>
      <p>In one study the contact between the fascicle and talar dome was observed throughout the whole range of motion of the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. They called this the &#x201C;arthroscopic impingement test,&#x201D; and it was positive in all of the cases with AITFL impingement they have studied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Contact between the accessory fascicle and the talus was also observed during eversion of the foot, being more prominent when the foot was placed in a dorsiflexion-eversion position [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. No interaction of the accessory ligament with the talus was noted during ankle plantar flexion [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].</p>
      <p>In 82.9% of the cases with AITFL impingement Ray and Kriz [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>] found an anterior abraded articular region of the talus. Akseki et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] found this in 17% of the cases. In the study of Basset et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] 71% of the patients, had an area of abraded articular cartilage on the anterolateral surface of the talar dome. There is no clarity if this abraded cartilage region is an anatomical variant of the talus or a pathological remodelling of the bone due to true ligamentous impingement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
      <p>On base of these studies we conclude that anterolateral hyperlaxity results in anterior extrusion of the talar dome with dorsiflexion, which contacts the inferior fascicle of the AITFL with more pressure and friction. This hyperlaxity was most likely due to an injured ATFL. Wider and longer fascicles and a fibular insertion point far from the joint level have more potential to become pathological. Often contact between the AITFL and the superolateral corner of the talus and an abraded region of the cartilage of the talus can be observed during arthroscopy.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4">
      <title>
        <bold>Diagnosis</bold>
      </title>
      <p>The diagnosis of ligamentous impingement in the anterior aspect of the ankle should be considered in patients who have chronic ankle pain in the anterolateral aspect of the ankle after an inversion sprain and who have a stable ankle, normal plain radiographs, and isolated point tenderness on the anterolateral aspect of the talar dome and in the anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. A popping sensation and aggravation of pain with dorsiflexion and eversion were noted [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. This audible popping is usually not seen in other causes of impingement of the anterior aspect of the ankle [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Pain in the beginning of plantarflexion-inversion may alert the physician for an impinging AITFL [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>It is usually impossible to distinguish the source of pain in patients with both instability and impingement. So if the patient complains of giving way and frequent sprains, the surgeon may choose a reconstructive procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. But it should be noted that a painful lesion in the joint (synovitis, meniscoid lesion, or an impinging fascicle of the AITFL) may cause reflex sprains [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. This process may confuse decision making in this type of combined pathology. The differential diagnosis for pain in the lateral aspect of the ankle after an inversion sprain includes osteochondral fracture, instability of the lateral aspect of the ankle, synovitis or rupture of the peroneal tendon, and ligamentous impingement in the anterior aspect of the ankle, with the latter being the least common [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5">
      <title>
        <bold>Treatment</bold>
      </title>
      <p>Patients should be treated conservatively after an inversion sprain of the ankle for at least 6&#xA0;months before operative intervention is considered [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This is with the exception of patients with an osteochondral fracture. Akseki et&#xA0;al. observed that conservative management with physical therapy, NSAIDs and bracing in patients with instability symptoms, for a period of 3&#xA0;months, failed in all 21 patients [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>].</p>
      <p>Not every patient with chronic ankle instability needs a reconstructive procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. If the history, physical examination, and other diagnostic tests suggest impingement in addition to instability, arthroscopic debridement of the soft tissue lesion may be all that is needed [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>. In cases with an area of abraded articular cartilage on the anterolateral surface of the talar dome, further debridement of this region was required [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. At long-term follow-up arthroscopic excision of soft tissue overgrowth and osteophytes proved to be an effective way of treating anterior impingement of the ankle in patients who had no narrowing of the joint space [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. Patients with less than 2&#xA0;years of ankle pain before surgery for anterior ankle impingement showed significant better scores in pain, swelling, ability to work, and engagement in sports [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>].</p>
      <p>The decision to perform an arthroscopy of the ankle is typically based on the patient&#x2019;s history and physical examination [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. Arthroscopically resection of the distal fascicle of the AITFL should be considered when there (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>): (1) is contact between the AITFL and the talus was prominent also in the beginning of plantarflexion-inversion of the ankle, (2) is increased contact between the talus and the ligament and this continued until maximum dorsiflexion with abrasion of the articular cartilage (the surgeon should remember that this finding may be normal), (3) bending of the fascicle on the anterolateral edge of the talus with dorsiflexion and dorsiflexion-inversion, (4) is a distally inserting fascicle on the fibula, close to the origin of the ATFL on the fibula. This finding may be missed if the distraction is preserved throughout the procedure [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. For this reason, temporarily relieving distraction is advised, when a distal fascicle is seen during arthroscopy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>].
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>There is contact between the distal fascicle of AITFL and the talus in dorsiflexion with bending of this fascicle</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="167_2006_275_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      <p>Only three studies reported on the results of the treatment of AITFL impingement [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Akseki et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] arthroscopically resected the distal fascicle of the AITFL in 21 patients with chronic ankle pain after an ankle sprain. During the procedure an impinging distal fascicle of the AITFL was found in all cases. Following anterolateral synovectomie, the fascicle was excised. At an average follow-up of 3&#xA0;years good to excellent results were obtained in 17 patients. Nineteen patients were satisfied with the procedure and 17 patients returned to previous level of activity. Two patients who had mild laxity were graded as poor because neuromas of the terminal branches of the superficial peroneal nerve. These patients became asymptomatic after an injection of steroids.</p>
      <p>Bassett et&#xA0;al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] treated seven patients who had talar impingement by an AITFL and they were followed for a mean of 39&#xA0;months. Two patients had arthroscopy and five had an arthrotomy. In all patients, a thickened distal fascicle of the AITFL was resected. Five patients also needed debridement of an area of abraded hyaline cartilage on the anterolateral aspect of the talar dome at the point where the distal fascicle made contact. Post-operative management consisted of 2&#x2013;4&#xA0;days of immobilisation, followed by progressive weightbearing. Four patients reported no pain in their ankle or limitation in activity, and the results were considered to be excellent. Two patients reported improvement, with only occasional pain related to overuse, and the result was considered good. The last patient had been followed for only 6&#xA0;months with excellent results.</p>
      <p>Horner and Liu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] treated nine athletes with anterolateral ankle pain during and following athletic activities without history of ankle injury. After 3&#xA0;months conservative management each patient was explored arthroscopically. Patients&#x2019; outcomes were rated subjectively and objectively based on the UCLA ankle scoring system. Pathological characteristics were easily identifiable through arthroscopy. The structure may be resected during this procedure without sacrificing the stability of the ankle joint. They report that good to excellent results can be expected from this procedure including in the highest level of athleticism at an average follow-up of 18&#xA0;months.</p>
      <p>The decision to perform an arthroscopy of the ankle is typically based on the patient&#x2019;s history and physical examination. When an impinging distal fascicle of the AITFL and an abraded anterolateral region of the talus were observed during an ankle arthroscopy, the surgeon should look for the criteria described above to decide whether it is pathological and needs to be resected.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6" sec-type="conclusion">
      <title>
        <bold>Conclusion</bold>
      </title>
      <p>Because of the lack of evidence only preliminary conclusions can be drawn. The AITFL started from the distal tibia, 5&#xA0;mm in average above the articular surface, and descended obliquely between the adjacent margins of the tibia and fibula, anterior to the syndesmosis to the anterior aspect of the lateral malleolus. The incidence of the accessory fascicle differs very widely in the several studies. The presence of the distal fascicle of the AITFL and also the contact with the anterolateral talus is probably a normal finding. It may become pathological, however, due to anatomical variations and/or anterolateral instability of the ankle resulting from an ATFL injury. When observed during an ankle arthroscopy, the surgeon should look for the criteria described to decide whether it is pathological and considering resection of the distal fascicle.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akseki</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bozkurt</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The distal fascicle of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament as a cause of anterolateral ankle impingement</article-title>
          <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>478</fpage>
          <lpage>482</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Akseki D, Pinar H, Bozkurt M, et al (1999) The distal fascicle of the anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament as a cause of anterolateral ankle impingement. Acta Orthop Scand 70(5):478&#x2013;482 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10622481</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akseki</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pinar</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yaldiz</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The anterior tibiofibular ligament and talar impingement: a cadaveric study</article-title>
          <source>Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>326</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Akseki D, Pinar H, Yaldiz K, et al (2002) The anterior tibiofibular ligament and talar impingement: a cadaveric study. Knee Surg Sports Traumatol Arthrosc 10:321&#x2013;326 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12355310</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrews</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Drez</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGinthy</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Symposium: arthroscopy of joints other than the knee</article-title>
          <source>Contemp Orthop</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>71</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Andrews JR, Drez DJ, McGinthy JB (1984) Symposium: arthroscopy of joints other than the knee. Contemp Orthop 9:71&#x2013;100 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bassett</surname>
              <given-names>FH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gates</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Billys</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Talar impingement by the anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>72A</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bassett FH III, Gates HS III, Billys JB, et al (1990) Talar impingement by the anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament. J Bone Joint Surg 72A:55&#x2013;59 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2295673</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Canale</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Canale</surname>
              <given-names>ST</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ankle injuries</article-title>
          <source>Cambell&#x2019;s operative orthopaedics</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <edition>9th edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>St Louis</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>CV Mosby</publisher-name>
          <fpage>1079</fpage>
          <lpage>1112</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Canale ST (1998) Ankle injuries. In: Canale ST (ed) Cambell&#x2019;s operative orthopaedics, 9th edn. CV Mosby, St Louis, pp 1079&#x2013;1112 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>DeBerdino</surname>
              <given-names>MT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arciero</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tayler</surname>
              <given-names>CD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of soft-tissue impingement of the ankle in athletes</article-title>
          <source>Arthroscopy</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>492</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">DeBerdino MT, Arciero RA, Tayler CD (1997) Arthroscopic treatment of soft-tissue impingement of the ankle in athletes. Arthroscopy 13(4):492&#x2013;498 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9276057</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname> Draves</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname> Draves</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Osteology and arthrology of the knee and leg</article-title>
          <source>Anatomy of the lower extremity</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured"> Draves DJ (1986) Osteology and arthrology of the knee and leg. In: Draves DJ (ed) Anatomy of the lower extremity. Williams &amp; Wilkins, Baltimore, p 95 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferkel</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential diagnosis of chronic ankle sprain pain in the athlete</article-title>
          <source>Sports Med Arthrosc Rev</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>274</fpage>
          <lpage>273</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ferkel RD (1994) Differential diagnosis of chronic ankle sprain pain in the athlete. Sports Med Arthrosc Rev 2:274&#x2013;273 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferkel</surname>
              <given-names>RD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karzel</surname>
              <given-names>RP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pizzo</surname>
              <given-names>WD</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of antero-lateral impingement of the ankle</article-title>
          <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>440</fpage>
          <lpage>446</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ferkel RD, Karzel RP, Pizzo WD, et al (1991) Arthroscopic treatment of antero-lateral impingement of the ankle. Am J Sports Med 19(5):440&#x2013;446 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1962707</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gray</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Goss</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Articulations of the lower limb</article-title>
          <source>Gray&#x2019;s anatomy</source>
          <year>1973</year>
          <edition>29th edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lea &amp; Febiger</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gray H (1973) Articulations of the lower limb. In: Goss CM (ed) Gray&#x2019;s anatomy, 29th edn. Lea &amp; Febiger, Philadelphia </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Guhl J (1993) Foot and ankle arthroscopy, vol 1, 2nd edn. Slack, Thorofare, pp 88&#x2013;105</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Horner</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of talar impingement by the accessory anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament</article-title>
          <source>Arthroscopy</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>384</fpage>
          <lpage>385</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Horner G, Liu S (1996) Arthroscopic treatment of talar impingement by the accessory anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament. Arthroscopy 12:384&#x2013;385 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Markolf</surname>
              <given-names>KL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The contribution of the anterior talofibular ligament to ankle laxity</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>81</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Johnson EE, Markolf KL (1983) The contribution of the anterior talofibular ligament to ankle laxity. J Bone Joint Surg 65:81&#x2013;88 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6848539</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kleiger</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior tibiotalar impingement syndromes in dancers</article-title>
          <source>Foot Ankle</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>73</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kleiger B (1982) Anterior tibiotalar impingement syndromes in dancers. Foot Ankle 3:69&#x2013;73 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7141357</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Kelikian H, Kelikian AS (1985) Correlative anatomy of the ankle joint. In: Kelikian H, Kelikian AS (eds) Disorders of the ankle. WB Saunders, Philadelphia, p 1</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raskin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osti</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of anterolateral ankle impingement</article-title>
          <source>Arthroscopy</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>215</fpage>
          <lpage>218</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Liu HS, Raskin A, Osti L, et al (1994) Arthroscopic treatment of anterolateral ankle impingement. Arthroscopy 10(2):215&#x2013;218 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8003152</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lundeen</surname>
              <given-names>RO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic evaluation of the traumatic injuries to the ankle and foot. Part: II chronic post-traumatic pain</article-title>
          <source>J Foot Surg</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>59</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lundeen RO (1990) Arthroscopic evaluation of the traumatic injuries to the ankle and foot. Part: II chronic post-traumatic pain. J Foot Surg 29(1):59&#x2013;71 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1969429</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McMurray</surname>
              <given-names>TP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Footballer&#x2019;s ankle</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg</source>
          <year>1950</year>
          <volume>32B</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>68</fpage>
          <lpage>69</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McMurray TP (1950) Footballer&#x2019;s ankle. J Bone Joint Surg 32B(1):68&#x2013;69 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Meislin</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rose</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parisien</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of synovial impingement of the ankle</article-title>
          <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>186</fpage>
          <lpage>189</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Meislin JR, Rose JD, Parisien SJ, et al (1993) Arthroscopic treatment of synovial impingement of the ankle. Am J Sports Med 21(2):186&#x2013;189 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8465910</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Morris LH (1943) Athlete&#x2019;s ankle. J Bone Joint Surg 25:220</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Nikolopoulos CE (1982) Anterolateral instability of the ankle joint: an anatomical, experimental and clinical study. Thesis, University of Athens, Athens, Greece</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nikolopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsirikos</surname>
              <given-names>AI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sourmelis</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The accessory anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament as a cause of talar impingement. A cadaveric study</article-title>
          <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>389</fpage>
          <lpage>395</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/0095399703258697</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nikolopoulos CE, Tsirikos AI, Sourmelis S, et al (2004) The accessory anteroinferior tibiofibular ligament as a cause of talar impingement. A cadaveric study. Am J Sports Med 32(2):389&#x2013;395 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14977663</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rasmussen</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tovborg-Jensen</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distal tibiofibular ligaments: analysis of function</article-title>
          <source>Acta Orthop Scand</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>681</fpage>
          <lpage>686</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rasmussen O, Tovborg-Jensen I, Boe S, et al (1982) Distal tibiofibular ligaments: analysis of function. Acta Orthop Scand 53:681&#x2013;686 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7102288</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ray</surname>
              <given-names>RG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kriz</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament. Variations and relationship to the talus</article-title>
          <source>J Am Podiatr Med Assoc</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>479</fpage>
          <lpage>485</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ray RG, Kriz BM (1991) Anterior inferior tibiofibular ligament. Variations and relationship to the talus. J Am Podiatr Med Assoc 81:479&#x2013;485 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1748963</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Renstrom</surname>
              <given-names>PAFH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Persistently painful sprained ankle</article-title>
          <source>J Am Acad Orthop Surg</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>270</fpage>
          <lpage>280</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Renstrom PAFH (1994) Persistently painful sprained ankle. J Am Acad Orthop Surg 2:270&#x2013;280 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10709019</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sarrafian</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Anatomy of the foot and ankle. Descriptive, topographic, functional. </source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>J.B. Lippincott</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sarrafian SK (1983) Anatomy of the foot and ankle. Descriptive, topographic, functional. J.B. Lippincott, Philadelphia </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schonholtz</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Arthroscopic surgery of the shoulder, elbow and ankle</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <publisher-loc>Springfield</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Charles C Thomas</publisher-name>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>71</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schonholtz GJ (1986) Arthroscopic surgery of the shoulder, elbow and ankle. Charles C Thomas, Springfield, pp 69&#x2013;71 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thein</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eichenblat</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of sports related synovitis of the ankle</article-title>
          <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>496</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Thein R, Eichenblat M (1992) Arthroscopic treatment of sports related synovitis of the ankle. Am J Sports Med 20(5):496&#x2013;498 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1443314</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tol</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Etiology of the anterior ankle impingement syndrome: a descriptive anatomical study</article-title>
          <source>Foot Ankle Int</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>382</fpage>
          <lpage>386</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tol JL, van Dijk CN (2004) Etiology of the anterior ankle impingement syndrome: a descriptive anatomical study. Foot Ankle Int 25(6):382&#x2013;386 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15215021</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tol</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verheyen</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arthroscopic treatment of anterior impingement in the ankle</article-title>
          <source>J Bone Joint Surg Br</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>83</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>13</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1302/0301-620X.83B1.10571</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tol JL, Verheyen CP, van Dijk CN (2001) Arthroscopic treatment of anterior impingement in the ankle. J Bone Joint Surg Br 83(1):9&#x2013;13 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11245545</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dijk</surname>
              <given-names>CN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tol</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verheyen</surname>
              <given-names>CC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A prospective study of prognostic factors concerning the outcome of arthroscopic surgery for anterior ankle impingement</article-title>
          <source>Am J Sports Med</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>737</fpage>
          <lpage>745</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Dijk CN, Tol JL, Verheyen CC (1997) A prospective study of prognostic factors concerning the outcome of arthroscopic surgery for anterior ankle impingement. Am J Sports Med 26(6):737&#x2013;745 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9397259</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">van Dijk CN (2005) Ankle impingement. In: Chan KM, Karlsson J (eds) ISAKOS/FIMS World consensus conference on ankle instability, Hong Kong</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Umans</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ankle impingement syndromes</article-title>
          <source>Semin Musculoskelet Radiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>133</fpage>
          <lpage>139</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1055/s-2002-32359</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Umans H (2002) Ankle impingement syndromes. Semin Musculoskelet Radiol 6:133&#x2013;139 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12077702</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wolin</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glassman</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sideman</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Internal derangement of the talofibular component of the ankle</article-title>
          <source>Surg Gynecol Obstet</source>
          <year>1950</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>193</fpage>
          <lpage>200</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wolin I, Glassman F, Sideman S, et al (1950) Internal derangement of the talofibular component of the ankle. Surg Gynecol Obstet 91:193&#x2013;200 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15442838</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>