<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Matern Child Health J</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Maternal and Child Health Journal</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1092-7875</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-6628</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer US</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Boston</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">16850276</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1592145</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">111</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10995-006-0111-1</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>The Importance of Preconception Care for Women With Disabilities</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Thierry</surname>
            <given-names>JoAnn M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD, MSW</degrees>
          <address>
            <email>jxt4@cdc.gov</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, 1600 Clifton Road, Mail Stop E-88, Atlanta, GA 30333 USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>19</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>10</volume>
      <issue>Suppl 1</issue>
      <fpage>175</fpage>
      <lpage>176</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>25</day>
          <month>4</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, Inc. 2006</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Disability</kwd>
        <kwd>Pregnancy</kwd>
        <kwd>Women's Health</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media, LLC 2006</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Overall estimates of the number of women with disabilities in the United States range from 16.8 to 28.6 million, or approximately one in every five women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. A large percentage of these women are in their reproductive years, and they often encounter greater obstacles to receiving health care than women without disabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]. Some disabling conditions, such as spinal cord injury (SCI) and multiple sclerosis (MS), have low prevalence rates but are more common in the reproductive age group. Such conditions are often associated with a greater severity of disability and increased need for specialized services, including prenatal care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Health care professionals need to be aware of the reproductive health care issues facing women with disabilities and take every opportunity to address them.</p>
    <p>Sexuality and reproductive health issues have received inadequate attention for women with disabilities. Many women with disabilities desire children and are capable of conceiving, but face considerable pressure not to reproduce [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Although a growing number of women with disabilities are becoming pregnant, anecdotal evidence suggests that many of these women encounter negative attitudes towards their pregnancies and report difficulty receiving comprehensive prenatal care [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
    <p>Women with disabilities who become pregnant face similar issues and concerns as pregnant women without disabilities. Although many pregnant women experience problems with weight gain, fatigue, fluid retention, bladder dysfunction, and urinary tract infections, these problems may be more serious in women with disabilities [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. All women are concerned about the health of their unborn child. Like other women, women with disabilities express concern about the possibility of giving birth to a child with disabilities and may seek genetic counseling. On the other hand, not all disabled women embrace the idea of genetic testing. To these women the idea of genetic counseling raises psychosocial issues that may be difficult for them to consider [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>].</p>
    <p>Some disabling conditions pose unique problems during or after pregnancy. Complications associated with specific conditions, such as systemic lupus erythematosus (SLE), SCI, or MS, can affect pregnancy and should be evaluated prior to conception [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. For example, an increased risk of fetal loss, growth retardation, premature placental aging with thrombosis, and preeclampsia are described in women with lupus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. Given the seriousness of these complications, ongoing monitoring and interventions to reduce them are critical. Pregnant women with SCI above the level of T6 also require special attention [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Such women have an increased risk of autonomic dysreflexia during all stages of pregnancy and, if it is not recognized and treated, autonomic dysreflexia can be fatal [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Although women with stable MS can safely carry a pregnancy to term, postpartum exacerbations of MS are quite common and occur in up to 30% of women within one month of delivery [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]. Pregnancy management in women with disabilities should therefore include preconception counseling and evaluation to identify these and other potential problems that can occur throughout the course of the pregnancy.</p>
    <p>Health care professionals need to know that physical barriers, such as the lack of accessible scales or examination tables, present enormous and recurring obstacles to obtaining adequate prenatal care. Also, communication barriers, particularly for those who are deaf or hard of hearing, affect a women's ability to receive appropriate medical care. In addition, there are some aspects of gynecologic health care such as informed consent, sedation, and contraceptive issues that are unique for women with developmental disabilities. A recent publication from the American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists highlights ways to improve care for this group of women [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>].</p>
    <p>Preconception care is associated with improved pregnancy outcomes. It is recommended that primary care providers assess all women of reproductive age for their preconception risk conditions and provide or refer individuals for interventions as appropriate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]. When caring for a woman with a disability, a team approach involving the primary physician, obstetrician, anesthesiologist, neurologist, physiatrist, and other allied health professionals such as occupational and physical therapists, is recommended [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. This is particularly important, as many obstetricians are unfamiliar with disability-related complications. A multidisciplinary approach, which involves nursing and social work, can further improve pregnancy outcomes. This shared approach to pregnancy management can also increase the level of comfort for women with disabilities, by knowing that more than one health care provider is looking out for their well-being.</p>
    <p>Preconception counseling for women with disabilities should address the medical, psychological, and social impact of a pregnancy [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]. During preconception counseling, it is particularly important to evaluate the prenatal and postpartum social support systems available to women with disabilities. Body changes such as decreased mobility or bladder dysfunction increase the need for personal assistance with routine activities of daily living. Many women with disabilities also benefit from an occupational therapy evaluation to assess environmental barriers and explore adaptive equipment and techniques that facilitate breast feeding and infant care. Health care providers might want to recommend that women with disabilities explore creative parenting strategies such as those offered by <italic>Through the Looking Glass</italic>, a national resource center on parenting with a disability, located in Berkeley, California [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>].</p>
    <p>An increasing number of women with disabilities are becoming pregnant. Despite this little is known about the reproductive experiences of these women. Population-based data describing the reproductive experiences of women with disabilities is virtually non-existent. Currently, disability is not regularly included in national or statewide surveys and surveillance tools related to pregnancy. Consequently, the true magnitude of health concerns, including reproductive issues, facing women with disabilities is largely unknown. To improve our understanding of these issues, disability should be included as a demographic variable in all national and state-level surveys addressing reproductive health issues.</p>
    <p>All women of childbearing age, including women with disabilities, should have access to preconception care that addresses the medical, psychological and social impacts of pregnancy. Women with disabilities can and do have healthy pregnancies. Accurate knowledge of disabling conditions and a shared multidisciplinary approach to pregnancy management are critical components for good pregnancy outcomes among women with disabilities.</p>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>LaPlante</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Carlson</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Disability in the United States: Prevalence and causes, 1992. Disabilities Statistics Report (7)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>U.S. Department of Education, National Center on Disability and Rehabilitation Research</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">LaPlante MP, Carlson D. Disability in the United States: Prevalence and causes, 1992. Disabilities Statistics Report (7). Washington, DC: U.S. Department of Education, National Center on Disability and Rehabilitation Research; 1996. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McNeil</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Americans with disabilities: 1997. U.S. Bureau of the Census. Current population reports</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>U.S. Government Printing Office</publisher-name>
          <fpage>70</fpage>
          <lpage>3</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McNeil JM. Americans with disabilities: 1997. U.S. Bureau of the Census. Current population reports. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office; 2001, p. 70&#x2013;3. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">U.S. Census Bureau. Disability status of the civilian noninstitutionalized population by sex and selected characteristics for the United States and Puerto Rico: 2000(PHC-T-32). Washington, DC: U.S. Census Bureau, 2004. Available at: www.census.gov/population/www/cen2000/phc-t32.html. Accessed on December 7, 2004.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Chevarley FM, Thierry JM, Gill CJ, Ryerson AB, Nosek MA. Health and well-being for women with disabilities. Unpublished data.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Altman</surname>
              <given-names>BM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Krotoski</surname>
              <given-names>DM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nosek</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turk</surname>
              <given-names>MA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Causes, risks, and consequences of disability among women</article-title>
          <source>Women with physical disabilities: Achieving and maintaining health and well-being</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <publisher-loc>Baltimore</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Paul H. Brooks</publisher-name>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>55</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Altman BM. Causes, risks, and consequences of disability among women. In: Krotoski DM, Nosek MA, Turk MA, editors. Women with physical disabilities: Achieving and maintaining health and well-being. Baltimore: Paul H. Brooks; 1996, p. 35&#x2013;55. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rogers</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The disabled woman's guide to pregnancy and birth</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Demos Publishing</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rogers J. The disabled woman's guide to pregnancy and birth. New York: Demos Publishing; 2005. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <source>Special issues in women's health</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-loc>Washington</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>ACOG</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">American College of Obstetricians and Gynecologists. Special issues in women's health. Washington, DC: ACOG; 2004. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Welner</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>A provider's guide for the care of women with physical disabilities and chronic medical conditions</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <publisher-loc>North Carolina</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Office on Disability &amp; Health</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Welner SL. A provider's guide for the care of women with physical disabilities and chronic medical conditions. North Carolina: Office on Disability &amp; Health; 1999. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Martinez-Rueda</surname>
              <given-names>JO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arce-Salinas</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kraus</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alcocer-Varela</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alarcon-Seqovia</surname>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Factors associated with fetal losses in severe systemic lupus erythematosus</article-title>
          <source>Lupus</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>9</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/096120339600500205</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Martinez-Rueda JO, Arce-Salinas CA, Kraus A, Alcocer-Varela J, Alarcon-Seqovia. Factors associated with fetal losses in severe systemic lupus erythematosus. Lupus 1996;5:113&#x2013;9. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8743123</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Demsasio K, Magriples U. Pregnancy complicated by maternal paraplegia or tetraplegia as a result of spinal cord injury and spina bifida. Sexual Disab 1999;17(3).</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baschat</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiner</surname>
              <given-names>CP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Welner</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haseltine</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chronic neurologic diseases and disabling conditions in pregnancy</article-title>
          <source>Welner's guide to the care of women with disabilities</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <publisher-loc>Philadelphia</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Baschat AA, Weiner CP. Chronic neurologic diseases and disabling conditions in pregnancy. In: Welner SL, Haseltine F, editors. Welner's guide to the care of women with disabilities. Philadelphia: Lippincott Williams &amp; Wilkins; 2004. </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davis</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maslow</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Multiple sclerosis and pregnancy: A review</article-title>
          <source>Obstet Gynecol Surv</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>6</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00006254-199205000-00002</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Davis RK, Maslow AS. Multiple sclerosis and pregnancy: A review. Obstet Gynecol Surv 1992;47:290&#x2013;6. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1570125</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">U.S. Department of Health and Human Services. Healthy people 2000: National health promotion and disease prevention objectives. Washington, DC: U.S. Government Printing Office; 1991.</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kirshbaum</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Serving families with disability issues: Through the looking glass</article-title>
          <source>Marriage Fam Rev</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <issue>1/2</issue>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>28</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1300/J002v21n01_02</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kirshbaum M. Serving families with disability issues: Through the looking glass. Marriage Fam Rev 1995;21(1/2):9&#x2013;28. </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>The findings and conclusions in this report are those of the author and do not necessarily represent the views of the Centers for Disease Control and Prevention.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>