<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Mol Genet Genomics</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Molecular Genetics and Genomics </journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1617-4615</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1617-4623</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18247056</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2270915</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">322</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00438-008-0322-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Characteristic expression of twelve rice <italic>PR1</italic> family genes in response to pathogen infection, wounding, and defense-related signal compounds (121/180)</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mitsuhara</surname>
            <given-names>Ichiro</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+81-29-8387440</phone>
            <fax>+81-29-8387469</fax>
            <email>mituhara@affrc.go.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Iwai</surname>
            <given-names>Takayoshi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Seo</surname>
            <given-names>Shigemi</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Yanagawa</surname>
            <given-names>Yuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kawahigasi</surname>
            <given-names>Hiroyuki</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hirose</surname>
            <given-names>Sakino</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ohkawa</surname>
            <given-names>Yasunobu</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Ohashi</surname>
            <given-names>Yuko</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>National Institute of Agrobiological Sciences (NIAS), Kannon-dai 2-1-2, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-8602 Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Miyagi Prefectural Agriculture and Horticulture Research Center, Takadate-kawakami, Natori, Miyagi 981-1243 Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Nara Institute of Science and Technology, The Graduate School of Biological Sciences, Ikoma, Nara 630-0101 Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>Communicated by K. Shirasu.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>5</day>
        <month>2</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>279</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>415</fpage>
      <lpage>427</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>21</day>
          <month>11</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins have been used as markers of plant defense responses, and are classified into 17 families. However, precise information on the majority members in specific PR families is still limited. We were interested in the individual characteristics of rice <italic>PR1</italic> family genes, and selected 12 putatively active genes using rice genome databases for expressed genes. All were upregulated upon compatible and/or incompatible rice-blast fungus interactions; three were upregulated in the early infection period and four in the late infection period. Upon compatible rice&#x2013;bacterial blight interaction, four genes were upregulated, six were not affected, and one was downregulated. These results are in striking contrast to those among 22 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>PR1</italic> genes where only one gene was pathogen-inducible. The responses of individual genes to salicylic acid, jasmonic acid, and ethylene induced defense signaling pathways in rice are likely to be different from those in dicot plants. Transcript levels in healthy leaves, roots, and flowers varied according to each gene. Analysis of the partially overlapping expression patterns of rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes in healthy tissues and in response to pathogens and other stresses would be useful to understand their possible functions and for use as characteristic markers for defense-related studies in rice.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Bacterial blight</kwd>
        <kwd>Histological analysis</kwd>
        <kwd>Defense gene expression</kwd>
        <kwd>Pathogen resistance</kwd>
        <kwd>PR protein</kwd>
        <kwd>Rice</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Pathogenesis-related (PR) proteins, which are classified into 17 families, accumulate after pathogen infection or related situations in many plant species (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). Among the <italic>PR</italic> gene family, <italic>PR1</italic> genes have been frequently used as marker genes for systemic acquired resistance in many plant species. However, only a small proportion of <italic>PR1</italic> genes have been studied among the many members in this family, and information on the other members is limited. For example, <italic>NtPR1a, b</italic>, and <italic>c</italic> genes for acidic proteins, and <italic>NtPRB1</italic> (<italic>PR-1g</italic>) and <italic>NtPRB1b</italic> genes for basic proteins were reported in tobacco (<italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic>) (van Loon and van Strien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1999</xref>), but little information is known on other <italic>PR1</italic> members. To understand the characteristics and redundancy of the majority of <italic>PR1</italic> family members, genome-based studies are necessary. For such studies, dicot <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and monocot rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> L.) plants have been used as the model plants.</p>
      <p>In <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, 22 genes are listed as predicted <italic>PR1</italic> genes that encode homologous proteins to tobacco PR1a protein, which was first reported as an acidic protein in tobacco leaves infected with <italic>Tobacco mosaic virus</italic> (TMV) (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). Among the 22 genes, only one <italic>PR1</italic> gene (At2g14610), which encodes a basic protein, is known to be pathogen-responsive, and the other <italic>PR1</italic> genes reportedly did not respond to either bacterial or fungal pathogens (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). From these results, we tend to suppose that only one <italic>PR1</italic> gene relates to pathogen resistance in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and the others contribute to other functions.</p>
      <p>In rice, the induction of two <italic>PR1</italic> genes, <italic>OsPR1a</italic> and <italic>1b</italic>, by blast fungus infection was reported (Agrawal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2001</xref>). They encode putative acidic and basic proteins, respectively, and also responded to environmental stresses and treatments with some chemicals (Agrawal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000a</xref>, b). However, for other rice <italic>PR1</italic> gene family members, there is only limited information except for their presence and expression: (1) at least 4 signals for possible rice PR1 proteins responsive to anti-tobacco PR1a antibodies were found in an extract of blast fungus-infected rice leaves (Schweizer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1997</xref>; Iwai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2007</xref>), and (2) 32 predicted <italic>PR1</italic> genes were proposed to be present in the rice genome (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>).</p>
      <p>To study the response of individual rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes to pathogens, we selected active rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes from the rice genome databases for expressed genes, and studied their induced expression by real time RT-PCR (qPCR). In striking contrast with the result in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, all 12 rice genes selected here were upregulated by blast fungus infection. The levels of constitutive expression in organs and induced expression by different treatments varied according to the gene. In addition to the data on tissue-specific <italic>PR1</italic> expression in transgenic rice with a <italic>OsPR1</italic> promoter::<italic>&#x3B2;-glucuronidase</italic> (<italic>GUS</italic>) fusion gene, we list the characteristics of the 12 rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes. This is the first example of a comparison of the expression of the majority of members of a monocot <italic>PR</italic> family to our knowledge. This information will be useful for further studies on <italic>PR</italic> genes and on resistance mechanism in rice plants.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Plant materials</title>
        <p>Wild-type (WT) rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> cv. Nipponbare) and the near isogenic line IL7 (Ise and Horisue <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1988</xref>), which contains the <italic>R</italic> gene <italic>Pi-i</italic> against blast fungus (<italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic>) race 003 (Yamada et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1976</xref>), were grown for 14&#x2013;16&#xA0;days in soil (Bonsol No. 1, Sumitomo Chemicals L., Japan) in a greenhouse at 28&#xB0;C in the day time and 25&#xB0;C at night. The fourth leaves of plants at the 4-leaf stage were mainly used as the experimental material. The seeds of transformants with <italic>OsPR1::GUS</italic> were germinated on agar medium containing 30&#xA0;&#x3BC;g&#xA0;ml<sup>&#x2212;1 </sup>hygromycin, transferred to soil at 7&#xA0;days after imbibition, and grown in the greenhouse. Five-day-old seedlings on agar medium and 2-month-old plants in the greenhouse were used for GUS-staining assays.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Infection with pathogens</title>
        <p><italic>Magneporthe grisea</italic> race 003 (isolate Kyu-89-241) was grown on oat-meal medium (Difco) for 2&#xA0;weeks and conidia were induced under BLB light (FL20S BLB, Toshiba) for 2&#xA0;days at 25&#xB0;C. The rice seedlings of Nipponbare and IL7 plants at the 4-leaf stage were spray-inoculated with a conidia suspension (1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup> conidia ml<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) containing 0.05% Tween 20, and the inoculated plants were incubated under high humidity in the dark for 20&#xA0;h, and then moved to the greenhouse. Under these conditions, about 100 local lesions were induced per leaf on Nipponbare and IL7. For bacterial blight infection, Nipponbare plants, which are compatible with <italic>Xanthomonas oryzae pv. oryzae (Xoo)</italic> strain T7174 (race I, MAFF 311018), were inoculated by cutting the leaf top with scissors that had been dipped in a suspension containing 10<sup>8</sup> cfu/ml of <italic>Xoo</italic>, and incubated in the greenhouse.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Treatment with chemicals</title>
        <p>Plastic pots (15&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;5.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10&#xA0;cm) with 12 rice seedlings at the 4-leaf stage, were dipped in 500&#xA0;ml solutions containing 1&#xA0;mM 1-aminocyclopropane-1-carboxylic acid (ACC) or 3&#xA0;mM sodium salicylate (SA) solution, and incubated for 24&#xA0;h in the greenhouse. For jasmonic acid (JA) treatment, pots with 12 seedlings each was put in an air-tight clear plastic box, and a cotton pad with volatile methyl jasmonate (MeJA) dissolved in EtOH was put at the corner of the box to give a final concentration of 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M, and incubated for 24&#xA0;h. The fourth leaves were used for RNA extraction.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR</title>
        <p>To analyze the response of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to biotic and abiotic stresses, quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qPCR) was conducted using iQ SYBR Green Supermix (BioRad, Hercules, CA, USA) and an iCycler (BioRad) according to the manufacturers&#x2019; instructions. At least three independent biological samples were used with specific primers for each individual gene (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). The data were normalized by the value of an <italic>actin</italic> gene (AK060893), and fold change in the expression level was calculated compared with that of healthy fourth leaves, and standard deviation (SD) values are shown.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Construction of plasmids for transformation of rice</title>
        <p>The promoter region of the <italic>OsPR1.1</italic> gene (<italic>OsPR1#074</italic> in this work) was obtained through PCR amplification from the Nipponbare genome, using a GenomeWalker<sup>TM</sup> kit (Invitrogen, CA, USA) in accordance with the manufacturer&#x2019;s instructions (Accession no. AP008213, Kawahigashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>). The amplified fragment was digested by <italic>Not</italic>I and <italic>Bam</italic>HI and inserted into the pTH2 vector to construct the <italic>PR1T::GUS</italic> plasmid (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). The <italic>PR1T::GUS</italic> plasmid contained 1,919&#xA0;bp of the promoter and the coding region for 16 amino acids at the N-terminus of the <italic>OsPR1</italic> gene to express a fused GUS protein effectively (Kawahigashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Transformation of rice</title>
        <p><italic>Agrobacterium tumefaciens</italic> LB4404 was transformed with the constructed vector (Kawahigashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>). The transformation of rice was performed by Agrobacterium infection as described by Toki et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2006</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Histological GUS analysis</title>
        <p>Histological analysis for GUS activity was performed at 37&#xB0;C essentially as described by Ohshima et al (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">1990</xref>) using a modified reaction mixture: 50&#xA0;mM phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) containing 1&#xA0;mM 5-bromo-4-chloro-3-indolyl glucuronide (X-gluc), 5% methanol, 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/ml cycloheximide, and 1&#xA0;mM dithiothreitol. The reaction was stopped by the addition of ethanol.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec10" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Characterization of the rice <italic>PR1</italic> gene family</title>
        <p>Using the amino acid sequence of the mature tobacco acidic PR1a protein (NtPR1a; 138 amino acids, Ohshima et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1987</xref>) as the probe, we searched for expressed genes in rice (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> cv. Nipponbare) encoding homologous proteins with a similar size range (within 150&#x2013;200 amino acids) using a full-length cDNA database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdna01.dna.affrc.go.jp/cDNA">http://www.cdna01.dna.affrc.go.jp/cDNA</ext-link>) and rice EST database (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.riceblast.dna.affrc.go.jp/">http://www.riceblast.dna.affrc.go.jp/</ext-link>). The presence and location of these genes were confirmed in the genome database of rice (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.rapdb.dna.affrc.go.jp/">http://www.rapdb.dna.affrc.go.jp/</ext-link>). After removing repetitive clones and confirmation of the sequences, finally 12 genes were selected as candidates for active rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes, which encode proteins with sequences &#x2265;41% identical to that of tobacco PR1a protein at least in the C-terminal 65 amino acids. Previously, two rice <italic>PR1</italic> genes were reported to encode an acidic PR1a protein and a basic PR1b protein (Agrawal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000a</xref>), which were upregulated by blast fungus infection. In addition to the two, we found another 10 active genes on chromosomes 1, 2, 5, 7, 10, and 12 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Proposed names were given to distinguish each gene to avoid confusion in this study according to the location on the chromosomes. For example, <italic>OsPR1b</italic> (AK107926, Os01g28450), located on the 5&#x2032; side of the gene for AK121108 (Os01g28500) on chromosome 1, was designated as <italic>OsPR1#011</italic> and AK121108 was <italic>OsPR1#012</italic>. On chromosome 7, four <italic>PR1</italic>-like genes, <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, and <italic>#074</italic>, were clustered in tandem from the 5&#x2032; side to the 3&#x2032; side in the sense orientation in this order. The predicted isoelectric point (pI) of each mature protein is shown in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> for reference. The amino acid sequences of the predicted mature proteins for the 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes were compared with those of representative acidic and basic PR1 proteins from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (AtPR1-like and AtPRB1) and tobacco (NtPR1a and NtPRB1b), respectively (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). The sequences of the 12 OsPR1s, 2 AtPR1s, and 2 NtPR1s listed here are well conserved. As the N-termini of OsPR1#051, #052, and #121 are not conserved, these regions were eliminated for the alignment in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a. Ten amino acid residues (closed circles) are completely conserved among the 12 rice, 2 <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, and 2 tobacco genes, indicating they are important for the predicted roles of PR1 proteins.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Classification of rice <italic>PR1</italic> protein genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Plant</th><th align="left">Accession No. (Symbol name)</th><th align="left">Locus name</th><th align="left">References</th><th align="left">PI</th><th align="left">Proposed symbols</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" rowspan="12">Rice</td><td align="left">AK107926 (<italic>OsPR1b</italic>)</td><td align="left">Os01g28450</td><td align="left">Agrawal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2000b</xref>)</td><td char="." align="char">7.6</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#011</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK121108</td><td align="left">Os01g28500</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">8.7</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#012</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK107467</td><td align="left">Os02g54540</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">8.5</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#021</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK105575</td><td align="left">Os02g54560</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">5.9</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#022</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK071326</td><td align="left">Os05g51660</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">7.1</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#051</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK100748</td><td align="left">Os05g51680</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">5.5</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#052</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK060057</td><td align="left">Os07g03279</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">4.2</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#071</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK062949</td><td align="left">Os07g03580</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">4.7</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#072</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK063248</td><td align="left">Os07g03590</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">5.8</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#073</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AU163470 (<italic>OsPR1a)</italic></td><td align="left">Os07g03710</td><td align="left">Agrawal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2000a</xref>)</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#074</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AU070895</td><td align="left">Os10g11500</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">10.7</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#101</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">AK100940</td><td align="left">Os12g43700</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td char="." align="char">5.1</td><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#121</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>Arabidopsis</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>(PR-1 like)</italic></td><td align="left">At2g19990</td><td align="left">Metzler et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">1991</xref>) </td><td char="." align="char">6.0</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>(AtPRB1)</italic></td><td align="left">At2g14580</td><td align="left">Santamaria et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>)</td><td char="." align="char">8.8</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" rowspan="2">Tobacco</td><td align="left">X06361 (<italic>NtPR1a)</italic> (X12737, X05959, X06930)</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Ohshima et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">1987</xref>)</td><td char="." align="char">4.4</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">X66942 <italic>(NtPRB1b)</italic></td><td align="left"/><td align="left">Eyal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1992</xref>)</td><td char="." align="char">7.6</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Characterization of the <italic>PR1</italic> gene family in rice plants. a Amino acid sequence alignment of 12 putative PR1 proteins from rice. The predicted mature proteins encoded by these genes were aligned by GENETICS 9.0 (Software Development Co., Tokyo). Because the N-termini of OsPR1#052, #051, and #121 are considerably different from those of the other 9 OsPR1s, these regions were eliminated from the figure and the conserved C-termini among the 12 OsPR1s were aligned. The acidic and basic PR1 proteins from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (AtPR1-like and AtPRB1) and tobacco (NtPR1a and NtPRB1b) were used as representatives of acidic and basic PR1 proteins, respectively. The conserved amino acid residues among the 16 proteins are marked with black circles. Identical amino acids are <italic>boxed</italic>. <bold>b</bold> Phylogenetic analysis of rice PR1 proteins based on the mature proteins using UPGMA method. The predicted isoelectric point (<italic>pI</italic>) for each mature protein is shown on the right. Acidic, basic, and neutral proteins are shown in <italic>red, blue, and green</italic>, respectively. Refer to the description in <bold>a</bold> for details</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>Using the data of Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, a phylogenetic tree was constructed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). Among the 12 OsPR1 proteins, 7 acidic and 4 basic protein members were found (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). The C-terminal region of OsPR1#051 was indicated to be neutral. The PR1 proteins from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> and tobacco grouped in one clade (framed), and OsPR1 proteins belonged to different clades.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Responses of OsPR1 genes to blast-fungus infection in young rice plants</title>
        <sec id="Sec13">
          <title>Compatible interaction</title>
          <p>The response of individual <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to blast-fungus infection was analyzed by qPCR using a set of primers specific for each gene (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). A conidia suspension of <italic>M. grisea</italic> race 003 was sprayed on the seedlings of Nipponbare at the four-leaf stage. In this system, the fungus infection results in the formation of whitish expanding lesions at 3&#xA0;days post inoculation (dpi), and increasing lesion size thereafter with conidia formation. The infected plants were severely wilted and died within 7&#x2013;9&#xA0;days indicating a typical compatible host&#x2013;parasite interaction (Sasaki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2004</xref>; Iwai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>). Using triplicate cDNA samples originating from independently prepared RNA templates from inoculated fourth leaves, the expression levels of each gene were compared with that of an <italic>actin</italic> gene, which was selected as a control gene. Although expression levels of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes in healthy Nipponbare leaves varied according to each gene (0&#xA0;dpi, white column in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), all <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes tested were up-regulated by blast-fungus inoculation at 3 and/or 6&#xA0;dpi (black column). When compared with mock-inoculation (gray column), the enhanced expression by the fungus was significant for each gene at 6 dpi, at which lesions were vigorously expanding. The transcripts of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, and <italic>#012</italic> had already accumulated to near maximal levels at 3&#xA0;dpi maintaining almost the same levels at 6&#xA0;dpi, indicating they are rapid response genes to blast fungus infection. However, the transcripts of <italic>OsPR1#073</italic>, <italic>#022</italic>, <italic>#101</italic>, <italic>#051</italic>, and <italic>#121</italic> had not increased significantly at 3&#xA0;dpi compared with mock-inoculated controls, indicating these are late response genes. Blast fungus infection induced around 1,000-fold transcript accumulation at 6&#xA0;dpi compared with 0&#xA0;dpi in 7 genes: <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, <italic>#071</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, <italic>#052</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, <italic>#101</italic>, and <italic>#121</italic>.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Primers for qPCR of <italic>OsPR1</italic>s and <italic>actin</italic> genes</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Name</th><th align="left">Forward primer</th><th align="left">Reverse primer</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#074</italic></td><td align="left">GTATGCTATGCTACGTGTTTATGC</td><td align="left">GCAAATACGGCTGACAGTACAG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#011</italic></td><td align="left">ACGCCTTCACGGTCCATAC</td><td align="left">AAACAGAAAGAAACAGAGGGAGTAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#071</italic></td><td align="left">CTTTAACTATGTATGGAGTATGATATAAATGTG</td><td align="left">TTATTTTCTTCTTTTATTCGAACGACAAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#012</italic></td><td align="left">CGCTGTGTGTTTGTGTTATGTC</td><td align="left">CGTGGTTTTGTCTTTATTTCAATCC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#073</italic></td><td align="left">TTATATATGTATGTTCGTATGTATGTATGC</td><td align="left">TGATGTACTTATTCCATCCGACAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#021</italic></td><td align="left">CGCAGCAACCAACCAATCTTG</td><td align="left">ACAGTTGTAGTACTCTTGTAACATCATC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#022</italic></td><td align="left">CCACAGAGTTTGTCAGGATTGTC</td><td align="left">CAGATTGCACACACCTGATTCC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#052</italic></td><td align="left">AGCTACCTGTCATTTCTTCATTTC</td><td align="left">TGCTACTCCAGAAGGAAATTAAAAG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#072</italic></td><td align="left">AATTAATACTGGAGTAGATGCATGTAC</td><td align="left">ACGAATAACGTACTGTATTCTGTATG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#121</italic></td><td align="left">ACCATCGTCGTCGTCTCATC</td><td align="left">AGCCTCTAGGGCATATCACTAAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#101</italic></td><td align="left">TCGCTGCCGCTAGTACATTTC</td><td align="left">ATTAAGATCATTACATGCTTTATTGTTCAC</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>OsPR1#051</italic></td><td align="left">CCTGCCTGCCTTCCTCATTC</td><td align="left">AGTGAAGATTTGGTTTCCATTGTATTG</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>Actin</italic></td><td align="left">GAGTATGATGAGTCGGGTCCAG</td><td align="left">ACACCAACAATCCCAAACAGAG</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Response of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to pathogen infection. <bold>a</bold> Blast fungus infection. A conidia suspension of blast fungus race 003 was spray-inoculated onto Nipponbare (compatible, <italic>upper panel</italic>), and IL7 (incompatible, <italic>lower panel</italic>). The inoculated fourth leaves were harvested at 0, 3, and 6&#xA0;days post inoculation (<italic>dpi</italic>) for RNA extraction. To semi-quantify the transcript level, RNA samples were subjected to qPCR, and the relative expression levels compared with that of a control <italic>actin</italic> gene are shown. The transcript levels at time 0, mock-inoculated, and blast-fungus inoculated leaves were shown as <italic>white, gray, and black columns</italic>, respectively. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SD. The up-regulated genes by blast fungus-infection are marked with arrowheads. Gray arrowheads in the lower panel indicate early responsive genes. <bold>b</bold> Bacterial blight infection. The fourth leaves of Nipponbare rice plants were inoculated with a suspension of <italic>Xoo</italic> for bacterial blight disease, and the leaves were harvested at 0, 4, and 8 dpi for RNA extraction. The transcript level was analyzed by qPCR. The relative expression levels compared with that of the control <italic>actin</italic> gene are shown. Transcript levels at time 0, mock-inoculated, and bacteria-blight inoculated leaves are shown as <italic>white, gray, and black columns</italic>, respectively. <italic>Xoo</italic>-upregulated and -downregulated genes are marked with forward and reverse arrowheads, respectively. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec14">
          <title>Incompatible interaction</title>
          <p>IL7 is a near isogenic line of Nipponbare, into which the resistance gene <italic>Pi-i</italic> for blast fungus race 003 has been introduced. In fungus-inoculated IL7, small HR lesions were induced at 2&#xA0;dpi with no remarkable fungal development thereafter, indicating a typical incompatible interaction (Sasaki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2004</xref>; Iwai et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2006</xref>). The transcript levels of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, and <italic>#012</italic> were maximized at 3&#xA0;dpi, and slightly reduced at 6 dpi (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, lower part, gray arrowheads), indicating they are early responsive genes to blast fungus infection. The 3 genes had been recognized as early responsive genes in compatible interaction. The levels of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> and <italic>#011</italic> transcripts increased by about 1,000-fold at 3 dpi. The transcripts of <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, and <italic>#101</italic> were higher at at 6 dpi than at 3 dpi, indicating they are late responsive genes (black arrowheads). The level of <italic>OsPR1#121</italic> was suppressed by mock-inoculation but the level was not changed by incompatible interaction. <italic>OsPR1#051</italic>, whose transcript increased in the compatible interaction at 6 dpi, was not clearly upregulated in the incompatible interaction.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Responses of OsPR1 genes to bacterial blight infection in young rice plants</title>
        <p>To study the response of the 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to a bacterial pathogen, the fourth leaves of Nipponbare were inoculated with <italic>Xoo</italic> for leaf blight disease. In the compatible rice&#x2013;bacterium interaction, the infected region was visualized as wilted necrosis, which spread from the cross cut end to the leaf base with time, and the area of necrosis grew to 2&#x2013;3&#xA0;cm long at 8 dpi. At 4 and 8 dpi, 5&#xA0;cm long leaf pieces from the inoculated point were used to prepare RNA samples. Transcripts of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, and <italic>#012</italic>, which are early responsive genes to blast fungus (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), accumulated remarkably at both 4 and 8 dpi compared with 0 dpi or a mock-inoculated control (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), indicating they were responsive to <italic>Xoo</italic> infection (closed forward arrowheads). Expression of <italic>OsPR1#021</italic> and <italic>#022</italic> were slightly suppressed after the infection compared with mock-inoculated leaves (closed reverse arrowheads). Expression of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, <italic>#012</italic>, and <italic>#101</italic> were upregulated by <italic>Xoo</italic> infection but other <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes did not respond or rather suppressed, while all <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes were upregulated in compatible blast fungus interaction (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Wound-induced expression of OsPR1 genes in young rice plants</title>
        <p>To study the response of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to wounding, the fourth leaves were wounded by cross cutting. Triplicate samples were extracted at 0, 1, 6, and 24&#xA0;h after wounding, and used for qPCR. Among the 12 genes, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> was wound-inducible with peak accumulation of the transcript at 6&#xA0;h after wounding, and <italic>OsPR1#051</italic> was found to be an early wound-responsive gene (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, forward arrowheads). The <italic>OsPR1#121</italic> and #052 transcripts decreased in response to wounding (reverse arrowheads) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Response of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to wounding The fourth leaves were cut into 1&#xA0;cm length sections for wounding, and floated on water for 0, 1, 6, and 24&#xA0;h under light, and then the leaf pieces were homogenized for RNA extraction. Relative expression levels compared with that of the control <italic>actin</italic> gene are shown. The wound-upregulated and -downregulated genes are marked with forward or reverse arrowheads, respectively. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Organ-specific expression of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes Leaves and roots of the seedlings at the fourth leaf stage (left panel), and flowers of adult plants (<italic>right panel</italic>) were subjected to qPCR analysis. Relative expression levels compared with that of the control <italic>actin</italic> gene are shown. The genes that express at a high level in roots and flowers are marked with <italic>white and gray arrowheads</italic>, respectively. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Organ specific expression of OsPR1 genes</title>
        <p>The basal transcript levels in various organs varied according to each gene; in the roots of healthy young rice plants at the 4-leaf stage, the transcript levels of the 5 genes, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#071</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, and <italic>#101</italic>, were clearly higher than in the fourth leaves (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) (open arrowheads). In flowers, the basal transcript levels of five genes, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, <italic>#012</italic>, <italic>#121</italic>, and <italic>#051</italic>, were at a high level (gray arrowheads). These results indicate that the organ-specific expression profiles of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes varied considerably. The <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#071</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, and <italic>#072</italic>, which are located on chromosome 7, were highly expressed in healthy roots. In healthy flowers the expression levels of five genes, <italic>OsPR#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, <italic>#012</italic>, <italic>#121</italic>, and <italic>#051</italic>, were also higher.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Responses of OsPR1 genes to defense signal compounds in young rice plants</title>
        <p>The responses of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to defense signal compounds were studied. Intact young rice plants in soil pots were dipped in water, SA, or ACC solutions, or exposed to the vapor of MeJA. RNA from the fourth leaves was subjected to qPCR (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> and <italic>#101</italic> were upregulated by all three signal compounds tested, while <italic>OsPR1#071, #073, #021</italic> and <italic>#121</italic> were upregulated by JA but not by ACC or SA. <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, and <italic>#012</italic>, which were early responsive genes to blast fungus (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>), were SA-inducible. <italic>OsPR1#011</italic> was upregulated by SA but suppressed by ACC. Among the six genes that were inducible by the wound signal compound JA, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> and <italic>#051</italic> were also upregulated by wounding (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). <italic>OsPR1#022</italic> and <italic>#052</italic> were not particularly sensitive to any of these compounds. <italic>OsPR1#011</italic> and <italic>#072</italic> were downregulated by ACC and SA respectively, and <italic>OsPR1#071</italic> was downregulated by both ACC and SA.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Response of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to defense-signal compounds ACC, SA, and JA. Expression levels of each <italic>OsPR1</italic> gene in fourth leaves at 24&#xA0;h after treatment with defense-signal compounds were analyzed by qPCR. Relative expression levels compared with that of the control <italic>actin</italic> gene are shown. The ACC-, SA-, and JA-inducible genes are marked with <italic>gray, dark gray, and black arrowheads</italic>, respectively. For ACC or SA treatment, plastic pots with rice seedlings were dipped in solutions containing 1&#xA0;mM ACC or 3&#xA0;mM SA solution, and incubated for 24&#xA0;h in the greenhouse. <italic>C1</italic> control for ACC- and SA-treatment (leaves of water treated plant); For JA treatment, pots with seedlings each was put in an air-tight clear plastic box, and a cotton pad with volatile methyl jasmonate (<italic>MeJA</italic>) dissolved in EtOH was put at the corner of the box to give a final concentration of 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M, and incubated for 24&#xA0;h. <italic>C2</italic> control for JA-treatment (leaves of plant treated with 0&#xA0;&#x3BC;M of JA), <italic>bars</italic> indicate mean&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;SD</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Comparison of the defense-signaling pathways conferred by ACC, SA, and JA in rice with those in tobacco and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic></title>
        <p>Using the 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes as probes, we analyzed the relationship of responsiveness to three defense signal compounds in rice. In tobacco, SA signaling was antagonistic to JA signaling on <italic>PR</italic> gene expression: Niki et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>) showed that the expression of acidic <italic>PR1</italic>, <italic>2</italic>, and <italic>3</italic> genes was upregulated by SA-treatment and it was suppressed in the presence of JA in a dose-dependent manner, while the expression of basic <italic>PR2</italic>, <italic>5</italic>, and <italic>6</italic> genes was upregulated by JA and suppressed by SA. Thomma et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1998</xref>) reported that the JA-signaling pathway is different from the SA-signaling pathway in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>. Glazebrook et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2003</xref>) reported that the expression patterns of some genes revealed mutual inhibition between SA- and JA-dependent signaling using global expression phenotyping analysis of mutant Arabidopsis plants. Synergistic induction by ET and JA was reported in basic tobacco <italic>PR</italic> genes (Xu et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1994</xref>). However, the expression patterns of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> showed no clear mutual inhibition between SA- and JA-dependent signaling, except for <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>. We further analyzed the relationship by means of Pearson&#x2019;s correlation coefficient (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Correlation coefficients for SA versus ACC, ACC versus JA, and SA versus JA were 0.75, 0.61, and 0.22, respectively. The linear correlation coefficient, <italic>r</italic>, represents the strength and the direction of the linear relationship between two variables. A correlation of +1 means an increasing linear relationship and complete correlation, while &#x2212;1 means a decreasing linear relationship. Cohen (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1988</xref>) proposed that |<italic>r</italic>| below 0.1 is regarded as insubstantial, 0.1&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;|<italic>r</italic>|&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.3 as weak, 0.3&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;|<italic>r</italic>|&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.5 as medium, and 0.5&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;|<italic>r</italic>|&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;1.0 as strong correlation. While, levels of statistical significance at 5 and 1% (<italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;12) are 0.576 and 0.708, respectively. The <italic>r</italic> values in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> suggest synergism between ACC versus SA and ACC versus JA, and low or no correlation between SA versus JA rather than antagonism.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Relationship of the three signaling pathways in <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes. Based on the data in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, the response of young rice plants to ACC- , SA-, or JA-treatments was compared with other treatments, and the correlation coefficients between the responses to pairs of signals were calculated. See the text for details</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>Tissue specific expression of a representative OsPR1 gene in rice plants</title>
        <p>Analysis of the tissue specific expression of rice <italic>PR1</italic> gene by means of histological studies has not been performed previously. To study the tissue specific expression profiles of a representative <italic>OsPR1</italic> gene, we selected <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> because it clearly responded to both compatible and incompatible fungal interactions, bacterial bright infection, wounding and the 3 defense signal compounds. The promoter sequence of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> was obtained by PCR amplification from the Nipponbare genome. The promoter sequence, containing 1,919&#xA0;bp, was inserted into the pTH2 vector (Kawahigashi et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>) to construct the plasmid <italic>PR1T::GUS</italic>, which contains the promoter and the coding region for 16 amino acids of the N-terminus of the OsPR1 protein to express the GUS protein effectively as a translational fusion (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a). The <italic>OsPR1T::GUS</italic> gene was introduced into rice plants (<italic>Oryza sativa</italic> cv. Nipponbare). Among 30 hygromycin-resistant plants regenerated, three independent lines were selected as representatives exhibiting a negligible level of GUS activity in healthy leaves and more than 30-fold higher levels after wounding or inoculation with a conidia suspension of <italic>M. grisea</italic>. The <italic>OsPR1T::GUS</italic> plants of the second or third generation were subjected to histological GUS analysis using X-gluc as the substrate.
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>Histological analysis of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> gene expression in transgenic rice plants. <bold>a</bold> Schematic diagram showing the construct of the introduced gene. The promoter sequence of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> was used. <bold>b</bold> Localized GUS staining in healthy 5&#xA0;day-old transgenic rice seedlings (<italic>a&#x2013;e</italic>). Because similar expression profiles were obtained in three independent transgenic lines, the data from a representative line is shown. <italic>f</italic> unhulled rice. <bold>c</bold> GUS staining of 2&#xA0;month-old transgenic rice plants. <italic>a</italic> Healthy roots, <italic>b</italic> roots at 2&#xA0;days after wounding, <italic>c&#x2013;e</italic> leaves at 2&#xA0;days after wounding. <bold>d</bold> GUS staining assay of 4th leaves at 5 (<italic>a, c, d</italic>) or 11 (<italic>b</italic>) dpi. <italic>Black arrows</italic> indicate stained mesophyll tissue. <italic>Brown arrows</italic> indicate the necrotic regions</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
        <p>Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B shows the localization of GUS activity in healthy 5-day-old transgenic rice seedlings. A high level of GUS activity was detected in the primary root (arrows, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B a&#x2013;c) and the root tip (arrowheads), but it was absent or considerably reduced in the elongation zone (white arrowheads). In cross sections of the middle part of the root 80&#xA0;&#x3BC;m in thickness (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B e), a strong GUS activity was detected in the vascular cylinder (vc) and sclerenchyma (sc), and a weak activity in the cortex (co). GUS staining was found in the slit surface of the coleoptile (yellow arrowheads, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B a, b), and on the surface of unhulled rice (white arrow, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B a, f). In the anther, a weak blue staining was found in the matrix of pollen loculus (data not shown). In the vector control plants, no GUS activity was detected in roots (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>B d) or any other part analyzed under these in condition (data not shown).</p>
        <p>In 2&#xA0;month-old <italic>OsPR1T::GUS</italic> plants, no GUS activity was found in healthy roots (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C a), while high levels of GUS activity were found in healthy 5&#xA0;day-old (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>Ba, b, and c) and 2&#xA0;week-old (data not shown) plants. Thus, <italic>OsPR1</italic> expression in roots is likely to be regulated developmentally. Wounding induced a high level of GUS activity in the roots of 2-month-old plants. When the aerial parts were removed by cross cut from of the plants, a strong GUS activity was induced in the roots of cut plants at 2&#xA0;days after cutting (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C b). In cross sections of the root in the middle region, GUS staining was found in all tissues, including the vascular cylinder, cortex, and sclerenchyma. No detectable GUS activity was found in healthy leaves of transgenic rice plants (data not shown); however, wounding induced a strong GUS activity in the neighbor region of the cut surface especially in the vascular systems including xylem parenchyma (xy) and phloem (ph) (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>C c&#x2013;e).</p>
        <p>Next, GUS activity in rice leaves infected with blast fungus was analyzed. In the compatible cultivar (WT) lacking the <italic>Pi-i</italic>resistance gene, enlarged lesions were found 3&#x2013;5 days after inoculation developing in size with time and with conidia formation on the infected leaf surface. After GUS staining, many blue spots were found at or around the lesions in the leaves 5 days after inoculation (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D a). When the leaf of Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D a was cross cut at the marked line, and shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D c, the blue staining was found to
localize in the mesophyll cells (black arrows) around the necrotic regions (brown arrows, Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D d). At 11 days after inoculation, GUS activity was found around the necrotic lesions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>D b).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec21" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>We studied here the response of 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to pathogens, wounding, and defense signal compounds and their constitutive expression in organs. This is the first example of a comparative study on the characterization of a set of <italic>PR 1</italic> family genes by qPCR, a high throughput method. The 12 genes include <italic>PR1a</italic> and <italic>b</italic>, which have been reported as pathogen-inducible genes by Agrawal et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2001</xref>), and ten of the 12 genes are contained in the 32 listed rice <italic>PR1</italic>-like genes including at least 3 pseudogenes whose expression profiles were not obvious (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). We searched rice <italic>PR1</italic>-like genes from full-length cDNA (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.cdna01.dna.affrc.go.jp/cDNA">http://www.cdna01.dna.affrc.go.jp/cDNA</ext-link>) and EST (<ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.riceblast.dna.affrc.go.jp/">http://www.riceblast.dna.affrc.go.jp/</ext-link>). Because strongly expressed genes should be easily extracted from the databases for expressed genes, a majority of highly expressed rice <italic>PR1</italic>-like genes are thought to be contained in the 12 genes. The sequences of the 12 OsPR1 proteins were well conserved with complete matches in 10 amino acid residues in the C-terminal half (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a). Because the 10 residues were also very well conserved in all 36 PR1-type proteins selected from 14 different plant species including <italic>Brassica napus</italic>, <italic>Hordeum vulgare</italic>, <italic>Lycopersicon esculentum</italic>, <italic>Medicago trunculata</italic>, <italic>Triticum aestivum</italic>, and <italic>Zea mays</italic> (van Loon and van Strien <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1999</xref>), these regions in the C-terminus should be important for the putative functions of PR1 proteins in plants.</p>
      <p>All 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes selected here were clearly upregulated in a compatible rice-blast fungus interaction, indicating that they really are pathogen related. Notable is that the induction pattern of each <italic>OsPR1</italic> gene by different pathogen&#x2013;host interactions was characteristic (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Four genes, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, <italic>#012</italic>, and <italic>#101</italic>, responded positively to blast fungus infection in both compatible and incompatible interactions, and also to <italic>Xoo</italic> infection. Among these, <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, <italic>#011</italic>, and <italic>#012</italic> were responsive to blast fungus in the early infection period in both interactions. Conversely, the expression of <italic>OsPR1#021</italic> and <italic>#022</italic> was reduced by <italic>Xoo</italic> infection compared with the control after mock-inoculation, which is a wound treatment. Assuming that <italic>Xoo</italic> infection may inhibit wound-induced expression of these genes, it is consistent that they are wound-inducible (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The above result that &#x201C;all 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic>s are characteristically pathogen inducible&#x201D; is apparently different from the data of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> where only one <italic>PR1</italic> gene was pathogen-inducible (AT2g14610) among 22 predicted <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>PR1</italic> genes (van Loon et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2006</xref>). We studied this result using an AtGenExpress Visualization Tool from <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.arabidopsis.org/">http://www.arabidopsis.org/</ext-link>, and confirmed that only the <italic>PR1</italic> gene was upregulated by infection with either <italic>Pseudomonas syringae</italic> pv. tomato DC3000 or <italic>Pytophythora infestans</italic>, and the other <italic>PR1</italic> genes were not. The reason for different responses of <italic>PR1</italic>s to pathogen infection in rice and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> is not clear, but we could speculate that <italic>OsPR1</italic>s have evolved in the rice genome to provide resistance to a broad range of pathogens, but a limited set of <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>PR1</italic>s has evolved to respond to pathogens.</p>
      <p>In rice, the level of free SA in young healthy rice leaves was as high as about 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;g per g fresh leaf (Silverman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1995</xref>), but it was only about 20&#xA0;ng (Seo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2007</xref>) or 100 &#x2013; 200&#xA0;ng (Silverman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1995</xref>) in tobacco leaves, and about 30&#xA0;ng (Park et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2007</xref>) or 150&#xA0;ng (our unpublished data) in <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves. Thus, the SA content in rice leaves corresponds to 50- to 500-fold of that in tobacco or <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> leaves, which is comparable to the induced SA level after HR lesion formation by TMV-infection. Such a high SA level in rice plants could affect <italic>OsPR1</italic> expression after pathogen infection, treatment with SA, JA, or ACC, and wounding. Actually, the responses of the <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes to defense signal compounds indicate that the signaling pathways in rice conferred by SA and JA were synergistic as well as that by ET and JA, and SA and ET (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). This finding is considerably different from the &#x201C;antagonistic relationship of SA and JA signaling&#x201D; found in tobacco (Niki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>) and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> (Gupta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>). In tobacco, acidic PR1 proteins such as NtPR1a, b, and c were inducible by SA (Ohashi and Matsuoka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1987</xref>), which is a defense signal compound for systemic acquired resistance. The <italic>NtPRB1b</italic> (Eyal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1992</xref>; Niki et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1998</xref>) and <italic>AtPRB1</italic> (Santamaria et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2001</xref>) genes, which encode basic PR proteins in tobacco and <italic>Arabidopsis</italic>, respectively, were reported to respond positively to JA and ET, and negatively to SA. The <italic>Arabidopsis</italic><italic>PR1</italic> gene (At2g14610) encodes a basic protein that is inducible by SA.</p>
      <p>To compare the natures of the <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes, the results of the expression of 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes are summarized in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. It is again impressive that the expression upregulated by various treatments differed considerably depending on the gene, and the transcript levels constitutively found in leaf, root, and flower also varied according to the genes. When comparing the four genes <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#72</italic>, <italic>#073</italic>, and <italic>#074</italic>, which are clustered in a locus on chromosome 7, we found the following common characteristics: all four genes (1) encode acidic proteins, (2) are constitutively expressed in healthy roots at a high level, and (3) are upregulated by blast fungus-infection. In spite of these similarities, their expression profiles after certain treatments were significantly different from each other. For example, (1) the transcript of <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> accumulated at an earlier time period than those of <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, or <italic>#073</italic> in fungus-infected resistant cultivar IL7, (2) <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> but not <italic>#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, or <italic>#073</italic> was upregulated by <italic>Xoo</italic>-infection, (3) <italic>OsPR1#074</italic>, but not <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, or <italic>#073</italic>, was wound-inducible, (4) <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> was ACC-, SA-, and JA-inducible, <italic>OsPR1#071</italic> was JA-inducible, <italic>OsPR1#072</italic> was not inducible by any signal compounds used here, and <italic>OsPR1#073</italic> appeared to be suppressed by ACC, (5) <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> was expressed in flowers at a high level, but <italic>OsPR1#071</italic>, <italic>#072</italic>, and <italic>#073</italic> were not.
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#xA0;8</label><caption><p>Comparison of expression characteristics of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes Induction levels of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes by pathogens, wounding, and defense signal compounds, and their constitutive expression levels in organs were compared. The transcript levels in healthy 4<sup>th</sup> leaves are shown in the right most column. <italic>++</italic> very highly inducible or expressed gene, <italic>+</italic> highly inducible or expressed gene, <italic>&#xB1;</italic> gene whose induction or expression was not clear, <italic>&#x2212;</italic> not inducible or expressed gene</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="438_2008_322_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p>
      <p>From the expression characteristics of the 12 Os<italic>PR1</italic> genes obtained here, the possible contribution of all Os<italic>PR1</italic> genes for plant self-defense against pathogen attack was indicated. Although the functions of <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes are not fully understood, PR1 proteins in some plant species have been reported to have antifungal activity including tobacco acidic <italic>PR1a</italic> overexpression that induced increased tolerance to two oomycete pathogens in tobacco (Alexander et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1993</xref>), and basic PR-1 proteins of tobacco and tomato, which have an antimicrobial activity against <italic>Phytophythora infestans</italic> (Niederman et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1995</xref>). Thus, the redundant expression of the 12 <italic>OsPR1</italic> genes may effectively contribute to defend the attack of various pathogens.</p>
      <p>The expression levels of the 12 genes in healthy tissues and wounded leaves were also very different according to each particular gene. The data in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref> shows a representative example of tissue- and organ-specific expression of <italic>OsPR1</italic>. The level of GUS activity in transgenic rice plants carrying the <italic>OsPR1T::GUS</italic> gene was confirmed to be similar to the <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> transcript level as shown in tobacco <italic>PR1a::GUS</italic> plants (Yamakawa et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1998</xref>), in which the <italic>GUS</italic> gene was expressed as a similar translational fusion gene described in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A. GUS analysis using independent transgenic lines showed <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> expression was developmentally regulated in roots and constitutively expressed in young rice plants, but not in 2-month old plants, in which the expression was strongly upregulated by wounding (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>A, B). The wound-induced <italic>OsPR1#074</italic> expression in adult plants was localized mainly in the vascular system, which is important as the sensing tissue of the water pressure change after wounding and as the site of bacterial pathogen propagation.</p>
      <p>The information on the 12 <italic>PR1</italic> genes obtained here will be useful for further studies on self-defense mechanisms in rice plants, and for the usage of each <italic>PR1</italic> gene as a characteristic marker gene.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <p>We thank Imbe T and Ando I of the National Agriculture and Food Research Organization for providing IL7 rice seeds, Miyasaka A in the same organization for providing <italic>M. grisea</italic> race 003 and Y. Gotoh, Y. Naito, and M. Teruse for their technical assistance. This study was supported in part by the Program for Promotion of Basic Research Activities for Innovative Biosciences.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jwa</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rakwal</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A novel rice (<italic>Oryza sativa L</italic>.) acidic PR1 gene highly responsive to cut, phytohormones, and protein phosphatase inhibitors</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>274</volume>
          <fpage>157</fpage>
          <lpage>165</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.3114</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal GK, Jwa NS, Rakwal R (2000a) A novel rice (Oryza sativa L.) acidic PR1 gene highly responsive to cut, phytohormones, and protein phosphatase inhibitors. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 274:157&#x2013;165 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10903912</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rakwal</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jwa</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Rice (<italic>Oryza sativa L</italic>.) <italic>OsPR1b</italic> gene is phytohormonally regulated in close interaction with light signals</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>278</volume>
          <fpage>290</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2000.3781</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal GK, Rakwal R, Jwa NS (2000b) Rice (Oryza sativa L.) OsPR1b gene is phytohormonally regulated in close interaction with light signals. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 278:290&#x2013;298 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11097833</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>GK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rakwal</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jwa</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>VP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Signaling molecules and blast pathogen attack activates rice OsPR1a and OsPR1b genes: a model illustrating components participating during defense/stress response</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol Biochem</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>1095</fpage>
          <lpage>1103</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0981-9428(01)01333-X</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal GK, Rakwal R, Jwa NS, Agrawal VP (2001) Signaling molecules and blast pathogen attack activates rice OsPR1a and OsPR1b genes: a model illustrating components participating during defense/stress response. Plant Physiol Biochem 39:1095&#x2013;1103 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alexander</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goodman</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gut-Rella</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glascock</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weymann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Friedrich</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maddox</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahl-Goy</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Luntz</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>War</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryals</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased tolerance to 2 oomycete pathogens in transgenic tobacco expressing pathogenesis-related protein 1a</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <fpage>7327</fpage>
          <lpage>7331</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.90.15.7327</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Alexander D, Goodman RM, Gut-Rella M, Glascock C, Weymann K, Friedrich L, Maddox D, Ahl-Goy P, Luntz T, War E, Ryals J (1993) Increased tolerance to 2 oomycete pathogens in transgenic tobacco expressing pathogenesis-related protein 1a. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 90:7327&#x2013;7331 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8346252</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Cohen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differences between correlation coefficients</article-title>
          <source>Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <edition>2nd edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Hillsdale</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers</publisher-name>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>143</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cohen J (1988) Differences between correlation coefficients. In: Cohen J (ed) Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences, 2nd edn. Lawrence Erlbaum Associates Publishers, Hillsdale, pp 109&#x2013;143 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eyal</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sagee</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fluhr</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dark-induced accumulation of a basic pathogenesis-related (PR-1) transcript and a light requirement for its induction by ethylene</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>589</fpage>
          <lpage>599</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00026785</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eyal Y, Sagee O, Fluhr R (1992) Dark-induced accumulation of a basic pathogenesis-related (PR-1) transcript and a light requirement for its induction by ethylene. Plant Mol Biol 19:589&#x2013;599 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1627772</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Estes</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nawrath</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metraus</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katagiri</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topology of the network integrating salicylate and jasmonate signal transduction derived from global expression phenotyping</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>217</fpage>
          <lpage>228</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-313X.2003.01717.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Glazebrook J, Chen W, Estes B, Chang HS, Nawrath C, Metraus JP, Zhu T, Katagiri F (2003) Topology of the network integrating salicylate and jasmonate signal transduction derived from global expression phenotyping. Plant J 34:217&#x2013;228 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12694596</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gupta</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willits</surname>
              <given-names>MG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title><italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic> EDS4 contributes to salicylic acid (SA)-dependent expression of defense responses: evidence for inhibition of jasmonic acid signaling by SA</article-title>
          <source>Mol Plant Microbe Interact</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>503</fpage>
          <lpage>511</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1094/MPMI.2000.13.5.503</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gupta V, Willits MG, Glazebrook J (2000) Arabidopsis thaliana EDS4 contributes to salicylic acid (SA)-dependent expression of defense responses: evidence for inhibition of jasmonic acid signaling by SA. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 13:503&#x2013;511 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10796016</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ise</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horisue</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characteristics of several near-isogenic lines of rice for blast resistance gene</article-title>
          <source>Breed Sci</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>38</volume>
          <issue>Suppl 2</issue>
          <fpage>404</fpage>
          <lpage>405</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ise K, Horisue N (1988) Characteristics of several near-isogenic lines of rice for blast resistance gene. Breed Sci 38(Suppl 2):404&#x2013;405 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iwai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyasaka</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Contribution of ethylene biosynthesis for resistance to blast fungus infection in young rice plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>142</volume>
          <fpage>1202</fpage>
          <lpage>1215</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.106.085258</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Iwai T, Miyasaka A, Seo S, Ohashi Y (2006) Contribution of ethylene biosynthesis for resistance to blast fungus infection in young rice plants. Plant Physiol 142:1202&#x2013;1215 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17012402</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Iwai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitsuhara</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Probenazole-induced accumulation of salicylic acid confers resistance to <italic>Magnaporthe grisea</italic> in adult rice plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>915</fpage>
          <lpage>924</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pcm062</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Iwai T, Seo S, Mitsuhara I, Ohashi Y (2007) Probenazole-induced accumulation of salicylic acid confers resistance to Magnaporthe grisea in adult rice plants. Plant Cell Physiol 48:915&#x2013;924 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17517758</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kawahigashi</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirose</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iwai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakamono</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maekawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohkawa</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Chemically induced expression of rice <italic>OSB2</italic> under the control of the <italic>OsPR1.1</italic> promoter confers increased anthocyanin accumulation in transgenic rice</article-title>
          <source>J Agric Food Chem</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>1241</fpage>
          <lpage>1247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/jf062339w</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kawahigashi H, Hirose S, Iwai T, Ohashi Y, Sakamono W, Maekawa M, Ohkawa Y (2007) Chemically induced expression of rice OSB2 under the control of the OsPR1.1 promoter confers increased anthocyanin accumulation in transgenic rice. J Agric Food Chem 55:1241&#x2013;1247 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17253710</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Metzler</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cutt</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Isolation and characterization of a gene encoding a PR-1-like protein from <italic>Arabidopsis thaliana</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>96</volume>
          <fpage>346</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Metzler MC, Cutt JR, Klessig DF (1991) Isolation and characterization of a gene encoding a PR-1-like protein from Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Physiol 96:346&#x2013;348 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16668181</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niederman</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Genetet</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruyere</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gees</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stinzi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Legrand</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fritig</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mosinger</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathogenesis-related PR-1 proteins are antifungal: isolation and characterization of three 14 kidodalton proteins of tomato and of a basic PR-1 of tobacco with inhibitory activity against <italic>Phytophythora infestans</italic></article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.108.1.17</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Niederman T, Genetet I, Bruyere T, Gees R, Stinzi A, Legrand M, Fritig B, Mosinger E (1995) Pathogenesis-related PR-1 proteins are antifungal: isolation and characterization of three 14 kidodalton proteins of tomato and of a basic PR-1 of tobacco with inhibitory activity against Phytophythora infestans. Plant Physiol 108:17&#x2013;27 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7784503</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niki</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitsuhara</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohtsuba</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Antagonistic effect of salicylic acid and jasmonic acid on the expression of pathogenesis-related (PR) protein genes in wounded mature tobacco leaves</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>500</fpage>
          <lpage>507</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Niki T, Mitsuhara I, Seo S, Ohtsuba N, Ohashi Y (1998) Antagonistic effect of salicylic acid and jasmonic acid on the expression of pathogenesis-related (PR) protein genes in wounded mature tobacco leaves. Plant Cell Physiol 39:500&#x2013;507 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuoka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Induction and secretion of pathogenesis-related proteins by salicylate or plant hormones in tobacco suspension cultures</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>28</volume>
          <fpage>573</fpage>
          <lpage>580</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ohashi Y, Matsuoka M (1987) Induction and secretion of pathogenesis-related proteins by salicylate or plant hormones in tobacco suspension cultures. Plant Cell Physiol 28:573&#x2013;580 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ohshima</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuoka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamamoto</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kano-Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ozeki</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kato</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harada Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>N Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nucleotide sequence of the PR-1 gene of <italic>Nicotiana tabacum</italic></article-title>
          <source>FEBS Lett</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>225</volume>
          <fpage>243</fpage>
          <lpage>246</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-5793(87)81166-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ohshima M, Matsuoka M, Yamamoto N, Tanaka Y, Kano-Murakami Y, Ozeki Y, Kato A, Harada N Ohashi Y (1987) Nucleotide sequence of the PR-1 gene of Nicotiana tabacum. FEBS Lett 225:243&#x2013;246 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3691804</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ohshima</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Itoh</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuoka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of stress-induced or salicylic acid-induced expression of the pathogenesis-related 1a protein gene in transgenic tobacco.</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.2.2.95</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ohshima M, Itoh H, Matsuoka M, Murakami T, Ohashi Y (1990) Analysis of stress-induced or salicylic acid-induced expression of the pathogenesis-related 1a protein gene in transgenic tobacco. Plant Cell 2:95&#x2013;106 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2136635</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>S-W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kaimoyo</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kumar</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mosher</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Klessig</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Methyl salicylate is a critical mobile signal for plant systemic acquired resistance</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>318</volume>
          <fpage>113</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1147113</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Park S-W, Kaimoyo E, Kumar D, Mosher S, Klessig DF (2007) Methyl salicylate is a critical mobile signal for plant systemic acquired resistance. Science 318:113&#x2013;116 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17916738</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Santamaria</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomson</surname>
              <given-names>CJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Read Loake</surname>
              <given-names>ND GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The promoter of a basic PR1-like gene, AtPRB1, from <italic>Arabidopsis</italic> establishes an organ-specific expression pattern and responsiveness to ethylene and ethyl jasmonate</article-title>
          <source>Plant Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>641</fpage>
          <lpage>652</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1012410009930</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Santamaria M, Thomson CJ, Read ND Loake GJ (2001) The promoter of a basic PR1-like gene, AtPRB1, from Arabidopsis establishes an organ-specific expression pattern and responsiveness to ethylene and ethyl jasmonate. Plant Mol Biol 47:641&#x2013;652 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11725949</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sasaki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iwai</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hiraga</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuroda</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitsuhara</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miyasaka</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iwano</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ito</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsui</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ten rice peroxidases redundantly respond to multiple stresses including infection with rice blast fungus</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Physiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1442</fpage>
          <lpage>1452</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/pcp/pch165</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sasaki K, Iwai T, Hiraga S, Kuroda K, Seo S, Mitsuhara I, Miyasaka A, Iwano M, Ito H, Matsui H, Ohashi Y (2004) Ten rice peroxidases redundantly respond to multiple stresses including infection with rice blast fungus. Plant Cell Physiol 45:1442&#x2013;1452 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15564528</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seto</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gomi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The mitogen-activated protein kinases WIPK and SIPK regulate the levels of jasmonic and salicylic acids in wounded tobacco plants</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>899</fpage>
          <lpage>909</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.03003.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Seo S, Katou S, Seto H, Gomi K, Ohashi Y (2007) The mitogen-activated protein kinases WIPK and SIPK regulate the levels of jasmonic and salicylic acids in wounded tobacco plants. Plant J 49:899&#x2013;909 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17253983</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seskar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kanter</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schweizer</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metraus</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raskin</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Salicylic acid in rice (biosynthesis, conjugation, and possible role)</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>633</fpage>
          <lpage>639</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Silverman P, Seskar M, Kanter D, Schweizer P, Metraus JP, Raskin I (1995) Salicylic acid in rice (biosynthesis, conjugation, and possible role). Plant Physiol 108:633&#x2013;639 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12228500</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schweizer</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buchala</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silverman</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seskar</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raskin</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metraux</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Jasmonate-inducible genes are activated in rice by pathogen attack without a concomitant increase in endogenous jasmonic acid levels</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schweizer P, Buchala A, Silverman P, Seskar M, Raskin I, Metraux JP (1997) Jasmonate-inducible genes are activated in rice by pathogen attack without a concomitant increase in endogenous jasmonic acid levels. Plant Physiol 114:79&#x2013;88 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12223690</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Thomma</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eggermont</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Penninckx</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mauch-Mani</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vogelsang</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cammue</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Broekaert</surname>
              <given-names>WF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Separate jasmonate-dependent and salicylate-dependent defense-response pathways in arabidopsis are essential for resistance to distinct microbial pathogens</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>15107</fpage>
          <lpage>15111</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.25.15107</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Thomma BP, Eggermont K, Penninckx IA, Mauch-Mani B, Vogelsang R, Cammue BP, Broekaert WF (1998) Separate jasmonate-dependent and salicylate-dependent defense-response pathways in arabidopsis are essential for resistance to distinct microbial pathogens. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 95:15107&#x2013;15111 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9844023</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toki</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hara</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ono</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Onodera</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tagiri</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Early infection of scutellum tissue with <italic>Agrobacterium</italic> allows high-speed transformation of rice</article-title>
          <source>Plant J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>969</fpage>
          <lpage>976</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-313X.2006.02836.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Toki S, Hara N, Ono K, Onodera H, Tagiri A, Oka S, Tanaka H (2006) Early infection of scutellum tissue with Agrobacterium allows high-speed transformation of rice. Plant J 47:969&#x2013;976 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16961734</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loon</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strien</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The families of pathogenesis-related proteins, their activities and comparative analysis of PR-1 type proteins</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Mol Plant Path</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>55</volume>
          <fpage>85</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/pmpp.1999.0213</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Loon LC, van Strien EA (1999) The families of pathogenesis-related proteins, their activities and comparative analysis of PR-1 type proteins. Physiol Mol Plant Path 55:85&#x2013;97 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Loon</surname>
              <given-names>LC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rep</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pieterse</surname>
              <given-names>CMJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Significance of inducible defense-related proteins in infected plants</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Phytopathol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <fpage>135</fpage>
          <lpage>162</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.phyto.44.070505.143425</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">van Loon LC, Rep M, Pieterse CMJ (2006) Significance of inducible defense-related proteins in infected plants. Annu Rev Phytopathol 44:135&#x2013;162 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16602946</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>P-F L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Narasimhan</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Raghothama</surname>
              <given-names>KG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haegawa</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bressan</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant defense genes are synergistically induced by ethylene and methyl jasmonate</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>1077</fpage>
          <lpage>1085</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1105/tpc.6.8.1077</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Xu Y, Chang P-F L, Liu D, Narasimhan ML, Raghothama KG, Haegawa PM, Bressan RA (1994) Plant defense genes are synergistically induced by ethylene and methyl jasmonate. Plant Cell 6:1077&#x2013;1085 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12244267</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamada</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kiyosawa</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hirano</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kushibuchi</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Proposal of a new method for differentiating races of <italic>Pyricularia oryzae</italic> Cavara in Japan</article-title>
          <source>Ann Phytopathol Soc Jpn</source>
          <year>1976</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>216</fpage>
          <lpage>219</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamada M, Kiyosawa S, Yamaguchi T, Hirano T, Kobayashi T, Kushibuchi K, Watanabe S (1976) Proposal of a new method for differentiating races of Pyricularia oryzae Cavara in Japan. Ann Phytopathol Soc Jpn 42:216&#x2013;219 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamakawa</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamada</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Satoh</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spermine is a salicylate-independent endogenous inducer for both tobacco acidic pathogenesis-related proteins and resistance against tobacco mosaic virus infection</article-title>
          <source>Plant Physiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>1213</fpage>
          <lpage>1222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1104/pp.118.4.1213</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamakawa H, Kamada H, Satoh M, Ohashi Y (1998) Spermine is a salicylate-independent endogenous inducer for both tobacco acidic pathogenesis-related proteins and resistance against tobacco mosaic virus infection. Plant Physiol 118:1213&#x2013;1222 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9847095</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
    <fn-group>
      <fn>
        <p>Ichiro Mitsuhara and Takayoshi Iwai contributed equally to this work.</p>
      </fn>
    </fn-group>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>