<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oecologia</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Oecologia</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0029-8549</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1939</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17609982</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2039789</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">792</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-007-0792-1</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Plant Animal Interactions</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Costs and benefits of induced resistance in a clonal plant network</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>G&#xF3;mez</surname>
            <given-names>Sara</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-24-3652907</phone>
            <fax>+31-24-3652409</fax>
            <email>S.Gomez@science.ru.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Latzel</surname>
            <given-names>V&#xED;t</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Verhulst</surname>
            <given-names>Yolanda M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Stuefer</surname>
            <given-names>Josef F.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Ecology, Radboud University Nijmegen, Toernooiveld 1, 6525 ED Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Institute of Botany, Academy of Sciences of the Czech Republic, T&#x159;ebo&#x148;, Czech Republic </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>3</day>
        <month>7</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>153</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>921</fpage>
      <lpage>930</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>18</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>4</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>Plant defense theory suggests that inducible resistance has evolved to reduce the costs of constitutive defense expression. To assess the functional and potentially adaptive value of induced resistance it is necessary to quantify the costs and benefits associated with this plastic response. The ecological and evolutionary viability of induced defenses ultimately depends on the long-term balance between advantageous and disadvantageous consequences of defense induction. Stoloniferous plants can use their inter-ramet connections to share resources and signals and to systemically activate defense expression after local herbivory. This network-specific early-warning system may confer clonal plants with potentially high benefits. However, systemic defense induction can also be costly if local herbivory is not followed by a subsequent attack on connected ramets. We found significant costs and benefits of systemic induced resistance by comparing growth and performance of induced and control plants of the stoloniferous herb <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> in the presence and absence of herbivores.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Adaptive plasticity hypothesis</kwd>
        <kwd>Physiological integration</kwd>
        <kwd>Plant communication</kwd>
        <kwd>Plant defense</kwd>
        <kwd>
          <italic>Trifolium repens</italic>
        </kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Plants can allocate a limited pool of resources to the three main functions of growth, reproduction and defense, suggesting that increased investments in one function may compromise the others. Empirical studies have shown that constitutive defense can be costly (e.g., tannins, Sagers and Coley <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1995</xref>; glandular trichomes, Elle et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">1999</xref>). Plant defense theory postulates that inducible defense mechanisms have evolved to reduce these costs by optimizing the temporal match between resource investment into defense and herbivory threats (Herms and Mattson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1992</xref>; Agrawal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1999</xref>). In the last decades numerous studies have attempted to find costs of induced defense (reviewed in Bergelson and Purlington <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1996</xref> and Strauss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2002</xref>) but evidence for costs of inducible plant defense remains scarce and inconclusive. More recently, empirical evidence has emerged supporting the allocation cost theory with the help of improved experimental designs, genetic engineering, and biochemical methodology (Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1998</xref>; Van Dam and Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2001</xref>; Heil and Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>Inducible resistance is a form of phenotypic plasticity as it allows plants to express an adequate phenotype in response to temporally and spatially variable herbivore damage. Herbivore-induced changes in the phenotypes of plants often relate to trait alterations which reduce the palatability and digestibility of consumed tissue by producing toxic metabolites and/or by up-regulating the production of a variety of defensive compounds. The ecological viability of induced resistance as an efficient defense strategy depends on the balance of costs and benefits associated with plastic defense induction. Assessing the benefits of induced defense in conjunction with possible costs is a prerequisite for estimating the advantages and disadvantages of plastic defense induction as a potentially adaptive form of phenotypic plasticity (Dudley and Schmitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1996</xref>; Schmitt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1999</xref>) and hence for understanding potential selection pressures leading to the evolution of induced plant defenses (Agrawal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2000</xref>).</p>
      <p>Costs of defense have been traditionally measured in terms of decreased plant fitness. Allocation costs refer to a direct fitness decrease as a consequence of resource-mediated trade-offs between defense investment and other plant functions. Recent empirical and conceptual work has provided convincing arguments for the notion that defense induction can also affect fitness in an indirect manner, via a multitude of potentially complex ecological interactions (Van Dam and Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2001</xref>; Heil and Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>; Strauss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2002</xref>). These costs are commonly referred to as ecological costs.</p>
      <p>Allocation theory suggests that costs of plastic defense induction should be more apparent in low-resource environments than under optimal growth conditions (Herms and Mattson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1992;</xref> Bergelson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">1994</xref>; Bergelson and Purlington <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1996</xref>; but see van Dam and Baldwin <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">2001</xref>) as the diversion of resources to defense can not easily be compensated for by enhanced resource acquisition. In addition, experiments to detect costs of defense conducted under quasi-optimal conditions are unlikely to reflect realistic situations, and therefore, tend to underestimate plasticity costs. To overcome this problem, several studies have used competitive and/or low-resource environments to quantify costs of induced defense (Siemens et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2003</xref> and studies quoted therein). Additionally, previous studies have shown that controlling the genetic background of plants can substantially enhance the chances to detect costs, by removing confounding effects due to genetic variation in the induced response (Bergelson and Purlington <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1996</xref>; Strauss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2002</xref>).</p>
      <p>Stoloniferous plants consist of multiple, genetically identical individuals (ramets) that are interconnected by aboveground horizontal stems (stolons). Resource transport within clonal plant networks has been extensively described in the literature (Pitelka and Ashmun <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">1985</xref>; Marshall <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1990</xref>; Alpert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1996</xref>; Alpert and Stuefer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1997</xref>). Nevertheless, the importance of stolon connections for the transport of defense agents is a novel aspect (Stuefer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2004</xref>) that has only recently been demonstrated (G&#xF3;mez and Stuefer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>). Ramets of the stoloniferous herb <italic>Trifolium repens</italic> are able to systemically induce other ramets after local herbivore damage. On the one hand, this form of physiological integration may confer clonal plant networks with considerable benefits by allowing for a fast, specific and efficient early-warning system among interconnected ramets. On the other hand, the potentially large spatial scale of clonal plant networks may also lead to substantial costs if network members become induced without being threatened by herbivores (G&#xF3;mez and Stuefer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>). These costs are due to a potential mismatch in the spatio-temporal scale of plastic defense expression and the dynamics and patterns of herbivore attacks.</p>
      <p>To assess the potentially adaptive nature of plastic responses, &#x201C;it is necessary to demonstrate that the phenotype induced in each relevant environment confers higher fitness in that environment relative to alternative phenotypes&#x201D; (Schmitt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1999</xref>). This is analogous to stating that the induced phenotype should incur costs in herbivore-free environments, while defense induction should lead to benefits in herbivore-exposed environments. To quantify costs and benefits we measured traits related to plant fitness and performance of induced and uninduced <italic>T. repens</italic> plants in the absence and presence of herbivores. Growing induced and uninduced plants in the absence of herbivores allows for a quantification of possible costs of induced resistance, simulating localized damage (e.g., by small herbivores with a low mobility) and the activation of defense in ramets beyond the feeding range of the herbivore. Benefits of induction, however, can only be assessed in the presence of herbivores after an initial attack, thereby simulating a scenario with mobile herbivores showing active foraging behavior beyond the first place of attack.</p>
      <p>In this study we tested the following specific hypotheses:</p>
      <p>
        <list list-type="order">
          <list-item>
            <p>In the absence of herbivores, systemically induced ramets of clonal plants perform worse than uninduced ramets of the same genotype. This is due to costs of defense induction when defense is not needed.</p>
          </list-item>
          <list-item>
            <p>In the presence of herbivores, induced ramets of clonal plants perform better than uninduced plants, due to an enhanced protection through induced defense.</p>
          </list-item>
        </list>
      </p>
      <p>To test these hypotheses we grew induced and uninduced (control) plants of the stoloniferous herb <italic>T. repens</italic> together to expose them to mutual competitive interactions, resembling sub-optimal growing conditions in a sward. To quantify costs and benefits of induced resistance we grew plants in herbivore-free and herbivore-exposed environments, respectively.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Study organisms</title>
        <p>Five genotypes of the stoloniferous herb <italic>T. repens</italic> L. were vegetatively propagated in a greenhouse at a mean temperature of 21&#xB0;C/19&#xB0;C (day/night), and at a 16&#xA0;h/8&#xA0;h (light/dark) photoperiod. The genotypes originated from natural riverine grassland populations situated along the river Waal, The Netherlands. They had been collected 4 years prior to the start of this experiment and were grown under common garden conditions, eliminating possible maternal and environmental carry-over effects.</p>
        <p>The beet armyworm (<italic>Spodoptera exigua</italic> H&#xFC;bner) used in this study is a generalist caterpillar with a broad host range. The caterpillar colony was maintained at a constant temperature of 24&#xB0;C and 16&#xA0;h/8&#xA0;h (light/dark) photoperiod. The larvae were reared on an artificial diet described in Biere et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2004</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Pre-growth of plant material</title>
        <p>We started the experiment with 64 cuttings of each of the five genotypes. The cuttings were planted in pairs in plastic trays (16&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;12&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;5&#xA0;cm) using sterilized clay grains as a substrate (Seramis; Masterfoods, Germany). Each tray was fertilized weekly with 50&#xA0;ml full-strength Hoagland solution before the start of the experiment. At the beginning of the experiment, all cuttings consisted of a main stolon with at least eight fully developed ramets. If present, side branches were removed immediately before starting the experiment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Experimental design</title>
        <p>The experimental set-up (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>) to measure costs and benefits of systemic induced resistance (SIR) consisted of four peripheral trays placed around a central tray, which we will refer to as the &#x201C;competition tray&#x201D;. All trays were of similar dimensions (16&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;12&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;5&#xA0;cm). Each of the peripheral trays contained two cuttings with at least eight ramets each. The cuttings in two of those trays received a treatment to induce defense during the entire duration of the experiment (for details see below), while the cuttings in the other two trays remained uninduced (control). Trays receiving the same treatment were placed diagonally opposite each other. The competition tray was placed inside a metal frame (20&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;15&#xA0;cm&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;20&#xA0;cm) covered by mosquito netting (mesh gauge 0.2&#xA0;cm<sup>2</sup>) with four small openings on both longitudinal sides. The two youngest ramets of each cutting were inserted through the mesh openings and allowed to grow (proliferate and root) in the competition tray for 19&#xA0;days. We used five <italic>T. repens</italic> genotypes, each of which was replicated 4 times to measure costs and 4 times to measure benefits of defense induction. All induced and control plants grown together in the same experimental set-up (as described above) belonged to the same genotype. The experimental systems were randomly distributed on greenhouse benches.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Schematic representation of the experimental set-up to measure costs and benefits of systemic induced resistance (SIR) in a clonal plant network. Control (<italic>white</italic>) and defense-induced (<italic>gray</italic>) plants grew from four peripheral trays into a common, central competition tray. The <italic>circles</italic> represent petri dishes used for a continued controlled herbivore attack (defense induction treatment). To measure costs of SIR, plants grew together in the absence of herbivores in the competition tray (<italic>upper drawing</italic>). To measure benefits, ten caterpillars (<italic>wavy black lines</italic>) were added to the competition tray (<italic>lower drawing</italic>). See Materials and methods for more details</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_792_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Systemic induction of resistance</title>
        <p>Systemic induction of resistance was achieved through a controlled herbivore attack. One <italic>S.</italic><italic>exigua</italic> larva was confined with two leaves in one petri dish mounted on the plants (G&#xF3;mez and Stuefer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>). The corresponding ramets of uninduced control plants were similarly enclosed in modified petri dishes but without adding any larvae. The controlled herbivore attack was maintained throughout the course of the experiment, starting on the ramet on the eighth position (counting from the tip of the stolon) from each cutting. When the two ramets inside the petri dish had lost at least 50% of leaf tissue, the petri dish was moved forward on the stolon and the adjacent, younger ramet was inserted into the petri dish. Whenever the induction treatment was moved forward on the induced cuttings, a comparable leaf area was removed with scissors from one ramet of each cutting in the control trays. This was done to compensate for the leaf area loss due to caterpillar feeding in the induced plants. Cutting the leaves with scissors does not induce resistance in <italic>T. repens</italic> (S. G&#xF3;mez, unpublished data). The induction treatment started 1 day after the cuttings were placed into the competition tray. If the caterpillar inside the petri dish died, it was replaced by a new one to maintain defense induction.</p>
        <p>In order to enhance plant interactions, induced and control plants were grown together in the competition tray. Since all plants growing together belonged to the same genotype, induction effects cannot be confounded with genetic differences in plant traits, including competitive ability, between induced and control plants. All measurements described below were performed on ramets growing in the competition trays.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Costs of SIR</title>
        <p>Costs of defense induction were measured as a reduction in plant performance. Costs can be measured after initial herbivore damage (and consequent defense induction) in the absence of subsequent herbivore attacks. To quantify costs of defense induction we measured the following traits which are known to be closely related to plant performance and fitness: total biomass production, relative biomass allocation to leaves, petioles, stolons, and roots, number and length of the main and side stolons and number of ramets on the main and side stolons. We also measured the petiole length, petiole dry mass, leaf area, leaf dry mass of the fourth and fifth youngest ramets of each cutting.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Benefits of SIR</title>
        <p>To quantify benefits of SIR we exposed the plants in the competition tray to a second, controlled herbivory attack (referred to as &#x201C;herbivory treatment&#x201D;). We released five fourth instar caterpillars on day 16 in the competition tray and then added two and three more on day 17 and 18, respectively, to achieve substantial levels of herbivore damage. The plants were harvested 19&#xA0;days after the start of the experiment. We quantified benefits of induced resistance by scoring herbivory damage in the induced and in the control plants. At the time of harvesting each ramet on the main stolon was classified according to the leaf area consumed. We visually estimated the damage and assigned each ramet a damage category ranging from 0 to 3. The values corresponded to the following amounts of damage: 0&#xA0;=&#xA0;no damage, 1&#xA0;=&#xA0;1&#x2013;33%, 2&#xA0;=&#xA0;33&#x2013;66% and 3&#xA0;=&#xA0;66&#x2013;100% of leaf area consumed. We also recorded the position of the damaged ramet on the stolon to investigate possible intra-clonal variation in the damage pattern according to ramet age. In addition to the degree of damage, we measured the dry mass of leaves, petioles, stolons and roots in induced and control plants.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Herbivore preference test</title>
        <p>One day before releasing the caterpillars (herbivory treatment) we performed two dual choice tests per competition tray to check whether plants assigned to the defense-induction treatment were systemically induced. For each competition tray we cut off two control and two induced ramets of a similar developmental stage (third-youngest fully expanded leaf). Each control ramet was paired with an induced one and placed together on a moist filter paper in a petri dish to perform a dual choice test. A fourth instar <italic>S. exigua</italic> caterpillar was placed in the middle and allowed to feed until more than 30% of one of the leaves was consumed or for 48&#xA0;h. By means of visual estimates the leaf with the largest area consumed was recorded for each choice test. In 78% of the cases more of the control leaf was consumed (sign test <italic>M</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;23, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001; <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;77) than the induced one, confirming that plants in the competition trays that had received local herbivore damage (defense induction treatment) were induced before the herbivory treatment started.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Statistical analysis</title>
        <p>Central competition trays were considered the units of replication in all statistical analyses. To avoid pseudo-replication and a consequent inflation of<italic> df</italic> (Hurlbert <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">1984</xref>), all traits measured on plants (cuttings) in the competition trays were pooled per treatment (by averaging the four control cuttings and the four defense-induced cuttings, respectively) prior to data analysis. Consequently, our experiment had 20 replicates for measuring costs and 20 replicates for assessing benefits. Competing plants cannot be considered independent from each other as, by definition, they change each other&#x2019;s environment, growth and development. To take this dependence into account we used a repeated measures design to analyze differences between competing plants that belonged to different treatment groups. Repeated measures analysis explicitly considers intrinsic relationships between treatment groups (Potvin et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">1990</xref>).</p>
        <sec id="Sec11">
          <title>Costs of SIR</title>
          <p>Repeated measures ANOVA was performed to test for costs of defense induction in number and length of the main and side stolons and number of ramets on the main and side stolons, relative biomass allocation to roots, stolons, petioles and leaves and petiole length, petiole dry mass, leaf area, leaf dry mass of the fourth and fifth youngest ramets. Defense induction (induced vs. control) was considered a within-subjects effect, and genotype was treated as a between-subjects effect. Absolute dry masses of roots, stolons, petioles and leaves were analyzed using two-way repeated measures ANOVA (within-subjects effect&#x2014;defense induction; between-subjects effects&#x2014;plant genotype and herbivory).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec12">
          <title>Benefits of SIR</title>
          <p>The amount of damage in the herbivory treatment was assessed with doubly repeated measures ANOVA using ramet age and defense induction as repeated factors and genotype as main effect. The analysis included a profile analysis (SAS procedure GLM; profile statement) to test for differences in the degree of damage between adjacent ramets on the stolons. To correct for differences in the developmental stage of different cuttings we used only the six youngest ramets of each cutting in the damage analysis. All analyses were conducted with SAS 9.1 (SAS Institute, Cary, N.C.).</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Costs of SIR</title>
        <p>Total dry mass did not differ between control and induced plants (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). However, defense induction caused a significant reduction in petiole dry mass. Additionally, defense induction resulted in a shift in biomass allocation to the different plant parts. Relative biomass allocation to leaves increased significantly after defense induction (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.01). The percentage of biomass allocated to roots, stolons and petioles did not significantly differ between control and induced plants. (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>)
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Repeated measures ANOVA for effects of genotype, herbivory and defense induction on roots, stolons, petioles, leaves and total dry mass</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Source</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>df</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Root</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Stolon</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Petioles</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Leaves</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Total</th></tr><tr><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="12">Between-subject effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genotype (Gen)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">981</td><td align="left">7.20***</td><td align="left">3,710</td><td align="left">4.12***</td><td align="left">3,741</td><td align="left">10.97***</td><td align="left">11,002</td><td align="left">10.85***</td><td align="left">60,377</td><td align="left">8.99***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Herbivory (Herb)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">28.1</td><td align="left">0.21</td><td align="left">78.6</td><td align="left">0.09</td><td align="left">1,646</td><td align="left">4.83*</td><td align="left">4,234</td><td align="left">4.18*</td><td align="left">11,926</td><td align="left">1.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Gen&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Herb</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">49.3</td><td align="left">0.36</td><td align="left">124</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left">105</td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">292</td><td align="left">0.29</td><td align="left">1,171</td><td align="left">0.17</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">136</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">899</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">342</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1,014</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">6,714</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12">Within-subject effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induction (Ind)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">79.8</td><td align="left">0.81</td><td align="left">574</td><td align="left">1.97</td><td align="left">416</td><td align="left">5.11*</td><td align="left">98.6</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">1,879</td><td align="left">0.99</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">53.9</td><td align="left">0.54</td><td align="left">83.1</td><td align="left">0.28</td><td align="left">50.7</td><td align="left">0.62</td><td align="left">367</td><td align="left">1.37</td><td align="left">1,054</td><td align="left">0.55</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Herb</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">106</td><td align="left">1.07</td><td align="left">57.1</td><td align="left">0.20</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left">160</td><td align="left">0.60</td><td align="left">1,143</td><td align="left">0.60</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Herb</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">139</td><td align="left">1.40</td><td align="left">542</td><td align="left">1.86</td><td align="left">159</td><td align="left">1.95</td><td align="left">265</td><td align="left">0.99</td><td align="left">3,525</td><td align="left">1.85</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">99.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">292</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">81.3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">268</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1,901</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*0.01&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05, ***<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001 </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Costs of systemic induced resistance (SIR). Repeated measures ANOVA for effects of genotype and defense induction on relative dry mass allocation to roots, stolons, petioles and leaves on plants without an herbivory treatment in the competition tray</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Source</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>df</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Roots</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Stolons</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Petioles</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Leaves</th></tr><tr><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="10">Between-subjects effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genotype (Gen)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">29.8</td><td align="left">6.61** </td><td align="left">496</td><td align="left">14.57***</td><td align="left">22.7</td><td align="left">3.54*</td><td align="left">35.7</td><td align="left">7.3**</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">127</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="10">Within-subject effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induction (Ind)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">12.0</td><td align="left">2.06</td><td align="left">0.04</td><td align="left">0.01</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">1.92</td><td align="left">35.8</td><td align="left">7.32*</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.38</td><td align="left">8.2</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.64</td><td align="left">10.9</td><td align="left">2.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*0.01&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05, **0.001&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01, ***<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001 </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Average (&#xB1;SE) absolute and relative dry mass allocated to roots, stolons, petioles and leaves of uninduced and induced plants in the absence of a subsequent herbivory treatment (<italic>Costs</italic>) and in the presence of a subsequent herbivory treatment (<italic>Benefits</italic>) in the competition tray</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left">Root (mg)</th><th align="left">Stolons (mg)</th><th align="left">Petioles (mg)</th><th align="left">Leaves (mg)</th><th align="left">Total (mg)</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Costs</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Uninduced</td><td align="left">15.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;3.0 (4.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.7%)</td><td align="left">103.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;6.7 (34.9&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;1.0%)</td><td align="left">72.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;4.8 (24.9&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.6%)</td><td align="left">107.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;8.3 (35.7&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.7%)</td><td align="left">298.9&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;21.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induced</td><td align="left">11.3&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;2.1 (3.4&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.6%)</td><td align="left">96.1&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;6.0 (34.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;1.0%)</td><td align="left">67.3&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;4.5 (24.2&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.5%)</td><td align="left">106.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;8.3 (37.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.6%)</td><td align="left">281.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;19.1</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Benefits</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Uninduced</td><td align="left">14.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;2.2 (5.1&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.8%)</td><td align="left">99.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;4.8 (37.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.8%)</td><td align="left">62.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;3.7 (23.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.8%)</td><td align="left">90.1&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;5.6 (33.5&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.8%)</td><td align="left">266.9&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;13.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induced</td><td align="left">14.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;3.7 (4.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.9%)</td><td align="left">95.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;6.1 (36.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;1.1%)</td><td align="left">59.0&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;4.5 (22.6&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.6%)</td><td align="left">95.1&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;7.6 (35.8&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;0.6%)</td><td align="left">264.7&#xA0;&#xB1;&#xA0;19.7</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p>The number of ramets produced on the main stolon was 7% lower in induced as compared to control plants (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; induction effect <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.003). The number and length of side stolons and the number of ramets formed on them did not change after defense induction.
<table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p> Costs of SIR. Repeated measures ANOVA for effects of genotype and defense induction on plant fitness and performance-related traits in the absence of herbivores</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Source</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>df</italic></th><th align="left" colspan="2">Ramet no. main stolon</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Length main stolon</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Ramet no. side stolons</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Length side stolons</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Side stolons number</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Fourth ramet petiole length</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Fourth ramet area</th></tr><tr><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="16">Between-subjects effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genotype (Gen)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">2.38</td><td align="left">3.41*</td><td align="left">23.5</td><td align="left">5.4***</td><td align="left">71.9</td><td align="left">6.72**</td><td align="left">30.8</td><td align="left">1.63</td><td align="left">16.0</td><td align="left">12.97***</td><td align="left">18.0</td><td align="left">14.93***</td><td align="left">8.57</td><td align="left">15.36***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">0.69</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">4.31</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">10.7</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">18.9</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.23</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">1.20</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.55</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="16">Within-subject effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induction (Ind)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1.80</td><td align="left">12.13**</td><td align="left">7.57</td><td align="left">2.45</td><td align="left">1.25</td><td align="left">0.25</td><td align="left">0.78</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.15</td><td align="left">0.31</td><td align="left">4.38</td><td align="left">5.22*</td><td align="left">0.10</td><td align="left">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">0.17</td><td align="left">1.19</td><td align="left">3.92</td><td align="left">1.27</td><td align="left">1.83</td><td align="left">0.37</td><td align="left">4.10</td><td align="left">1.22</td><td align="left">0.12</td><td align="left">0.24</td><td align="left">0.35</td><td align="left">0.42</td><td align="left">0.09</td><td align="left">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">0.14</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">3.08</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">4.95</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">3.37</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.51</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.84</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.46</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>*0.01&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05, **0.001&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.01, ***<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001 </p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>The fourth and fifth youngest ramets on the main stolon produced petioles 5% shorter in the induced plants (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; fourth ramet <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.03, fifth ramet <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.07). Leaf area, leaf dry mass and petiole dry mass measured on those ramets were not significantly affected by the induction treatment.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Benefits of SIR</title>
        <p>Defense induction had a very strong effect on the amount of damage inflicted by <italic>S. exigua</italic> larvae on the plants (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; induction effect <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The number of ramets that were partially or fully consumed during the herbivore attack was consistently higher in control than in induced plants. Most of the damaged ramets lost only a small part of their leaf area (1&#x2013;5%). This was consistent for both control and induced plants (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). In induced plants up to 44% of the ramets on the main stolon were not damaged, whereas in control plants only 22% of ramets on the main stolon were undamaged.
<table-wrap id="Tab5"><label>Table&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Benefits of SIR. Doubly repeated measures ANOVA for effects of genotype, defense induction and ramet age on leaf area loss due to herbivory</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Source</th><th align="left"><italic>df</italic></th><th align="left">MS</th><th align="left"><italic>F</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Between-subjects effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Genotype (Gen)</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">1,102</td><td align="left">2.39&#x2020;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">461</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="4">Within-subjects effects</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Induction (Ind)</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">6,847</td><td align="left">63.92***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">244</td><td align="left">2.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error (induction)</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">107</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Age</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">18,988</td><td align="left">133.0***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Age&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">630</td><td align="left">4.41***</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error (age)</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">142</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Age</td><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">125</td><td align="left">1.22</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Age&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Gen</td><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">172</td><td align="left">1.67&#x2020;</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Error (Ind&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;Age)</td><td align="left">75</td><td align="left">103</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x2020;&#xA0;0.1&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;0.05, ***<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Average damage (&#xB1;1 SE) inflicted on ramets of the main stolon (the 1st ramet being the youngest and the 6th being the oldest) of control and induced plants in the competition tray after carrying out a controlled herbivore attack (herbivory treatment). Damage categories: no damage (0), 1&#x2013;33% (1), 33&#x2013;66% (2), 66&#x2013;100% (3). The<italic> asterisks</italic> above the bars indicate the statistical significance of the result of a profile analysis (SAS procedure GLM; profile statement) to test for differences in the degree of damage between ramets of successive age classes. The amount of damage was significantly higher for control than for induced plants in all age classes. ***<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.001, <italic>ns</italic> not significant</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_792_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>The herbivory treatment significantly reduced the biomass of leaves and petioles (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>; <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.049 and <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.036, respectively; Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>) in both induced and uninduced plants. In the presence of herbivores, induced and uninduced plants had a comparable total biomass. However, induced plants showed a larger percentage of biomass in their leaves (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; repeated measures ANOVA; <italic>F</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;17.44 <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.0008), suggesting that the induced plants benefitted from increased relative biomass in those organs under attack.</p>
        <p>Ramet age, regardless of the induction state, had a very strong effect on herbivore preference (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; age effect <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001). Younger ramets, especially the first and second youngest ones, were heavily preferred over older ones (profile analysis; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The first ramet exhibited particularly severe damage in both induced and control plants (average leaf area consumed&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;65%; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>).</p>
        <p>Defense induction had a significant effect on leaf area loss due to herbivory in all ramet age classes (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). The degree to which systemic defense induction reduced herbivory damage was similar for ramets of all age classes (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; no age&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;induction effect). There was a marginally significant genotype effect on the feeding of the caterpillars (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab5" ref-type="table">5</xref>; genotype effect <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.09).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Our study provides empirical evidence of significant costs and benefits of SIR in a clonal plant network. In agreement with our hypotheses, induced and control plants showed clear differences in performance and fitness-related traits when grown in the absence and presence of herbivores. In environments without herbivores, induced plants produced fewer ramets, shorter petioles and exhibited a shift in biomass allocation patterns. In environments with herbivores, control plants suffered consistently higher degrees of leaf damage than induced plants. Even though defense induction resulted in changes in plant growth, and significantly affected the amount of damage caused by the herbivores, total plant biomass did not respond as expected under the adaptive plasticity hypothesis (Dudley and Schmitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1996</xref>; Schmitt et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">1999</xref>), as we could not find a significant induction&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;herbivory interaction effect. However, we propose that the differences observed in our study (e.g., reduced ramet production rates and shorter petioles in the cost experiment, decreased amount of leaf damage in the benefits experiment) are likely to translate into substantial differences in plant productivity, and hence biomass, in the longer term.</p>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Costs of SIR</title>
        <sec id="Sec18">
          <title>Biomass production and allocation</title>
          <p>Total plant biomass production did not change as a consequence of defense induction, implying that defense induction did not incur direct and immediate productivity costs. After induction, however, biomass allocation shifted significantly towards the leaves. We suggest that this allocation shift may enable plants to better cope with current and future herbivory by reducing resource allocation to those organs that are not currently impacted by herbivore damage. While potentially beneficial in the short term, this response might result in longer term indirect costs due to reduced performance under certain environmental conditions, such as drought, root herbivory and severe root competition. A similar shift in the biomass allocation pattern was observed in <italic>Lepidium virginicum</italic> plants after defense induction. Induced plants grown at a high density showed a reduction in root biomass and an increase in aboveground biomass (Agrawal <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">2005</xref>). In agreement with our findings, total biomass production was not significantly altered by defense induction in that study. A reduction in belowground biomass was also reported for induced wild parsnip plants. In this case, however, the aboveground biomass did not change significantly after defense induction (Zangerl et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1997</xref>). Further studies are necessary to assess the generality, functional significance (including costs and benefits) and mechanistic basis of changes in root&#x2013;shoot allocation in response to induced resistance to herbivory.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec19">
          <title>Reduction in developmental growth rate</title>
          <p>Defense induction negatively affected plant fitness by reducing the number of ramets produced. This delayed developmental growth rate was expressed as a reduction in the number of ramets on the main stolon produced during the experiment (7.4 ramets on the control and 7.0 on the induced plants). In the shorter run (i.e., time span of this experiment) this effect is unlikely to translate into biomass differences. In the longer run, however, subtle changes in the developmental growth rate are known to result in very major divergences in performance, structure and clonal fitness of stoloniferous plants (Birch and Hutchings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1992a</xref>; Birch and Hutchings <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">1992b</xref>; Huber and Stuefer <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">1997</xref>; Stuefer and Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1998</xref>).</p>
        </sec>
        <sec id="Sec20">
          <title>Reduction in petiole length</title>
          <p>Defense induction had significant negative effects on petiole lengths. This effect can have severe performance and fitness consequences for a stoloniferous plant like <italic>T. repens</italic>, which often grows in dense herbaceous canopies, and which relies on petiole elongation for shade avoidance (Huber <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1997</xref>). Petiole length largely determines the ability of stoloniferous plants to place their leaves higher up in the canopy (Huber and Wiggerman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1997</xref>; Weijsched&#xE9; et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2006</xref>). Even a small reduction in petiole length could have serious performance costs since differences in the relative position of leaves in herbaceous canopies are likely to be amplified by asymmetric competition for light (Weiner <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1990</xref>; Pierik et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2003</xref>). Defense induction may also cause physiological trade-offs which impede the simultaneous expression of plasticity to herbivores and to shading by competitors (Cipollini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2004</xref>). A decrease in petiole length as a result of defense induction can hence, compromise the competitive ability of plants and result in an enhanced risk of induced plants being over-shaded by neighbors. A recent study by Kurashige and Agrawal (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">2005</xref>) supports this notion by showing that <italic>Chenopodium album</italic> plants, which had previously been damaged by herbivores, were able to elongate stems to a similar proportional degree as undamaged plants when grown in competition for light. However, the damaged plants were smaller due to the expression of induced resistance, thereby incurring potential opportunity costs due to asymmetric competition.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec21">
        <title>Benefits of SIR</title>
        <sec id="Sec22">
          <title>Reduced damage</title>
          <p>Our results provide direct evidence for short-term benefits of having an early-warning system in clonal plant networks. In the presence of herbivores, induced plants suffered considerably less damage than control plants. As many as 50% fewer ramets were attacked in induced plants as compared to controls. Localized damage (defense-induction treatment) resulted in a greater degree of protection against herbivores for ramets further along that main stolon and its side branches. The reduced damage did not translate into a significant effect of defense induction on biomass production, due to the fact that the youngest, usually not fully developed leaves were heavily preferred by the herbivores. The biomass loss due to young leaf consumption is very likely to strongly underestimate the negative effects of herbivory and defense induction on future plant growth and performance. Coleman and Leonard (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1995</xref>) demonstrated how leaf area consumption, and its consequences for plant performance, can be severely underestimated if the developmental stage of leaves is not taken into account. They showed that a certain amount of damage inflicted on young expanding <italic>Nicotiana tabaccum</italic> leaves is more detrimental than the same amount received by mature, fully developed leaves. As leaf tissue expanded, the area of the holes increased almost fourfold and the final area of the leaf decreased by approximately 40%. In addition, they observed a 35% decrease in the number and mass of fruits on the plants that received the damage to expanding young tissues. Therefore, an initially small amount of damage inflicted on young developing leaves may have dramatic consequences for plant performance and fitness over time. Similarly, the differences found in our experiment can be expected to result in considerable performance differences between induced and uninduced plants as increased damage and loss of young leaves in uninduced plants will compromise plant productivity by reducing the number of future source ramets.</p>
          <p>Our results show that ramet age largely determines herbivore damage. The first and second ramets were heavily attacked as compared to the rest. This damage, although still large, was significantly reduced in induced plants. The reduction in leaf area loss in induced young ramets likely increases their chance of survival and establishment. Young ramets in clonal plants constitute the most valuable tissue since they represent the future reproductive potential of the plant (Huber and During <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2000</xref>) and their protection is critical since they are responsible for a high proportion of the future biomass production (Beinhart <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1963</xref>). We present evidence supporting the hypothesis that an early-warning system after herbivory in a clonal plant network grants vulnerable young offspring ramets with parental support (Stuefer et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2004</xref>) that non-clonal plants are unable to confer their offspring at the moment of the attack (but see Agrawal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1999</xref>).</p>
          <p>Our study provides evidence for significant costs and benefits of systemic defense induction in <italic>T. repens</italic>. The experimental approach used in this study, however, does not allow for balancing costs and benefits in terms of plant fitness and overall plant performance, because both positive and negative effects of induction reported here, although likely to have significant longer-term effects on productivity and ultimately on fitness, did not have an effect on biomass at the short time scale during which the experiment took place. While our results indicate clear advantages and disadvantages of network induction in the subsequent presence and absence of herbivores, respectively, an accurate and reliable quantification of the cost&#x2013;benefit ratio should make use of long-term experiments.</p>
          <p>In conclusion, the present study shows that in the short term, the activation of early-warning responses in clonal plant networks has both costs and benefits. In the absence of herbivores, the performance of the induced phenotype was compromised as compared to the uninduced phenotype in terms of potential competitive ability. In the presence of herbivores, the induced phenotype was favored by suffering considerably less herbivore damage suggesting potential advantages for the phenotype correctly matching its environment. Whether this represents an adaptive value of the induced responses remains to be demonstrated in longer-term studies where the initial small changes observed in our study can be measured directly in terms of fitness. The long-term balance of costs and benefits of induced resistance in clonal plant networks is likely to be strongly context dependent and a function of the match between spatio-temporal aspects of systemic defense expression and the feeding behavior of herbivores.</p>
        </sec>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank P. Walker, C. Jansen, T. van M&#xF6;lken, H. de Caluwe, X. Chen, J. Weijsched&#xE9;, A. Smit-Tiekstra, P. Rodersman and T. Koubek for practical assistance, and H. de Kroon, T. van M&#xF6;lken, and N. van Dam for useful comments on a previous version of this manuscript. This study was funded by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO, VIDI fellowship to J.&#xA0;F.&#xA0;S.). V.&#xA0;L. was funded by the Czech Science Foundation, grant no. 206/03/H034.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Strauss</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stout</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Costs of induced responses and tolerance to herbivory in male and female fitness components of wild radish</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>1093</fpage>
          <lpage>1104</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2640814</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal AA, Strauss SY, Stout MJ (1999) Costs of induced responses and tolerance to herbivory in male and female fitness components of wild radish. Evolution 53:1093&#x2013;1104 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Benefits and costs of induced plant defense for <italic>Lepidium virginicum</italic> (Brassicaceae)</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <fpage>1804</fpage>
          <lpage>1813</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal AA (2000) Benefits and costs of induced plant defense for Lepidium virginicum (Brassicaceae). Ecology 81:1804&#x2013;1813 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Future directions in the study of induced plant responses to herbivory</article-title>
          <source>Entomol Exp Appl</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>97</fpage>
          <lpage>105</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1570-7458.2005.00294.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Agrawal AA (2005) Future directions in the study of induced plant responses to herbivory. Entomol Exp Appl 115:97&#x2013;105 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alpert</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nutrient sharing in natural clonal fragments of <italic>Fragaria chiloensis</italic></article-title>
          <source>J Ecol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>395</fpage>
          <lpage>406</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2261201</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Alpert P (1996) Nutrient sharing in natural clonal fragments of Fragaria chiloensis. J Ecol 84:395&#x2013;406 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Alpert</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stuefer</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenendael</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Division of labour in clonal plants</article-title>
          <source>The ecology and evolution of clonal plants</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-loc>The Netherlands</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Backhuys</publisher-name>
          <fpage>137</fpage>
          <lpage>154</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Alpert P, Stuefer JF (1997) Division of labour in clonal plants. In: de Kroon H, van Groenendael J (eds) The ecology and evolution of clonal plants. Backhuys, The Netherlands, pp 137&#x2013;154 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Jasmonate-induced responses are costly but benefit plants under attack in native populations</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>95</volume>
          <fpage>8113</fpage>
          <lpage>8118</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.95.14.8113</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Baldwin IT (1998) Jasmonate-induced responses are costly but benefit plants under attack in native populations. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 95:8113&#x2013;8118 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9653149</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Beinhart</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of environment on meristematic development, leaf area, and growth of white clover</article-title>
          <source>Crop Sci</source>
          <year>1963</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Beinhart G (1963) Effects of environment on meristematic development, leaf area, and growth of white clover. Crop Sci 3:209&#x2013;213 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergelson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effects of genotype and the environment on costs of resistance in lettuce</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>143</volume>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>359</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285607</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bergelson J (1994) The effects of genotype and the environment on costs of resistance in lettuce. Am Nat 143:349&#x2013;359 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bergelson</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Purrington</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Surveying patterns in the cost of resistance in plants</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>148</volume>
          <fpage>536</fpage>
          <lpage>558</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285938</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bergelson J, Purrington CB (1996) Surveying patterns in the cost of resistance in plants. Am Nat 148:536&#x2013;558 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Biere</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marak</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Damme</surname>
              <given-names>JMM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Plant chemical defense against herbivores and pathogens: generalized defense or trade-offs?</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>140</volume>
          <fpage>430</fpage>
          <lpage>441</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-004-1603-6</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Biere A, Marak HB, van Damme JMM (2004) Plant chemical defense against herbivores and pathogens: generalized defense or trade-offs? Oecologia 140:430&#x2013;441 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15146326</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Birch</surname>
              <given-names>CPD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutchings</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stolon growth and branching in <italic>Glechoma hederacea</italic> L.&#x2014;an application of a plastochron index</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>122</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>545</fpage>
          <lpage>551</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.1992.tb00084.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Birch CPD, Hutchings MJ (1992a) Stolon growth and branching in Glechoma hederacea L.&#x2014;an application of a plastochron index. New Phytol 122(3):545&#x2013;551 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Birch</surname>
              <given-names>CPD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hutchings</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Analysis of ramet development in the stoloniferous herb <italic>Glechoma heredacea</italic> using a plastochron index</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>63</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>387</fpage>
          <lpage>394</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3544964</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Birch CPD, Hutchings MJ (1992b) Analysis of ramet development in the stoloniferous herb Glechoma heredacea using a plastochron index. Oikos 63(3):387&#x2013;394 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cipollini</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Stretching the limits of plasticity: can a plant defend against both competitors and herbivores?</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>85</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>28</fpage>
          <lpage>37</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/02-0615</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cipollini D (2004) Stretching the limits of plasticity: can a plant defend against both competitors and herbivores? Ecology 85(1):28&#x2013;37 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Coleman</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leonard</surname>
              <given-names>AS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Why it matters where on a leaf a folivore feeds</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <fpage>324</fpage>
          <lpage>328</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00328818</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Coleman JS, Leonard AS (1995) Why it matters where on a leaf a folivore feeds. Oecologia 101:324&#x2013;328 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dudley</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmitt</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Testing the adaptive plasticity hypothesis: density-dependent selection on manipulated stem length in <italic>Impatiens capensis</italic></article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>445</fpage>
          <lpage>465</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285860</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Dudley SA, Schmitt J (1996) Testing the adaptive plasticity hypothesis: density-dependent selection on manipulated stem length in Impatiens capensis. Am Nat 147:445&#x2013;465 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Elle</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dam</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hare</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cost of glandular trichomes, a &#x201C;resistance&#x201D; character in <italic>Datura wrightii</italic> Regel (Solanaceae)</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>22</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2640917</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Elle E, Van Dam NM, Hare JD (1999) Cost of glandular trichomes, a &#x201C;resistance&#x201D; character in Datura wrightii Regel (Solanaceae). Evolution 53:22&#x2013;35 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stuefer</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Members only: induced systemic resistance to herbivory in a clonal plant network</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>147</volume>
          <fpage>461</fpage>
          <lpage>468</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-005-0293-z</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">G&#xF3;mez S, Stuefer JF (2006) Members only: induced systemic resistance to herbivory in a clonal plant network. Oecologia 147:461&#x2013;468 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16333642</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Heil</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fitness costs of induced resistance: emerging experimental support for a slippery concept</article-title>
          <source>Trends Plant Sci</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>61</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1360-1385(01)02186-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Heil M, Baldwin IT (2002) Fitness costs of induced resistance: emerging experimental support for a slippery concept. Trends Plant Sci 7:61&#x2013;67 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11832276</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Herms</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mattson</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The dilemma of plants&#x2014;to grow or defend</article-title>
          <source>Q Rev Biol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>283</fpage>
          <lpage>335</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/417659</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Herms DA, Mattson WJ (1992) The dilemma of plants&#x2014;to grow or defend. Q Rev Biol 67:283&#x2013;335 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Architectural plasticity of stoloniferous and erect herbs in response to light climate</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-loc>Utrecht, The Netherlands</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Utrecht University</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Huber H (1997) Architectural plasticity of stoloniferous and erect herbs in response to light climate. Utrecht University, Utrecht, The Netherlands </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>During</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>No long-term costs of meristem allocation to flowering in stoloniferous <italic>Trifolium</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>731</fpage>
          <lpage>748</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1011643904616</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Huber H, During HJ (2000) No long-term costs of meristem allocation to flowering in stoloniferous Trifolium species. Evol Ecol 14:731&#x2013;748 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stuefer</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Shade-induced changes in the branching pattern of a stoloniferous herb: functional response or allometric effect?</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>478</fpage>
          <lpage>486</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050183</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Huber H, Stuefer JF (1997) Shade-induced changes in the branching pattern of a stoloniferous herb: functional response or allometric effect? Oecologia 110:478&#x2013;486 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wiggerman</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Shade avoidance in the clonal herb <italic>Trifolium fragiferum</italic>: a field study with experimentally manipulated vegetation height</article-title>
          <source>Plant Ecol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>53</fpage>
          <lpage>62</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1009702611270</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Huber H, Wiggerman L (1997) Shade avoidance in the clonal herb Trifolium fragiferum: a field study with experimentally manipulated vegetation height. Plant Ecol 130:53&#x2013;62 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hurlbert</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pseudoreplication and the design of ecological field experiments</article-title>
          <source>Ecol Monogr</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>187</fpage>
          <lpage>211</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1942661</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hurlbert SH (1984) Pseudoreplication and the design of ecological field experiments. Ecol Monogr 54:187&#x2013;211 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kurashige</surname>
              <given-names>NS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Agrawal</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phenotypic plasticity to light competition and herbivory in <italic>Chenopodium album</italic> (Chenopodiaceae)</article-title>
          <source>Am J Bot</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>21</fpage>
          <lpage>26</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kurashige NS, Agrawal AA (2005) Phenotypic plasticity to light competition and herbivory in Chenopodium album (Chenopodiaceae). Am J Bot 92:21&#x2013;26 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marshall</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Groenendael</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Source&#x2013;sink relations of interconnected ramets</article-title>
          <source>Clonal growth in plants: regulation and function</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <publisher-loc>The Hague</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>SPB</publisher-name>
          <fpage>23</fpage>
          <lpage>41</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Marshall C (1990) Source&#x2013;sink relations of interconnected ramets. In: van Groenendael J, de Kroon H (eds) Clonal growth in plants: regulation and function. SPB, The Hague, pp 23&#x2013;41 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierik</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Visser</surname>
              <given-names>EJW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voesenek</surname>
              <given-names>LACJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ethylene is required in tobacco to successfully compete with proximate neighbours</article-title>
          <source>Plant Cell Environ</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>1229</fpage>
          <lpage>1234</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-3040.2003.01045.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pierik R, Visser EJW, De Kroon H, Voesenek LACJ (2003) Ethylene is required in tobacco to successfully compete with proximate neighbours. Plant Cell Environ 26:1229&#x2013;1234 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pitelka</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashmun</surname>
              <given-names>JW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Jackson</surname>
              <given-names>JBC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Physiology and integration of ramets in clonal plants</article-title>
          <source>Population biology and evolution of clonal organisms</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <publisher-loc>New Haven, Conn.</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Yale University Press</publisher-name>
          <fpage>399</fpage>
          <lpage>435</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pitelka LF, Ashmun JW (1985) Physiology and integration of ramets in clonal plants. In: Jackson JBC (ed) Population biology and evolution of clonal organisms. Yale University Press, New Haven, Conn., pp 399&#x2013;435 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Potvin</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lechowicz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tardif</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The statistical analysis of ecophysiological response curves obtained from experiments involving repeated measures</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>71</volume>
          <fpage>1389</fpage>
          <lpage>1400</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1938276</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Potvin CM, Lechowicz J, Tardif S (1990) The statistical analysis of ecophysiological response curves obtained from experiments involving repeated measures. Ecology 71:1389&#x2013;1400 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sagers</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coley</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Benefits and costs of defense in a neotropical shrub</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>76</volume>
          <fpage>1835</fpage>
          <lpage>1843</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1940715</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sagers CL, Coley PD (1995) Benefits and costs of defense in a neotropical shrub. Ecology 76:1835&#x2013;1843 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmitt</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dudley</surname>
              <given-names>SA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pigliucci</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Manipulative approaches to testing adaptive plasticity: phytochrome-mediated shade-avoidance</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>154</volume>
          <fpage>43</fpage>
          <lpage>54</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/303282</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmitt J, Dudley SA, Pigliucci M (1999) Manipulative approaches to testing adaptive plasticity: phytochrome-mediated shade-avoidance. Am Nat 154:43&#x2013;54 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Siemens</surname>
              <given-names>DH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lischke</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Maggiulli</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schurch</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Roy</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cost of resistance and tolerance under competition: the defense-stress benefit hypothesis</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>263</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1025517229934</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Siemens DH, Lischke H, Maggiulli N, Schurch S, Roy BA (2003) Cost of resistance and tolerance under competition: the defense-stress benefit hypothesis. Evol Ecol 17:247&#x2013;263 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Strauss</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rudgers</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lau</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Irwin</surname>
              <given-names>RE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Direct and ecological costs of resistance to herbivory</article-title>
          <source>Trends Ecol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>278</fpage>
          <lpage>285</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0169-5347(02)02483-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Strauss SY, Rudgers JA, Lau JA, Irwin RE (2002) Direct and ecological costs of resistance to herbivory. Trends Ecol 17:278&#x2013;285 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stuefer</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>G&#xF3;mez</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;lken</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clonal integration beyond resource sharing: implications for defence signalling and disease transmission in clonal plant networks</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>647</fpage>
          <lpage>667</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s10682-004-5148-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stuefer JF, G&#xF3;mez S, Van M&#xF6;lken T (2004) Clonal integration beyond resource sharing: implications for defence signalling and disease transmission in clonal plant networks. Evol Ecol 18:647&#x2013;667 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stuefer</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential effects of light quantity and spectral light quality on growth, morphology and development of two stoloniferous <italic>Potentilla</italic> species</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050624</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stuefer JF, Huber H (1998) Differential effects of light quantity and spectral light quality on growth, morphology and development of two stoloniferous Potentilla species. Oecologia 117:1&#x2013;8 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dam</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Costs of jasmonate-induced responses in plants competing for limited resources</article-title>
          <source>Ecol Lett</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>30</fpage>
          <lpage>33</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1461-0248.1998.00010.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Van Dam NM, Baldwin IT (1998) Costs of jasmonate-induced responses in plants competing for limited resources. Ecol Lett 1:30&#x2013;33 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dam</surname>
              <given-names>NM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Baldwin</surname>
              <given-names>IT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Competition mediates costs of jasmonate-induced defences, nitrogen acquisition and transgenerational plasticity in <italic>Nicotiana attenuata</italic></article-title>
          <source>Funct Ecol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>406</fpage>
          <lpage>415</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2435.2001.00533.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Van Dam NM, Baldwin IT (2001) Competition mediates costs of jasmonate-induced defences, nitrogen acquisition and transgenerational plasticity in Nicotiana attenuata. Funct Ecol 15:406&#x2013;415 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiner</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Asymmetric competition in plant populations</article-title>
          <source>Trends Ecol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>360</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0169-5347(90)90095-U</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Weiner J (1990) Asymmetric competition in plant populations. Trends Ecol 5:360&#x2013;364 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weijsched&#xE9;</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Martinkova</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kroon</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huber</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Shade avoidance in <italic>Trifolium</italic><italic>repens</italic>: costs and benefits of plasticity in petiole length and leaf size</article-title>
          <source>New Phytol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>172</volume>
          <fpage>655</fpage>
          <lpage>666</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-8137.2006.01885.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Weijsched&#xE9; J, Martinkova J, De Kroon H, Huber H (2006) Shade avoidance in Trifoliumrepens: costs and benefits of plasticity in petiole length and leaf size. New Phytol 172:655&#x2013;666 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17096792</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zangerl</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Arntz</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Berenbaum</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Physiological price of an induced chemical defense: photosynthesis, respiration, biosynthesis, and growth</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>109</volume>
          <fpage>433</fpage>
          <lpage>441</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s004420050103</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zangerl AR, Arntz AM, Berenbaum MR (1997) Physiological price of an induced chemical defense: photosynthesis, respiration, biosynthesis, and growth. Oecologia 109:433&#x2013;441 </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>