<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Oecologia</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Oecologia</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0029-8549</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-1939</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18196279</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2270366</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">952</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00442-007-0952-3</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Population Ecology - Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Scaling of offspring number and mass to plant and animal size: model and meta-analysis</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hendriks</surname>
            <given-names>A. Jan</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-24-3652932</phone>
            <email>a.j.hendriks@science.ru.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Mulder</surname>
            <given-names>Christian</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>christian.mulder@rivm.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Environmental Science, Radboud University Nijmegen, P.O. Box 9010, 6500 GL Nijmegen, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Laboratory for Ecological Risk Assessment, National Institute for Public Health and the Environment, P.O. Box 1, 3720 BA Bilthoven, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <author-notes>
        <fn fn-type="com">
          <p>Communicated by Bernhard Schmid.</p>
        </fn>
      </author-notes>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>15</day>
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>4</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>155</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>705</fpage>
      <lpage>716</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>15</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>12</day>
          <month>12</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The scaling of reproductive parameters to body size is important for understanding ecological and evolutionary patterns. Here, we derived allometric relationships for the number and mass of seeds, eggs and neonates from an existing model on population production. In a separate meta-analysis, we collected 79 empirical regressions on offspring mass and number covering different taxa and various habitats. The literature review served as a validation of the model, whereas, vice versa, consistency of isolated regressions with each other and related ecological quantities was checked with the model. The total offspring mass delivered in a reproductive event scaled to adult size with slopes in the range of about 3/4 to 1. Exponents for individual seed, egg and neonate mass varied around 1/2 for most heterotherms and between 3/4 and 1 for most homeotherms. The scaling of the progeny number released in a sowing, clutch or litter was opposite to that of their size. The linear regressions fitted into a triangular envelope where maximum offspring mass is limited by the size of the adult. Minimum seed and egg size scaled with weight exponents of approximately 0 up to 1/4. These patterns can be explained by the influence of parents on the fate of their offspring, covering the continuum of<italic> r</italic>-strategists (pelagic&#x2013;aquatic, arial, most invertebrates, heterotherms) and<italic> K</italic>-strategists (littoral&#x2013;terrestrial, some invertebrates, homeotherms).</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Macroecology</kwd>
        <kwd>Reproduction</kwd>
        <kwd>Allometric scaling</kwd>
        <kwd>Body size</kwd>
        <kwd>Fecundity</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Scaling of processes and patterns to body size has fascinated biologists for centuries (e.g., Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>; Damuth <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2007</xref>). Plant and animal characteristics have been correlated to organisms&#x2019; body mass (<italic>m</italic>) by simple scaling relationships of the form <italic>a</italic>&#xB7;<italic>m</italic><sup>b</sup> or, if log transformed, log(<italic>a</italic>)&#xA0;+&#xA0;<italic>b</italic>&#xA0;log(<italic>m</italic>). Properties include various reproductive parameters, such as the mass and number of the offspring, important for understanding life history strategies of species. The scaling of reproduction reflects several important trade-offs, e.g., investment of energy in somatic versus gonadic growth, in continuous or intermittent release and in many small or a few large offspring.</p>
      <p>Studies have derived empirical regressions for offspring mass and number within one taxon (see review by Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>). In addition, several partly contradictive physical, biochemical and ecological constraints related to parental energy investment, have been hypothesized to be responsible for the observed patterns (May <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">1978</xref>; Gordon <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">1989</xref>; Reiss <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR58">1989</xref>; Charnov and Downhower <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">1995</xref>; Hendry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2001</xref>; Charnov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2001</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2002</xref>; Aarssen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2005</xref>). Although the trade-offs in reproductive investment reflect universal dilemmas that every species has to face, most work so far has covered either several progeny characteristics within a single species group or a single offspring parameter within at most two taxa (Moles et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">2005</xref>a; Grubb et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2005</xref>).</p>
      <p>In the present paper, we will focus on the relationship of offspring mass and number to adult weight for miscellaneous groups of species. The aim is to obtain a set of straightforward equations that are coherent with allometric theory and underpinned by empirical regressions available in literature. To this end, we will first derive body-size functions for the mass and number of offspring delivered in a reproductive event which comply with allometric macroecology (e.g., West et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR66">1997</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>). Next, we will compare the acquired relationships to independent empirical regressions collected in a meta-analysis. Separating model development and testing allows for a comparison of theoretical and empirical evidence, reducing weaknesses of both. In this approach, model predictions of, e.g., offspring mass, are underpinned by independent measurements. Likewise, isolated empirical regressions for this reproductive parameter are checked for consistency with body-size dependence of related ecological factors, such as population production or survival.</p>
      <p>In our analysis, we will seek a balance between model transparency and accuracy, needed for underpinning assumed mechanisms and identifying exceptions. The equations are not intended to cover detailed or speculative differences, observed in empirical regressions for sufficient taxa. In our interpretation, we will follow the classical distinction between <italic>r</italic>-strategists and<italic> K</italic>-strategists (MacArthur and Wilson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1967</xref>; Pianka <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR54">1970</xref>) as well as more recent applications thereof (Winemiller and Rose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">1992</xref>; McCann and Shuter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>; Cox and Moore <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">2005</xref>). However, it should be emphasized that the traditional classification of many small offspring versus few large offspring as used in the present paper is no more than a convenient way to structure the discussion.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Regression collection and treatment</title>
        <p>Allometric regressions derived from data before 1983 were collected from an extensive review (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>). Papers published afterwards were obtained by screening books and by an electronic literature search in Web of Science in 2006. All body-size correlations acquired for the meta-analysis were checked in the original papers. Collection and treatment of data by the authors was assumed to be adequate. Where multiple types of regressions were reported, we took the least-squares equations, to increase compatibility with the other studies. If regression characteristics were not given or suspected to be wrong, we derived them from the original data or digitized graphs.</p>
        <p>To allow for comparison, all values were converted to fresh biomass, using dry&#x2013;wet weight fractions. A database containing dry matter fractions of 110 species, collected by the present authors for various purposes, yielded averages (with 95% confidence intervals) of 20% (18&#x2013;22%) for herbs, 22% (19&#x2013;25%) for invertebrates, 25% (18&#x2013;32%) for cold-blooded vertebrates and 30% (21&#x2013;39%) for warm-blooded vertebrates. In addition, the literature reports means of 53% for wood, 15&#x2013;21% for fruit, 87% for seeds, 23 for insects, 19% for marine invertebrates, 25% for fish and 29% for birds and mammals (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>; Suzuki <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR64">1999</xref>). Although the samples may be somewhat biased towards particular taxa, average levels do not deviate substantially. In the present analysis, we therefore used dry&#x2013;wet weight fractions of 20% for fruits, forbs, herbs and invertebrates, of 25% for cold-blooded vertebrates, of 30% for warm-blooded vertebrates, of 40% for shrubs and trees (wood and leaves together) and of 80% for seeds. Differences between species around these values have, on average, a negligible influence on the intercept of the regressions. Even more apparent, conversion does not affect the slope of the allometric relationships. Seeds mass was multiplied by 80/20%&#xA0;=&#xA0;4 to arrive at the fresh weight of sprouts with a water content that is comparable to that of eggs and neonates. Since total plant weight is not used as the independent variable for vegetation regressions, we took the closest alternatives, being the above-ground or stem mass. In one study on insects, animal size was expressed on a length basis instead of a weight basis (Berrigan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>). For these regressions, length (m) was converted to weight (kg) as mass&#xA0;=&#xA0;1/15<sup>2</sup>&#x3C0;&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>3</sup>&#xA0;length<sup>3</sup>, assuming that the total size equals 1.5 times the elythra length and twice the abdomen length.</p>
        <p>Rate constants for reproduction of plants were reported as annual standing reproductive mass delivered by all plants, including both reproducing and non-reproducing individuals. We assumed that the seed and fruit mass are renewed each year. For animals, total clutch mass reflected the total reproductive mass released in an event or present in ovaries, sometimes calculated in the original studies as a product of the total number of eggs (neonates) in a clutch (litter), the number of eggs per clutch (neonates per litter) and the egg (neonate) weight.</p>
        <p>To allow for comparison between plants, invertebrates, cold-blooded vertebrates and warm-blooded vertebrates, we calculated the arithmetic average of all slopes (<italic>b</italic>) reported for each taxonomic group. To correct for differences in the amount of information included in the regressions, we also computed an average weighted by the number of data. For instance, the weighted average of a regression with <italic>b</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.5 and <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;10 and another with <italic>b</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.3 and <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;20 was calculated to be 0.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10/30&#xA0;+&#xA0;0.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;20/30&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.37. As we are interested in both the absence and presence of links to organism mass, weak and insignificant correlations were included in the analysis as well. Where used, however, they will be explicitly mentioned in the text.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Model development</title>
        <p>The relationship of offspring mass and size to adult weight can also be derived theoretically from previous modeling efforts (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). The starting point in this model is production because coefficients and slopes of allometric regressions for this parameter differ only slightly for various groups of species. The rate constant for population turnover (production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub>), measured as the production/biomass ratio (<italic>P</italic>/<italic>B</italic>) (kg&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) is related to adult mass (<italic>m</italic>) as: <disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ k_{{\text{p}}} = q_{{\text{T}}} \cdot \gamma _{{\text{p}}} \cdot m^{{ - \kappa }} . $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The exponent (<italic>&#x3BA;</italic>) was close to 1/4 for a wide range of cold-blooded species but tended to be somewhat higher for homeotherms (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). The coefficient (<italic>&#x3B3;</italic><sub>p</sub>) represents the intercept at the standard temperature of 20&#xB0;C and has a universal value of 7.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4&#xA0;</sup>kg<sup>&#x3BA;</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> for all species (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). Following biochemical reaction kinetics, the intercept increases by a factor of <italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub> as a function of temperature (Gillooly et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">2001</xref>). Production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> by warm-blooded species with a body temperature of 37&#xB0; is <italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;3.5 times higher than that of equally sized cold-blooded species at 20&#xB0;C (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>).</p>
        <p>Production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> is allocated to somatic and gonadic growth. We will consider the rate constant for reproduction (reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub>) to be a fraction (<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>) of total production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> according to: <disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ \begin{aligned}{} k_{{{\text{pr}}}} = &amp; p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot k_{{\text{p}}} \\ = &amp; p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot q_{{\text{T}}} \cdot \gamma _{{\text{p}}} \cdot m^{{ - \kappa }} . \\ \end{aligned} $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>In Spermatophyta, 7% of the total dry weight production is diverted to reproduction via seeds (Niklas and Enquist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>). After correction to a dry&#x2013;wet weight fraction of 20% as described in the methods section, the reproductive fraction (<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>) equals 28% (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In animals, <italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub> varies between 0 for juveniles and 1 for adults without somatic growth. Filling in the slope and the intercepts, yields the reproduction rate constant as a function of<italic> m</italic> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Main factors used in the equations</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Symbol</th><th align="left">Description</th><th align="left">Unit</th><th align="left">Value<sup>a</sup>, source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left"><italic>&#x3B3;</italic><sub>p</sub></td><td align="left">Scaling coefficients for production</td><td align="left">kg<sup>&#x3BA;</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td align="left">7.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup> (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub>, <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub></td><td align="left">Rate constants for production and reproduction</td><td align="left">day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td align="left">Equation <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>&#x3BA;</italic></td><td align="left">Scaling exponent</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"><sup>p,c,w</sup>1/4, <sup>w</sup>1/3 (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>m</italic></td><td align="left">Adult mass</td><td align="left">kg</td><td align="left">Variable</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub></td><td align="left">Total reproductive mass in a batch</td><td align="left">kg</td><td align="left">Equation <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub></td><td align="left">Seed, egg or neonate mass</td><td align="left">kg</td><td align="left">min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)&#xA0;=&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>, <sup>i</sup>10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>, <sup>p,acv</sup>10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup>, <sup>tcv</sup>10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>&#x2026; m<sub>r</sub>/3</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub></td><td align="left">Fraction inter-reproductive period of average life time</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left">0.2</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub></td><td align="left">Fraction of production directed to reproduction</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"><sup>p</sup>0.28 (Niklas and Enquist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>), <sup>i,v</sup>1</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="left">Fecundity, number of offspring released in a reproductive event</td><td align="left">no. individual<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td align="left">Equation <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">6</xref></td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>q</italic><sub>T</sub></td><td align="left">Temperature quotient</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"><sup>p,c</sup>1, <sup>w</sup>3.5 (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left"><italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub></td><td align="left">Inter-reproductive period</td><td align="left">day</td><td align="left">Equation <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p><sup>a</sup>Superscripts:<italic> p</italic> plants,<italic> c</italic> cold-blooded,<italic> w</italic> warm-blooded,<italic> i</italic> invertebrates<italic>, v</italic> vertebrates<italic>, a</italic> aquatic<italic>, t</italic> terrestrial</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Reproduction rate constants (<italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub>) (kg&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) decrease with adult mass (<italic>m</italic>) (kg) to the power of about 1/4&#x2013;1/3. Model estimations (<italic>thick lines with letter</italic>) as well as empirical regressions (<italic>thin lines</italic>) for vascular plants (<italic>A</italic>, <italic>green dotted</italic>), invertebrates (<italic>B</italic>, <italic>yellow dashed-dotted</italic>), cold-blooded vertebrates (<italic>C</italic>, <italic>blue dashed</italic>) and warm-blooded vertebrates (<italic>D</italic>, <italic>red solid</italic>), as listed in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>. d<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> Day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_952_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>Usually seeds, eggs and neonates are not delivered continuously but released in discrete batches, i.e., sowings, clutches and litters. The total offspring mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>) accumulated in a period between two successive reproductive events (<italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub>) equals: <disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ m_{{\text{r}}} = p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot k_{{\text{p}}} \cdot m \cdot \tau _{{\text{r}}} . $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The inter-reproductive interval (<italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub>) might be related to the organisms&#x2019; metabolism and to environmental conditions. Initially, we did not find empirical regressions that link <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> to organism size. However, many other biological time parameters, including gestation and weaning time of homeotherms, scale to <italic>m</italic> with an exponent of <italic>&#x3BA;</italic> (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>). For an average mammal, the age at birth, weaning off and average death is at about 2, 3, 50% of the total period from conception to death, respectively (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>). <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub>, covering at least gestation and weaning (2&#xA0;+&#xA0;3%), thus equals at least (2&#xA0;+&#xA0;3%)/50%&#xA0;=&#xA0;10% of the average lifetime <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>, i.e., <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>&#xB7;<italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>&#xA0;&gt;&#xA0;10%&#xB7;<italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>. To allow for additional time to recover and mate we set the inter-reproductive period at a fraction (<italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>)&#xA0;=&#xA0;20% of the average lifetime <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>. This lemma is indirectly demonstrated by one long-term study on metabolism, reproductivity and average lifetime (<italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>) of earthworms (Mulder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">2007</xref>). In fact, although no evidence of a correlation between <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> and the offspring was found, <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub> and <italic>m</italic> were strongly correlated. Following a more general theory, <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub> can indeed be defined here as the mean residence period in the population and can thus be replaced by 1/<italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> (Odum <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR50">1983</xref>). In this way, <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> can now be assumed to equal: <disp-formula id="Equ4"><label>4</label><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ \tau _{{\text{r}}} = p_{{{\text{rl}}}} \cdot \tau _{{\text{l}}} = \frac{{p_{{{\text{rl}}}} }} {{k_{{\text{p}}} }}. $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Filling in the parameter values for mammals yields <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>l</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.3/(3.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;7.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>&#xA0;m<sup>&#x2212;1/4</sup>)&#xA0;=&#xA0;114&#xA0;m<sup>1/4</sup>. This is a factor of 2 larger than the value of 55&#xA0;m<sup>0.23</sup> (<italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.37, <italic>n</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;41) derived from a compilation of data on South American mammals that was published after our estimation (Pereira and Daily <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR52">2007</xref>). Obviously, this relationships needs to be confirmed for other species groups.</p>
        <p>Substituting Eq. <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref> into Eq. <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref> yields the reproductive mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>) accumulated between batches as a linear function of adult size (<italic>m</italic>) as (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>): <disp-formula id="Equ5"><label>5</label><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ m_{{\text{r}}} = p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot p_{{{\text{rl}}}} \cdot m. $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Clutch or litter (reproductive) mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>) (kg) increases with <italic>m</italic> (kg) to the power of about 3/4 to 1. Legend as in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>. Regressions listed in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_952_Fig2_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig></p>
        <p>The total reproductive mass derived from Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref> can be divided into many small or a few large young. At one end of the interval, species called &#x201C;<italic>r</italic>&#x201D;-strategists here, maximize the number of young per female (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) up to a limit set by the absolute minimum size [min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)] of a seed, egg or neonate. The existence of such a threshold has been attributed to various restrictions but, to our knowledge, supporting quantitative evidence is still lacking. Since each individual starts off as a single cell, the average size of parental cells may serve as a first indication for the minimum egg or seed mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>). The weight of a cell is reported to be in the range of 10<sup>&#x2212;15</sup>&#x2013;10<sup>&#x2212;11</sup>&#xA0;kg for plants and animals (Raven <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR57">1998</xref>; West et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR67">2001</xref>; Mulder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">2005</xref>). Lower taxa with multi-cellular organization, such as mycorrhizal conidia and fruit bodies of basidiomycetes, actually release offspring as single cells (Mulder et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2003</xref>). Higher species reproduce by multi-cellular sexual spores, seeds, eggs and neonates, with sizes at or above that range. With this variability in mind, min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) was tentatively set at the minimum observed for the taxon covered (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). At the other side of the range, &#x201C;K&#x201D;-type organisms invest all reproductive mass into a few young. In this strategy, seed, egg and neonate mass are maximized by dividing the total reproductive mass over a few offspring. Low values are noted for, e.g., birds with an average of 4.8 eggs per clutch and for mammals with means of 2.7&#x2013;2.8 neonates per litter (Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>; Ernest <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2003</xref>). Apparently, the risk of premature death is typically spread over, on average, at least three young, so that the maximum mass of individual offspring [max(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)] is calculated as max(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)&#xA0;=&#xA0;<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>/3&#xA0;=&#xA0;<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>&#xB7;<italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>&#xB7;<italic>m</italic>/3. With seed, egg and neonate mass ranging between min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) and max(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>), we can now derive <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> as: <disp-formula id="Equ6"><label>6</label><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ \begin{aligned}{} R_{0} = &amp; \frac{{m_{r} }} {{{\text{min(}}m_{e} {\text{)}} \ldots {\text{max(}}m_{e} {\text{)}}}} \\ = &amp; \frac{{m_{r} }} {{{\text{min(}}m_{e} {\text{)}} \ldots m_{r} /3}} \\ = &amp; \frac{{p_{{rp}} \cdot p_{{rl}} }} {{{\text{min(}}m_{e} {\text{)}}}} \cdot m \ldots 3 \\ \end{aligned} $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>The number of seeds, eggs and neonates (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) is thus expected to scale to <italic>m</italic> with exponents in the range of 0&#x2013;1, for<italic> K</italic>-strategists and <italic>r</italic>-strategists, respectively. The corresponding intercepts are <italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>&#xB7;<italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>/min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) and 3, respectively. Intermediate values indicate that both types of species are present in the sampled taxon. If strategies are uniformly distributed among species, one expects a mean slope of 1/2, with the geometric average of <italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>&#xB7;<italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>/min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) and 3 as a coefficient. Vice versa, the mass of a seed, egg or neonate (i.e.<italic> m</italic><sub>e</sub>) varies between min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)&#xA0;&#x221D;&#xA0;<italic>m</italic><sup>1</sup> and max(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) &#xA0;&#x221D;&#xA0;<italic>m</italic><sup>0</sup>, also with an average at <italic>m</italic><sup>1/2</sup> (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>, <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Egg or neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) (kg) increases with<italic> m</italic> (kg) to a power varying around 1/2 for cold-blooded animals and in the range of 3/4&#x2013;1 for warm-blooded animals. Legend as in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; in addition, model estimations for organisms in general (<italic>E</italic>, <italic>dashed-dotted</italic>, <italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.0000046&#xA0;m<sup>1/2</sup>, <italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.2&#xA0;m). Regressions listed in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_952_Fig3_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Seed, egg or neonate number in ovaries, clutch or litter (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) (young/individual) increases with <italic>m</italic> (kg) to a power varying around 1/2 for cold-blooded animals and close to 0 for warm-blooded animals. Legend as in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; in addition, model estimations for organisms in general (<italic>E</italic>, <italic>dashed-dotted</italic>, <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;45,000&#xA0;m<sup>1/2</sup>, <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1). Regressions as listed in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_952_Fig4_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>Equations <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">6</xref> apply to cases where <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> is related to the metabolism of the organisms. Alternatively, <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> may depend on cyclic processes in the environment. Since optimal conditions for offspring usually occur in specific seasons, synchronization of reproduction to annual cycles of temperature, light or food availability by e.g., hibernation or fetal growth retardation, is most likely. With <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub>&#xA0;=&#xA0;365&#xA0;days, Eq. <xref rid="Equ3" ref-type="">3</xref> becomes: <disp-formula id="Equ7"><label>7</label><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ m_{{\text{r}}} = p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot k_{{\text{p}}} \cdot m \cdot 365 = p_{{{\text{rp}}}} \cdot q_{{\text{T}}} \cdot \gamma _{{\text{p}}} \cdot m^{{1 - \kappa }} \cdot 365 $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>indicating that the mass released in a yearly sowing, clutch or litter (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>) scales to <italic>m</italic> with an exponent of 1&#x2212;<italic>&#x3BA;</italic>. Organisms with an intrinsic <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> close to 1&#xA0;year can exploit such synchronization most readily. Smaller species may somewhat postpone their reproduction, increasing the gonadic mass released. Larger species may do the opposite, decreasing the slope of the regression towards 3/4. Fitting Eq. <xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref> into <xref rid="Equ4" ref-type="">4</xref> and writing <italic>m</italic> explicitly gives: <disp-formula id="Equ8"><label>8</label><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$ m = {\left( {p_{{{\text{rl}}}} \cdot \frac{1} {{\tau _{{\text{r}}} \cdot q_{{\text{T}}} \cdot \gamma _{{\text{p}}} }}} \right)}^{{(1/ - \kappa )}} $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Using the typical values for the parameters (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), cold-blooded and warm-blooded organisms with a <italic>&#x3C4;</italic><sub>r</sub> of 365&#xA0;days are expected to have an <italic>m</italic> of about 4 and 500&#xA0;kg, respectively. Organisms that are much smaller mature sufficiently fast to allow multiple generations within a year or growing season. Species which are substantially larger need more than 1&#xA0;year to produce one egg or neonate.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec5" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Reproduction rate constant</title>
        <p>We will now compare the derived equations to the empirical regressions obtained in the meta-analysis. The few correlations available for gonadic growth show that reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub> indeed decrease significantly with increasing adult mass (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001&#x2026;&lt;0.002, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). Average slopes for plants and animals are in the range of &#x2212;0.16 to &#x2212;0.39 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). Slopes for warm-blooded species tend to be steeper than those for cold-blooded species. The empirical regressions for seed plants were derived from one study, with annual reproductive mass expressed as a function of foliage and stem mass because total weight correlations were not provided (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>; Niklas and Enquist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>). The invertebrate regressions apply to short-term studies on different types of copepods. The outlier noted in field experiments with sac spawners was not confirmed by other correlations, including those for high food levels (Hirst and Bunker <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2003</xref>, p 1,995). Low intercepts for fish and mammals apply to long-term observations, including intervals without gonadic growth (Charnov <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2001</xref>; Charnov et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2001</xref>). High values were noted for reproductive growth in gestation periods (Payne and Wheeler <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1968</xref>; Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>). Reproduction within primates is slower, as earlier noted for production (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, no.&#xA0;34; Western and Ssemakula <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1982</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>).
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p><italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub> (kg&#xA0;female&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;</sup><sup>1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;</sup><sup>1</sup>) as a function of <italic>m</italic> (kg) according to empirical regressions (<italic>y</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<italic>am</italic><sup>b</sup>) collected in the meta-analysis. For abbreviations, see Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">No</th><th align="left">Taxon</th><th align="left"><italic>a</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>b</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th><th align="left">Source</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta</td><td align="left">1.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.16</td><td char="." align="char">279</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Niklas and Enquist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta</td><td align="left">3.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.33</td><td char="." align="char">418</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Niklas and Enquist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">9.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.25</td><td char="." align="char">3081</td><td char="." align="char">0.06</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">Hirst and Bunker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">1.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.17</td><td char="." align="char">452</td><td char="." align="char">0.05</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">Hirst and Bunker (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">2.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.26</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td align="left">Ki&#xF8;rboe and Sabatini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1995</xref>) </td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.26</td><td char="." align="char">10</td><td char="." align="char">0.72</td><td char="." align="char">0.002</td><td align="left">Ki&#xF8;rboe and Sabatini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">3.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.19</td><td char="." align="char">139</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Charnov et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2001</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">4.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.33</td><td char="." align="char">192</td><td char="." align="char">0.89</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Charnov (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">2001</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">1.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.43</td><td char="." align="char">92</td><td char="." align="char">0.65</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">33</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">3.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.40</td><td char="." align="char">30</td><td char="." align="char">0.90</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Payne and Wheeler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1968</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">Primates</td><td align="left">8.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.44</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Payne and Wheeler (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR51">1968</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p>The differences between regressions for the reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub> (kg&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) follow the trends expected from the model, based on average turnover <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> (Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>). That is to say, slopes &#x2212;<italic>&#x3BA;</italic> for both reproduction and production tend to be close to &#x2212;1/4 for heterotherms and at or below &#x2212;1/3 for homeotherms (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>; White and Seymour <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR69">2004</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). Intercepts for seed growth in plant populations, including all life stages, follow Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>, independently confirming the value of 28% for the <italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>. The reproduction rate regressions for animals are expressed on a female basis. With the exception of deviations noted for some regressions on copepods and primates, levels for true gonadic growth in heterotherms are within a factor of 3 of the model, based on a <italic>&#x3B3;</italic><sub>p</sub> of 7.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;4</sup>&#xA0;kg&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup> previously derived for production (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). In general, the variability of the intercepts for reproduction reflects differences in methods, conditions and species and is similar to the variability observed for, e.g., individual growth or consumption (Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">2007</xref>). Keeping this variability in mind, we might approximate reproduction by 0.28&#xA0;<italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> in plants and 1&#xA0;<italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> in adult animals as predicted by Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref> of the model.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Total offspring mass in a reproductive batch</title>
        <p>With average production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> as a predictor of reproduction, we can now compare measurements and estimations for the reproductive masses and numbers (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Regressions indicate that total seed, egg and neonate weight increase with parent size (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001&#x2026;&lt;0.05 in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Most 95% confidence intervals for the average of the slopes encompass 3/4 or 1, but the whole animal size range can only be covered by an exponent of 1 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The outcome for plants is dominated by a regression with a slope of 0.67 observed for fruit versus stem mass (1 in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Expressed on leaf mass, annual standing reproductive weight in plants scaled to 0.84 (Niklas and Enquist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>). Comparing weighted averages, the mean slope for invertebrates 0.95 is significantly higher than the confidence interval calculated for plants and cold-blooded vertebrates (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The confidence intervals noted for exponents of birds and mammals cover 3/4 but not 1. All intercepts for cold-blooded and warm-blooded species are close to each other with the exception of one low value noted for fish (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>; Stolz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2005</xref>). This outlier, however, reflects year-round observations while other regressions apply to peak gonad mass. Similar intercept differences were noted for the reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub>.
<table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Reproductive mass [sowing, clutch, litter (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>); seed, egg, neonate (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)] (kg) as well as the number of offspring (seed, egg, neonate; <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) as a function of <italic>m</italic> (kg), according to empirical regressions (<italic>y</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;<italic>am</italic><sup>b</sup>) collected in the meta-analysis. Values in<italic> italics</italic> approximated by us because not/wrongly reported in the original study. Offspring mass or number measured in event (clutch, litter) or organ (ovary, fruits). <italic>n.a.</italic> Not available, <italic>n.s.</italic> not significant; for other abbreviations, see Tables <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and &#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">No.</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Taxon</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>e</italic>, o</th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub> (kg)</th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub> (kg)</th><th align="left" colspan="5"><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> (no./female)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">Source</th></tr><tr><th align="left"><italic>a</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>b</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>a</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>b</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>p</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>a</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>b</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>n</italic></th><th align="left"><italic>r</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">1.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.67</td><td char="." align="char">418</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Niklas and Enquist (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR48">2003</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">2</td><td align="left">Angiospermae<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">1.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.02</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td char="." align="char">0.87</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left"><italic>5.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;6</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.23</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>15</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.08</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.30</italic></td><td align="left">2.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.01</td><td char="." align="char">15</td><td char="." align="char">0.49</td><td char="." align="char">0.004</td><td align="left">Aarssen and Jordan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2001</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">5.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.08</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.94</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>1.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;5</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.60</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>13</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.26</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.07</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>6.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.43</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>13</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.20</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.13</italic></td><td align="left">Greene and Johnson (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1994</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">4</td><td align="left">Angiospermae</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left"><italic>5.5</italic>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.95</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>57</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.68</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"><italic>1.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>3</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.56</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>220</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.38</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Shipley and Dion (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">1992</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">5</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">8.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.47</td><td char="." align="char">224</td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Moles et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2005b</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">6</td><td align="left">Spermatophyta</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">4.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td><td char="." align="char">226</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Grubb et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2005</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">11</td><td align="left">Rotifera</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">3.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.60</td><td char="." align="char">43</td><td char="." align="char">0.55</td><td char="." align="char">0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Walz et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR65">1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">4.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td><td char="." align="char">21</td><td char="." align="char">0.87</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Ki&#xF8;rboe and Sabatini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">13</td><td align="left">Copepoda</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">41</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Ki&#xF8;rboe and Sabatini (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">14</td><td align="left">Crustacea</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">2.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.16</td><td char="." align="char">23</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.99</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">5.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;8</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.24</td><td char="." align="char">22</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>2.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>4</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.59</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>23</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.59</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">Diptera<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">6.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.00</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">2.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;6</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.31</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">2.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">48</td><td char="." align="char">0.19</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">Berrigan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">16</td><td align="left">Hymenoptera<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">1.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.96</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">0.80</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">1.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.89</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">0.75</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">7.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.07</td><td char="." align="char">31</td><td char="." align="char">0.02</td><td char="." align="char">n.s.</td><td align="left">Berrigan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">17</td><td align="left">Coleoptera<sup>a</sup></td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">6.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">1.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.69</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="." align="char">0.72</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.05</td><td align="left">4.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td><td char="." align="char">56</td><td char="." align="char">0.05</td><td char="." align="char">n.s.</td><td align="left">Berrigan (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">18</td><td align="left">Araneomorphae</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.09</td><td char="." align="char">13</td><td char="." align="char">0.90</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001</td><td align="left">2.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">33</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001</td><td align="left">4.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.66</td><td char="." align="char">39</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char">0.0001</td><td align="left">Marshall and Gittleman (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1994</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">19</td><td align="left">Aphidae</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"><italic>1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>3</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.16</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>137</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.35</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Llewellyn and Brown (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1953</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">20</td><td align="left">Cephalopoda</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"><italic>2.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;5</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.26</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>18</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.08</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.25</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Wood and O&#x2019;dor (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2000</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">21</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">1.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.04</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">0.85</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Stolz (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR63">2005</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">22</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes-Reptilia</td><td align="left">oe</td><td align="left"><italic>1.1</italic>&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.92</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>85</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.86</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.43</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.0007</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>1.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>4</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.55</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>121</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.56</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">23</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">1.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">1.08</td><td char="." align="char">9</td><td char="." align="char">0.91</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">McCann and Shuter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">24</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">o</td><td align="left">4.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.86</td><td char="." align="char">20</td><td char="." align="char">0.91</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">McCann and Shuter (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">25</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">4.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>4</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td char="." align="char">108</td><td char="." align="char">0.62</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Winemiller and Rose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">1992</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">26</td><td align="left">Osteichthyes</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">1.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>5</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.78</td><td char="." align="char">108</td><td char="." align="char">0.35</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.0001</td><td align="left">Winemiller and Rose (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">1992</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">27</td><td align="left">Salamandrae</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">2.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">74</td><td char="." align="char">0.89</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.01</td><td align="left"><italic>2.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;5</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.19</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.02</italic></td><td align="left"><italic>7.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>2</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.31</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.01</italic></td><td align="left">Kaplan and Salthe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">28</td><td align="left">Salamandrae</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"><italic>1.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;4</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.37</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>25</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.58</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Kaplan and Salthe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">29</td><td align="left">Salamandrae</td><td align="left">&#x2013;</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"><italic>7.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10</italic><sup><italic>&#x2212;4</italic></sup></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.49</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>21</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.55</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Kaplan and Salthe (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">30</td><td align="left">Reptilia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.88</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">0.96</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left">7.5&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.42</td><td char="." align="char">35</td><td char="." align="char">0.70</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">2.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.48</td><td char="." align="char">54</td><td char="." align="char">0.78</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">31</td><td align="left">Aves</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">2.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.64</td><td char="." align="char">114</td><td char="." align="char">0.69</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">6.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.67</td><td char="." align="char">76</td><td char="." align="char">0.88</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">4.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.08</td><td char="." align="char">114</td><td char="." align="char">0.10</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">Cabana et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1982</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">32</td><td align="left">Aves</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">2.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char">220</td><td char="." align="char">0.85</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">5.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td><td char="." align="char">160</td><td char="." align="char">0.83</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">4.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2248;0</td><td char="." align="char">100</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">33</td><td align="left">Aves</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.72</td><td char="." align="char">350</td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left">5.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.77</td><td char="." align="char">230</td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Western and Ssemakula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1982</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">34</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.84</td><td char="." align="char">76</td><td char="." align="char">0.93</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">4.0&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">114</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Cabana et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">1982</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">35</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.82</td><td char="." align="char">110</td><td char="." align="char">0.97</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">5.6&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.92</td><td char="." align="char">200</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">2.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2248;0</td><td char="." align="char">100</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left">Blueweiss et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">36</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left">1.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.79</td><td char="." align="char">92</td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">n.a.</td><td align="left">5.1&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char">91</td><td char="." align="char">0.94</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">2.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.14</td><td char="." align="char">91</td><td char="." align="char">0.74</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Western and Ssemakula (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR68">1982</xref>), Sacher and Staffeldt (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR60">1974</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">37</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">2.7&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.71</td><td char="." align="char">95</td><td char="." align="char">0.88</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.01</td><td align="left">3.9&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.00</td><td char="." align="char">100</td><td char="." align="char">0</td><td char="." align="char">n.s.</td><td align="left">Millar (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">1977</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">38</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">3.4&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.16</td><td char="." align="char">29</td><td char="." align="char">0.54</td><td char="." align="char">&lt;0.001</td><td align="left">Millar and Zammuto (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">1983</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">39</td><td align="left">Mammalia</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">2.2&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.95</td><td char="." align="char">4</td><td char="." align="char">0.98</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">2.8&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>0</sup></td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.12</td><td char="." align="char">63</td><td char="." align="char">0.32</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left">Purvis and Harvey (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR56">1995</xref>)</td></tr><tr><td align="left">40</td><td align="left">Primates</td><td align="left">e</td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">8.3&#xA0;&#xD7;&#xA0;10<sup>&#x2212;2</sup></td><td char="." align="char">0.85</td><td char="." align="char">100</td><td char="." align="char"><italic>0.93</italic></td><td char="." align="char"><italic>&lt;0.0001</italic></td><td align="left"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td char="." align="char"/><td align="left">Ross (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR59">1998</xref>)</td></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Allometric scaling of reproductive parameters as listed in Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> and <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> plotted in Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Measured arithmetic mean and data-weighted mean (in <italic>italics</italic>) for the regression exponent<italic> b</italic> with 95% confidence interval and model values. For abbreviations, see Tables <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and &#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref></p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left">Parameter</th><th align="left">Reproduction rate</th><th align="left">Batch mass</th><th align="left">Offspring mass</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Offspring number</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Symbol</td><td align="left"><italic>p</italic><sub>ap</sub>&#xB7;<italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub></td><td align="left"><italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>/<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub></td></tr><tr><td align="left">Unit</td><td align="left">d<sup>&#x2212;1</sup></td><td align="left">kg</td><td align="left">kg</td><td align="left" colspan="2">Number of individuals</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Empirical average</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Plants</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.33, &#x2212;0.16</td><td align="left">0.93 (0.65&#x2013;1.22)</td><td align="left">0.48 (0.20&#x2013;0.75)</td><td align="left">0.66 (&#x2212;0.10 to 1.43)</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>0.78 </italic>(<italic>0.65&#x2013;0.91</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.53 </italic>(<italic>0.45&#x2013;0.60</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.58 </italic>(<italic>0.38&#x2013;0.78</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">0.25</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Invertebrates</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.15 (&#x2212;0.49 to 0.19)</td><td align="left">1.00 (0.83<italic>&#x2013;</italic>1.17)</td><td align="left">0.55 (0.35<italic>&#x2013;</italic>0.75)</td><td align="left">0.32 (&#x2212;0.04 to 0.68)</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>&#x2212;0.20 </italic>(<italic>&#x2212;0.33 to &#x2212;0.07</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.95 </italic>(<italic>0.87&#x2013;1.03</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.56 </italic>(<italic>0.51&#x2013;0.62</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.27 </italic>(<italic>0.13&#x2013;0.42</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cold-blooded vertebrates</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.19</td><td align="left">0.90 (0.74<italic>&#x2013;</italic>1.06)</td><td align="left">0.39 (0.28<italic>&#x2013;</italic>0.50)</td><td align="left">0.58 (0.26&#x2013;0.91)</td><td char="." align="char">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"><italic>0.85 </italic>(<italic>0.78&#x2013;0.91</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.40 </italic>(<italic>0.27&#x2013;0.53</italic>)</td><td align="left"><italic>0.67 </italic>(<italic>0.54&#x2013;0.81</italic>)</td><td char="." align="char">0.45</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Birds</td><td align="left"/><td align="left">0.70 (0.56<italic>&#x2013;</italic>0.84)</td><td align="left">0.74 (0.59<italic>&#x2013;</italic>0.88)</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.04 (&#x2212;0.55 to 0.47)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Mammals</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.39 (&#x2212;0.53 to &#x2212;0.25)</td><td align="left">0.82 (0.75<italic>&#x2013;</italic>0.88)</td><td align="left">0.88 (0.77&#x2013;1.00)</td><td align="left">&#x2212;0.08 (&#x2212;0.28 to 0.11)</td><td char="." align="char">&#x2212;0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="6">Model value</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Cold-blooded</td><td align="left">&#x2212;1/4</td><td align="left">1</td><td align="left">1/2</td><td align="left">1/2</td><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">Warm-blooded</td><td align="left">&#x2212;1/4 to &#x2212;1/3</td><td align="left">(3/4)&#x2013;1</td><td align="left">(3/4)&#x2013;1</td><td align="left">0</td><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
        <p>For the overall range, empirical slopes for heterotherms approach the value of 1 expected from Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref> of the model. In addition, the intercepts for plants and animals are at the level expected from the coefficients <italic>p</italic><sub>rl</sub>&#xB7;<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub> of Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>. Exponents collected for homeotherms and some large-sized heterotherms tend towards 3/4, suggesting synchronization to annual cycles as explained by Eq. <xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="">7</xref>. The steep lines observed for invertebrates in comparison to the flatter slopes of cold-blooded vertebrates confirm the prediction that heterotherms of ca. 4&#xA0;kg are likely to experience some kind of synchronization. In addition, exponents for mammals, including large species weighting up to 500&#xA0;kg, are close to 3/4. Exponents for birds are smaller and obviously their weight range does not include this value.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Seed, egg and neonate mass</title>
        <p>Regressions show that seed and egg masses are significantly related to adult size for most heterothermic species groups (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Exceptions are noted for some correlations that cover a small size range or a few data (<italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&#x2265;&#xA0;0.07;Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, nos. 2 and 3 and 20). The slope varies within a small interval around the mid-point value of 1/2 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Averages for invertebrates are higher than those for plants and cold-blooded vertebrates, mainly because regressions on egg-carrying copepods and wasps have slopes closer to 1 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, 12 and 16; Berrigan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>; Ki&#xF8;rboe and Sabatini <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">1995</xref>). The egg and seed masses (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) for plants, invertebrates and (semi-)aquatic vertebrates of the same size are within 1 order of magnitude of each other (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Eggs of aquatic crustaceans tend to be smaller than those of terrestrial spiders and insects with equal body size (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, nos. 12&#x2013;14&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;14&#x2013;18). Likewise, intercepts for cold-blooded vertebrates increase in the sequence of fish, water-bound salamanders, land-dwelling salamanders and reptiles (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, 22&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;27&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;28&#xA0;&#x2264;&#xA0;29&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;30; Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>; Kaplan and Salthe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>). Warm-blooded animals distribute their reproductive effort over a small and size-invariant <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>, leading to exponents for egg and neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) between 3/4 and 1 (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>).</p>
        <p>The partitioning of the reproductive mass over seeds, eggs and neonate thus follows a combination of both strategies distinguished in the model. The empirical regressions collected are within the minimum and maximum boundaries set by Eq. <xref rid="Equ6" ref-type="">6</xref> of the model (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). The slopes for plants, most invertebrates and all cold-blooded vertebrates vary around &#xBD; indicating some intermediate value between min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)&#x2013;<italic>m</italic><sup>0</sup> and max(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)&#x2013;<italic>m</italic><sup>1</sup>. Egg-carrying copepods, wasps, birds and mammals largely consists of <italic>K</italic>-strategists, with egg and neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) exponents near those noted for clutch and litter mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>). Almost all regressions are above the intermediate intercept calculated by the model for an overall minimum offspring size min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) of 10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>&#xA0;kg (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). Using typical minimum values min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) of 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup>&#xA0;kg for plants, fish and amphibians and of 10<sup>&#x2212;3</sup>&#xA0;kg for reptiles rather than the overall 10<sup>&#x2212;10</sup>&#xA0;kg gives a better fit of the model.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Seed, egg and neonate number</title>
        <p>The number of seeds and eggs released by heterotherms scales to size with exponents largely between 1/2 and 1 (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). The difference between intercepts reflects the fraction of the lifetime covered, being near 100% for herbs and a few percent of less for trees, reflecting lifetime and batch fecundity (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>), respectively (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, 2 vs. 3&#x2013;4; Shipley and Dion <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR61">1992</xref>; Greene and Johnson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">1994</xref>; Aarssen and Jordan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2001</xref>). The amount of eggs delivered by crustaceans, flies, spiders and aphids is significantly correlated to adult size but those for wasps and beetles are size-independent (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, nos. 14&#x2013;15, 18&#x2013;19 vs. 16&#x2013;17; Llewellyn and Brown <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">1953</xref>; Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>; Berrigan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>; Marshall and Gittleman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1994</xref>). The low intercept for vertebrate heterotherms applies to reptiles (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, 30; Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>). The clutch and litter size of warm-blooded species does not increase with adult size. In fact, four out of seven regressions have slightly negative slopes.</p>
        <p>As expected, average slopes of regressions for <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> are in the same range as those calculated for the ratio of total and individual offspring mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>/<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>). The largest deviation between arithmetic means is noted for plants and equals 0.66&#x2212;0.45&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.21. However, this difference is due to one study in which sowing weight and number but not seed weight scale significantly to <italic>m</italic> (<italic>b</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1.01&#x2026;1.02, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.00001&#x2026;0.004, vs. <italic>b</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.23, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.30). With parameters set at typical values, the model follows these trends (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec10" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Data variability</title>
        <p>The meta-analysis yielded regressions for various species groups. However, important phylogenetically lower taxa, such as bacteria, algae, fungi, mosses, ferns, Protozoa and annelids have not been included in allometric relationship on reproductive parameters. Budding or binary fission in unicellular organisms yields new cells that become independent at about 30&#x2013;50% of the parent cell volume, respectively (Woldringh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR71">1993</xref>). Unicellular taxa thus maximize the mass rather than the number of their offspring. Fungi, mosses and ferns release spores that are at the lower end of the palynological range noted for seed plants (e.g., Nilsson <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR49">1983</xref>; Haig and Westoby <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1991</xref>; Moore et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">1991</xref>; Mulder and Janssen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">1999</xref>). Their strategy is thus comparable to that of some seed plants, such as orchids. Additional study of the size-related reproduction of these cryptogams is required.</p>
        <p>Plant offspring is characterized by seed and fruit mass with or without ancillary tissues, while adult mass refers to leaves and/or stems. Animal studies either cover the whole annual cycle or reproductive periods only. In addition, deviations from average values of other factors, such those for length&#x2013;weight conversion or life-stage may increase variability.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Slopes on the trade-off between reproduction and production</title>
        <p>Despite uncertainties, clear patterns on the average trends emerge (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub> (kg&#xA0;kg<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>&#xA0;day<sup>&#x2212;1</sup>) decrease with size, as expected from the model. According to Eq. <xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref>, reproduction is considered to be a fraction (<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>) of the production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub>, representing the<italic> P</italic>/<italic>B</italic> of a population. Reproduction <italic>k</italic><sub>pr</sub> by homeotherms has steeper slopes and larger intercepts in comparison with heterotherms, as earlier noted for production <italic>k</italic><sub>p</sub> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>). It indicates that the trade-off between somatic and gonadic growth is rather invariant to size and metabolism. The fraction of the production directed to reproduction (<italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>) was found to be 28% for plants after conversion to seedling wet weight, indeed independent of the species weight (Niklas and Enquist <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2002</xref>). The similarity between slopes for reproduction and overall population production indicates that such a relationship also exists for animals. However, the derivation of such a fraction is yet impeded by large variability among intercepts, by a lack of information on many heterothermic species and by the focus on adult animals instead of whole populations.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Theoretical (<italic>lines</italic>) and empirical (<italic>dotted area</italic>) trends of seed, egg or neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>, <italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) (kg) and number (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>) versus <italic>m</italic> (kg) for several species groups</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="442_2007_952_Fig5_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>Slopes on the trade-off between offspring number and mass</title>
        <p>The meta-analysis in the present paper shows that the mass released in a single reproductive event (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>) (kg) is a constant fraction of the parents&#x2019; weight for a remarkable variety of plant and animal species (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>). Over the whole range of species studied, the slope is close to 1 but exponents for specific groups, such as homeotherms and possibly plants, are smaller. Ignoring differences in slopes and intercepts, about 20% of the adult mass is released in a sowing, clutch or litter (Eq. <xref rid="Equ5" ref-type="">5</xref>). This supports, though not necessarily implies, the existence of a size-independent <italic>p</italic><sub>rp</sub>.</p>
        <p>In addition to the trade-off between somatic and gonadic growth, organisms may divert their reproductive mass over many small or a few large offspring (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In other words, the <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> is inverse proportional to seed, egg or neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>). As elaborated in the Model development section, one may distinguish between species with <italic>r</italic>-tactics that maximize the number of offspring with increasing adult mass (<italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>~<italic>m</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>~<italic>m</italic><sup>0</sup>) and <italic>K</italic>-strategists that amplify seed, egg or neonate weight (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>~<italic>m</italic><sup>1</sup>, <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub>~<italic>m</italic><sup>0</sup>). Slopes of regressions on <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> and <italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub> of the offspring generally vary around the intermediate value of 1/2, expected if species with an <italic>r</italic>- and <italic>K</italic>-strategy are equally distributed (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). However, regressions on egg-carrying copepods, wasps, birds and mammals have exponents close to 1 for egg and neonate size (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) and near 0 for <italic>R</italic><sub>0</sub> (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). These species groups thus largely consist of <italic>K</italic>-strategists.</p>
        <p>Graphically, seed, egg and neonate mass are confined to a triangular envelope that contains small species with small offspring and large species with small or large offspring (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Such a pattern has been previously recognized in original data on plants and fish. The triangle was found to be right-angled for fish, with a minimum egg size [min(<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>)] of 10<sup>&#x2212;7</sup>&#xA0;kg independent of the <italic>m</italic> (e.g., Duarte and Alearaz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1989</xref>). In plants, the envelope was reported to be obtuse-angled, where the 5%-tile and the 95%-tile of seed size scaled to total plant mass with exponents in the range of 0.21&#x2013;0.32 and 0.38&#x2013;0.68, respectively (Grubb et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2005</xref>; Moles et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">2005</xref>b). The slopes for the lower boundary encompass the value of 1/4, known for scaling of biological time variables (Peters <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR53">1983</xref>; Hendriks <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1999</xref>). Although the period to adulthood has been suggested to limit egg and seed size, such a relationship may be more complex than a 1/4 power scaling to size (see, e.g., Kiflawi <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2006</xref>). In addition, some proof for the underlying mechanisms, including an explanation for its absence and presence in different species, as well as taxon-specific slope values, is yet lacking.</p>
        <p>Similar considerations apply to the upper boundary. The egg and neonate mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>e</sub>) in warm-blooded species is proportional to the weight of their parents. Each of the slopes is steeper than observed for clutch or litter mass (<italic>m</italic><sub>r</sub>). However, confidence intervals for the averages indicate that 3/4 may be the appropriate exponent in addition to 1, at least within small size ranges such as noted for birds. Slopes of 3/4 can be understood from inter-reproductive periods that synchronize to annual cycles rather than to adult mass (Eq. <xref rid="Equ7" ref-type="">7</xref>). Yet, the difference between cold-blooded (&#x2248;1/2) and warm-blooded [(3/4)&#x2013;1] species indicate that metabolism-related mechanisms may be important too. Just as size of warm-blooded adults appears to be constrained by heat exchange, neonate mass may be also be determined by thermodynamic principles. However, the exploration and underpinning of other values for the slopes is beyond the scope of the present paper. For now, we assume that the lower and upper end of the range scale to between 0 and 1. Most species groups contain both an <italic>r</italic>- and <italic>K</italic>-strategists yielding an average of slope of about 1/2, whereas some animal taxa were shown to scale to 1. Future refinement by thermodynamic principles may lead to a smaller range between, e.g., 1/4 and 3/4, still yielding average slopes around 1/2.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Intercepts on the trade-off between aquatic and terrestrial habitats</title>
        <p>Having described the possible values of the slopes, we will now take a look at the intercepts. The variability of the exponents excludes detection of subtle differences between coefficients. Yet, there is an evident increase in egg size from aquatic to terrestrial habitats, both among invertebrates and vertebrates. The difference has historically been attributed to oxygen limitations as its diffusion in air is 10,000 times faster than in water (Hendry et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2001</xref>). However, experiments within the same species do not confirm this explanation (Einum et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2002</xref>). We therefore suggest that an alternative, more universal, mechanism may be more important. A parent is more willing to invest in the size of a seed or egg when it can influence its fate. Organisms have little control of transport and development in large homogeneous compartments such as water and air. Consequently, clutches of aquatic animals consist of many small eggs (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>; Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>; Kaplan and Salthe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>; Berrigan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>; Winemiller and Rose <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR70">1992</xref>; McCann and Shuter <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1997</xref>; Wood and O&#x2019;dor <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR72">2000</xref>). Even within fish, pelagic species reproduce by smaller and more eggs than demersal counterparts of equal size (Duarte and Alearaz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1989</xref>). The intercepts for the amphibians increase in the sequence of pond breeders that attach eggs to plants followed by stream and land breeders with nests (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>, 27&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;28&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;29; Kaplan and Salthe <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">1979</xref>). Within the heterogeneous terrestrial environment, land animals can direct their offspring to sites that provide shelter or food to avoid wasting reproductive mass in unfavorable patches (Blueweiss et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">1978</xref>; Berrigan <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">1991</xref>; Marshall and Gittleman <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">1994</xref>). The small seed size of terrestrial plants in comparison to egg masses in reptiles can be understood from the extra dispersal function of propagules in the former case.</p>
        <p>Obviously, other factors that covary with the water&#x2013;land gradient may be responsible for the observed patterns. For instance, the dry&#x2013;wet weight fraction of adults increases from aquatic to terrestrial habitats and a similar trend might exist in their offspring too. However, this explanation, and the related interpretation, is unlikely to cover the orders of magnitude of the noted differences.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Integration of theoretical and empirical evidence</title>
        <p>Integrating these trends, we can now derive common patterns within the triangular envelope of offspring and adult mass (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). In general, <italic>r</italic>-strategists are found amongst small adults (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, left-hand side) with many small offspring in aquatic environments (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, lower end). Large adults (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, right-hand side) with a few large young live in terrestrial habitats (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>, upper end). Obviously, these patterns cannot cover all reproductive and non-reproductive characteristics associated with <italic>r</italic>&#x2212;<italic>K</italic> gradients. For instance, ruderal plants typically reproduce as <italic>r</italic>-strategists, but more<italic> K</italic>-type species, especially in close canopies, may also regenerate via wind dispersal of small seeds (Grime et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">1997</xref>; Grime <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2001</xref>; Aarssen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">2005</xref>). In addition, seed mass is known to be negatively correlated with the leaf size or the life span of 640 plant species (D&#xED;az et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2004</xref>). Such results for plants strongly imply the existence of correlated traits in other taxa and demand further investigation.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank Wilco Verberk, Bernhard Schmid and two anonymous reviewers for useful comments on an earlier version of the manuscript.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aarssen</surname>
              <given-names>LW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Why don&#x2019;t bigger plants have proportionately bigger seeds?</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <fpage>109</fpage>
          <lpage>277</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0030-1299.2005.14206.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aarssen LW (2005) Why don&#x2019;t bigger plants have proportionately bigger seeds? Oikos 111:109&#x2013;277 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aarssen</surname>
              <given-names>LW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jordan</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Between species patterns of covariation in plant size, seed size and fecundity in monocarpic herbs</article-title>
          <source>Ecoscience</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>471</fpage>
          <lpage>477</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aarssen LW, Jordan CY (2001) Between species patterns of covariation in plant size, seed size and fecundity in monocarpic herbs. Ecoscience 8:471&#x2013;477 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berrigan</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The allometry of egg size and number in insects</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>60</volume>
          <fpage>13</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3545073</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Berrigan D (1991) The allometry of egg size and number in insects. Oikos 60:13&#x2013;32 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blueweiss</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fox</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kudzma</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakashima</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sams</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relationships between body size and some life history parameters</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>272</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00344996</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Blueweiss L, Fox H, Kudzma V, Nakashima D, Peters R, Sams S (1978) Relationships between body size and some life history parameters. Oecologia 37:257&#x2013;272 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cabana</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frewin</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Randall</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The effect of sexual size dimorphism on variations in reproductive effort of birds and mammals</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>17</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/283966</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cabana G, Frewin A, Peters RH, Randall L (1982) The effect of sexual size dimorphism on variations in reproductive effort of birds and mammals. Am Nat 120:17&#x2013;25 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charnov</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evolution of mammal life histories</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol Res</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>521</fpage>
          <lpage>535</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Charnov EL (2001) Evolution of mammal life histories. Evol Ecol Res 3:521&#x2013;535 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charnov</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reproductive effort, offspring size and benefit&#x2013;cost ratios in the classification of life histories</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol Res</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>749</fpage>
          <lpage>758</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Charnov EL (2002) Reproductive effort, offspring size and benefit&#x2013;cost ratios in the classification of life histories. Evol Ecol Res 4:749&#x2013;758 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charnov</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Downhower</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A trade-off invariant life history rule for optimal offspring size</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>376</volume>
          <fpage>418</fpage>
          <lpage>419</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/376418a0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Charnov EL, Downhower JF (1995) A trade-off invariant life history rule for optimal offspring size. Nature 376:418&#x2013;419 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7630415</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Charnov</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Turner</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Winemiller</surname>
              <given-names>KO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reproductive constraints and the evolution of life histories with indeterminate growth</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>1134</fpage>
          <lpage>1137</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.161294498</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Charnov EL, Turner TF, Winemiller KO (2001) Reproductive constraints and the evolution of life histories with indeterminate growth. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 98:1134&#x2013;1137 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>PD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Biogeography. An ecological and evolutionary approach</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <edition>7th edn.</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cox CB, Moore PD (2005) Biogeography. An ecological and evolutionary approach. 7th edn. Blackwell, London </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Damuth</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A macroevolutionary explanation for energy equivalence in the scaling of body size and population density</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>169</volume>
          <fpage>621</fpage>
          <lpage>631</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/513495</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Damuth J (2007) A macroevolutionary explanation for energy equivalence in the scaling of body size and population density. Am Nat 169:621&#x2013;631 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17427133</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>D&#xED;az</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hodgson</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cabido</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornelissen</surname>
              <given-names>JHC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jalili</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montserrat-Mart&#xED;</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grime</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zarrinkamar</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Asri</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The plant traits that drive ecosystems: evidence from three continents</article-title>
          <source>J Veg Sci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>295</fpage>
          <lpage>304</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1658/1100-9233(2004)015[0295:TPTTDE]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">D&#xED;az S, Hodgson JG, Thomson K, Cabido M, Cornelissen JHC, Jalili A, Montserrat-Mart&#xED; G, Grime JP, Zarrinkamar F, Asri Y, et al. (2004) The plant traits that drive ecosystems: evidence from three continents. J Veg Sci 15:295&#x2013;304 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duarte</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Alearaz</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>To produce many small or few large eggs: a size-independent reproductive tactic of fish</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>80</volume>
          <fpage>401</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00379043</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Duarte CM, Alearaz M (1989) To produce many small or few large eggs: a size-independent reproductive tactic of fish. Oecologia 80:401&#x2013;404 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Einum</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hendry</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fleming</surname>
              <given-names>IA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Egg-size evolution in aquatic environments: does oxygen availability constrain size?</article-title>
          <source>Proc R Soc Lond B</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>269</volume>
          <fpage>2325</fpage>
          <lpage>2330</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1098/rspb.2002.2150</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Einum S, Hendry AP, Fleming IA (2002) Egg-size evolution in aquatic environments: does oxygen availability constrain size? Proc R Soc Lond B 269:2325&#x2013;2330 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <citation citation-type="other">Ernest SKM (2003) Life history characteristics of placental nonvolant mammals. Ecology 84:3402. <ext-link ext-link-type="uri" xlink:href="http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E084/093/">http://www.esapubs.org/archive/ecol/E084/093/</ext-link></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gillooly</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Savage</surname>
              <given-names>VM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Charnov</surname>
              <given-names>EL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of size and temperature on metabolic rate</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>293</volume>
          <fpage>2248</fpage>
          <lpage>2251</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1061967</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gillooly JF, Brown JH, West GB, Savage VM, Charnov EL (2001) Effects of size and temperature on metabolic rate. Science 293:2248&#x2013;2251 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11567137</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gordon</surname>
              <given-names>IJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The interspecific allometry of reproduction: do larger species invest relatively less in their offspring?</article-title>
          <source>Funct Ecol</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>288</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2389367</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gordon IJ (1989) The interspecific allometry of reproduction: do larger species invest relatively less in their offspring? Funct Ecol 3:285&#x2013;288 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Greene</surname>
              <given-names>DF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estimating the mean annual seed production of trees</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>642</fpage>
          <lpage>647</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1941722</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Greene DF, Johnson EA (1994) Estimating the mean annual seed production of trees. Ecology 75:642&#x2013;647 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grime</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Plant strategies, vegetation processes, ecosystem properties</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <edition>2nd edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Chichester</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grime JP (2001) Plant strategies, vegetation processes, ecosystem properties. 2nd edn. Wiley, Chichester </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grime</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thompson</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hunt</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hodgson</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cornelissen</surname>
              <given-names>JHC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rorison</surname>
              <given-names>IH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hendry</surname>
              <given-names>GAF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ashenden</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Askew</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Band</surname>
              <given-names>SR</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Integrated screening validates primary axes of specialization in plants</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>281</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3546011</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grime JP, Thompson K, Hunt R, Hodgson JG, Cornelissen JHC, Rorison IH, Hendry GAF, Ashenden TW, Askew AP, Band SR, et al. (1997) Integrated screening validates primary axes of specialization in plants. Oikos 79:259&#x2013;281 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grubb</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coomes</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Metcalf</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comment on &#x201C;A brief history of seed size&#x201D;</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>783a</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116097</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grubb PJ, Coomes DA, Metcalf DJ (2005) Comment on &#x201C;A brief history of seed size&#x201D;. Science 310:783a <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272102</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haig</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westoby</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Seed size, pollination costs and angiosperm success</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>231</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF02214230</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Haig D, Westoby M (1991) Seed size, pollination costs and angiosperm success. Evol Ecol 5:231&#x2013;247 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hendriks</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allometric scaling of rate, age and density parameters in ecological models</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>310</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3546447</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hendriks AJ (1999) Allometric scaling of rate, age and density parameters in ecological models. Oikos 86:293&#x2013;310 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hendriks</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The power of size: a meta-analysis reveals consistency of allometric regressions for ecological modelling</article-title>
          <source>Ecol Modell</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>205</volume>
          <fpage>196</fpage>
          <lpage>208</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ecolmodel.2007.02.029</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hendriks AJ (2007) The power of size: a meta-analysis reveals consistency of allometric regressions for ecological modelling. Ecol Modell 205:196&#x2013;208 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hendry</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cooper</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Optimal size and number of propagules: allowance for discrete stages and effects of maternal size on reproductive output and offspring fitness</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>157</volume>
          <fpage>387</fpage>
          <lpage>407</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/319316</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hendry AP, Day T, Cooper AB (2001) Optimal size and number of propagules: allowance for discrete stages and effects of maternal size on reproductive output and offspring fitness. Am Nat 157:387&#x2013;407 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18707249</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hirst</surname>
              <given-names>AG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bunker</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Growth of marine planktonic copepods: global rates and patterns in relation to chlorophyll a, temperature, and body weight</article-title>
          <source>Limnol Oceanogr</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>1988</fpage>
          <lpage>2010</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hirst AG, Bunker AJ (2003) Growth of marine planktonic copepods: global rates and patterns in relation to chlorophyll a, temperature, and body weight. Limnol Oceanogr 48:1988&#x2013;2010 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kaplan</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Salthe</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The allometry of reproduction: an empirical view of salamanders</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>671</fpage>
          <lpage>689</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/283425</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kaplan RH, Salthe SN (1979) The allometry of reproduction: an empirical view of salamanders. Am Nat 113:671&#x2013;689 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kiflawi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On optimal propagule size and developmental time</article-title>
          <source>Oikos</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>113</volume>
          <fpage>168</fpage>
          <lpage>173</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0030-1299.2001.14378.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kiflawi M (2006) On optimal propagule size and developmental time. Oikos 113:168&#x2013;173 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ki&#xF8;rboe</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sabatini</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Scaling of fecundity, growth and development in marine planktonic copepods</article-title>
          <source>Mar Ecol Progr Ser</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.3354/meps120285</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ki&#xF8;rboe T, Sabatini M (1995) Scaling of fecundity, growth and development in marine planktonic copepods. Mar Ecol Progr Ser 120:285&#x2013;298 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Llewellyn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>VK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A general relationship between adult weight and the reproductive potential of aphids</article-title>
          <source>J Anim Ecol</source>
          <year>1953</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>663</fpage>
          <lpage>673</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Llewellyn M, Brown VK (1953) A general relationship between adult weight and the reproductive potential of aphids. J Anim Ecol 54:663&#x2013;673 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>MacArthur</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>EO</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The theory of island biogeography</source>
          <year>1967</year>
          <publisher-loc>Princeton</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Princeton University Press</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">MacArthur RH, Wilson EO (1967) The theory of island biogeography. Princeton University Press, Princeton </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marshall</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gittleman</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Clutch size in spiders&#x2013;&#x2013;is more better?</article-title>
          <source>Funct Ecol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <fpage>118</fpage>
          <lpage>124</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2390120</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Marshall SD, Gittleman JL (1994) Clutch size in spiders&#x2013;&#x2013;is more better? Funct Ecol 8:118&#x2013;124 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>May</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Mound</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waloff</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The dynamics and diversity of insect faunas</article-title>
          <source>Diversity of insect faunas</source>
          <year>1978</year>
          <publisher-loc>Oxford</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>
          <fpage>188</fpage>
          <lpage>204</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">May RM (1978) The dynamics and diversity of insect faunas. In: Mound LA, Waloff N (eds) Diversity of insect faunas. Blackwell, Oxford, pp 188&#x2013;204 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McCann</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shuter</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Bioenergetics of life history strategies and the comparative allometry of reproduction</article-title>
          <source>Can J Fish Aquat Sci</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>1289</fpage>
          <lpage>1298</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1139/cjfas-54-6-1289</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McCann K, Shuter B (1997) Bioenergetics of life history strategies and the comparative allometry of reproduction. Can J Fish Aquat Sci 54:1289&#x2013;1298 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Millar</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adaptive features of mammalian reproduction</article-title>
          <source>Evolution</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>370</fpage>
          <lpage>386</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/2407759</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Millar JS (1977) Adaptive features of mammalian reproduction. Evolution 31:370&#x2013;386 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Millar</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zammuto</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Life histories of mammals: an analysis of life tables</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>631</fpage>
          <lpage>636</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/1937181</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Millar JS, Zammuto RM (1983) Life histories of mammals: an analysis of life tables. Ecology 64:631&#x2013;636 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moles Ackerly</surname>
              <given-names>AT DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webb</surname>
              <given-names>CO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tweddle</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickie</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westoby</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A brief history of seed size</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>307</volume>
          <fpage>576</fpage>
          <lpage>580</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1104863</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moles AT Ackerly DD, Webb CO, Tweddle JC, Dickie JB, Westoby M (2005a) A brief history of seed size. Science 307:576&#x2013;580 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15681384</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moles Ackerly</surname>
              <given-names>AT DD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webb</surname>
              <given-names>CO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tweddle</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dickie</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Westoby</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Response to comment on &#x2018;&#x2018;A brief history of seed size&#x2019;&#x2019;</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>310</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.1116276</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moles AT Ackerly DD, Webb CO, Tweddle JC, Dickie JB, Westoby M (2005b) Response to comment on &#x2018;&#x2018;A brief history of seed size&#x2019;&#x2019;. Science 310:783 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16272102</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moore</surname>
              <given-names>PB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Webb</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Collinson</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Pollen analysis</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <edition>2nd edn</edition>
          <publisher-loc>London</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Blackwell</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moore PB, Webb JA, Collinson ME (1991) Pollen analysis. 2nd edn. Blackwell, London </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Janssen</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Occurrence of pollen and spores in relation to present-day vegetation in a Dutch heathland area</article-title>
          <source>J Veg Sci</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>100</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2307/3237164</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mulder C, Janssen CR (1999) Occurrence of pollen and spores in relation to present-day vegetation in a Dutch heathland area. J Veg Sci 10:87&#x2013;100 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breure</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joosten</surname>
              <given-names>JHJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Fungal functional diversity inferred along Ellenberg&#x2019;s abiotic gradients: palynological evidence from different soil microbiota</article-title>
          <source>Grana</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <fpage>55</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mulder C, Breure AM, Joosten JHJ (2003) Fungal functional diversity inferred along Ellenberg&#x2019;s abiotic gradients: palynological evidence from different soil microbiota. Grana 42:55&#x2013;64 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wijnen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wezel</surname>
              <given-names>AP</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Numerical abundance and biodiversity of below-ground taxocenes along a pH gradient across the Netherlands</article-title>
          <source>J Biogeogr</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>1775</fpage>
          <lpage>1790</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1365-2699.2005.01321.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mulder C, Van Wijnen HJ, Van Wezel AP (2005) Numerical abundance and biodiversity of below-ground taxocenes along a pH gradient across the Netherlands. J Biogeogr 32:1775&#x2013;1790 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <citation citation-type="other">Mulder C, Hendriks AJ, Baerselman R, Posthuma L (2007) Age structure and senescence in long-term cohorts of <italic>Eisenia andrei</italic> (Oligochaeta: Lumbricidae). J Gerontol A Biol Sci 62 (in press)</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niklas</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enquist</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On the vegetative biomass partitioning of seed plant leaves, stems and roots</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>159</volume>
          <fpage>482</fpage>
          <lpage>497</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/339459</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Niklas KJ, Enquist BJ (2002) On the vegetative biomass partitioning of seed plant leaves, stems and roots. Am Nat 159:482&#x2013;497 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">18707431</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR48">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Niklas</surname>
              <given-names>KJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enquist</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An allometric model for seed plant reproduction</article-title>
          <source>Evol Ecol Res</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>79</fpage>
          <lpage>88</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Niklas KJ, Enquist BJ (2003) An allometric model for seed plant reproduction. Evol Ecol Res 5:79&#x2013;88 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR49">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nilsson</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Atlas of airborne fungal spores in Europe</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Vienna</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nilsson S (1983) Atlas of airborne fungal spores in Europe. Springer, Vienna </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR50">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Odum</surname>
              <given-names>HT</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Systems ecology</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Wiley</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Odum HT (1983) Systems ecology. Wiley, New York </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR51">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Payne</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wheeler</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparative nutrition in pregnancy and lactation</article-title>
          <source>Proc Nutr Soc</source>
          <year>1968</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>129</fpage>
          <lpage>137</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1079/PNS19680037</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Payne PR, Wheeler EF (1968) Comparative nutrition in pregnancy and lactation. Proc Nutr Soc 27:129&#x2013;137 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5749945</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR52">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pereira</surname>
              <given-names>HM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Daily</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modeling biodiversity dynamics in countryside landscapes</article-title>
          <source>Ecology</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>1877</fpage>
          <lpage>1885</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1890/0012-9658(2006)87[1877:MBDICL]2.0.CO;2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pereira HM, Daily GC (2007) Modeling biodiversity dynamics in countryside landscapes. Ecology 87:1877&#x2013;1885 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16937624</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR53">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Peters</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The ecological implications of body size</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Peters RH (1983) The ecological implications of body size. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR54">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pianka</surname>
              <given-names>ER</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>On <italic>r</italic>- and<italic> K</italic>-selection</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1970</year>
          <volume>104</volume>
          <fpage>592</fpage>
          <lpage>597</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/282697</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pianka ER (1970) On r- and K-selection. Am Nat 104:592&#x2013;597 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR56">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Purvis</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Harvey</surname>
              <given-names>PH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mammal life-history evolution: a comparative test of Charnov&#x2019;s model</article-title>
          <source>J Zool</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>237</volume>
          <fpage>259</fpage>
          <lpage>283</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Purvis A, Harvey PH (1995) Mammal life-history evolution: a comparative test of Charnov&#x2019;s model. J Zool 237:259&#x2013;283 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR57">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Raven</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Small is beautiful: the picophytoplankton</article-title>
          <source>Funct Ecol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>503</fpage>
          <lpage>513</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1365-2435.1998.00233.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Raven JA (1998) Small is beautiful: the picophytoplankton. Funct Ecol 12:503&#x2013;513 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR58">
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Reiss</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>The allometry of growth and reproduction</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <publisher-loc>Cambridge</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Cambridge University Press</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Reiss MJ (1989) The allometry of growth and reproduction. Cambridge University Press, Cambridge </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR59">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ross</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Primate life histories</article-title>
          <source>Evol Anthropol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>54</fpage>
          <lpage>63</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1520-6505(1998)6:2&lt;54::AID-EVAN3&gt;3.0.CO;2-W</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ross C (1998) Primate life histories. Evol Anthropol 6:54&#x2013;63 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR60">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sacher</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Staffeldt</surname>
              <given-names>EF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Relation of gestation time to brain weight for placental mammals: implications for the theory of vertebrate growth</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>615</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/282938</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sacher GA, Staffeldt EF (1974) Relation of gestation time to brain weight for placental mammals: implications for the theory of vertebrate growth. Am Nat 108:593&#x2013;615 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR61">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shipley</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dion</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The allometry of seed production in herbaceous angiosperms</article-title>
          <source>Am Nat</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>467</fpage>
          <lpage>483</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/285339</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Shipley B, Dion J (1992) The allometry of seed production in herbaceous angiosperms. Am Nat 139:467&#x2013;483 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR63">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stolz</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Allometric growth and sperm competition in fishes</article-title>
          <source>J Fish Biol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>67</volume>
          <fpage>470</fpage>
          <lpage>480</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.0022-1112.2005.00756.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stolz JA (2005) Allometric growth and sperm competition in fishes. J Fish Biol 67:470&#x2013;480 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR64">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Diversity in specific gravity and water content of wood among tropical rainforest trees</article-title>
          <source>Ecol Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>211</fpage>
          <lpage>224</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1440-1703.1999.143301.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Suzuki E (1999) Diversity in specific gravity and water content of wood among tropical rainforest trees. Ecol Res 14:211&#x2013;224 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR65">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Walz</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sarma</surname>
              <given-names>SSS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benker</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Egg size in relation to body size in rotifers: an indication of reproductive strategy?</article-title>
          <source>Hydrobiologia</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>313/314</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>170</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00025946</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Walz N, Sarma SSS, Benker U (1995) Egg size in relation to body size in rotifers: an indication of reproductive strategy? Hydrobiologia 313/314:165&#x2013;170 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR66">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enquist</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A general model for the origin of allometric scaling laws in biology</article-title>
          <source>Science</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>122</fpage>
          <lpage>126</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1126/science.276.5309.122</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">West GB, Brown JH, Enquist BJ (1997) A general model for the origin of allometric scaling laws in biology. Science 276:122&#x2013;126 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9082983</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR67">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>West</surname>
              <given-names>GB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>JH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Enquist</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A general model for ontogenetic growth</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>413</volume>
          <fpage>628</fpage>
          <lpage>631</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35098076</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">West GB, Brown JH, Enquist BJ (2001) A general model for ontogenetic growth. Nature 413:628&#x2013;631 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11675785</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR68">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Western</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ssemakula</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Life-history patterns in birds and mammals and their evolutionary interpretation</article-title>
          <source>Oecologia</source>
          <year>1982</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>281</fpage>
          <lpage>290</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF00379994</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Western D, Ssemakula J (1982) Life-history patterns in birds and mammals and their evolutionary interpretation. Oecologia 54:281&#x2013;290 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR69">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>CR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seymour</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Does basal metabolic rate contain a useful signal? Mammalian BMR allometry and correlations with a selection of physiological, ecological, and life-history variables</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Biochem Zool</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>77</volume>
          <fpage>929</fpage>
          <lpage>941</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1086/425186</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">White CR, Seymour RS (2004) Does basal metabolic rate contain a useful signal? Mammalian BMR allometry and correlations with a selection of physiological, ecological, and life-history variables. Physiol Biochem Zool 77:929&#x2013;941 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15674767</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR70">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Winemiller</surname>
              <given-names>KO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rose</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reproductive constraints and the evolution of life histories with indeterminate growth</article-title>
          <source>Can J Fish Aquat Sci</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>49</volume>
          <fpage>2196</fpage>
          <lpage>2218</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Winemiller KO, Rose KA (1992) Reproductive constraints and the evolution of life histories with indeterminate growth. Can J Fish Aquat Sci 49:2196&#x2013;2218 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR71">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Woldringh</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huls</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vischer</surname>
              <given-names>NOE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Volume growth of daughter and parent cells during the cell cycle of <italic>Saccharomyces cerevisiae</italic> as determined by image cytometry</article-title>
          <source>J Bacteriol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>175</volume>
          <fpage>3174</fpage>
          <lpage>3181</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Woldringh CL, Huls PG, Vischer NOE (1993) Volume growth of daughter and parent cells during the cell cycle of Saccharomyces cerevisiae as determined by image cytometry. J Bacteriol 175:3174&#x2013;3181 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8491731</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR72">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wood</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>O&#x2019;dor</surname>
              <given-names>RK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Do larger cephalopods live longer? Effects of temperature and phylogeny on interspecific comparisons of age and size at maturity</article-title>
          <source>Mar Biol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>136</volume>
          <fpage>91</fpage>
          <lpage>99</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002270050012</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wood JB, O&#x2019;dor RK (2000) Do larger cephalopods live longer? Effects of temperature and phylogeny on interspecific comparisons of age and size at maturity. Mar Biol 136:91&#x2013;99 </citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>