<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Pflugers Arch</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Pflugers Archiv </journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0031-6768</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-2013</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17805561</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2082651</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">326</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00424-007-0326-z</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Cardiovascular System</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Criteria for arrhythmogenicity in genetically-modified Langendorff-perfused murine hearts modelling the congenital long QT syndrome type 3 and the Brugada syndrome</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sabir</surname>
            <given-names>Ian N.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Li</surname>
            <given-names>Lucia M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Jones</surname>
            <given-names>Victoria J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Goddard</surname>
            <given-names>Catharine A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Grace</surname>
            <given-names>Andrew A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Huang</surname>
            <given-names>Christopher L.-H.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+44-1223-333822</phone>
            <fax>+44-1223-333840</fax>
            <email>clh11@cam.ac.uk</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Physiological Laboratory, University of Cambridge, Downing Street, Cambridge, CB2 3EG UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Papworth Hospital, Papworth Everard, Cambridge, CB23 3RE UK </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Department of Biochemistry, University of Cambridge, Tennis Court Road, Cambridge, CB2 1QW UK </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>1</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>455</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>637</fpage>
      <lpage>651</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>30</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="rev-recd">
          <day>9</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>10</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>The experiments investigated the applicability of two established criteria for arrhythmogenicity in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> murine hearts modelling the congenital long QT syndrome type 3 (LQT3) and the Brugada syndrome (BrS). Monophasic action potentials (APs) recorded during extrasystolic stimulation procedures from Langendorff-perfused control hearts and hearts treated with flecainide (1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M) or quinidine (1 or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M) demonstrated that both agents were pro-arrhythmic in wild-type (WT) hearts, quinidine was pro-arrhythmic in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts, and that flecainide was pro-arrhythmic whereas quinidine was anti-arrhythmic in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts, confirming clinical findings. Statistical analysis confirmed a quadratic relationship between epicardial and endocardial AP durations (APDs) in WT control hearts. However, comparisons between plots of epicardial against endocardial APDs and this reference curve failed to correlate with arrhythmogenicity. Restitution curves, relating APD to diastolic interval (DI), were then constructed for the first time in a murine system and mono-exponential growth functions fitted to these curves. Significant (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) alterations in the DI at which slopes equalled unity, an established indicator of arrhythmogenicity, now successfully predicted the presence or absence of arrhythmogenicity in all cases. We thus associate changes in the slopes of restitution curves with arrhythmogenicity in models of LQT3 and BrS.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Action potential</kwd>
        <kwd>Arrhythmia</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart rate</kwd>
        <kwd>Heart excitation</kwd>
        <kwd>Venticular muscle</kwd>
        <kwd>Ventricle</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Mutations in the <italic>SCN5a</italic> gene encoding the &#x3B1;-subunit of the cardiac voltage-gated Na<sup>+</sup> channel are well established to underlie hereditary arrhythmic syndromes which may result in sudden cardiac death. On the one hand, <italic>gain-of-function</italic> mutations which increase inward depolarising currents and consequently prolong the ventricular action potential are associated with arrhythmogenicity in the congenital long QT syndrome type 3 (LQT3) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. On the other hand, <italic>loss-of-function</italic> mutations which decrease such currents are associated with arrhythmogenicity in the Brugada syndrome (BrS) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. In this case, spatial heterogeneities in the degree of shortening of the ventricular action potential result in characteristic electrocardiographic changes, namely a partial right bundle branch block pattern with ST segment elevation in the right precordial leads [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>].</p>
      <p>Despite the similar clinical outcomes of LQT3 and BrS, class 1A and 1C, anti-arrhythmic agents, exemplified by quinidine and flecainide respectively, exert contrasting effects on arrhythmogenicity in these two syndromes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]. Thus in LQT3, quinidine is pro-arrhythmic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] and flecainide is anti-arrhythmic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]. In contrast, in BrS quinidine is anti-arrhythmic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>], while flecainide is pro-arrhythmic [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>] and used to unmask the arrhythmic phenotype in asymptomatic patients. These contrasts are precisely reflected in results from our murine models of LQT3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and BrS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>], emphasizing the translatability of results obtained from such systems. Furthermore, both quinidine and flecainide are known to have the potential for pro-arrhythmic effects [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>].</p>
      <p>These similarities and differences have parallels in the physiological changes thought to underlie arrhythmogenicity in LQT3 and BrS. Thus circus-type re-entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>], requiring both an initiating trigger and a re-entrant substrate, has been implicated in arrhythmogenicity in both these conditions. Of these requirements, both conditions are associated with triggering extrasystoles [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In LQT3, these are initiated by early after-depolarizations attributable to action potential prolongation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>], while in BrS they are initiated by phase 2 re-entry [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">46</xref>]. Furthermore, in both LQT3 and BrS, arrhythmia occurs against a re-entrant substrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In LQT3 this is provided by increased transmural dispersion of repolarization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. While increased transmural dispersion of repolarization has also been demonstrated in some studies on BrS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>], increased epicardial dispersion of repolarization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>] and slowed conduction [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] are also implicated. Thus studies in murine hearts have associated alterations in transmural dispersion of repolarization, reflected in relationships between epicardial and endocardial action potential durations, with arrhythmogenicity in models of LQT3 but failed to do so in models of BrS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>].</p>
      <p>Arrhythmogenicity has often been associated with increases in the slopes of restitution curves, plotting action potential duration against the preceding diastolic interval, to greater than unity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Possible mechanisms that might underlie this association have been discussed in detail on a number of occasions [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. Furthermore, decreases in the slopes of such curves are associated with the anti-arrhythmic effects of several clinically important agents including amiodarone, bretylium and procainamide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Such associations have previously been demonstrated in a pharmacological model of LQT2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] but has not been assessed in LQT3 or in BrS.</p>
      <p>The present study compares an analysis examining transmural dispersion of repolarization, assessed by comparing epicardial and endocardial action potential durations obtained over a range of heart rates and previously established to predict arrhythmogenicity in hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>], with another examining effects on restitution curve parameters. This represents the first occasion on which restitution curves have been constructed in a murine system, in relation to BrS or LQT3, or indeed in any genetic model of an hereditary arrhythmic syndrome. To this end, the monophasic action potential (MAP) technique and an established Langendorff-perfused system [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] are used to study genetically modified mice modelling LQT3 (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and BrS (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] before and after exposure to quinidine and flecainide. We proceed to demonstrate that while the former criterion fails, the latter produces predictions in full agreement with the arrhythmogenic findings in every case and thus suggest that alterations in the slopes of restitution curves are associated with arrhythmogenicity in both LQT3 and BrS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Experimental animals</title>
        <p>Wild-type (WT), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> 129 Sv mice aged 3&#x2013;6&#xA0;months were housed at 21&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1&#xB0;C with 12&#xA0;h light/dark cycles. They were fed sterile chow (RM3 Maintenance Diet, SDS, Witham, Essex, UK) and had free access to water. All procedures complied with the UK Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Solutions</title>
        <p>Solutions were based on bicarbonate-buffered Krebs-Henseleit solution (119&#xA0;mM NaCl, 25&#xA0;mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 4&#xA0;mM KCl, 1.2&#xA0;mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub>, 1&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 1.8&#xA0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10&#xA0;mM glucose and 2&#xA0;mM Na-pyruvate; pH adjusted to 7.4) and were bubbled with 95% O<sub>2</sub>/5% CO<sub>2</sub> (British Oxygen Company, Manchester, U.K). Drug-containing solutions were prepared by adding flecainide (Sigma-Aldrich, Poole, UK) to final concentration of 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M and quinidine (Sigma-Aldrich, Poole, UK) to final concentrations of 1 and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M: these concentrations were chosen to reflect clinically therapeutic values (effective free and total plasma concentrations of 0.79 and 1.48&#xA0;&#x3BC;M, respectively, for flecainide and 0.74 and 7.9&#xA0;&#x3BC;M, respectively, for quinidine) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Preparation</title>
        <p>A Langendorff-perfusion protocol previously adapted for murine hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>] was used. Briefly, mice were killed by cervical dislocation [Schedule 1: UK Animals (Scientific Procedures) Act 1986] before hearts were quickly excised and placed in ice-cold bicarbonate-buffered Krebs-Henseleit solution. Short sections of aorta were cannulated under the surface of the solution and attached to a custom-made 21-gauge cannula filled using an aneurysm clip (Harvard Apparatus, Edenbridge, Kent, UK), within 90&#xA0;s of excision. Fresh Krebs-Henseleit solution was passed through 200- and 5-&#x3BC;m filters (Millipore, Watford, UK) and warmed to 37&#xB0;C using a water jacket and circulator (Techne model C-85A, Cambridge, UK). This solution was then used for constant-flow retrograde perfusion, thereby circumventing any changes in coronary vascular resistance and therefore flow that might otherwise result from the effects of the drugs studied [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], at 2&#x2013;2.5&#xA0;ml/min, driven by a peristaltic pump (Watson-Marlow Bredel model 505S, Falmouth, Cornwall, UK). Hearts were regarded as suitable for experimentation if they regained a healthy pink colour and began to contract spontaneously on re-warming.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Electrophysiological measurements</title>
        <p>An epicardial MAP electrode (Hugo Sachs, Harvard Apparatus, UK) was placed against the basal left ventricular epicardium. A custom-made endocardial MAP electrode consisting of two twisted strands of high-purity Teflon-coated silver wire of 0.25&#xA0;mm diameter (Advent Research Materials, UK) was manufactured. A small access window was created in the interventricular septum to allow access to the left ventricular endocardium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. The Teflon coating was removed from the distal 1&#xA0;mm of the electrode; this was then galvanically chlorided to eliminate DC offset, inserted and placed against the septal endocardial surface. MAPs were amplified, band-pass filtered (0.5&#xA0;Hz to 1&#xA0;kHz: Gould 2400S, Gould-Nicolet Technologies, Ilford, Essex, UK) and digitised at a sampling frequency of 5&#xA0;kHz (micro1401, Cambridge Electronic Design, Cambridge, UK). Analysis of MAPs was performed using Spike II (Cambridge Electronic Design, Cambridge, UK).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Experimental protocol</title>
        <p>A bipolar platinum stimulating electrode (1&#xA0;mm inter-pole spacing) was placed on the basal surface of the right ventricular epicardium. Square-wave stimuli (Grass S48 stimulator, Grass-Telefactor, Slough, UK) of 2&#xA0;ms duration and amplitudes of twice the excitation threshold were initially applied to hearts at a constant baseline cycle length (BCL) of 125&#xA0;ms until MAPs showed stable baselines, rapid upstroke phases that reached consistent amplitudes and smooth repolarization phases [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>] and for at least 10&#xA0;min. Before subsequent recordings were made, hearts were then exposed to test solutions for 20&#xA0;min while stimulation was continued.</p>
        <p>In initial experiments, MAPs were recorded during regular stimulation at a BCL of 125&#xA0;ms. Arrhythmogenicity was then assessed both during regular stimulation and using an <italic>extrasystolic stimulation protocol</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>] previously adapted for the study of arrhythmogenesis in murine hearts incorporating the <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] and described below. Hearts were then subjected to an adapted <italic>dynamic pacing protocol</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] explained in detail below, and the data obtained used to construct restitution curves.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>All data are presented as means &#xB1; standard errors of the means and include the number of hearts studied. Comparisons between data sets used analysis of variance (significance threshold set at <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&#x2264;&#x2009;0.05). Curve fitting of particular functions to data sets used a Levenberg-Marquardt algorithm (OriginPro 7.5, OriginLab, MA, USA).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The experiments made direct measurements of MAPs from intact Langendorff-perfused murine hearts. They compared the extents to which relationships between epicardial and endocardial action potential durations and the slopes of restitution curves are associated with arrhythmogenicity in genetic models of the congenital LQT3 (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>) and of the BrS (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>), and in wild-type (WT) controls. They began by successfully demonstrating that these experimental models recapitulated arrhythmic phenotypes observed clinically as well as confirming the anticipated effects of treatment with clinically-relevant [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>] concentrations of flecainide (1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M) and quinidine (1 or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M). Hearts were exposed to solutions for 20&#xA0;min while stimulated at a constant BCL of 125&#xA0;ms before recording was commenced.</p>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Arrhythmogenicity in WT, <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts subject to both regular and extrasystolic stimulation recapitulates clinical observations</title>
        <p>Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> show results obtained from WT (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c, <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c) hearts treated with control solution (A) and with solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (B), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D). Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> illustrates MAP waveforms recorded from the epicardia of hearts during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure showing arrhythmic waveforms in situations where arrhythmic activity was observed in &gt;50% of cases; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> quantifies the incidence of such arrhythmic activity both during regular stimulation (i) and during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure (ii).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Arrhythmic activity resulting from extrasystolic stimulation. Epicardial monophasic action potential (MAP) recordings illustrating the result of the application of extrasystolic stimuli to WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts treated with control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and with solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>). Traces show arrhythmic activity where this was observed in &#x2265;50% of cases</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig><fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Incidences of arrhythmic activity in WT, <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts subjected to the extrasystolic stimulation procedure. Percentage of WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts demonstrating arrhythmic activity during regular stimulation (i) and during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure (ii). In both these cases, MAPs were obtained during treatment with control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and with solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>). <italic>Hashing</italic> indicates hearts demonstrating arrhythmic activity, and <italic>dots</italic> indicate hearts not demonstrating such activity</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>The frequencies of arrhythmic phenomena in hearts subjected to regular stimulation at a BCL of 125&#xA0;ms were relatively low irrespective of the genetic or pharmacological conditions but were nevertheless consistent with clinical expectations. First, zero out of seven WT hearts (~0%, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, i) exposed to control solution (A) demonstrated arrhythmic activity, while treatment with flecainide (B) led to arrhythmic activity in only one out of six (~17%) cases. Furthermore, such hearts never showed arrhythmic activity during treatment with 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C, zero out of six hearts, ~0%) and again did so in only one out of six cases (~17%) with 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D). Secondly, arrhythmic activity did occur in one out of six (~17%) <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b) treated with control solution (A) and was absent in all cases (zero out of six hearts, ~0%) during treatment with flecainide (B). Arrhythmic activity was not observed (zero out of four hearts, ~0%) during treatment with 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C) but did occur in one out of five hearts (~20%) exposed to 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D). Thirdly, two out of nine <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts (~22%, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c) exhibited arrhythmic activity during exposure to control solution (A). Such arrhythmic activity was also observed in one out of five hearts (~20%) treated with flecainide (B). Arrhythmic activity was then absent after treatment with either 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M (C) or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M (D) quinidine (zero out of five, 0%, and zero out of six, 0%, hearts, respectively).</p>
        <p>In contrast, extrasystolic stimulation (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref> and <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii) revealed clearer trends in arrhythmogenicity in full agreement with clinical expectations. First, while zero out of seven WT hearts (0%, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, ii) exposed to control solution (A) exhibited arrhythmic activity, treatment with flecainide (B) increased the incidence of such events to two out of six hearts (~33%). Furthermore, exposure to 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C) resulted in arrhythmic activity in four out of eight hearts (~50%), while exposure to 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D) resulted in arrhythmic activity in three out of six hearts (~50%). Secondly, one out of five <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts (~20%, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, ii) demonstrated arrhythmic activity during exposure to either control solution (A) or flecainide (B). However, exposure to quinidine resulted in arrhythmic activity in three out of five hearts (~60%) at 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M (C) and four out of four hearts (~100%) at 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M (D). Thirdly, <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, ii) demonstrated such arrhythmic activity in three out of nine cases (~33%) during treatment with control solution (A) but in five out of six cases (~83%) during treatment with flecainide (B). Furthermore, arrhythmic activity was observed in only one out of six such hearts (~17%) during treatment with 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C) and in zero out of six hearts during exposure to 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Graphical analyses of arrhythmogenic tendency</title>
        <p>In an effort to explore the possible basis for these arrhythmic phenomena, subsequent experiments made systematic measurements of epicardial and endocardial action potential durations (at 90% repolarization, APD<sub>90</sub>s) during a dynamic pacing protocol [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. This consisted of cycles each comprising 100 stimuli, initially delivered at a BCL of 175&#xA0;ms. BCL was then decremented in 50-ms steps with each subsequent cycle until a reproducible sequence of consistently shaped MAP waveforms was no longer obtained. Steady states were consistently reached within the first 50 responses, and therefore mean values of APD<sub>90</sub> were obtained from the final 50 action potentials in each cycle. This approach provided data that could be used to evaluate over the full range of BCLs the relationship between arrhythmogenicity and two possible electrophysiological properties. Thus it was possible first to evaluate transmural repolarization gradients and secondly to evaluate slopes of restitution curves relating APD<sub>90</sub> to the preceding DI, given by BCL minus APD<sub>90</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Relationships between epicardial and endocardial action potential durations are not consistently associated with either the presence or absence of arrhythmogenicity</title>
        <p>Alterations in relationship between epicardial and endocardial APD<sub>90</sub> determined at a single BCL has previously been associated with arrhythmogenicity in hearts obtained from our <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> mice [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. The present study now extends this analysis from a single BCL to a range of BCLs and applies it to <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts for the first time, plotting endocardial APD<sub>90</sub> on the abscissa and epicardial APD<sub>90</sub> on the ordinate over the full range of BCLs investigated (triangles, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Such plots have previously been used to assess arrhythmogenicity in hypokalaemic WT murine hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and provided possible criteria for arrhythmogenicity. The control plot obtained from WT hearts perfused with control solution (six hearts, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a, A) gave a quadratic relationship between endocardial and epicardial APD<sub>90</sub> (solid line), in agreement with previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Thus the curve <italic>y</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;<italic>ax</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x2009;+&#x2009;<italic>bx</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;<italic>c</italic>, where <italic>a</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.0097&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0028, <italic>b</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.46&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.27 and <italic>c</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;&#x2212;5.06&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.34, gave a reduced <italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup> of 0.49. Repeating the regression analysis this time fitting the line <italic>y</italic> = <italic>mx</italic> + <italic>c</italic> gave a reduced <italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup> of 0.86, and permitted the derivation of an <italic>F</italic> statistic for the appropriate, <italic>N</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#x2009;=&#x2009;17 data points, given by <inline-formula id="IEq1"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 424_2007_326_Article_IEq1.gif --><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ F_{\chi }  = N{\left( {\frac{{\chi _{2} ^{2}  - \chi _{3} ^{2} }} {{\chi _{3} ^{2} }}} \right)} $$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> in which the subscripts on the right-hand side of the equation denote the number of parameters involved [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This yielded a probability of exceeding <italic>F</italic> of &lt;0.05, suggesting that inclusion of the quadratic term was justified, again in full agreement with the previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>].
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Relationships between epicardial and endocardial action potential durations (at 90% repolarization, APD<sub>90</sub>s) obtained over a range of baseline cycle lengths. WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts were exposed to control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and to solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>) and stimulated at baseline cycle lengths of between 80&#xA0;ms and 175&#xA0;ms. <italic>Broken lines</italic> indicate reference curves constructed by least-squares fitting of the equation <italic>y</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;<italic>ax</italic><sup>2</sup>&#x2009;+&#x2009;<italic>bx</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;<italic>c</italic> to data points obtained from wild-type hearts treated with control solution</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>Data points obtained under the range of genetic and pharmacological conditions studied could then be compared with this reference curve (broken lines, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>) with the expectation that the departure of points to the left of this curve might be associated with arrhythmogenicity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. However, data sets obtained before and after the pharmacological manoeuvres satisfied this expectation in WT but clearly failed to do so in the remaining genetically modified hearts.</p>
        <p>First, treatment of WT hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) with flecainide (five hearts, B), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (six hearts, C) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (six hearts, D) all resulted in points falling to the left of the reference curve, <italic>in parallel with</italic> the occurrence of arrhythmic activity under these conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a, B, C and D). Secondly, data points obtained from <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b) treated with control solution (five hearts, A) again fell to the left of the reference curve <italic>in contrast with</italic> the low incidence of arrhythmic activity in this setting (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, A). This pattern was maintained when such hearts were exposed to flecainide (five hearts, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, B), once again in contrast with the low frequency which arrhythmic activity was observed under these conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, B). Exposure to 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (five hearts, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, C) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (six hearts, D) again both resulted in points falling to the left of the control curve, this time in parallel with the high incidence of arrhythmic activity in these settings (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b, C and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, D). Thirdly, data points obtained from <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c) treated with control solution (six hearts, A) consistently fell on the reference curve, in contrast with the occurrence of arrhythmic activity in this setting (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, A). Furthermore, treatment with flecainide (six hearts, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, B) failed to result in a left-shift of data points, in contrast with the large increase in the incidence of arrhythmic activity (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, B). In addition, points obtained during treatment with either 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (five hearts, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, C) or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (seven hearts, D) again fell to the left of the reference curve, in contrast with the anti-arrhythmic effect of this agent demonstrated in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c, C and D.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>Alterations in the slopes of restitution curves correlate with the presence and absence of arrhythmic activity</title>
        <p>Restitution curves (data points, left ordinate) were then plotted using the APD<sub>90</sub> (left ordinate) and DI data obtained during the dynamic pacing protocol from the epicardia (circles, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>) and endocardia (squares, Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>) of WT (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>c, <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c) hearts for the first time. Hearts were studied during treatment with control solution (A) and with solutions containing flecainide (B), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (C) or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (D). Under all conditions, epicardial and endocardial APD<sub>90</sub> both decreased as DI decreased. Increases or decreases in the slopes of such relationships were in full agreement with the presence or absence of arrhythmic activity under all conditions studied.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Epicardial restitution curves plotting action potential duration (at 90% repolarization, APD<sub>90</sub>) against preceding diastolic interval (DI). Data were obtained from the epicardia (<italic>circles</italic>) of WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts exposed to control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and to solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>). Curves are fitted with mono-exponential growth functions obtained by least squares fitting to the experimental values of APD<sub>90</sub> and DI (<italic>solid lines</italic>, <italic>left ordinates</italic>). Gradients were obtained by differentiation of the fitted functions (<italic>broken lines</italic>, <italic>right axes</italic>). <italic>Shaded boxes</italic> indicate ranges of DI values at which such gradients exceed unity</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig><fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Endocardial restitution curves plotting action potential duration (at 90% repolarization, APD<sub>90</sub>) against preceding diastolic interval (DI). Data were obtained from the endocardia (<italic>squares</italic>) of WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts exposed to control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and to solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>). Curves are fitted with mono-exponential growth functions obtained by least squares fitting to the experimental values of APD<sub>90</sub> and DI (<italic>solid lines</italic>, <italic>left ordinates</italic>). Gradients were obtained by differentiation of the fitted functions (<italic>broken lines</italic>, <italic>right axes</italic>). <italic>Shaded boxes</italic> indicate ranges of DI values at which such gradients exceed unity</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Restitution curves yield parameters predictive of arrhythmogenicity</title>
        <p>To permit quantitative analysis, simple mono-exponential growth functions, as used previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], were fitted to the experimental data. These took the form:
<disp-formula id="Equ1"><label>1</label><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$y = y_{0}  + A{\left( {1 - e^{{{ - x} \mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{ - x} \tau }} \right. \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} \tau }} } \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>where <italic>y</italic> represents APD<sub>90</sub>, <italic>x</italic> represents DI, and <italic>y</italic><sub><italic>0</italic></sub>, <italic>A</italic> and <italic>&#x3C4;</italic> are constants obtained by least squares fitting to the experimental values of APD<sub>90</sub> and DI in each case. These fitted parameters, along with corresponding reduced <italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup> values, are shown in Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> (epicardium) and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> (endocardium). Curve fits performed on data sets obtained by separating successive odd- and even-numbered action potentials yielded statistically indistinguishable (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05) parameters in all cases (Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref> and <xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>) thus eliminating the possibility of error arising as a result of averaging. The corresponding gradients were then given by:
<disp-formula id="Equ2"><label>2</label><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ \frac{{dy}} {{dx}} = \frac{A} {\tau } \cdot e^{{ - x/\tau }}  $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>and take their largest values at the shortest BCLs studied.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Fit parameters for epicardial restitution curves</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Condition</th><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>WT (6 hearts)</td><td>1.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.4</td><td>56.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.4</td><td>58.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.8</td><td>1.4</td></tr><tr><td>WT + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;16.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.4</td><td>104.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.1</td><td>82.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;28.0</td><td>5.9</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;38.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;17.4</td><td>92.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.7</td><td>45.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.4</td><td>2.5</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;863.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,387.1</td><td>981.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,369.1</td><td>27.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15.9</td><td>113.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;19.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.2</td><td>90.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.4</td><td>53.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.7</td><td>14.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;16.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.5</td><td>82.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.3</td><td>95.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;42.1</td><td>3.5</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;677.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;306.1</td><td>748.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;304.7</td><td>15.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.2</td><td>10.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;674.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;329.9</td><td>729.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;329.1</td><td>14.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.1</td><td>8.4</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> + flecainide (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;56,359.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2,559.7</td><td>52,677.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.2</td><td>7.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.5</td><td>14.8</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;118.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;57.4</td><td>202.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;49.4</td><td>36.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.5</td><td>16.7</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (7 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;44.7</td><td>131.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;62.3</td><td>158.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;262.2</td><td>10.8</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results of least-squares fits to the function <inline-formula id="IEq2"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 424_2007_326_Article_IEq2.gif --><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$y = y_{0}  + A{\left( {1 - e^{{{ - x} \mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{ - x} \tau }} \right. \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} \tau }} } \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> under the conditions indicated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Fit parameters for endocardial restitution curves</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Condition</th><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>WT (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;11.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.7</td><td>73.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.7</td><td>65.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.4</td><td>1.2</td></tr><tr><td>WT + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;769.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;244.1</td><td>827.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;243.7</td><td>14.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3</td><td>1.4</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;65.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;100.4</td><td>113.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;98.3</td><td>24.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.0</td><td>11.7</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;41.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;71.5</td><td>78.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;68.7</td><td>32.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;19.3</td><td>13.6</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;31.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.0</td><td>109.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.1</td><td>49.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.0</td><td>10.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;561.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2</td><td>631.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15.1</td><td>18.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.3</td><td>6.7</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;499.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;143.8</td><td>563.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;142.9</td><td>16.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6</td><td>56.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;281.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.8</td><td>43.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.4</td><td>48.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;19.0</td><td>4.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> + flecainide (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1,050.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,558.5</td><td>1,100.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,557.8</td><td>11.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.0</td><td>10.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;261.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;117.9</td><td>350.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;107.8</td><td>34.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.3</td><td>21.7</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (7 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;220.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;322.0</td><td>319.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;316.8</td><td>26.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.7</td><td>45.5</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results of least-squares fits to the function <inline-formula id="IEq3"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 424_2007_326_Article_IEq3.gif --><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$y = y_{0}  + A{\left( {1 - e^{{{ - x} \mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{ - x} \tau }} \right. \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} \tau }} } \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> under the conditions indicated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Fit parameters for endocardial restitution curves separating successive odd- and even-numbered action potentials</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Condition</th><th colspan="4">Odd</th><th colspan="4">Even</th></tr><tr><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>WT (6 hearts)</td><td>13.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.6</td><td>40.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.9</td><td>50.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;21.4</td><td>6.3</td><td>8.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.2</td><td>58.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;25.4</td><td>48.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;32.3</td><td>4.6</td></tr><tr><td>WT + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;14.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.9</td><td>105.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.0</td><td>88.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;31.3</td><td>5.8</td><td>&#x2212;44.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;18.5</td><td>117.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.2</td><td>49.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.9</td><td>1.5</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;20.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.9</td><td>75.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.2</td><td>56.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.2</td><td>3.8</td><td>&#x2212;34.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.7</td><td>89.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.3</td><td>45.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.8</td><td>3.3</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1,391.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,195.9</td><td>1,496.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,182.0</td><td>21.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.3</td><td>117.9</td><td>&#x2212;393.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.3.0</td><td>532.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;481.7</td><td>41.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;27.6</td><td>115.7</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;23.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.3</td><td>92.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.3</td><td>47.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.0</td><td>12.4</td><td>&#x2212;24.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.6</td><td>92.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.6</td><td>47.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.9</td><td>11.8</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>14.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.3</td><td>77.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.4</td><td>84.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;32.2</td><td>3.4</td><td>&#x2212;33.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;46.4</td><td>110.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;41.9</td><td>36.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.1</td><td>2.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;250.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.8</td><td>483.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;24.5</td><td>18.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.8</td><td>12.4</td><td>&#x2212;254.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;321.2</td><td>328.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;318.3</td><td>20.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.7</td><td>5.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;850.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;282.7</td><td>904.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;282.1</td><td>13.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.3</td><td>4.3</td><td>&#x2212;913.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;283.3</td><td>968.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;282.7</td><td>13.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2</td><td>3.7</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> + flecainide (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1,473.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,144.5</td><td>1,534.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2,141.2</td><td>14.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.6</td><td>34.3</td><td>&#x2212;2,108.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4,489.9</td><td>2,171.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4,486.8</td><td>14.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.7</td><td>35.0</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;46.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;51.2</td><td>146.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;21.3</td><td>59.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;43.5</td><td>9.4</td><td>&#x2212;46.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;50.6</td><td>149.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;20.2</td><td>61.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;44.2</td><td>9.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (7 hearts)</td><td>7.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;34.2</td><td>167.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;264.8</td><td>272.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;78.3</td><td>10.8</td><td>2.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;44.6</td><td>143.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;121.3</td><td>192.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;405.8</td><td>12.0</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results of least-squares fits to the function <inline-formula id="IEq4"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 424_2007_326_Article_IEq4.gif --><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$y = y_{0}  + A{\left( {1 - e^{{{ - x} \mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{ - x} \tau }} \right. \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} \tau }} } \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> under the conditions indicated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Fit parameters for endocardial restitution curves separating successive odd- and even-numbered action potentials</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2">Condition</th><th colspan="4">Odd</th><th colspan="4">Even</th></tr><tr><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th><th><italic>y</italic><sub>0</sub> (ms)</th><th><italic>A</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C4;</italic> (ms)</th><th><italic>&#x3C7;</italic><sup>2</sup></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>WT (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;17.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.3</td><td>73.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.8</td><td>67.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.5</td><td>4.7</td><td>&#x2212;38.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15.4</td><td>91.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.0</td><td>46.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.5</td><td>1.8</td></tr><tr><td>WT + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;49.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;26.2</td><td>113.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;23.0</td><td>35.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.2</td><td>7.6</td><td>&#x2212;367.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;171.3</td><td>426.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;170.6</td><td>17.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.4</td><td>1.3</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;393.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;368.6</td><td>437.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;368.6</td><td>14.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.3</td><td>18.1</td><td>&#x2212;1,337.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,206.4</td><td>1,384.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,205.7</td><td>11.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.5</td><td>14.7</td></tr><tr><td>WT&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;17.7&#x2009;+&#x2009;&#x2212;39.0</td><td>53.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;35.0</td><td>42.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;28.9</td><td>11.2</td><td>&#x2212;28.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;62.7</td><td>66.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;58.2</td><td>39.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;29.7</td><td>17.3</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;149.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;131.4</td><td>221.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;128.6</td><td>26.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.6</td><td>0.9</td><td>&#x2212;42.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.5</td><td>115.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.2</td><td>40.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.0</td><td>2.6</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> + flecainide (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1,133.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;784.2</td><td>1,201.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;783.1</td><td>15.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.6</td><td>2.0</td><td>&#x2212;2,164.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,195.7</td><td>2,233.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,195.0</td><td>13.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.6</td><td>1.4</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;2,720.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,917.8</td><td>2,779.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,917.2</td><td>10.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.8</td><td>3.4</td><td>&#x2212;3,527.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4,674.78</td><td>3,603.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4,674.1</td><td>11.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.7</td><td>3.9</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;134.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;28.9</td><td>195.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;28.0</td><td>22.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.1</td><td>3.3</td><td>&#x2212;149.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;33.5</td><td>212.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;32.6</td><td>22.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.2</td><td>3.6</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> + flecainide (6 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;13.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;29.2</td><td>66.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;27.1</td><td>32.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.1</td><td>1.8</td><td>&#x2212;55.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;55.5</td><td>108.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;54.6</td><td>23.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.9</td><td>1.2</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (5 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;1,979.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,709.0</td><td>2,051.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,704.6</td><td>15.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.8</td><td>13.4</td><td>&#x2212;108.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15,101.8</td><td>10,911.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15,098.3</td><td>11.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.0</td><td>14.8</td></tr><tr><td><italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>&#x2009;+&#x2009;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (7 hearts)</td><td>&#x2212;332.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;447.2</td><td>431.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;439.8</td><td>25.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.7</td><td>116.0</td><td>&#x2212;160.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;289.5</td><td>262.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;281.9</td><td>20.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;18.1</td><td>48.1</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results of least-squares fits to the function <inline-formula id="IEq5"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 424_2007_326_Article_IEq5.gif --><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$y = y_{0}  + A{\left( {1 - e^{{{ - x} \mathord{\left/ {\vphantom {{ - x} \tau }} \right. \kern-\nulldelimiterspace} \tau }} } \right)}$$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> under the conditions indicated</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
        <p>Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> thus superimpose optimisations of Eq.&#xA0;<xref rid="Equ1" ref-type="">1</xref> to the data shown in Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref> and <xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref> (solid lines, left-hand ordinates). Furthermore, they show the corresponding gradients calculated using Eq.&#xA0;<xref rid="Equ2" ref-type="">2</xref> (broken lines, right-hand axes). Shaded regions where present indicate DIs less than the critical DI at which these gradients exceed unity: the existence of such a region is an established criterion for arrhythmogenesis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Critical DI was calculated as:
<disp-formula id="Equ3"><label>3</label><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$ {\text{critical}} \,{\text{DI}} =  - \tau  \cdot \ln {\left( {\frac{\tau } {A}} \right)} $$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula></p>
        <p>Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref> proceeds to show these values of critical DI derived from the fitted values of <italic>A</italic> and <italic>&#x3C4;</italic> for the epicardia (filled bars) and endocardia (open bars) under each of the above conditions. In contrast to the findings from the analysis of the relationships between epicardial and endocardial APD<sub>90</sub>s described above, the present analysis of epicardial and endocardial restitution properties together provided datasets <italic>in complete agreement</italic> with the observed incidences of arrhythmic activity.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Critical diastolic intervals obtained from restitution curves. Critical diastolic intervals at which gradients equalled unity obtained from epicardial (<italic>filled bars</italic>) and endocardial (<italic>open bars</italic>) restitution curves shown in Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref> and <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref> in WT (<bold>a</bold>), <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> (<bold>b</bold>) and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> (<bold>c</bold>) hearts exposed to control solution (<italic>A</italic>) and to solutions containing 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M flecainide (<italic>B</italic>), 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>C</italic>) and 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (<italic>D</italic>). <italic>Asterisks</italic> indicate values that are significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) larger than those recorded in WT hearts exposed to control solution</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="424_2007_326_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
        <p>First, in WT hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) exposed to control solution (A) the critical DI took a value of &#x2212;63.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.41&#xA0;ms in the epicardium and &#x2212;15.43&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.97&#xA0;ms in the endocardium. Treatment with flecainide (B) significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) increased these values to 19.45&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.39&#xA0;ms in the epicardium and 58.75&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;18.71&#xA0;ms in the endocardium. This critical DI was attained in the endocardium (shaded region in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, B), in parallel with the increased incidence of arrhythmogenesis observed during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure under these conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii). Treatment with 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, C) also significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) increased the critical DI in both the epicardium and endocardium (32.30&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.80&#xA0;ms and 27.80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.53&#xA0;ms respectively) in parallel with the observed arrhythmogenicity on extrasystolic stimulation under these conditions (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii), although such values were not attained during the dynamic pacing protocol. Furthermore, treatment with 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, D) again significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) increased these values to 97.20&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;57.90&#xA0;ms in the epicardium and to 28.50&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;34.52&#xA0;ms in the endocardium. This DI was attained in the epicardium in parallel with the observed arrhythmogenicity during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii). Thus, increases in the critical DI are precisely <italic>paralleled</italic> with arrhythmogenicity in WT hearts treated with flecainide and quinidine.</p>
        <p>Secondly, critical DIs obtained from <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b) were always significantly greater than those in WT controls (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05 in all cases) in parallel with the increased incidence of arrhythmic activity observed during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii). Thus, in hearts treated with control solution (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, A) the critical DI increased to 28.04&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.08&#xA0;ms in the epicardium and 39.38&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.28&#xA0;ms in the endocardium: These values were attained in both the epicardium and endocardium in association with the increased incidence of arrhythmic activity on extrasystolic stimulation observed (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii) and in full agreement with clinical expectations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]. Treatment with flecainide (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, B) decreased the epicardial value (&#x2212;14.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.05&#xA0;ms, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05 as compared to hearts treated with control solution) but did not significantly affect the endocardial value (21.41&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.58&#xA0;ms, <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&gt;&#x2009;0.05 as compared to hearts treated with control solution), having no effect on the observed incidence of arrhythmic activity on extrasystolic stimulation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii). However, treatment with 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b, C) significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) increased both epicardial and endocardial values (59.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;26.91&#xA0;ms and 57.64&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;16.68&#xA0;ms, respectively) as compared to those obtained from such hearts treated with control solution, in association with the observed increases in the incidence of arrhythmic activity resulting from extrasystolic stimulation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii) and again in agreement with expectations from clinical work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]. It was not possible to obtain MAPs over a sufficiently wide range of BCLs to permit the construction of such curves in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts treated with 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M quinidine.</p>
        <p>Thirdly, critical DI values were also increased in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c) in association with the increased incidence of arrhythmic activity observed. Thus, in hearts treated with control solution (A), the critical DIs were significantly (<italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) increased as compared to WT controls in both the epicardium and endocardium to 56.00&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;27.79&#xA0;ms and 52.59&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.50&#xA0;ms, respectively. These values were attained in both the epicardium and endocardium, fulfilling clinical expectations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. Treatment with flecainide (B) did not significantly alter these values (68.14&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;24.09&#xA0;ms in the epicardium and 58.56&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.75&#xA0;ms in the endocardium). These were again attained in both epicardium and endocardium in association with the arrhythmic activity observed on extrasystolic stimulation (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii). Furthermore, treatment with quinidine at a concentration of 1&#xA0;&#x3BC;M (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c, C) had no significant effect on critical DIs in either the epicardium or endocardium (62.45&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;29.74&#xA0;ms and 79.63&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;39.31&#xA0;ms, respectively). These values were again attained in both epicardium and endocardium. However, treatment with quinidine at 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;M significantly decreased both epicardial and endocardial critical DIs, such that they became statistically indistinguishable from WT controls (29.01&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.27&#xA0;ms and &#x2212;80&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.58&#xA0;ms, respectively). This was associated with the complete absence of arrhythmogenesis during the extrasystolic stimulation procedure (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>, ii).</p>
        <p>Thus, while relationships between epicardial and endocardial action potential durations obtained over a range of cycle lengths are poorly correlated with arrhythmogenicity, restitution curves are, in general, predictive of arrhythmogenicity under the genetic and pharmacological conditions studied.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec15" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>The congenital LQT3 and the BrS constitute two important examples of genetic causes for ventricular arrhythmia and sudden cardiac death [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. These conditions result from similarly targeted mutations in the <italic>SCN5a</italic> gene coding for the cardiac Na<sup>+</sup> channel: gain-of-function mutations are characteristic of LQT3, while loss-of-function mutations are characteristic of BrS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
      <p>The present study began by using the MAP technique to verify that Langendorff-perfused murine hearts modelling LQT3 (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>] and BrS (<italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic>) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] recapitulated features of the incidence of arrhythmic activity reported clinically. These results were in full agreement with previous physiological and pharmacological findings from our LQT3 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>] and BrS [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>] models. Epicardial and endocardial MAP recordings were then used to evaluate the applicability of two established criteria in predicting arrhythmogenicity in these models over the full physiological range of heart rates (quantified as baseline cycle lengths, BCLs).</p>
      <p>Transmural dispersion of repolarization was studied over a range of BCLs by comparing epicardial and endocardial action potential durations (at 90% repolarization, APD<sub>90</sub>s) in the two genetic models. Such an analysis had previously been demonstrated to reveal arrhythmogenicity in hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Furthermore, changes in this relationship investigated <italic>at a single</italic> BCL had previously been associated with arrhythmogenicity in our <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Plots of epicardial against endocardial APD<sub>90</sub> in WT hearts treated with control solution gave reference relationships best fitted by a quadratic function, in full agreement with previous work [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Treatment of such WT hearts with either quinidine or flecainide resulted in the data points falling to the left of the reference curves, reflecting increased transmural repolarization gradients, in association with increased incidences of arrhythmic activity and again in full agreement with a previous study [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. However, such plots failed to consistently predict the presence or absence of arrhythmogenicity in the <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts. Such left-shifting of points was observed in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts under <italic>all</italic> pharmacological conditions studied, despite the established anti-arrhythmic effect of flecainide in this setting. Furthermore, data points obtained from <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts treated with control solution fell <italic>on</italic> the reference curve despite the <italic>increased</italic> incidence of arrhythmic activity observed. Treatment with flecainide <italic>failed</italic> to result in a left-shift of points, despite its established <italic>pro</italic>-arrhythmic effect; treatment with quinidine <italic>did</italic> result in such a shift, despite its <italic>anti</italic>-arrhythmic effect.</p>
      <p>These discrepancies prompted an investigation for alternative criteria for arrhythmogenicity. We therefore explored the applicability of a second approach involving restitution curves plotting APD<sub>90</sub> against the preceding DI. Arrhythmic activity occurring in a range of settings has previously been associated with increases in the slopes of such curves to greater than unity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]. Such an association has been demonstrated in a canine pharmacological model of the congenital long QT syndrome type 2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>] but has not previously been studied in <italic>any</italic> models of LQT3 or BrS in <italic>any</italic> species. Furthermore, decreases in the slopes of such curves have been associated with the effects of clinically important anti-arrhythmic drugs, including the class 1A agent procainamide in a canine model [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. However, such slopes have not been examined in relation to either quinidine or flecainide, nor have any such studies previously been attempted in murine models. This study accordingly proceeded to construct epicardial and endocardial restitution curves for the first time in a murine system and in relation to LQT3 or BrS in <italic>any</italic> species.</p>
      <p>In contrast to the previous criterion, epicardial and endocardial restitution curves taken together yielded parameters in precise agreement with the presence or absence of arrhythmic phenomena demonstrated. In WT hearts, treatment with either quinidine or flecainide significantly increased the critical DI at which the slopes of the restitution curves exceeded unity, in full agreement with the increased incidences of arrhythmic activity observed. Not only did the <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> mutations result in significant increases in critical DI in association with increased rates of arrhythmic activity, but quinidine and flecainide exerted contrasting effects on this critical DI in agreement with clinical expectations in both cases. Thus, in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> hearts, treatment with quinidine increased critical DIs in association with its pro-arrhythmic effect. Furthermore, in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> hearts, treatment with quinidine decreased critical DIs in association with the decreased incidence of arrhythmic activity observed, while treatment with flecainide had the opposite effect. Thus class 1A agents may result in either increases (quinidine in WT and <italic>Scn5a+/&#x394;</italic> murine hearts) or decreases (quinidine in <italic>Scn5a+/&#x2212;</italic> murine hearts and procainamide in canine hearts) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] in the critical DI: Such changes are in full agreement with effects on arrhythmogenicity in all cases.</p>
      <p>Taken together, these results demonstrate that criteria considering effects on the slopes of restitution curves successfully account for arrhythmogenicity in murine models of arrhythmic syndromes resulting from mutations in the <italic>Scn5a</italic> Na<sup>+</sup> channel, as well as for the effects of quinidine and flecainide on such arrhythmogenicity. These observations might form the basis for future clinical explorations of the utility of restitution curves obtained using the MAP technique [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] in the assessment of arrhythmic propensity in hereditary arrhythmic syndromes. Such a robust means of assessing arrhythmogenicity might be particularly useful given the known variable expressivity of the arrhythmic phenotype in patients harbouring such mutations [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>We thank the James Baird Fund, the Frank Elmore Fund, the Medical Research Council, the Wellcome Trust, the British Heart Foundation and Downing College, Cambridge for their generous support. Ian N. Sabir and Lucia M. Li have contributed equally to this work.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Antzelevitch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brugada</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brugada</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brugada</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Towbin</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nademanee</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brugada syndrome: 1992&#x2013;2002: A historical perspective</article-title>
          <source>J Am Coll Cardiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>1665</fpage>
          <lpage>1671</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0735-1097(03)00310-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Antzelevitch C, Brugada P, Brugada J, Brugada R, Towbin JA, Nademanee K (2003) Brugada syndrome: 1992&#x2013;2002: A historical perspective. J Am Coll Cardiol 41:1665&#x2013;1671 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12767644</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Antzelevitch C, Burashnikov A, Di Diego JM (2003) Cellular and ionic mechanisms underlying arrhythmogenesis. In: Cardiac repolarization: bridging basic and clinical science. Humana Press, Totowa, N.J</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Antzelevitch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>GX</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shimizu</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transmural dispersion of repolarization and arrhythmogenicity: the Brugada syndrome versus the long QT syndrome</article-title>
          <source>J Electrocardiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <issue>Suppl</issue>
          <fpage>158</fpage>
          <lpage>165</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0022-0736(99)90074-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Antzelevitch C, Yan GX, Shimizu W (1999) Transmural dispersion of repolarization and arrhythmogenicity: the Brugada syndrome versus the long QT syndrome. J Electrocardiol 32(Suppl):158&#x2013;165 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10688320</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Balasubramaniam</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saumarez</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenberg</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electrogram prolongation and nifedipine-suppressible ventricular arrhythmias in mice following targeted disruption of KCNE1</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>552</volume>
          <fpage>535</fpage>
          <lpage>546</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2003.048249</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Balasubramaniam R, Grace AA, Saumarez RC, Vandenberg JI, Huang CL (2003) Electrogram prolongation and nifedipine-suppressible ventricular arrhythmias in mice following targeted disruption of KCNE1. J Physiol 552:535&#x2013;546 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14561835</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bevington</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Data reduction and error analysis for the physical sciences</source>
          <year>1969</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>McGraw-Hill</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bevington PR (1969) Data reduction and error analysis for the physical sciences. McGraw-Hill, New York </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Birkett</surname>
              <given-names>DJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Therapeutic drug monitoring</article-title>
          <source>Aust Prescr</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>9</fpage>
          <lpage>11</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Birkett DJ (1997) Therapeutic drug monitoring. Aust Prescr 20:9&#x2013;11 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brugada</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Use of intravenous antiarrhythmics to identify concealed Brugada syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Curr Control Trials Cardiovasc Med</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>45</fpage>
          <lpage>47</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/CVM-1-1-045</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brugada R (2000) Use of intravenous antiarrhythmics to identify concealed Brugada syndrome. Curr Control Trials Cardiovasc Med 1(1):45&#x2013;47 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11714408</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Casimiro</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Knollmann</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ebert</surname>
              <given-names>SN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vary</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greene</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franz</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grinberg</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>SP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pfeifer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Targeted disruption of the Kcnq1 gene produces a mouse model of Jervell and Lange-Nielsen Syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>2526</fpage>
          <lpage>2531</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.041398998</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Casimiro MC, Knollmann BC, Ebert SN, Vary JC Jr, Greene AE, Franz MR, Grinberg A, Huang SP, Pfeifer K (2001) Targeted disruption of the Kcnq1 gene produces a mouse model of Jervell and Lange-Nielsen Syndrome. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 98:2526&#x2013;2531 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11226272</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Farkas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Curtis</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Limited antifibrillatory effectiveness of clinically relevant concentrations of class I antiarrhythmics in isolated perfused rat hearts</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>39</volume>
          <fpage>412</fpage>
          <lpage>424</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00005344-200203000-00013</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Farkas A, Curtis MJ (2002) Limited antifibrillatory effectiveness of clinically relevant concentrations of class I antiarrhythmics in isolated perfused rat hearts. J Cardiovasc Pharmacol 39:412&#x2013;424 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11862121</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez del Pozo</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perez-Vizcaino</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zaragoza</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tamargo</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of several class I antiarrhythmic drugs on isolated rat aortic vascular smooth muscle</article-title>
          <source>Gen Pharmacol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>29</volume>
          <fpage>539</fpage>
          <lpage>543</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-3623(96)00517-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fernandez del Pozo B, Perez-Vizcaino F, Fernandez C, Zaragoza F, Tamargo J (1997) Effects of several class I antiarrhythmic drugs on isolated rat aortic vascular smooth muscle. Gen Pharmacol 29:539&#x2013;543 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9352299</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garfinkel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voroshilovsky</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kil</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karagueuzian</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Preventing ventricular fibrillation by flattening cardiac restitution</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>6061</fpage>
          <lpage>6066</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.090492697</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Garfinkel A, Kim YH, Voroshilovsky O, Qu Z, Kil JR, Lee MH, Karagueuzian HS, Weiss JN, Chen PS (2000) Preventing ventricular fibrillation by flattening cardiac restitution. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 97:6061&#x2013;6066 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10811880</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Camm</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Quinidine</article-title>
          <source>N Engl J Med</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>338</volume>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>45</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1056/NEJM199801013380107</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grace AA, Camm AJ (1998) Quinidine. N Engl J Med 338:35&#x2013;45 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9414330</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Head</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balasubramaniam</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lei</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colledge</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paced electrogram fractionation analysis of arrhythmogenic tendency in DeltaKPQ Scn5a mice</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>1329</fpage>
          <lpage>1340</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Head CE, Balasubramaniam R, Thomas G, Goddard CA, Lei M, Colledge WH, Grace AA, Huang CL (2005) Paced electrogram fractionation analysis of arrhythmogenic tendency in DeltaKPQ Scn5a mice. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol 16:1329&#x2013;1340 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16403066</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Karagueuzian</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Khan</surname>
              <given-names>SS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kobayashi</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Denton</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mandel</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Diamond</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Action potential alternans and irregular dynamics in quinidine-intoxicated ventricular muscle cells. Implications for ventricular proarrhythmia</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>1661</fpage>
          <lpage>1672</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Karagueuzian HS, Khan SS, Hong K, Kobayashi Y, Denton T, Mandel WJ, Diamond GA (1993) Action potential alternans and irregular dynamics in quinidine-intoxicated ventricular muscle cells. Implications for ventricular proarrhythmia. Circulation 87:1661&#x2013;1672 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8491022</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Killeen</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gurung</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraser</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mahaut-Smith</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colledge</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Arrhythmogenic mechanisms in the isolated perfused hypokalemic murine heart</article-title>
          <source>Acta Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>189</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1748-1716.2006.01643.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Killeen M, Thomas G, Gurung I, Goddard C, Fraser J, Mahaut-Smith M, Colledge H, Grace A, Huang C (2007) Arrhythmogenic mechanisms in the isolated perfused hypokalemic murine heart. Acta Physiol 189:33&#x2013;46 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Knollmann</surname>
              <given-names>BC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katchman</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Franz</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Monophasic action potential recordings from intact mouse heart: validation, regional heterogeneity, and relation to refractoriness</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>12</volume>
          <fpage>1286</fpage>
          <lpage>1294</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1540-8167.2001.01286.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Knollmann BC, Katchman AN, Franz MR (2001) Monophasic action potential recordings from intact mouse heart: validation, regional heterogeneity, and relation to refractoriness. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol 12:1286&#x2013;1294 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11761418</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koller</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riccio</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmour</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dynamic restitution of action potential duration during electrical alternans and ventricular fibrillation</article-title>
          <source>Am J Physiol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>275</volume>
          <fpage>H1635</fpage>
          <lpage>H1642</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Koller ML, Riccio ML, Gilmour RF Jr (1998) Dynamic restitution of action potential duration during electrical alternans and ventricular fibrillation. Am J Physiol 275:H1635&#x2013;H1642 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9815071</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Koller</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Riccio</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmour</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of [K<sup>+</sup>]<sub>o</sub> on electrical restitution and activation dynamics during ventricular fibrillation</article-title>
          <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <fpage>H2665</fpage>
          <lpage>H2672</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Koller ML, Riccio ML, Gilmour RF Jr (2000) Effects of [K+]o on electrical restitution and activation dynamics during ventricular fibrillation. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol 279:H2665&#x2013;H2672 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11087219</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kamjoo</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hough</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fan</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fishbein</surname>
              <given-names>MC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bonometti</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikeda</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karagueuzian</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reentrant wave fronts in Wiggers&#x2019; stage II ventricular fibrillation. Characteristics and mechanisms of termination and spontaneous regeneration</article-title>
          <source>Circ Res</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>660</fpage>
          <lpage>675</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lee JJ, Kamjoo K, Hough D, Hwang C, Fan W, Fishbein MC, Bonometti C, Ikeda T, Karagueuzian HS, Chen PS (1996) Reentrant wave fronts in Wiggers&#x2019; stage II ventricular fibrillation. Characteristics and mechanisms of termination and spontaneous regeneration. Circ Res 78:660&#x2013;675 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8635224</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lukas</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antzelevitch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Phase 2 reentry as a mechanism of initiation of circus movement reentry in canine epicardium exposed to simulated ischemia</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>32</volume>
          <fpage>593</fpage>
          <lpage>603</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0008-6363(96)00115-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lukas A, Antzelevitch C (1996) Phase 2 reentry as a mechanism of initiation of circus movement reentry in canine epicardium exposed to simulated ischemia. Cardiovasc Res 32:593&#x2013;603 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8881520</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Milberg</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reinsch</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wasmer</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Monnig</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stypmann</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osada</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breithardt</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haverkamp</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckardt</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transmural dispersion of repolarization as a key factor of arrhythmogenicity in a novel intact heart model of LQT3</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>65</volume>
          <fpage>397</fpage>
          <lpage>404</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cardiores.2004.10.016</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Milberg P, Reinsch N, Wasmer K, Monnig G, Stypmann J, Osada N, Breithardt G, Haverkamp W, Eckardt L (2005) Transmural dispersion of repolarization as a key factor of arrhythmogenicity in a novel intact heart model of LQT3. Cardiovasc Res 65:397&#x2013;404 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15639478</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Moss A, Windle J, Hall W, Zareba W, Robinson J, McNitt S, Severski P, Rosero S, Daubert J, Qi M, Cieciorka M, Manalan A (2005) Safety and efficacy of flecainide in subjects with Long QT-3 syndrome (KPQ mutation): a randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled clinical trial. Annals of Non-invasive Electrocardiology 10(suppl):59&#x2013;66</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Moss</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kass</surname>
              <given-names>RS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long QT syndrome: from channels to cardiac arrhythmias</article-title>
          <source>J Clin Invest</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>115</volume>
          <fpage>2018</fpage>
          <lpage>2024</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1172/JCI25537</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Moss AJ, Kass RS (2005) Long QT syndrome: from channels to cardiac arrhythmias. J Clin Invest 115:2018&#x2013;2024 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16075042</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Napolitano</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Priori</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brugada Syndrome</article-title>
          <source>Orphanet J Rare Dis</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>35</fpage>
          <lpage>40</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1750-1172-1-35</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Napolitano C, Priori S (2006) Brugada Syndrome. Orphanet J Rare Dis 1:35&#x2013;40 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16972995</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nolasco</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahlen</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A graphic method for the study of alternation in cardiac action potentials</article-title>
          <source>J Appl Physiol</source>
          <year>1968</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>191</fpage>
          <lpage>196</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nolasco JB, Dahlen RW (1968) A graphic method for the study of alternation in cardiac action potentials. J Appl Physiol 25:191&#x2013;196 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">5666097</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Omichi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naik</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garfinkel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>SF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karagueuzian</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of amiodarone on wave front dynamics during ventricular fibrillation in isolated swine right ventricle</article-title>
          <source>Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>282</volume>
          <fpage>H1063</fpage>
          <lpage>H1070</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Omichi C, Zhou S, Lee MH, Naik A, Chang CM, Garfinkel A, Weiss JN, Lin SF, Karagueuzian HS, Chen PS (2002) Effects of amiodarone on wave front dynamics during ventricular fibrillation in isolated swine right ventricle. Am J Physiol Heart Circ Physiol 282:H1063&#x2013;H1070 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11834505</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Opthof</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coronel</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transmural dispersion in LQT3 and arrhythmogenesis</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>336</fpage>
          <lpage>337</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.cardiores.2005.07.006</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Opthof T, Coronel R (2005) Transmural dispersion in LQT3 and arrhythmogenesis. Cardiovasc Res 68:336&#x2013;337, author reply 338&#x2013;339 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16054611</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pak</surname>
              <given-names>HN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwang</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Park</surname>
              <given-names>SW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ahn</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moo Ro</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>YH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spatial dispersion of action potential duration restitution kinetics is associated with induction of ventricular tachycardia/fibrillation in humans</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1357</fpage>
          <lpage>1363</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1540-8167.2004.03569.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pak HN, Hong SJ, Hwang GS, Lee HS, Park SW, Ahn JC, Moo Ro Y, Kim YH (2004) Spatial dispersion of action potential duration restitution kinetics is associated with induction of ventricular tachycardia/fibrillation in humans. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol 15:1357&#x2013;1363 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15610278</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papadatos</surname>
              <given-names>GA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wallerstein</surname>
              <given-names>PM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Head</surname>
              <given-names>CE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ratcliff</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brady</surname>
              <given-names>PA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Benndorf</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saumarez</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Trezise</surname>
              <given-names>AE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vandenberg</surname>
              <given-names>JI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colledge</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Slowed conduction and ventricular tachycardia after targeted disruption of the cardiac sodium channel gene Scn5a</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>6210</fpage>
          <lpage>6215</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.082121299</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Papadatos GA, Wallerstein PM, Head CE, Ratcliff R, Brady PA, Benndorf K, Saumarez RC, Trezise AE, Huang CL, Vandenberg JI, Colledge WH, Grace AA (2002) Slowed conduction and ventricular tachycardia after targeted disruption of the cardiac sodium channel gene Scn5a. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 99:6210&#x2013;6215 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11972032</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pratt</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moye</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The cardiac arrhythmia suppression trial. Casting suppression in a different light</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>245</fpage>
          <lpage>247</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pratt CM, Moye LA (1995) The cardiac arrhythmia suppression trial. Casting suppression in a different light. Circulation 91:245&#x2013;247 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7805210</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Priori</surname>
              <given-names>SG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Napolitano</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schwartz</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bloise</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crotti</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronchetti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The elusive link between LQT3 and Brugada syndrome: The role of flecainide challenge</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>102</volume>
          <fpage>945</fpage>
          <lpage>947</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Priori SG, Napolitano C, Schwartz PJ, Bloise R, Crotti L, Ronchetti E (2000) The elusive link between LQT3 and Brugada syndrome: The role of flecainide challenge. Circulation 102:945&#x2013;947 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10961955</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Riccio</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koller</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gilmour</surname>
              <given-names>RF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electrical restitution and spatiotemporal organization during ventricular fibrillation</article-title>
          <source>Circ Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>955</fpage>
          <lpage>963</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Riccio ML, Koller ML, Gilmour RF Jr (1999) Electrical restitution and spatiotemporal organization during ventricular fibrillation. Circ Res 84:955&#x2013;963 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10222343</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Roden</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Anderson</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Proarrhythmia</article-title>
          <source>Handb Exp Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <fpage>73</fpage>
          <lpage>97</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Roden D, Anderson M (2006) Proarrhythmia. Handb Exp Pharmacol 171:73&#x2013;97 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16610341</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Sabir IN, Fraser JA, Cass TR, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007a) A quantitative analysis of the effect of cycle length on arrhythmogenicity in hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts. Pflugers Arch PMID: 17437126</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sabir</surname>
              <given-names>IN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fraser</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Killeen</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The contribution of refractoriness to arrhythmic substrate in hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts</article-title>
          <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>454</volume>
          <fpage>209</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00424-007-0217-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sabir IN, Fraser JA, Killeen MJ, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007b) The contribution of refractoriness to arrhythmic substrate in hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts. Pflugers Arch 454:209&#x2013;222 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17295037</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sabir</surname>
              <given-names>IN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Killeen</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gray</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Transient alterations in transmural repolarization gradients following premature ventricular depolarizations in arrhythmogenic hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>581</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>289</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2007.128637</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sabir IN, Killeen MJ, Goddard CA, Thomas G, Gray S, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007c) Transient alterations in transmural repolarization gradients following premature ventricular depolarizations in arrhythmogenic hypokalaemic Langendorff-perfused murine hearts. J Physiol 581:277&#x2013;289 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17331992</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Saumarez</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Paced ventricular electrogram fractionation and sudden death in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and other non-coronary heart diseases</article-title>
          <source>Cardiovasc Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0008-6363(00)00096-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Saumarez RC, Grace AA (2000) Paced ventricular electrogram fractionation and sudden death in hypertrophic cardiomyopathy and other non-coronary heart diseases. Cardiovasc Res 47:11&#x2013;22 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10869526</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stokoe</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Balasubramaniam</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colledge</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of flecainide and quinidine on arrhythmogenic properties of Scn5a+/&#x2212; murine hearts</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>578</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2006.117945</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stokoe KS, Balasubramaniam R, Goddard CA, Colledge WH, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007) Effects of flecainide and quinidine on arrhythmogenic properties of Scn5a+/&#x2212; murine hearts. J Physiol 578:69&#x2013;84 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023504</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stokoe</surname>
              <given-names>KS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Thomas</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goddard</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colledge</surname>
              <given-names>WH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grace</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of flecainide and quinidine on arrhythmogenic properties of <italic>Scn5a</italic>+/&#x394; murine hearts modelling long QT syndrome 3</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>578</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>84</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2006.117945</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stokoe KS, Thomas G, Goddard CA, Colledge WH, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007) Effects of flecainide and quinidine on arrhythmogenic properties of Scn5a+/&#x394; murine hearts modelling long QT syndrome 3. J Physiol 578:69&#x2013;84 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17023504</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Taggart</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sutton</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chalabi</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boyett</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simon</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Elliott</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gill</surname>
              <given-names>JS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of adrenergic stimulation on action potential duration restitution in humans</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>107</volume>
          <fpage>285</fpage>
          <lpage>289</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.CIR.0000044941.13346.74</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Taggart P, Sutton P, Chalabi Z, Boyett MR, Simon R, Elliott D, Gill JS (2003) Effect of adrenergic stimulation on action potential duration restitution in humans. Circulation 107:285&#x2013;289 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12538429</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tan</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hofman</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langen</surname>
              <given-names>IM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wal</surname>
              <given-names>AC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wilde</surname>
              <given-names>AA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sudden unexplained death: heritability and diagnostic yield of cardiological and genetic examination in surviving relatives</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>207</fpage>
          <lpage>213</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/CIRCULATIONAHA.104.522581</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tan HL, Hofman N, van Langen IM, van der Wal AC, Wilde AA (2005) Sudden unexplained death: heritability and diagnostic yield of cardiological and genetic examination in surviving relatives. Circulation 112:207&#x2013;213 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15998675</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <citation citation-type="other">Thomas G, Gurung IS, Killeen MJ, Hakim P, Goddard CA, Mahaut-Smith MP, Colledge WH, Grace AA, Huang CL (2007a) Effects of L-type Ca2+ channel antagonism on ventricular arrhythmogenesis in murine hearts containing a modification in the Scn5a gene modelling human long QT syndrome 3. J Physiol 578:85&#x2013;97</citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karagueuzian</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garfinkel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ventricular fibrillation: how do we stop the waves from breaking?</article-title>
          <source>Circ Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>1103</fpage>
          <lpage>1107</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Weiss JN, Chen PS, Qu Z, Karagueuzian HS, Garfinkel A (2000) Ventricular fibrillation: how do we stop the waves from breaking? Circ Res 87:1103&#x2013;1107 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11110766</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weiss</surname>
              <given-names>JN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karma</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shiferaw</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garfinkel</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>From pulsus to pulseless: the saga of cardiac alternans</article-title>
          <source>Circ Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <fpage>1244</fpage>
          <lpage>1253</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1161/01.RES.0000224540.97431.f0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Weiss JN, Karma A, Shiferaw Y, Chen PS, Garfinkel A, Qu Z (2006) From pulsus to pulseless: the saga of cardiac alternans. Circ Res 98:1244&#x2013;1253 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16728670</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yamauchi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamaki</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watanabe</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yuuki</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubota</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tomoike</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Restitution properties and occurrence of ventricular arrhythmia in LQT2 type of long QT syndrome</article-title>
          <source>J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <fpage>910</fpage>
          <lpage>914</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1540-8167.2002.00910.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yamauchi S, Yamaki M, Watanabe T, Yuuki K, Kubota I, Tomoike H (2002) Restitution properties and occurrence of ventricular arrhythmia in LQT2 type of long QT syndrome. J Cardiovasc Electrophysiol 13:910&#x2013;914 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12380931</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Yan</surname>
              <given-names>G-X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Antzelevitch</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cellular Basis for the Brugada Syndrome and Other Mechanisms of Arrhythmogenesis Associated With ST-Segment Elevation</article-title>
          <source>Circulation</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>100</volume>
          <fpage>1660</fpage>
          <lpage>1666</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Yan G-X, Antzelevitch C (1999) Cellular Basis for the Brugada Syndrome and Other Mechanisms of Arrhythmogenesis Associated With ST-Segment Elevation. Circulation 100:1660&#x2013;1666 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10517739</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>