<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Psychopharmacology (Berl)</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Psychopharmacology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0033-3158</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1432-2072</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Berlin/Heidelberg</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18347780</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2362139</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">1100</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-008-1100-4</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Investigation</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Expression of amphetamine sensitization is associated with recruitment of a reactive neuronal population in the nucleus accumbens core</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Nordquist</surname>
            <given-names>R. E.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+31-30-2531248</phone>
            <fax>+31-30-2521887</fax>
            <email>r.e.nordquist@uu.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff4">4</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
            <given-names>L. J. M. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Jonker</surname>
            <given-names>A. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bergsma</surname>
            <given-names>M.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>de Vries</surname>
            <given-names>T. J.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Pennartz</surname>
            <given-names>C. M. A.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Voorn</surname>
            <given-names>P.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>p.voorn@vumc.nl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Anatomy and Neurosciences, Vrije Universiteit Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Rudolf Magnus Institute of Neuroscience, Department of Neuroscience and Pharmacology, University Medical Center Utrecht, Utrecht, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>Animal Physiology and Cognitive Neuroscience, Swammerdam Institute for Life Sciences, University of Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands </aff>
        <aff id="Aff4"><label>4</label>Emotion and Cognition Program, Department of Farm Animal Health, Faculty of Veterinary Medicine, University Utrecht, Marburglaan 2, 3584 CN Utrecht, The Netherlands </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>18</day>
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>198</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>113</fpage>
      <lpage>126</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>1</day>
          <month>2</month>
          <year>2008</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; The Author(s) 2008</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Rationale</title>
          <p>Repeated exposure to psychostimulant drugs causes a long-lasting increase in the psychomotor and reinforcing effects of these drugs and an array of neuroadaptations. One such alteration is a hypersensitivity of striatal activity such that a low dose of amphetamine in sensitized animals produces dorsal striatal activation patterns similar to acute treatment with a high dose of amphetamine.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Objectives</title>
          <p>To extend previous findings of striatal hypersensitivity with behavioral observations and with cellular activity in the nucleus accumbens and prefrontal cortex in sensitized animals.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Materials and methods</title>
          <p>Rats treated acutely with 0, 1, 2.5, or 5&#xA0;mg/kg i.p. amphetamine and sensitized rats challenged with 1&#xA0;mg/kg i.p. amphetamine were scored for stereotypy, rearing, and grooming, and locomotor activity recorded. c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei were quantified in the nucleus accumbens and prefrontal cortex after expression of sensitization with 1&#xA0;mg/kg i.p. amphetamine.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Intense stereotypy was seen in animals treated acutely with 5&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine, but not in the sensitized group treated with 1&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine. The c-<italic>fos</italic> response to amphetamine in the accumbens core was augmented in amphetamine-pretreated animals with a shift in the distribution of optical density, while no effect of sensitization was seen in the nucleus accumbens shell or prefrontal cortex.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>A lack of stereotypy in the sensitized group indicates a dissociation of behavioral responses to amphetamine and striatal immediate-early gene activation patterns. The increase in c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei and shift in the distribution of optical density observed in the nucleus accumbens core suggests recruitment of a new population of neurons during expression of sensitization.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Behavioral sensitization</kwd>
        <kwd>Immediate-early gene</kwd>
        <kwd>Stereotypy</kwd>
        <kwd>Locomotion</kwd>
        <kwd>Striatum</kwd>
        <kwd>Prefrontal cortex</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer-Verlag 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Repeated exposure to psychostimulant drugs causes a long-lasting enhancement of certain behavioral responses to the drug, such as psychomotor activity and stereotypy, and behaviors related to incentive motivation, a process termed behavioral sensitization (Stewart and Badiani <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">1993</xref>). Behavioral sensitization is known to be associated with long-lasting functional changes within limbic corticostriatal systems (Pierce and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1997</xref>; Robinson and Kolb <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">2004</xref>; Vanderschuren and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>). These systems comprise functionally and anatomically heterogeneous areas with a fine-grained specificity of anatomical projections connecting the divisions within the dorsal striatum, ventral striatum, and prefrontal cortex (Groenewegen et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">1997</xref>; Voorn et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">2004</xref>). This anatomical and functional heterogeneity is of potential importance to the roles of these areas in sensitization.</p>
      <p>Within the dorsal striatum, subareas termed patches (or striosomes) show more reactivity to amphetamine than the surrounding matrix areas in sensitized animals (Canales and Graybiel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>; Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). Our previous studies demonstrated that this pattern of neuronal reactivity is also seen in acutely challenged animals with the important difference that sensitized animals show preferential activation in patches at much lower doses of amphetamine than those required to produce this type of differentiation in activation in drug-naive animals (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). An imbalance in patch&#x2013;matrix activation has been suggested to underlie stereotyped behavior (Canales and Graybiel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>). Because our drug treatment regimen caused robust locomotor sensitization, which is incompatible with profound stereotypy, we hypothesized that hyperreactivity of patch compartments is not sufficient to produce stereotypy (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). To extend our previous findings, we ran new experiments using the same doses and regimen of amphetamine administration previously used and measured locomotor activity, stereotypy, grooming, and rearing to establish whether our drug treatment regimen, which causes hyperreactivity of dorsal striatal patches, produces stereotypy.</p>
      <p>The ventral striatum, specifically the nucleus accumbens (Acb), and the prefrontal cortex (PFC) are both involved in behavioral sensitization (Pierce and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">1997</xref>; Vanderschuren and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>), an involvement which has received particular attention because of the important role that both areas play in appetitive and consummatory properties of both natural and drug rewards (Everitt and Wolf <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">2002</xref>; Robbins and Everitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>; Salamone et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">2003</xref>; Volkow and Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>). There are functional differences between subregions within both the Acb, i.e., core and shell, and within subregions of the PFC (Cardinal et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">2002</xref>; Robbins and Everitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>). However, there is presently inconclusive evidence on the respective roles that the subregions play during the expression of behavioral sensitization to psychostimulants. Studies using neurochemistry, lesions, cellular activity markers, and study of morphological changes have suggested exclusive roles for the core (Cadoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2004</xref>; Phillips et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2003</xref>) or the shell (Filip and Siwanowicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2001</xref>; Hsieh et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">2002</xref>; Pierce and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1995</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>). Other studies, including previous work from our own laboratory, suggest a lack of sensitization of accumbens activity all together (Ostrander et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2003</xref>; Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). The medial PFC, and particularly the prelimbic area, has been implicated in induction of psychostimulant sensitization (Tzschentke and Schmidt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">1998</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2000</xref>), although conflicting results have been found for cocaine- vs. amphetamine-induced sensitization (Tzschentke and Schmidt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2000</xref>). The dorsomedial prefrontal cortex has been shown to be involved in the expression of sensitization (Pierce et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">1998</xref>). However, the roles of the orbital and lateral areas in psychostimulant sensitization remain to be investigated. Thus, clarification of the specific roles of the Acb and PFC subregions is needed. To study the activation of the Acb and PFC in detail during the expression of behavioral sensitization, we examined levels of c-<italic>fos</italic>-like proteins (henceforth c-<italic>fos</italic>) in detail in the subregions of the Acb and PFC of the rat after an amphetamine challenge in behaviorally sensitized rats.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Animals and drug treatments</title>
        <p>All experiments were approved by the Animal Ethics Committee of the Vrije Universiteit and were conducted in agreement with Dutch laws (Wet op de Dierproeven 1996) and European regulations (Guideline 86/609/EEC).</p>
        <p>A total of 48 male Wistar rats weighing 180&#x2013;200&#xA0;g upon arrival in the laboratory (as in, e.g., De Vries et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1996</xref>; Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">b</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>) were housed in Macrolon cages in groups of two animals per cage under controlled laboratory conditions (lights on 0700 to 1900 hours). Food and water were available ad libitum. Drug treatment started after an acclimatization period of at least 1&#xA0;week. Animals were briefly handled during the 2&#xA0;days before all injections. In the acute amphetamine experiments, animals were injected with either saline or 1, 2.5, or 5&#xA0;mg/kg <sc>d</sc>-amphetamine sulfate (O.P.G., Utrecht, The Netherlands; <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4 per dose). Sensitization regimens were according to a protocol previously established to produce locomotor sensitization in our laboratory (De Vries et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">1996</xref>; Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">1999a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">b</xref>), and doses were the same as used previously in a c-<italic>fos</italic> study in our laboratory (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). Animals received once daily injections for five consecutive days of 2.5&#xA0;mg/kg <sc>d</sc>-amphetamine sulfate or saline in the home cage (pretreatment phase). Two weeks post treatment, half of the animals from each pretreatment group were given challenge injections of 1&#xA0;mg/kg <sc>d</sc>-amphetamine sulfate while the other half was injected with saline. This gave a total of four experimental groups, <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8 per group: amphetamine-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged (AA); amphetamine-pretreated, saline-challenged (AS); saline-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged (SA); and saline-pretreated, saline-challenged (SS).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Locomotor activity quantification and behavioral scoring</title>
        <p>All injections for the acute experiments and challenge injections for the sensitization experiments took place in our locomotor activity setup. On the challenge injection day, animals were first placed in the Perspex cages (length&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;width&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;height&#x2009;=&#x2009;40&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;40&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;35&#xA0;cm) in which locomotor activity was measured and allowed to acclimate for 2&#xA0;h. After that period, challenge injections were administered and horizontal activity was measured in 10-min blocks for 90&#xA0;min using a video tracking system (EthoVision, Noldus Information Technology B.V., Wageningen, The Netherlands), which determined the position of the animal five times per second. Behavior of the animals was also videotaped and scored afterwards for three mutually exclusive categories: grooming (rubbing two paws over head and/or body), rearing (both front paws off of the ground but not grooming), or stereotypical behavior (repeated movements without horizontal movement, e.g., head shaking). Behavior was scored for 5&#xA0;min of every 15&#xA0;min, giving a total of seven measurements per animal, by an observer unaware of the treatment of the animals using a time-sampling program written in PC Basic. Time spent performing each behavior was expressed as the percentage of total time for each 5-min block. Replication scoring several months after initial scoring produced results identical to initial observations, demonstrating the reliability of our scoring procedures.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>c-<italic>fos</italic> Immunocytochemistry</title>
        <p>At 90&#xA0;min after the challenge injection, animals were decapitated, the brains were snap-frozen in isopentane and stored at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C until use. Sections of 20&#xA0;&#x3BC;m were cut on a cryostat and mounted onto coated slides (SuperFrost Plus) which were dried and stored at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C until use. For visualization of c-<italic>fos</italic>, sections were defrosted and fixed in a 4% paraformaldehyde solution in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS; 0.1&#xA0;M, pH&#xA0;7.4). Sections were washed with Tris-buffered saline (TBS, 0.1&#xA0;M, pH&#xA0;7.4) then incubated with primary antibody against c-<italic>fos</italic> (1:1,800, Oncogene Research, Burlington, MA, USA) in TBS with 0.5% Triton-X and 0.5% bovine serum albumin (TBS-TX-BSA) overnight at 4&#xB0;C. After rinsing with TBS, endogenous peroxidase activity was removed by incubation of sections in a 1% hydrogen peroxide solution for 15&#xA0;min. Sections were rinsed with TBS, then incubated in biotinylated goat antirabbit antibody (1:100, Dako, Denmark) in TBS-TX-BSA for 1&#xA0;h, washed in TBS and incubated in avidin&#x2013;biotin complex with horseradish peroxidase (HRP) (1:100, Vector Laboratories, Burlingame, CA, USA) for 1&#xA0;h. Sections were rinsed in Tris&#x2013;HCl then incubated in 3&#x2032;3-diaminobenzidine (DAB; Sigma Chemical, 0.05% DAB in Tris&#x2013;HCl) and rinsed in Tris&#x2013;HCl. Sections containing the prefrontal cortex were incubated with Hoechst 33258 (1:2,000; Molecular Probes, Eugene, OR, USA), a fluorescent nuclear stain used to visualize cytoarchitecture. Sections were dried and finally coverslipped with Merckoglas (Merck, Darmstadt, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Histological quantification</title>
        <p>Quantification of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei was performed using an MCID Elite imaging system (Imaging Research, Ontario, Canada). Images of the nucleus accumbens in the c-<italic>fos</italic> DAB immunostained sections were digitized using an objective magnification of &#xD7;10 on a Leica DM/RBE photomicroscope with a Xillix MicroImager digital camera (1,280&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;1,024&#xA0;pixels). Digitized images were combined so that the core and the shell areas were included, using the MCID tiling tool. Three (in some cases, two) sections per rat were chosen for quantification at the rostral&#x2013;caudal levels in which inputs from the prefrontal cortex, thalamus, and amygdala have been particularly well characterized (Wright and Groenewegen <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR46">1995</xref>). The prefrontal cortex was digitized in the same fashion with the exception that color digital images were acquired using a Sony HAD camera (Sony DXC 950v, 640&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;512&#xA0;pixels) of both the DAB staining and the epifluorescence of the Hoechst 33258 staining. The core and shell areas of the nucleus accumbens were delineated on the basis of atlas drawings from sections stained for calbindin (Jongen-Relo et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">1993</xref>). The prefrontal cortex was delineated into prelimbic, infralimbic, orbital, and lateral areas on the basis of cytoarchitectonic criteria visible in the Hoechst 33258 staining.</p>
        <p>The c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei in the nucleus accumbens were segregated from background staining levels using several point operators and spatial filters combined in an algorithm designed to detect local changes in the relative optical density (ROD). Briefly, images underwent histogram equalization and smoothing (low-pass filter, kernel size 7&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;7). The unfiltered image was subtracted from the smoothed image, followed by a series of steps to optimize the processed image and make it a suitable measuring template for detecting objects the size and shape of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei. This algorithm was preferred over ROD thresholding because it does not involve an observer-dependent operation. The number of nuclei counted was corrected with a factor indicating approximate size of a c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nucleus, thus preventing two groups of stained pixels touching one another in the image being mistakenly counted as one nucleus. The results of all counting were expressed as the number of nuclei per surface area (mm<sup>2</sup>). Integrated ROD for each segmented immunopositive nucleus was determined. Segregation of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the color-digitized images was performed in a similar fashion.</p>
        <p>Subsequently, we set out to compare c-<italic>fos</italic> positive density (i.e., the number of cells per surface area) in a manner that accounts for labeling intensity: dark, light, or midrange. First, histograms of c-<italic>fos</italic> nuclei ROD values (for black and white images) or intensity values (for color images) were constructed for each brain area for each treatment group and qualitatively compared. These histograms were used to determine the value of the 33rd and 66th percentile optical density within the SS group. Based on these values, all nuclei from all animals for each area were binned as &#x201C;light&#x201D; (ROD values under the 33rd percentile of the SS group), &#x201C;midrange&#x201D; (ROD values between the 33rd and 66th percentile of the SS group) or &#x201C;dark&#x201D; (ROD values above the 66th percentile of the SS group). The number of immunopositive nuclei per bin was counted per rat, and the group averages were determined from the rat averages. For the prefrontal cortex, the same technique was used, but as these areas were digitized in color, intensity was used to bin rather than optical density. An increase in the number of nuclei in the &#x201C;dark&#x201D; bin would signify a rightward shift in the histograms, indicating that the increased cellular activity measured was primarily the result of more c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in the same group of neurons. An increase in the number of nuclei in the &#x201C;midrange&#x201D; bin would signify an upward shift in the histograms, indicating that the increase in the total number of nuclei measured was the result of the addition of a new group of nuclei to the cellular response (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Theoretical conceptualization of shifts in the ROD histograms. The total number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei per mm<sup>2</sup> counted is represented as the area under the curves to the right of the detection level, indicated as an <italic>arrow</italic> on the <italic>x</italic>-axis. <italic>Curve 1</italic> indicates the control group; <italic>vertical lines</italic> indicate the ROD used to separate the neurons into light, midrange, and dark. An increase in the treatment group compared to the control group in the total number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei per mm<sup>2</sup> could be the result of an increase in the frequency of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei, indicated by an increase in frequency in <italic>curve 2</italic>, causing an increase in the number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the midrange. This would indicate that a new group of neurons is being recruited in the c-<italic>fos</italic> response, represented by the difference between <italic>curves 1</italic> and <italic>2</italic> in frequency. Alternatively, the same number of neurons could be active, but expressing more c-<italic>fos</italic> protein. This would cause a rightward shift in the curve (<italic>curve 3</italic>) and allowing more c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei to come above the detection level and causing more c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei to be measured in the dark range. A similar line of reasoning can be followed for other options, for instance a leftward shift in the case of reduced levels of c-<italic>fos</italic> protein (not illustrated)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>The dorsal striatum of the AA group was qualitatively inspected by two observers, both blind to the experimental conditions. The distribution pattern of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei was described and compared with that in a series of closely adjacent sections from the same animals stained immunocytochemically for the &#x3BC;-opioid receptor to visualize striatal patches (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Statistics</title>
        <p>For the quantification of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunoreactivity, the experimental groups were compared for effects of pretreatment and challenge (saline vs. amphetamine) and for interactions between these effects using a two-way ANOVA test followed by a Tukey post hoc test. For locomotor activity and behavioral scores, a repeated-measures ANOVA was conducted using time as within-subjects factor and followed by a Tukey post hoc test.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Behavioral results</title>
        <p>For all behavioral measures, time was included as a within-subjects measure in a repeated-measures ANOVA followed by a post hoc test when significant time&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;pretreatment or time&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interactions were found. For brevity, only the most relevant of the results of these post hoc test results are described in this section and other results are presented in the figures.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Behavioral measures: responses to acute amphetamine</title>
        <p>Locomotor activity was dose-dependently altered in animals treated acutely with amphetamine (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a; main effect dose <italic>F</italic><sub>(3,10)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;43.914; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001). Saline-treated animals showed generally low activity levels, averaging a total of 1,335&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;514&#xA0;cm traveled during the 90-min period. The groups treated with 1&#xA0;mg/kg (14,045&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,836&#xA0;cm) and 5&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine (14,906&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2,321&#xA0;cm) showed comparable levels of locomotor activity, whereas the highest locomotor response to amphetamine was observed in the 2.5&#xA0;mg/kg group (25,543&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1,704&#xA0;cm). All amphetamine-treated groups differed from saline in the post hoc test. Acute amphetamine caused a significant increase in rearing (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,12)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.971; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b), although not dose-dependently, as all doses differed significantly from the saline-treated group in post hoc testing, but there were no significant differences among the amphetamine-treated groups (average percent time spent rearing, saline&#x2009;=&#x2009;2.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.75; 1&#xA0;mg/kg&#x2009;=&#x2009;15.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.7; 2.5&#xA0;mg/kg&#x2009;=&#x2009;20.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.5; 5&#xA0;mg/kg&#x2009;=&#x2009;16.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.7). No significant effect of amphetamine on grooming was seen (main effect of dose: <italic>F</italic><sub>(3,12)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.098, n.s.; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). Stereotypy was exclusively observed in the group treated with 5&#xA0;mg/kg of amphetamine (average percent time spent in stereotypical behavior, 5&#xA0;mg/kg&#x2009;=&#x2009;28.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;16.5; all other groups average&#x2009;=&#x2009;0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). A clear main effect of dose was seen (<italic>F</italic><sub>(3,12)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;11.724; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005). The 5-mg/kg group differed significantly from all other groups in the post hoc test.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Locomotor activity (<bold>a</bold>) and behavioral observations (<bold>b</bold>) for animals treated acutely with saline or 1, 2.5, or 5&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine. The highest levels of locomotor activity were seen in the 2.5-mg/kg treated group, which differed significantly from all other groups in the post hoc tests. Stereotypical behavior was observed in the animals treated with 5&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine, which differed significantly from all other groups, but no stereotypy was seen in any of the other treatment groups. No significant differences were seen in grooming behavior (<bold>b</bold>). All amphetamine-treated groups showed significantly more rearing than the saline-treated group (<bold>b</bold>), but the amphetamine treatment groups did not differ from one another. <italic>Bars</italic> indicate group averages, <italic>error bars</italic> represent SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4 per group. <italic>Asterisks</italic> indicate significant difference in post hoc testing (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>Behavioral measures: responses to challenge after repeated amphetamine</title>
        <p>Pretreatment with amphetamine caused a clear-cut augmentation of the locomotor response to amphetamine, as illustrated in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a. Overall across the 90-min period, the AA group of amphetamine-pretreated rats that were challenged with amphetamine on the test day showed a 70% increase in activity compared to the SA group, which was pretreated with saline and challenged with amphetamine (total traveled distance during the 90-min test period&#x2009;=&#x2009;20,432&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3,403&#xA0;cm by AA compared to 11,924&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2,149&#xA0;cm by SA). Both groups that were challenged with saline on the test day (AS and SS, pretreated with amphetamine and saline, respectively) showed considerably less locomotor activity, showing approximately 10% of the activity displayed by the AA group (total traveled distance during 90&#xA0;min, SS&#x2009;=&#x2009;1,770&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;493&#xA0;cm; AS&#x2009;=&#x2009;2,196&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;623&#xA0;cm). These differences were reflected in significant main effects of pretreatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6.15; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) and challenge (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;62.07; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001), and a significant pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;5.029; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Locomotor activity (<bold>a</bold>) and behavioral observations (<bold>b</bold>) in amphetamine-pretreated and amphetamine-challenged animals and control groups. <italic>Bars</italic> represent group average of locomotor activity (<bold>a</bold>) or percentage of time spent displaying each mutually exclusive category of behavior (grooming, rearing or stereotypical behavior; <bold>b</bold>). No bars are present representing stereotypical behavior because this behavior was not observed in any animals included in this experiment. <italic>Error bars</italic> indicate SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6 per group. <italic>AA</italic> amphetamine-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged; <italic>SA</italic> saline-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged; <italic>AS</italic> amphetamine-pretreated, saline-challenged; <italic>SS</italic> saline-pretreated, saline-challenged. <italic>Asterisks</italic> indicate significant difference in post hoc testing (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b, the evaluation of the percentage of time spent rearing revealed an increase in rearing in the AA group compared to all other groups (average over 90&#xA0;min, AA&#x2009;=&#x2009;14.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.9%, AS&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.84&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.64%, SA&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.09&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.2%, SS&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.34&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.92%). This was confirmed by a significant main effect of challenge (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;27.52; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001) and pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.96; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). No main effect of pretreatment was observed for this parameter (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.41; n.s.).</p>
        <p>Percentages of time spent grooming were generally low with average scores under 4% in all groups (average over 90&#xA0;min, AA&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.66&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.64, AS&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.54&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;1.97, SA&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.78&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.86, SS&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.97&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.87; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). Despite the somewhat higher averages in the saline-challenged groups compared to the amphetamine-challenged groups, no significant effects of pretreatment, challenge, or interaction between the two were seen on grooming (pretreatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.64, n.s.; challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.42, n.s.; pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,20)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.21, n.s.).</p>
        <p>No stereotyped behavior was observed in any animal in any of the groups included in the repeated amphetamine experiments during any of the time periods scored (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Cellular reactivity results</title>
        <p>In the nucleus accumbens and prefrontal cortex, the quantification of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei was tested for statistical significance by two-way ANOVAs using pretreatment and challenge as factors, followed by a Tukey HSD post hoc. For brevity, results of these post hoc tests are presented in the figures and in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Mean&#xB1;SEM density (number of cells per mm<sup>2</sup>) of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunoreactive nuclei in light, dark, and midranges of cellular staining intensity</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th rowspan="2" colspan="3">&#xA0;</th><th align="left" colspan="4">Treatment group</th></tr><tr><th align="left">AA</th><th align="left">AS</th><th align="left">SA</th><th align="left">SS</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td rowspan="6">Nucleus accumbens</td><td rowspan="3">Core</td><td>Light</td><td>21.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.9</td><td>17.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.2</td><td>17.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.2</td><td>21.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.2</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange<sup>&#xA7;</sup></td><td>34.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.8<sup>&amp;</sup></td><td>19.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.2<sup>#</sup></td><td>20.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.7</td><td>22.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.1</td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>&#xB6;/****</sup></td><td>94.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.1<sup>&amp;/+</sup></td><td>35.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.6<sup>#</sup></td><td>61.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.4</td><td>24.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.6<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Shell</td><td>Light</td><td>28.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.7</td><td>26.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.3</td><td>28.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.9</td><td>38.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.4</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange</td><td>42.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.2</td><td>41.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.2</td><td>34.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.6</td><td>40.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.6</td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>*</sup></td><td>96.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;17.1</td><td>63.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;9.2</td><td>86.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;20.7</td><td>44.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.6</td></tr><tr><td rowspan="12">Prefrontal cortex</td><td rowspan="3">Prelimbic</td><td>Light</td><td>48.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.0</td><td>34.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.7</td><td>39.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.4</td><td>32.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.8</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange<sup>**</sup></td><td>50.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.9</td><td>31.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.0</td><td>46.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.0</td><td>27.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.3</td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>***</sup></td><td>74.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;12.4</td><td>32.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.7<sup>%</sup></td><td>82.28&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;18.8<sup>+/&amp;</sup></td><td>28.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.9<sup>%</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Infralimbic</td><td>Light</td><td>37.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.8</td><td>33.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.8</td><td>30.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.6</td><td>29.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.1</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange</td><td>46.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.3</td><td>34.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.8</td><td>35.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.9</td><td>28.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.4</td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>***</sup></td><td>78.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;13.7<sup>+</sup></td><td>40.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.1</td><td>70.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;14.5</td><td>30.2&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.9<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Orbital</td><td>Light</td><td>27.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.6</td><td>24.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;6.1</td><td>23.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.3</td><td>21.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.4</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange<sup>**</sup></td><td>61.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.5<sup>+</sup></td><td>32.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.7</td><td>45.0&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.4</td><td>30.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.9<sup>#</sup></td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>****</sup></td><td>129.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;21.7<sup>&amp;/+</sup></td><td>32.6&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;8.6<sup>#</sup></td><td>120.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;24.2<sup>+</sup></td><td>26.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.7<sup>#/%</sup></td></tr><tr><td rowspan="3">Lateral</td><td>Light<sup>*</sup></td><td>22.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.3</td><td>14.8&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;10.0</td><td>18.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;2.8</td><td>14.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.3</td></tr><tr><td>Midrange<sup>*</sup></td><td>39.9&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.2</td><td>19.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;5.1</td><td>27.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;7.6</td><td>18.4&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;3.7</td></tr><tr><td>Dark<sup>****</sup></td><td>69.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;11.6<sup>&amp;/+</sup></td><td>18.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.4<sup>#</sup></td><td>65.1&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;15.6<sup>+</sup></td><td>16.7&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;4.6<sup>#/%</sup></td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Results of ANOVA testing are shown in the column indicating ROD range as follows: <italic>paragraph mark</italic> significant main effect of pretreatment, <italic>asterisk</italic> significant main effect of challenge, <italic>section mark</italic> significant pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction; one symbol: <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05, two symbols: <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01, three symbols: <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005, four symbols: <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001. Results of post hoc testing are indicated in the cells containing the value of the average number of nuclei as follows: <italic>plus sign</italic> significantly different from SS, <italic>percent sign</italic> significantly different from SA, <italic>ampersand</italic> significantly different from AS, <italic>number sign</italic> significantly different from AA.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>Sensitization alters distribution of reactivity in dorsal striatum</title>
        <p>In the dorsal striatum, visual inspection of the sections from animals both pretreated and challenged with amphetamine (AA group) showed overall more c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei compared to the AS group, and a differential distribution throughout the area (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei were more abundant medially than laterally. Within the general distribution, heterogeneity of reactivity was seen conforming to patterns previously observed in patches in sensitized animals. Comparison of c-<italic>fos</italic> staining pattern with &#x3BC;-opioid stained patches in sections from another series from the same animals confirmed the location of high concentrations of nuclei in &#x3BC;-opioid stained patches.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Digital micrographs of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei in the dorsal striatum of representative animals from groups pretreated with amphetamine and challenged with either saline (<bold>a</bold>, group AS) or amphetamine (<bold>b</bold>, group AA). Scale bars indicate 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;m, <italic>arrows</italic> point to c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei. Note the higher number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the AA animal compared to the SA animal, and the inhomogeneous distribution of nuclei in the AA animal</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Cellular reactivity sensitizes in nucleus accumbens core, but not accumbens shell or prefrontal cortex</title>
        <p>Within the nucleus accumbens, the core and shell subdivisions showed different c-<italic>fos</italic> immunoreactivity response patterns to an amphetamine challenge after the sensitizing regimen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a&#x2013;d and Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). The core showed a clear effect of sensitization with a number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the AA group 48% higher than that of the SA group and more than 100% compared to both saline-challenged groups (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Significant main effects of pretreatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;10.59; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005) and challenge (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;44.75; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001) and a significant pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.55; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) confirmed this observation. In the nucleus accumbens shell, more c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei were counted in the amphetamine than saline-challenged groups, but no sensitization effect was seen (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). A significant main effect of challenge (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.41; <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05), but not of pretreatment (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.57; n.s.), was observed, and no pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.04; n.s.) was present in the ANOVA of the nucleus accumbens shell data.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Digital micrographs of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei and representations of nuclei quantified in the nucleus accumbens from representative animals treated acutely with amphetamine (SA group; <bold>a</bold>, <bold>c</bold>, and <bold>e</bold>) and challenged with amphetamine after amphetamine pretreatment (AA group; <bold>b</bold>, <bold>d</bold>, and <bold>f</bold>). The low magnification overviews of nucleus accumbens in <bold>a</bold> (SA animal) and <bold>b</bold> (AA animal) show differences in the number of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei between the two experimental groups. Corresponding detail images of the nucleus accumbens core, shown in <bold>c</bold> (detail from <bold>b</bold>) and <bold>d</bold> (detail from <bold>b</bold>), are medial to anterior commissure. Nuclei counted for quantification in <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold> are illustrated in <bold>e</bold> and <bold>f</bold>, respectively. <italic>Red squares</italic> indicate immunoreactive nuclei classified as &#x201C;dark,&#x201D; <italic>green squares</italic> as &#x201C;midrange,&#x201D; and <italic>blue squares</italic> as &#x201C;light&#x201D; (see text for classification procedures). <italic>Broad white arrows</italic> in <bold>d</bold> and <bold>f</bold> indicate a &#x201C;dark&#x201D; immunopositive nucleus and its representation in the counted nuclei; <italic>gray arrows</italic> represent &#x201C;midrange&#x201D;; <italic>narrow white arrows</italic> indicate &#x201C;light.&#x201D; Scale bar in <bold>a</bold> indicates 300&#xA0;&#x3BC;m for <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>; scale bar in <bold>c</bold> represents 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;m for <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold>. <italic>cp</italic> caudate putamen, <italic>ac</italic> anterior commissure, <italic>core</italic> nucleus accumbens core, <italic>shell</italic> nucleus accumbens shell</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Mean number of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei in nucleus accumbens core and shell and prelimbic, infralimbic, orbital, and lateral prefrontal cortex. Two-way ANOVA analysis of accumbens data showed significant main effects of pretreatment and challenge and a pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction in the nucleus accumbens core. A significant effect of challenge was observed in the nucleus accumbens shell and for all PFC areas measured. <italic>Bars</italic> represent the number of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei per mm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>error bars</italic> indicate SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8 per group. <italic>Asterisk</italic> indicates significant differences in post hoc testing. See Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref> for abbreviations of treatment groups</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
        <p>In the prefrontal cortex, an increase in c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in amphetamine-challenged groups compared to saline-challenged groups was observed in all four subregions measured. No differences were seen between amphetamine- and saline-pretreated animals in the number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei after an amphetamine challenge (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>). Significant main effects of challenge were observed in all areas (PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;13.87, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6.94, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05; orbital PFC: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;25.96, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001; lateral PFC: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;20.55, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001). No significant effects of pretreatment (PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.14, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.20, n.s.; orbital PFC: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.945, n.s.; lateral PFC: 0.79, n.s.) or pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interactions (PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.08, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.037, n.s.; orbital PFC: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.039; lateral PFC: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.67) were observed.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Frequency distributions of relative optical densities across groups show sensitization of midrange in accumbens core</title>
        <p>When comparing the ROD of the c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei of each area across groups, significantly higher (=darker) averages were seen in amphetamine- compared to saline-challenged groups in the core (optical density 0.1216&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0026 in saline-challenged, 0.1372&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0040 in amphetamine-challenged; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;10.815, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005), the shell (optical density 0.1208&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0023 in saline-challenged, 0.1307&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0035 in amphetamine-challenged; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;5.513, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05), the infralimbic area (intensity 0.7173&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0057 in saline-challenged, 0.6985&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0660 in amphetamine-challenged; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.368, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05), the orbital prefrontal area (intensity 0.7181&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0048 in saline-challenged, 0.6921&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0073 in amphetamine-challenged; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8.258, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001), and the lateral prefrontal area (intensity 0.7208&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0045 in saline-challenged, 0.6992&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.0067 in amphetamine-challenged; <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6.753, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). Significant differences were seen between the AA and SS groups and between the SA and SS group in the core in post hoc testing. No significant differences were seen in the shell in post hoc testing.</p>
        <p>The distributional patterns of the cellular ROD suggested differences in the distributions of ROD across the treatment groups. To further analyze the optical densities and compare the frequencies of the various optical densities between groups, histograms of the optical densities of all cells per area, per group were constructed (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>e&#x2013;f and <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a and b) and used to divide immunostained nuclei into light, midrange, and dark optical density (OD) ranges based on the 33rd and 66th percentile values in the SS group (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>), as described in the &#x201C;<xref rid="Sec2" ref-type="sec">Materials and methods</xref>&#x201D; section. Two-way ANOVAs for pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge were conducted, followed by Tukey HSD post hoc tests. For brevity, the results of the post hoc tests are indicated in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>.
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>Representations of distributions of optical densities in the nucleus accumbens. In <bold>a</bold> and <bold>b</bold>, histograms of relative optical densities of individual c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei in nucleus accumbens core (<bold>a</bold>) and shell (<bold>b</bold>) are depicted. <italic>T1</italic> and <italic>T2 lines</italic> represent the 33rd and 66th percentile values, respectively, for the SS group. In the nucleus accumbens core, the AA group shows more neurons in the midrange segment (between T1 and T2), as confirmed by the analysis of number of cells per segment (<bold>c</bold>). A significant pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction is present in the midrange of the nucleus accumbens core. The amphetamine-challenged groups both contain more neurons in the dark segment of both core (<bold>c</bold>) and shell (<bold>d</bold>) compared to saline-challenged groups, as evidenced by a significant effect of challenge in the ANOVA test. No significant differences were observed in post hoc testing in the shell; <italic>asterisks</italic> indicate significant differences in post hoc testing for core in <bold>c</bold> (<italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). <italic>Line colors</italic> and <italic>patterns</italic> or <italic>bar fillings</italic> indicating groups are as shown in <bold>a</bold> and <bold>c</bold>. For <bold>c</bold> and <bold>d</bold>, <italic>bars</italic> represent the number of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in each OD segment per mm<sup>2</sup>, <italic>error bars</italic> indicate SEM, <italic>n</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8 per group. See Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> for abbreviations of treatment groups</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="213_2008_1100_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
        <p>In both the core and the shell, amphetamine-challenged animals showed higher numbers of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei than saline-pretreated animals in the dark range (core challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;23.928, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001; shell challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;6.421, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). A significant effect of pretreatment was seen in the core in this range (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;5.202, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05), and no effect was seen in the shell (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.949, n.s.). No pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interactions were observed in the core (pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.227, n.s.; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c and Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) or shell (pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.103, n.s.; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d and Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>) in this range. In the midrange nuclei, the core area showed a distinct pattern of distribution compared to all other areas measured as a sensitization effect was confirmed by a significant pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.901, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c), while no significant main effects were observed (pretreatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.985, n.s.; challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.195, n.s.). No differences between groups were observed in the midrange nuclei in the shell (pretreatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.474, n.s.; challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.146, n.s.; pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.229, n.s.; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d). No differences between groups were seen in the light range nuclei in the core (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>c; pretreatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.000, n.s.; challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.002, n.s.; pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.532, n.s.) or the shell (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>d; pretreatment: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.624, n.s.; challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.280, n.s.; pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.632, n.s.).</p>
        <p>Within the prefrontal cortex, the areas measured showed a relatively homogenous pattern of distribution of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunoreactivity across the OD ranges (Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In the dark range, all areas showed significantly more c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the amphetamine-treated groups compared to the saline-treated groups (main effect challenge: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;14.974, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;11.563, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.005; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;31.370, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;23.751, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.001) but no effects of pretreatment (main effect pretreatment: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.035, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.645, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.209, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.092, n.s.) or interaction between pretreatment and challenge (pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.207, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.014, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.008, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.015, n.s.). In the midrange, increased numbers of c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in amphetamine-challenged animals were seen in the prelimbic (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;8.081, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01), orbital (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;7.941, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.01), and lateral (7.029, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05) areas, but not the infralimbic area (<italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.545, n.s.). No effects were seen in the midrange segment of pretreatment (main effect pretreatment: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.265, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.511, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.453, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.461, n.s.), and no pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interactions were seen (pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.001, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.113, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.928, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.076, n.s.). In the light range, only the lateral prefrontal cortex showed a significant increase in c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei in the amphetamine-challenged groups (main effect challenge: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;4.228, <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05). No other challenge effects were observed (main effect challenge: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;3.751, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.243, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.302, n.s.). No effects of pretreatment (main effect pretreatment: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.225, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;1.060, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.863, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.793, n.s.) or of sensitization (pretreatment&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;challenge interaction: PL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.356, n.s.; IL: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.156, n.s.; orbital: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.015, n.s.; lateral: <italic>F</italic><sub>(1,28)</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0.573, n.s.) were seen in the light range of the PFC c-<italic>fos</italic> immunopositive nuclei.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec16" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In the present study, we set out to characterize the behavioral response to amphetamine in drug-naive and amphetamine-pretreated animals, as we had previously observed that treatment with a high dose (5&#xA0;mg/kg) of amphetamine in drug-naive animals resulted in a similar pattern of cellular reactivity in the dorsal striatum as a challenge with an intermediate dose (1&#xA0;mg/kg) in amphetamine-pretreated, behaviorally sensitized rats (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). Furthermore, we aimed to characterize the reactivity of subregions within the nucleus accumbens and prefrontal cortex during the expression of psychostimulant sensitization. Our results showed that previously demonstrated similarity of cellular activation patterns in the dorsal striatum after amphetamine in sensitized or drug-naive rats was not accompanied by similar behavioral responses. Thus, animals given acute amphetamine at a dose that produces heightened patch activation (5&#xA0;mg/kg) displayed intense stereotypy, which was not seen during the expression of sensitization at a challenge dose (1&#xA0;mg/kg) that also produces higher activation of patches than surrounding matrix. Cellular activation was sensitized in response to a drug challenge in the nucleus accumbens core, but not the shell or the prefrontal cortex. Examination of the distribution patterns of the optical densities of the individual immunopositive nuclei revealed an upward shift in the histograms of the core in the AA group, resulting in a significant increase in the midrange stained nuclei in the accumbens core in sensitized animals.</p>
      <sec id="Sec17">
        <title>Sensitization of locomotor activity and rearing without stereotypy</title>
        <p>After amphetamine pretreatment, an augmented locomotor and rearing response to amphetamine was seen compared to saline-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged animals, thus supporting the notion that stereotypy and patch hyperreactivity could take place independently. The behavioral pattern of the amphetamine-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged group most resembled the animals treated acutely with 1.0 or 2.5&#xA0;mg/kg of amphetamine. No stereotyped behavior was observed in the sensitized animals after an amphetamine challenge, while intense stereotypy was seen in animals treated acutely with 5&#xA0;mg/kg of amphetamine. In our previous paper (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>), we noted that the decrease in locomotion normally observed in animals treated acutely with a high dose of amphetamine was likely a result of stereotypy, an idea which is strengthened by the present observations.</p>
        <p>In previous studies by our laboratory and others, animals treated acutely with the relatively high dose of 5&#xA0;mg/kg of amphetamine (Graybiel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1990</xref>; Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>) or with the same amphetamine regimen for sensitization followed by a challenge with 1&#xA0;mg/kg amphetamine used in the present study (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>) show enhanced ratios of response in patches compared to the matrix in the dorsal striatum, findings visually confirmed in the present set of experiments. We concluded on the basis of our previous results that the changes seen in striatal reactivity represent a shift in sensitivity to amphetamine rather than long-term adaptations in circuitry. If the increased sensitivity to amphetamine underlying behavioral sensitization paralleled the hyperreactivity of patches, the same pattern of behavior would be expected in animals showing similar immediate-early gene expression patterns, namely, the 5-mg/kg acutely challenged group and the amphetamine-sensitized, amphetamine-challenged group. However, the expression of stereotypy in the 5-mg/kg group, not seen in the sensitized animals, and the erratic locomotor activity seen in the 5-mg/kg group, clearly indicate behavioral differences after the two treatments. It is interesting to note that the dissociation of hyperreactivity of patches and sensitized behavioral responses manifests in a lack of stereotypical behavior in sensitized animals, as increased reactivity of patches compared to the matrix has been suggested to underlie stereotypical behavior (Canales and Graybiel <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">2000</xref>). Given the fact that the sensitization regimen and challenge dose used in the present study causes heightened patch to matrix ratios of c-<italic>fos</italic> expression, but does not cause stereotyped behavior, changes in striatal patterns of activity are apparently not causally related to stereotypy.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Sensitization of immediate-early gene activation in a specific neural population of the nucleus accumbens core</title>
        <p>The sensitized immediate-early gene expression we observed in the nucleus accumbens core during the expression of psychostimulant sensitization after a withdrawal period of 14&#xA0;days contradicts a number of previous immediate-early gene studies where no sensitization effect was observed in the core (Ostrander et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2003</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>), including one study from our own laboratory (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). There are two main differences between the present study and the previous study from our group. First, in our previous study, a 3-week abstinence period was observed, while in the present study, animals were tested after 14&#xA0;days of abstinence. It is interesting to note that studies examining immediate-early gene expression after shorter abstinence periods (2&#xA0;days) do show sensitization of reactivity within the core (Hedou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2002</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>), indicating that abstinence time is of potential importance for sensitization of c-<italic>fos</italic> in the nucleus accumbens core. However, this explanation seems unsatisfactory as the study by Totenkopf et al. (<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>) also tested c-<italic>fos</italic> expression after 2&#xA0;weeks of abstinence and found no sensitization of c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in the nucleus accumbens core. This discrepancy might be explained by a second difference between the studies where no effect was observed and the present study: in studies finding no effect of sensitization on the nucleus accumbens core, animals were at least partially pretreated and challenged in the same environment. Exposure to amphetamine in a relatively novel environment has been shown to potentiate the c-<italic>fos</italic> response to the drug in the nucleus accumbens core (Ostrander et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">2003</xref>).The importance of the testing environment was recently underscored by a study showing that sensitized c-<italic>fos</italic> responses to cocaine in the nucleus accumbens only occurred when cocaine was always administered in a discrete environment outside of the home cage (Hope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>).</p>
        <p>Expression of c-<italic>fos</italic> in the striatum can be elicited by stimulation of dopamine receptors (Berretta et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">1992</xref>), which have been demonstrated to be crucially involved in the expression of amphetamine sensitization (Vanderschuren and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">2000</xref>). As mentioned in the &#x201C;<xref rid="Sec1" ref-type="sec">Introduction</xref>&#x201D;, a number of studies point to the sensitization of dopamine transmission in the accumbens core during the expression of sensitization (Cadoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>; Phillips et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">2003</xref>), and increased dopamine is also seen in the core compared to the shell in yoked controls in cocaine and heroin self-administration studies (Lecca et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">2007a</xref>; Lecca et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">2007b</xref>). It is thus possible that dopamine may play a role in eliciting the increased c-<italic>fos</italic> response seen in the accumbens core in the present study.</p>
        <p>In the accumbens core, more cells in the midrange of optical densities were present in the amphetamine-pretreated, amphetamine-challenged group than in all other groups. This &#x201C;upward&#x201D; shift in sensitized animals, visible in the histogram of optical density frequencies, indicates that the increase in c-<italic>fos</italic> positive nuclei is not due to nuclei that were under our detection threshold for c-<italic>fos</italic> increasing their reactivity enough to be measured. In the case of increased c-<italic>fos</italic> expression within the same population of nuclei that normally respond to amphetamine, a rightward shift in the histogram of optical densities would be expected, which would manifest in a sensitization effect in the dark range and increase of the average optical density. No increase was seen in the overall average optical density, no significant interaction observed between pretreatment and challenge in the dark group, and there is no significant difference between the AA and SA groups in the dark group. However, an obvious trend to sensitization in the darkly stained group is visible in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>. Although the lack of significance precludes firm conclusions, it might be that some neurons which normally respond to amphetamine by producing c-<italic>fos</italic> react by producing more c-<italic>fos</italic> after sensitization.</p>
        <p>The increase of frequency of neurons stained in the midrange without a significant shift in average optical density suggests the recruitment of a new population of nuclei becoming responsive to amphetamine in the sensitized animals. The population most likely to be involved in that sensitized response is the dopamine D<sub>2</sub> receptor-containing, enkephalin-positive population that project via the subthalamic nucleus to the substantia nigra pars reticulata and entopenduncular nucleus. Indeed, sensitization of cocaine-induced c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in the nucleus accumbens in animals treated with the drug in a discrete environment was only found in enkephalin-positive cells, but not in dynorphin-positive, dopamine D<sub>1</sub> receptor-expressing neurons that directly project to the substantia nigra (Hope et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">2006</xref>). Differences in responsivity to amphetamine in these two cellular populations have also been demonstrated in a study where dopamine D<sub>2</sub> receptor-containing neurons became activated when amphetamine is administered in a novel environment (Badiani et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1999</xref>). Remarkably, c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in dopamine D<sub>1</sub> receptor-containing accumbens neurons was shown to be important for the induction of cocaine sensitization (Zhang et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">2006</xref>), suggesting that these two different cell populations play distinct roles in the induction and expression of behavioral sensitization.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>Immediate-early gene responses to acute amphetamine in the nucleus accumbens shell and prefrontal cortex</title>
        <p>The cellular response of the nucleus accumbens shell to acute amphetamine, which did not sensitize after repeated amphetamine, corresponds well with previous results from our laboratory demonstrating the same effect (Vanderschuren et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">2002</xref>). The role of the shell in the expression of psychostimulant sensitization is not clear-cut. On the one hand, psychostimulant sensitization-induced long-term changes in cellular reactivity or cellular morphology are not generally found in the nucleus accumbens shell after psychostimulant administration (Cadoni et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">2000</xref>; Li et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">2004</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>). Moreover, post induction lesions of the shell leave the expression of cocaine sensitization intact (Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">2002b</xref>), although preinduction lesions of a subarea of the shell result in reduced sensitized, but not acute responses to cocaine (Brenhouse and Stellar <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">2006</xref>). On the other hand, microinjection of amphetamine or cocaine into the shell (but not core) produces sensitized psychomotor responses and augmented dopamine levels in animals pretreated with cocaine (Filip and Siwanowicz <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">2001</xref>; Pierce and Kalivas <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">1995</xref>), and sensitized cellular reactivity has been observed in specific subareas within the accumbens shell after repeated cocaine administration (Brenhouse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">2006</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>). Discrepancies between studies finding the effects of sensitization in the shell and the present study could be due to the use of cocaine pretreatment and/or challenges in other studies and amphetamine pretreatment and challenge in the present study. Cocaine and amphetamine have been observed to produce different activation patterns in the dorsal striatum with acute amphetamine producing activation of patches and acute cocaine producing a more homogenous staining pattern (Graybiel et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">1990</xref>); it is possible that cocaine and amphetamine pretreatment produce different patterns of reactivity in the ventral striatum as well.</p>
        <p>Within the prefrontal cortex, all areas showed c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in response to amphetamine, but there was no effect of amphetamine preexposure. To our knowledge, this is the first examination of c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in orbital and lateral prefrontal areas. However, the lack of sensitization of c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in the medial prefrontal cortex corresponds well with results from other groups showing similar results after 2&#xA0;weeks of abstinence (Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">2002a</xref>). Sensitization of c-<italic>fos</italic> immunoreactivity does occur when animals are challenged after 2&#xA0;days of abstinence (Hedou et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">2002</xref>; Todtenkopf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">2002a</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">b</xref>), suggesting a role in the induction or early phases of sensitization. In support of a role for the prefrontal cortex in the induction and early phases of expression, lesion studies have demonstrated region-specific effects in the involvement of prefrontal areas in the induction of cocaine sensitization (Tzschentke and Schmidt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2000</xref>), and lesions of the entire medial prefrontal cortex have been shown to prevent the induction of amphetamine sensitization (Wolf et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">1995</xref>; Cador et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">1999</xref>, but see Tzschentke and Schmidt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">2000</xref>). Studies examining expression of psychostimulant sensitization suggest that the dorsal areas of the medial prefrontal cortex that project to the nucleus accumbens core are involved in the expression of psychostimulant sensitization (Steketee <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">2003</xref>). Although no sensitization of immediate-early gene expression was observed in the present study, a dorsal&#x2013;ventral gradient was seen in acute response to amphetamine with the prelimbic area showing a 74% increase in the SA group over the SS group and the infralimbic area showing a smaller increase at 45%. The high responsivity of lateral prefrontal neurons to amphetamine (114% increase in SA over SS) is also interesting in this respect, as the projections from this area to the nucleus accumbens are nearly exclusive to the nucleus accumbens core (Berendse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1992</xref>). The highly active prefrontal cortical inputs projecting to the core may play a role in enhancing the activation of the core during the expression of sensitization.</p>
        <p>Remarkably, the highest responsivity to acute amphetamine was found in the orbital frontal area, a prefrontal cortex area that projects primarily to the dorsal striatum and only very sparsely to the nucleus accumbens (Berendse et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">1992</xref>). Metabolic and structural changes within the orbital prefrontal cortex have been demonstrated in human drug addicts and nonhuman primates and rodents with a history of drug self-administration (Crombag et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">2005</xref>; Porrino and Lyons <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">2000</xref>; Volkow and Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>). A recent study showed that rats sensitized to cocaine are impaired on a task that is sensitive to orbital prefrontal lesions (Schoenbaum et al. <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">2004</xref>). The high responsivity of this area to acute amphetamine indicates that corticostriatal circuits not involving the nucleus accumbens also play an important role in the acute response to amphetamine.</p>
        <p>In conclusion, challenging animals sensitized to amphetamine with a dose of the drug that produces preferential activation of dorsal striatal patches did not produce stereotyped behavior, unlike the behavioral pattern observed in animals treated acutely with a dose of amphetamine that causes the same pattern of neural activation. Sensitized immediate-early gene activity was found in the nucleus accumbens core, but not the accumbens shell or the prefrontal cortex. The gradients observed in the present study in cellular responses to amphetamine in subareas of the prefrontal cortex with specific afferents to the nucleus accumbens suggest a specific role for various corticostriatal loops in the behavioral responses to psychostimulant drugs, further supporting the importance of accumbens&#x2013;prefrontal cortex interactions in drug addiction (Volkow and Li <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">2004</xref>; Robbins and Everitt <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">2002</xref>).</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>The support provided by the Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO grant 903-47-092) for this project is gratefully acknowledged.</p>
      <p><bold>Open Access</bold> This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Noncommercial License which permits any noncommercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author(s) and source are credited.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Badiani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Oates</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>HE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akil</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Environmental modulation of amphetamine-induced c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in D1 versus D2 striatal neurons</article-title>
          <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>103</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>209</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-4328(99)00041-8</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Badiani A, Oates MM, Day HE, Watson SJ, Akil H, Robinson TE (1999) Environmental modulation of amphetamine-induced c-fos expression in D1 versus D2 striatal neurons. Behav Brain Res 103:203&#x2013;209 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10513588</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berendse</surname>
              <given-names>HW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galis-de Graaf</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenewegen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Topographical organization and relationship with ventral striatal compartments of prefrontal corticostriatal projections in the rat</article-title>
          <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>316</volume>
          <fpage>314</fpage>
          <lpage>347</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.903160305</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Berendse HW, Galis-de Graaf Y, Groenewegen HJ (1992) Topographical organization and relationship with ventral striatal compartments of prefrontal corticostriatal projections in the rat. J Comp Neurol 316:314&#x2013;347 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1577988</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Berretta</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graybiel</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dopamine and glutamate agonists stimulate neuron-specific expression of Fos-like protein in the striatum</article-title>
          <source>J Neurophysiol</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>767</fpage>
          <lpage>777</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Berretta S, Robertson HA, Graybiel AM (1992) Dopamine and glutamate agonists stimulate neuron-specific expression of Fos-like protein in the striatum. J Neurophysiol 68:767&#x2013;777 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1359024</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brenhouse</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stellar</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>c-Fos and &#x394;FosB expression are differentially altered in distinct subregions of the nucleus accumbens shell in cocaine-sensitized rats</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>137</volume>
          <fpage>773</fpage>
          <lpage>780</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.09.039</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brenhouse HC, Stellar JR (2006) c-Fos and &#x394;FosB expression are differentially altered in distinct subregions of the nucleus accumbens shell in cocaine-sensitized rats. Neuroscience 137:773&#x2013;780 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16337088</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brenhouse</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Montalto</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stellar</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electrolytic lesions of a discrete area within the nucleus accumbens shell attenuate the long-term expression, but not early phase, of sensitization to cocaine</article-title>
          <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>170</volume>
          <fpage>219</fpage>
          <lpage>223</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbr.2006.02.029</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brenhouse HC, Montalto S, Stellar JR (2006) Electrolytic lesions of a discrete area within the nucleus accumbens shell attenuate the long-term expression, but not early phase, of sensitization to cocaine. Behav Brain Res 170:219&#x2013;223 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16580740</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cadoni</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Solinas</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychostimulant sensitization: differential changes in accumbal shell and core dopamine</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>388</volume>
          <fpage>69</fpage>
          <lpage>76</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-2999(99)00824-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cadoni C, Solinas M, Di Chiara G (2000) Psychostimulant sensitization: differential changes in accumbal shell and core dopamine. Eur J Pharmacol 388:69&#x2013;76 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10657548</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cador</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bjijou</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cailho</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stinus</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>D-amphetamine-induced behavioral sensitization: implication of a glutamatergic medial prefrontal cortex-ventral tegmental area innervation</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>94</volume>
          <fpage>705</fpage>
          <lpage>721</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(99)00361-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cador M, Bjijou Y, Cailho S, Stinus L (1999) D-amphetamine-induced behavioral sensitization: implication of a glutamatergic medial prefrontal cortex-ventral tegmental area innervation. Neuroscience 94:705&#x2013;721 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10579562</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Canales</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graybiel</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A measure of striatal function predicts motor stereotypy</article-title>
          <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>377</fpage>
          <lpage>383</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/73949</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Canales JJ, Graybiel AM (2000) A measure of striatal function predicts motor stereotypy. Nat Neurosci 3:377&#x2013;383 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10725928</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Cardinal</surname>
              <given-names>RN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Parkinson</surname>
              <given-names>JA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hall</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Everitt</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Emotion and motivation: the role of the amygdala, ventral striatum, and prefrontal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Neurosci Biobehav Rev</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>321</fpage>
          <lpage>352</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0149-7634(02)00007-6</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Cardinal RN, Parkinson JA, Hall J, Everitt BJ (2002) Emotion and motivation: the role of the amygdala, ventral striatum, and prefrontal cortex. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 26:321&#x2013;352 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12034134</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Crombag</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gorny</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolb</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Opposite effects of amphetamine self-administration experience on dendritic spines in the medial and orbital prefrontal cortex</article-title>
          <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>341</fpage>
          <lpage>348</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/bhh136</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Crombag HS, Gorny G, Li Y, Kolb B, Robinson TE (2005) Opposite effects of amphetamine self-administration experience on dendritic spines in the medial and orbital prefrontal cortex. Cereb Cortex 15:341&#x2013;348 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15269111</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vries</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoffelmeer</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tjon</surname>
              <given-names>GH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nestby</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mifepristone prevents the expression of long-term behavioural sensitization to amphetamine</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>304</volume>
          <fpage>R3</fpage>
          <lpage>R4</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0014-2999(96)00308-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">De Vries TJ, Schoffelmeer AN, Tjon GH, Nestby P, Mulder AH, Vanderschuren LJ (1996) Mifepristone prevents the expression of long-term behavioural sensitization to amphetamine. Eur J Pharmacol 304:R3&#x2013;R4 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8832229</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Everitt</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Psychomotor stimulant addiction: a neural systems perspective</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>3312</fpage>
          <lpage>3320</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Everitt BJ, Wolf ME (2002) Psychomotor stimulant addiction: a neural systems perspective. J Neurosci 22:3312&#x2013;3320 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11978805</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Filip</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Siwanowicz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Implication of the nucleus accumbens shell, but not core, in the acute and sensitizing effects of cocaine in rats</article-title>
          <source>Pol J Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>459</fpage>
          <lpage>466</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Filip M, Siwanowicz J (2001) Implication of the nucleus accumbens shell, but not core, in the acute and sensitizing effects of cocaine in rats. Pol J Pharmacol 53:459&#x2013;466 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11990063</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Graybiel</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moratalla</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robertson</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Amphetamine and cocaine induce drug-specific activation of the c-<italic>fos</italic> gene in striosome-matrix compartments and limbic subdivisions of the striatum</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>87</volume>
          <fpage>6912</fpage>
          <lpage>6916</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.87.17.6912</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Graybiel AM, Moratalla R, Robertson HA (1990) Amphetamine and cocaine induce drug-specific activation of the c-fos gene in striosome-matrix compartments and limbic subdivisions of the striatum. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 87:6912&#x2013;6916 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2118661</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Groenewegen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Uylings</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The anatomical relationships of the prefrontal cortex with limbic structures and the basal ganglia</article-title>
          <source>J Psychopharmacol</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>11</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>106</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1177/026988119701100202</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Groenewegen HJ, Wright CI, Uylings HB (1997) The anatomical relationships of the prefrontal cortex with limbic structures and the basal ganglia. J Psychopharmacol 11:99&#x2013;106 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9208373</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hedou</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jongen-Relo</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murphy</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Heidbreder</surname>
              <given-names>CA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Feldon</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sensitized Fos expression in subterritories of the rat medial prefrontal cortex and nucleus accumbens following amphetamine sensitization as revealed by stereology</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>950</volume>
          <fpage>165</fpage>
          <lpage>179</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(02)03034-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hedou G, Jongen-Relo AL, Murphy CA, Heidbreder CA, Feldon J (2002) Sensitized Fos expression in subterritories of the rat medial prefrontal cortex and nucleus accumbens following amphetamine sensitization as revealed by stereology. Brain Res 950:165&#x2013;179 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12231241</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hope</surname>
              <given-names>BT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Simmons</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitchell</surname>
              <given-names>TB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kreuter</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mattson</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cocaine-induced locomotor activity and Fos expression in nucleus accumbens are sensitized 6 months after repeated cocaine administration outside the home cage</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <fpage>867</fpage>
          <lpage>875</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2006.04969.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hope BT, Simmons DE, Mitchell TB, Kreuter JD, Mattson BJ (2006) Cocaine-induced locomotor activity and Fos expression in nucleus accumbens are sensitized 6 months after repeated cocaine administration outside the home cage. Eur J Neurosci 24:867&#x2013;875 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16930414</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hsieh</surname>
              <given-names>HC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>HY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiou</surname>
              <given-names>YF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lin</surname>
              <given-names>SY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wong</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Spatial and temporal profile of haloperidol-induced immediate-early gene expression an phosphoCREB binding in the dorsal and ventral striatum of amphetamine-sensitized rats</article-title>
          <source>Synapse</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>230</fpage>
          <lpage>244</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/syn.10099</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hsieh HC, Li HY, Lin MY, Chiou YF, Lin SY, Wong CH, Chen JC (2002) Spatial and temporal profile of haloperidol-induced immediate-early gene expression an phosphoCREB binding in the dorsal and ventral striatum of amphetamine-sensitized rats. Synapse 45:230&#x2013;244 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12125044</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jongen-Relo</surname>
              <given-names>AL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenewegen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voorn</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence for a multi-compartmental histochemical organization of the nucleus accumbens in the rat</article-title>
          <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>337</volume>
          <fpage>267</fpage>
          <lpage>276</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.903370207</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jongen-Relo AL, Groenewegen HJ, Voorn P (1993) Evidence for a multi-compartmental histochemical organization of the nucleus accumbens in the rat. J Comp Neurol 337:267&#x2013;276 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8277000</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lecca</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cacciapaglia</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valentini</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Acquas</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential neurochemical and behavioral adaptation to cocaine after response contingent and noncontingent exposure in the rat</article-title>
          <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>191</volume>
          <fpage>653</fpage>
          <lpage>667</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-006-0496-y</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lecca D, Cacciapaglia F, Valentini V, Acquas E, Di Chiara G (2007a) Differential neurochemical and behavioral adaptation to cocaine after response contingent and noncontingent exposure in the rat. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 191:653&#x2013;667 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16932924</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lecca</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Valentini</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cacciapaglia</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Acquas</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiara</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Reciprocal effects of response contingent and noncontingent intravenous heroin on in vivo nucleus accumbens shell versus core dopamine in the rat: a repeated sampling microdialysis study</article-title>
          <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>194</volume>
          <fpage>103</fpage>
          <lpage>116</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00213-007-0815-y</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lecca D, Valentini V, Cacciapaglia F, Acquas E, Di Chiara G (2007b) Reciprocal effects of response contingent and noncontingent intravenous heroin on in vivo nucleus accumbens shell versus core dopamine in the rat: a repeated sampling microdialysis study. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 194:103&#x2013;116 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17541779</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Acerbo</surname>
              <given-names>MJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The induction of behavioural sensitization is associated with cocaine-induced structural plasticity in the core (but not shell) of the nucleus accumbens</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>20</volume>
          <fpage>1647</fpage>
          <lpage>1654</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03612.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Li Y, Acerbo MJ, Robinson TE (2004) The induction of behavioural sensitization is associated with cocaine-induced structural plasticity in the core (but not shell) of the nucleus accumbens. Eur J Neurosci 20:1647&#x2013;1654 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15355332</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ostrander</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badiani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Day</surname>
              <given-names>HE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Norton</surname>
              <given-names>CS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Watson</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akil</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Environmental context and drug history modulate amphetamine-induced c-<italic>fos</italic> mRNA expression in the basal ganglia, central extended amygdala, and associated limbic forebrain</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>120</volume>
          <fpage>551</fpage>
          <lpage>571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(03)00247-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ostrander MM, Badiani A, Day HE, Norton CS, Watson SJ, Akil H, Robinson TE (2003) Environmental context and drug history modulate amphetamine-induced c-fos mRNA expression in the basal ganglia, central extended amygdala, and associated limbic forebrain. Neuroscience 120:551&#x2013;571 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12890524</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Phillips</surname>
              <given-names>GD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setzu</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vugler</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hitchcott</surname>
              <given-names>PK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An immunohistochemical examination of the effects of sensitisation on the mesotelencephalic dopaminergic response to <sc>d</sc>-amphetamine</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>741</fpage>
          <lpage>753</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(02)00800-X</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Phillips GD, Setzu E, Vugler A, Hitchcott PK (2003) An immunohistochemical examination of the effects of sensitisation on the mesotelencephalic dopaminergic response to d-amphetamine. Neuroscience 117:741&#x2013;753 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12617978</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalivas</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Amphetamine produces sensitized increases in locomotion and extracellular dopamine preferentially in the nucleus accumbens shell of rats administered repeated cocaine</article-title>
          <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>275</volume>
          <fpage>1019</fpage>
          <lpage>1029</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pierce RC, Kalivas PW (1995) Amphetamine produces sensitized increases in locomotion and extracellular dopamine preferentially in the nucleus accumbens shell of rats administered repeated cocaine. J Pharmacol Exp Ther 275:1019&#x2013;1029 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7473128</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalivas</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A circuitry model of the expression of behavioral sensitization to amphetamine-like psychostimulants</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res Brain Res Rev</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>192</fpage>
          <lpage>216</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0173(97)00021-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pierce RC, Kalivas PW (1997) A circuitry model of the expression of behavioral sensitization to amphetamine-like psychostimulants. Brain Res Brain Res Rev 25:192&#x2013;216 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9403138</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pierce</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Reeder</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hicks</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morgan</surname>
              <given-names>ZR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalivas</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ibotenic acid lesions of the dorsal prefrontal cortex disrupt the expression of behavioral sensitization to cocaine</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1103</fpage>
          <lpage>1114</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(97)00366-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pierce RC, Reeder DC, Hicks J, Morgan ZR, Kalivas PW (1998) Ibotenic acid lesions of the dorsal prefrontal cortex disrupt the expression of behavioral sensitization to cocaine. Neuroscience 82:1103&#x2013;1114 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9466434</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Porrino</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lyons</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Orbital and medial prefrontal cortex and psychostimulant abuse: studies in animal models</article-title>
          <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>326</fpage>
          <lpage>333</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/10.3.326</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Porrino LJ, Lyons D (2000) Orbital and medial prefrontal cortex and psychostimulant abuse: studies in animal models. Cereb Cortex 10:326&#x2013;333 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10731227</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Everitt</surname>
              <given-names>BJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Limbic-striatal memory systems and drug addiction</article-title>
          <source>Neurobiol Learn Mem</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>625</fpage>
          <lpage>636</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/nlme.2002.4103</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Robbins TW, Everitt BJ (2002) Limbic-striatal memory systems and drug addiction. Neurobiol Learn Mem 78:625&#x2013;636 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12559840</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robinson</surname>
              <given-names>TE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kolb</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Structural plasticity associated with exposure to drugs of abuse</article-title>
          <source>Neuropharmacology</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>47</volume>
          <fpage>33</fpage>
          <lpage>46</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neuropharm.2004.06.025</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Robinson TE, Kolb B (2004) Structural plasticity associated with exposure to drugs of abuse. Neuropharmacology 47:33&#x2013;46 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15464124</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Salamone</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Correa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mingote</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>SM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nucleus accumbens dopamine and the regulation of effort in food-seeking behavior: implications for studies of natural motivation, psychiatry, and drug abuse</article-title>
          <source>J Pharmacol Exp Ther</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>305</volume>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>8</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/jpet.102.035063</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Salamone JD, Correa M, Mingote S, Weber SM (2003) Nucleus accumbens dopamine and the regulation of effort in food-seeking behavior: implications for studies of natural motivation, psychiatry, and drug abuse. J Pharmacol Exp Ther 305:1&#x2013;8 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12649346</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schoenbaum</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saddoris</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ramus</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Shaham</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Setlow</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cocaine-experienced rats exhibit learning deficits in a task sensitive to orbitofrontal cortex lesions</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>19</volume>
          <fpage>1997</fpage>
          <lpage>2002</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1460-9568.2004.03274.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schoenbaum G, Saddoris MP, Ramus SJ, Shaham Y, Setlow B (2004) Cocaine-experienced rats exhibit learning deficits in a task sensitive to orbitofrontal cortex lesions. Eur J Neurosci 19:1997&#x2013;2002 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078575</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Steketee</surname>
              <given-names>JD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neurotransmitter systems of the medial prefrontal cortex: potential role in sensitization to psychostimulants</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res Brain Res Rev</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>41</volume>
          <fpage>203</fpage>
          <lpage>228</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0165-0173(02)00233-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Steketee JD (2003) Neurotransmitter systems of the medial prefrontal cortex: potential role in sensitization to psychostimulants. Brain Res Brain Res Rev 41:203&#x2013;228 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12663081</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stewart</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Badiani</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Tolerance and sensitization to the behavioral effects of drugs</article-title>
          <source>Behav Pharmacol</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>289</fpage>
          <lpage>312</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stewart J, Badiani A (1993) Tolerance and sensitization to the behavioral effects of drugs. Behav Pharmacol 4:289&#x2013;312 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11224198</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Todtenkopf</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mihalakopoulos</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stellar</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Withdrawal duration differentially affects c-<italic>fos</italic> expression in the medial prefrontal cortex and discrete subregions of the nucleus accumbens in cocaine-sensitized rats</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>114</volume>
          <fpage>1061</fpage>
          <lpage>1069</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Todtenkopf MS, Mihalakopoulos A, Stellar JR (2002a) Withdrawal duration differentially affects c-fos expression in the medial prefrontal cortex and discrete subregions of the nucleus accumbens in cocaine-sensitized rats. Neuroscience 114:1061&#x2013;1069 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379259</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Todtenkopf</surname>
              <given-names>MS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stellar</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Melloni</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Neither ibotenic acid nor volkensin lesions of the nucleus accumbens shell affect the expression of cocaine sensitization</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>541</fpage>
          <lpage>546</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2002.02121.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Todtenkopf MS, Stellar JR, Melloni RH Jr (2002b) Neither ibotenic acid nor volkensin lesions of the nucleus accumbens shell affect the expression of cocaine sensitization. Eur J Neurosci 16:541&#x2013;546 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12193198</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tzschentke</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Discrete quinolinic acid lesions of the rat prelimbic medial prefrontal cortex affect cocaine- and MK-801-, but not morphine- and amphetamine-induced reward and psychomotor activation as measured with the place preference conditioning paradigm</article-title>
          <source>Behav Brain Res</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>97</volume>
          <fpage>115</fpage>
          <lpage>127</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0166-4328(98)00034-5</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tzschentke TM, Schmidt WJ (1998) Discrete quinolinic acid lesions of the rat prelimbic medial prefrontal cortex affect cocaine- and MK-801-, but not morphine- and amphetamine-induced reward and psychomotor activation as measured with the place preference conditioning paradigm. Behav Brain Res 97:115&#x2013;127 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9867237</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Tzschentke</surname>
              <given-names>TM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmidt</surname>
              <given-names>WJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential effects of discrete subarea-specific lesions of the rat medial prefrontal cortex on amphetamine- and cocaine-induced behavioural sensitization</article-title>
          <source>Cereb Cortex</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>10</volume>
          <fpage>488</fpage>
          <lpage>498</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/cercor/10.5.488</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Tzschentke TM, Schmidt WJ (2000) Differential effects of discrete subarea-specific lesions of the rat medial prefrontal cortex on amphetamine- and cocaine-induced behavioural sensitization. Cereb Cortex 10:488&#x2013;498 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10847599</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kalivas</surname>
              <given-names>PW</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alterations in dopaminergic and glutamatergic transmission in the induction and expression of behavioral sensitization: a critical review of preclinical studies</article-title>
          <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>151</volume>
          <fpage>99</fpage>
          <lpage>120</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002130000493</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vanderschuren LJ, Kalivas PW (2000) Alterations in dopaminergic and glutamatergic transmission in the induction and expression of behavioral sensitization: a critical review of preclinical studies. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 151:99&#x2013;120 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10972458</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoffelmeer</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vries</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Dopaminergic mechanisms mediating the long-term expression of locomotor sensitization following pre-exposure to morphine or amphetamine</article-title>
          <source>Psychopharmacology (Berl)</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>143</volume>
          <fpage>244</fpage>
          <lpage>253</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s002130050943</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vanderschuren LJ, Schoffelmeer AN, Mulder AH, De Vries TJ (1999a) Dopaminergic mechanisms mediating the long-term expression of locomotor sensitization following pre-exposure to morphine or amphetamine. Psychopharmacology (Berl) 143:244&#x2013;253 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10353426</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoffelmeer</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mulder</surname>
              <given-names>AH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vries</surname>
              <given-names>TJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lack of cross-sensitization of the locomotor effects of morphine in amphetamine-treated rats</article-title>
          <source>Neuropsychopharmacology</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>21</volume>
          <fpage>550</fpage>
          <lpage>559</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0893-133X(99)00051-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vanderschuren LJ, Schoffelmeer AN, Mulder AH, De Vries TJ (1999b) Lack of cross-sensitization of the locomotor effects of morphine in amphetamine-treated rats. Neuropsychopharmacology 21:550&#x2013;559 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10481839</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schoffelmeer</surname>
              <given-names>AN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Leeuwen</surname>
              <given-names>SD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hof</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jonker</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Voorn</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Compartment-specific changes in striatal neuronal activity during expression of amphetamine sensitization are the result of drug hypersensitivity</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>2462</fpage>
          <lpage>2468</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2002.02308.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vanderschuren LJ, Schoffelmeer AN, Van Leeuwen SD, Hof L, Jonker AJ, Voorn P (2002) Compartment-specific changes in striatal neuronal activity during expression of amphetamine sensitization are the result of drug hypersensitivity. Eur J Neurosci 16:2462&#x2013;2468 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12492441</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Volkow</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>TK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Drug addiction: the neurobiology of behaviour gone awry</article-title>
          <source>Nat Rev Neurosci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>5</volume>
          <fpage>963</fpage>
          <lpage>970</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nrn1539</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Volkow ND, Li TK (2004) Drug addiction: the neurobiology of behaviour gone awry. Nat Rev Neurosci 5:963&#x2013;970 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15550951</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Voorn</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vanderschuren</surname>
              <given-names>LJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenewegen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Robbins</surname>
              <given-names>TW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pennartz</surname>
              <given-names>CM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Putting a spin on the dorsal&#x2013;ventral divide of the striatum</article-title>
          <source>Trends Neurosci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>468</fpage>
          <lpage>474</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.tins.2004.06.006</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Voorn P, Vanderschuren LJ, Groenewegen HJ, Robbins TW, Pennartz CM (2004) Putting a spin on the dorsal&#x2013;ventral divide of the striatum. Trends Neurosci 27:468&#x2013;474 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15271494</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wolf</surname>
              <given-names>ME</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dahlin</surname>
              <given-names>SL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hu</surname>
              <given-names>XT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xue</surname>
              <given-names>CY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>White</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of lesions of prefrontal cortex, amygdala or fornix on behavioral sensitization to amphetamine: Comparison with N-methyl-D-aspartate antagonists</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>419</fpage>
          <lpage>439</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(95)00248-H</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wolf ME, Dahlin SL, Hu XT, Xue CY, White K (1995) Effects of lesions of prefrontal cortex, amygdala or fornix on behavioral sensitization to amphetamine: Comparison with N-methyl-D-aspartate antagonists. Neuroscience 69:419&#x2013;439 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wright</surname>
              <given-names>CI</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Groenewegen</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Patterns of convergence and segregation in the medial nucleus accumbens of the rat: relationships of prefrontal cortical, midline thalamic, and basal amygdaloid afferents</article-title>
          <source>J Comp Neurol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>361</volume>
          <fpage>383</fpage>
          <lpage>403</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.903610304</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wright CI, Groenewegen HJ (1995) Patterns of convergence and segregation in the medial nucleus accumbens of the rat: relationships of prefrontal cortical, midline thalamic, and basal amygdaloid afferents. J Comp Neurol 361:383&#x2013;403 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8550887</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiao</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>Q</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lou</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Katz</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>c-Fos facilitates the acquisition and extinction of cocaine-induced persistent changes</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>13287</fpage>
          <lpage>13296</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3795-06.2006</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zhang J, Zhang L, Jiao H, Zhang Q, Zhang D, Lou D, Katz JL, Xu M (2006) c-Fos facilitates the acquisition and extinction of cocaine-induced persistent changes. J Neurosci 26:13287&#x2013;13296 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17182779</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>