<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" xml:lang="EN" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Purinergic Signal</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Purinergic Signalling</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1573-9538</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-9546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18404492</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2096647</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9004</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11302-006-9004-4</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Article</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Excitatory effect of ATP on rat area postrema neurons</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Sorimachia</surname>
            <given-names>Masaru</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <email>ciliary@m.kufm.kagoshima-u.ac.jp</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Wakamoria</surname>
            <given-names>Minoru</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Akaikeb</surname>
            <given-names>Norio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Department of Physiology, Graduate School of Medical and Dental Sciences, Kagoshima University, Kagoshima,  890-8520 Japan </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Research Division for Life Sciences,  Kumamoto Health Science University, Kumamoto, 861-5598 Japan </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>30</day>
        <month>5</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>2</volume>
      <issue>3</issue>
      <fpage>545</fpage>
      <lpage>557</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>11</day>
          <month>10</month>
          <year>2005</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>26</day>
          <month>1</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer Science + Business Media B.V. 2006</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract xml:lang="EN">
        <p>ATP-induced inward currents and increases in the cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration ([Ca]<sub>in</sub>) were investigated in neurons acutely dissociated from rat area postrema using whole-cell patch-clamp recordings and fura-2 microfluorometry, respectively. The ATP-induced current (<italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>) and [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases were mimicked by 2-methylthio-ATP and ATP-&#x3B3;S, and were inhibited by P2X receptor (P2XR) antagonists. The current&#x2013;voltage relationship of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> exhibited a strong inward rectification, and the amplitude of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was concentration-dependent. The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was markedly reduced in the absence of external Na<sup>+</sup>, and the addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to Na<sup>+</sup>-free saline increased the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. ATP did not increase [Ca]<sub>in</sub> in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, and Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel antagonists partially inhibited the ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase, indicating that ATP increases [Ca]<sub>in</sub> by Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx through both P2XR channels and voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels. There was a negative interaction between P2XR- and nicotinic ACh receptor (nAChR)-channels, which depended on the amplitude and direction of current flow through either channel. Current occlusion was observed at <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>s between &#x2212;70 and &#x2212;10 mV when the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and ACh-induced current (<italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>) were inward, but no occlusion was observed when these currents were outward at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of +40&#xA0;mV. The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was not inhibited by co-application of ACh when the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was markedly decreased either by removal of permeant cations, by setting <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> close to the equilibrium potential of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, or by the addition of <italic>d</italic>-tubocurarine or serotonin. These results suggest that the inhibitory interaction is attributable to inward current flow of cations through the activated P2XR- and nAChR-channels.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>ATP</kwd>
        <kwd>ACh</kwd>
        <kwd>cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration</kwd>
        <kwd>Fura-2 microfluorometry</kwd>
        <kwd>negative interaction between nicotinic and P2X channels</kwd>
        <kwd>whole-cell patch-clamp recording</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science + Business Media B.V. 2006</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>The rat area postrema (AP) is a medullary circum-ventricular organ located in the hindbrain at the level of the obex, with a dense vascular supply devoid of a blood-brain barrier. The lack of a blood-brain barrier makes the AP ideally placed to act as a chemosensitive trigger zone involved in the control of vomiting in response to circulating emetic substances (Borison [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]). Neurons in the AP are also responsive to changes in osmolarity or sodium concentration (Franchini et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]), and can be activated by circulating vasoactive peptides such as angiotensin II (Fink et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>]), and arg-vasopressin (Undesser et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]). Anatomical studies have revealed that the AP sends dense efferent projections to the nucleus tractus solitarius, parabrachial nucleus, nucleus ambiguus, and the dorsal motor nucleus of the vagus, and receives afferent inputs from the hypothalamic paraventricular and dorsomedial nucleii, and from the caudal nucleus tractus solitarius (Morest [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]; Kooy and Koda [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]; Shapiro and Miselis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]). Thus, the AP is not only capable of responding to circulating hormones, but is also anatomically well situated to regulate a range of other central neurons, including those important in cardiovascular control (Sun and Spyer [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]). The low intrinsic firing rates of AP neurons <italic>in vivo</italic> (Papas et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>]) suggests that understanding and modulating excitatory inputs to AP could be particularly important in the functional output of AP neurons. A number of transmitters can evoke excitatory currents in the AP. Inward currents and increases in cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> ([Ca]<sub>in</sub>) via non-NMDA-glutamate receptors have been reported in rabbit and rat AP neurons, respectively (Jahn et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]; Hay and Lindsley [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]). Our preliminary reports indicated that ATP also induces inward currents and [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases via the activation of P2X receptor (P2XR) in isolated rat AP neurons (Sorimachi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]). In addition, pre- and post-synaptic nicotinic ACh receptors (nAChR) have been demonstrated in the AP in rat brain slices (Funahashi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]), and we have recently reported the presence of nAChRs in dissociated rat AP neurons (Sorimachi and Wakamori [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]). During that study, we also noticed that many of these AP neurons also responded to ATP, which has prompted us to further investigate ATP responses in AP neurons, and potential interactions between nAChR and P2XR responses. In a variety of different peripheral neurons, including sympathetic neurons of bullfrog (Akasu and Koketsu [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]), rat (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]), and guinea-pig (Searl et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]), cultured guinea-pig enteric and submucosal neurons (Zhou and Galligan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] Barajas-Lopez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]), a negative interaction between P2XR- and nAChR responses has been reported. Such an interaction has also been observed for recombinant P2X2 and &#x3B1;3&#x3B2;4 nAChR channels in Xenopus oocytes and HEK cells (Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]; Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]), where it has been recently suggested that this results from direct physical interactions between co-localized receptors (Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]). In this study we more fully describe P2XR responses in AP neurons, demonstrate cross-inhibition between P2XRs and nAChRs and characterize some of the features of this cross-inhibition.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Experimental procedures</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Preparation of AP neurons</title>
        <p>The study was approved by the Committee on Animal Experimentation, Kagoshima University. Wistar rats (13&#x2013;18 days-old) were anaesthetized with ether and decapitated. The brain was quickly removed from the skull and placed in ice-cold HEPES-buffered saline containing 150 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES and 5.5 mM glucose. The pH of the saline solution was adjusted to 7.4 by adding tris (hydroxymethyl) aminomethane. The brain was sliced at a thickness of 400 &#xB5;m with a microslicer (DTK-1000, Dosaka, Kyoto, Japan), and the slices were kept in bicarbonate-buffered saline bubbled continuously with 95% O<sub>2</sub>&#x2013;5% CO<sub>2</sub> at room temperature (21&#x2013;26 &#xB0;C). The bicarbonate-buffered saline contained 120 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20 mM NaHCO<sub>3</sub>, 2 mM KH<sub>2</sub>PO<sub>4</sub> and 5.5 mM glucose. Following 30&#x2013;60 min incubation, the slices were treated with pronase (0.2 mg/ml) in bicarbonate-buffered saline for 20 min at 33 &#xB0;C, followed by incubation for 30 min with bicarbonate-buffered saline containing thermolysin (0.12&#x2013;0.15 mg/ml). The bilateral AP regions were identified with a binocular microscope (Zeiss, Germany), and were cut out using the tip of an injection needle, and subsequently mechanically triturated with fire-polished glass pipettes of decreasing diameters. Dissociated neurons were placed on to the bottom of 35 mm culture dishes (Falcon, USA) for electrophysiological recordings, or on to glass coverslips (Matsunami, Japan) coated with poly-<sc>l</sc>-lysine for [Ca]<sub>in</sub> measurements.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Electrophysiological recordings</title>
        <p>Electrical measurements were done using the whole-cell patch-clamp recording configuration under voltage-clamp conditions. Patch pipettes were fabricated from borosilicate glass tubes in five or six stages using a pipette puller (Model P-97, Sutter Instrument, San Rafael, CA, USA). The resistance between the recording electrode filled with the internal solution, and the reference electrode in the external solution, was 3&#x2013;6 M&#x3A9;. Ionic currents were measured, and voltages controlled, using a patch-clamp amplifier (EPC-9, Heka, Darmstadt, Germany). All experiments were carried out at 24&#x2013;26 &#xB0;C. Culture dishes were placed on an inverted microscope (TE200, Nikon, Japan), and drugs were rapidly applied to single cells using a Y-tube perfusion device. The internal solution (patch pipette solution) contained 70 mM K-gluconate, 50 mM KCl, 10 mM NaCl, 0.5 mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 3 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 10 mM HEPES, 10 mM EGTA, and 2 mM ATP. The pH was adjusted to 7.2 with KOH. For measuring current-voltage (<italic>I&#x2013;V</italic>) relationships, a Cs-based internal solution was employed, which contained 98 mM CsOH, 40 mM CsCl, 98 mM aspartate, 2 mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 5 mM HEPES, 5 mM EGTA, and 2 mM ATP. pH was adjusted to 7.2 with CsOH. The external solution was the HEPES-buffered saline, pH7.4, described above. When <italic>N</italic>-methyl-<sc>d</sc>-glucamine (NMDG<sup>+</sup>) or sucrose was substituted for external Na<sup>+</sup> or NaCl, respectively, the osmolarity of the solution was kept constant as measured using an osmometer (Vogel OM801, Germany). To obtain the Ca<sup>2+</sup>/Na<sup>+</sup> permeability ratio (<italic>P</italic><sub>Ca</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Na</sub>), we measured the reversal potential of the ATP-activated current (<italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub>) in the presence of 1 or 110 mM of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> by stepping the holding potential (<italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>) between 10 and 30 mV, using increments of 10 mV. The 1 and 110 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> solutions contained 155 or 0 mM NaCl, respectively, in addition to 10 mM HEPES with pH adjusted to 7.4 with NaOH or Ca(OH)<sub>2</sub>, respectively. The values of <italic>P</italic><sub>Ca</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Cs</sub> and <italic>P</italic><sub>Na</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Cs</sub> were calculated using the constant field equation as described by Lewis ([<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]), taking the activity coefficients of Na<sup>+</sup>, Cs<sup>+</sup>, and Ca<sup>2+</sup> as 0.75, 0.75, and 0.3, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Measurement of [Ca]<sub>in</sub></title>
        <p>Dissociated AP neurons on a glass coverslip were incubated with 1&#x2013;2 &#xB5;M fura-2 acetoxymethyl ester (fura-2/AM), 0.1% dimethyl sulfoxide, and 1% bovine serum albumin for 45 min at 37 &#xB0;C. The coverslips were then mounted in a superfusion chamber and placed on the stage of an inverted microscope (Diaphot-TMD, Nikon, Japan). Cells were continuously superfused at a rate of 1 ml/min with HEPES-buffered saline at 24&#x2013;26 &#xB0;C via a polyethylene tube placed 1&#x2013;2 mm away from the cells.</p>
        <p>Cells were viewed with a 40&#xD7; Fluor objective lens (Nikon), and a single cell (10&#x2013;12 &#xB5;m diameter) was fixed in a window positioned between the photomultiplier and the microscope. The changes in fluorescence ratios at 340 and 380 nm excitation wavelengths were measured using a CAM-200 spectrometer (Jasco, Japan). The absolute value of [Ca]<sub>in</sub> was calculated using the formulae as given by Grynkiewicz et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]: <inline-formula id="IEq1"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2006_Article_9004_TeX2GIFIEq1.gif --><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}
$$\lbrack Ca \rbrack_{in} = b \times Kd(R - R_{min})/(R_{max} - R)$$
\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. Calibration constants were determined in separate experiments with the same experimental set-up, as described previously (Sorimachi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]).</p>
        <p>Student&#x2019;s paired t test was used to evaluate differences between mean values obtained from the same cells, and Student&#x2019;s unpaired t test was used for data obtained from different groups of cells.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Reagents</title>
        <p>The following reagents were used: Fura-2/AM [Dojindo, Kumamoto, Japan], ACh [Horai Chem. Co., Japan], PPADS (pyridoxal-phosphate-6-azophenyl-2&#x2032;, 4&#x2032;-disulphonic acid) [RBI, USA.], pronase [Calbiochem., USA], thermolysin, ATP, 2-methylthio-ATP, ATP&#x3B3;S, &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-methylene-ATP, &#x3B2;,&#x3B3;-methylene-ATP, ADP, nitrendipine, nicardipine, suramin [all from Sigma, Aldrich, Tokyo, Japan], &#x3C9;-conotoxin-MVIIA, &#x3C9;-conotoxin-MVIIC and &#x3C9;-agatoxin-IVA [all from Peptide Institute, Osaka, Japan].</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>ATP-induced current</title>
        <p>Rapid application of ATP (100 &#xB5;M) to isolated AP neurons voltage clamped at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV induced an inward current, which desensitized slowly (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1A</xref>). The ATP-induced current (<italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>) was recorded at various <italic>V</italic><sub>hs</sub> between &#x2212;70 and +50 mV (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>: <italic>N</italic> = 6), and the relative current amplitude was plotted against <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> exhibiting a strong inward rectification. The <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, estimated from the intersection of the current response and the zero voltage-axis (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>), was 22.7 &#xB1; 0.9 mV (<italic>N</italic> = 18).
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig. 1</label><caption><p>Current-voltage relationship for ATP-induced currents. <bold>A</bold>) Representative currents in response to 200 &#xB5;M ATP recorded at <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>s between &#x2212;70 and +50 mV. <bold>B</bold>) Current-voltage relationship for the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. All responses are normalized to the peak current amplitude obtained at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV, and each point is the mean &#xB1; S.E.M. of five neurons. <bold>C</bold>) Averaged concentration-current relationships for ATP in the presence of 0.1, 2, and 10 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. All responses were normalized to the mean of two control responses induced by 100 &#xB5;M ATP in saline containing 2 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup> before and after the test response. Each point is the average &#xB1; S.E.M of responses from four to six neurons.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig1" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
        <p>To investigate the ATP concentration-response relationship, care was taken to adjust the pH of the solutions containing higher concentrations of ATP to 7.3, since addition of ATP reduced pH and a small decrease in pH to 7.1 increased the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> to 189 &#xB1; 8% (<italic>N</italic> = 6) of control (pH7.3), as previously reported for recombinant P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors (King et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]). The responses to different ATP concentrations were flanked by responses to the control concentration of 100 &#xB5;M, and normalized responses were expressed relative to the average of these control responses (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>; Ca2mM). We also examined the effects of 0.1 and 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> on <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. As summarized in Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>, an increase in the external concentration of Ca<sup>2+</sup> shifted the concentration-response curve for ATP to the right, with the half-maximum effective concentration (EC<sub>50</sub>) values at 0.1, 2 and 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> being 30, 70, and 190 &#xB5;M, respectively.</p>
        <p>The purinergic agonists, 2-methylthio-ATP (50 &#xB5;M) and ATP&#x3B3;S (50 &#xB5;M) induced currents that were 41 &#xB1; 3% (<italic>N</italic> = 4), and 41 &#xB1; 4% (<italic>N</italic> = 5), respectively, of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in response to 100 &#xB5;M ATP. ADP (0.5 mM) did not produce any response. The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in response to 50 &#xB5;M ATP was inhibited by the P2 antagonists; suramin (10 &#xB5;M and 20 &#xB5;M) and PPADS (50 &#xB5;M), with the response being 35 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 5), 25 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 4), and 56 &#xB1; 5% (<italic>N</italic> = 5), of the control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, respectively.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase</title>
        <p>ATP also increased [Ca]<sub>in</sub> in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2A</xref>). These responses were all recorded in the presence of 2 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, and the [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases by various concentrations of ATP were normalized to that induced by 100 &#xB5;M ATP. The normalized and averaged responses to ATP, 2-methylthio-ATP and ATP&#x3B3;S are shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2B</xref>. There was no ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> (<italic>N</italic> = 6; data not shown). Furthermore, neither ADP, &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-methylene-ATP nor &#x3B2;,&#x3B3;-methylene-ATP increased [Ca]<sub>in</sub> when tested at concentrations of 200 &#xB5;M(data not shown). The ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases were inhibited by suramin and PPADS (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>).
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig. 2</label><caption><p>Concentration-response relationships for the [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases in response to ATP and ATP analogues. <bold>A</bold>) Representative [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases induced by various concentrations of ATP in the presence of 2 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>B</bold>) Averaged concentration-response relationships for ATP and ATP analogues. All responses were normalized to the mean of two control responses induced by 100 &#xB5;M ATP before and after the test response. Each point is the mean &#xB1; S.E.M. of data from five to nine neurons. MeS-ATP: 2-methylthio-ATP.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig2" id="MO2"/></fig><table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table 1</label><caption><p>Effects of P2 receptor antagonists and Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel blockers on the [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases induced by ATP and high K<sup>+</sup>-saline</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th>Stimulus</th><th>Blockers</th><th>Percent of control</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td>ATP100 M</td><td>Suramin 10 M</td><td>55 &#xB1; 7 (<italic>N</italic> = 5)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>20 M</td><td>30 &#xB1; 5(<italic>N</italic> = 6)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>50 M</td><td>13 &#xB1; 3 (<italic>N</italic> = 5)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>PPADS 10 M</td><td>96 &#xB1; 6 (<italic>N</italic> = 3)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>20 M</td><td>70 &#xB1; 8 (<italic>N</italic> = 9)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>50 M</td><td>25 &#xB1; 5 (<italic>N</italic> = 6)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>100 M</td><td>11 &#xB1; 5 (<italic>N</italic> = 4)</td></tr><tr><td>110 mMKCl</td><td>Nitrendipine 2 M</td><td>44 &#xB1; 4 (<italic>N</italic> = 16)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>&#x2212;CT.M C 2 M</td><td>61 &#xB1; 4 (<italic>N</italic> = 16)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>&#x2212;CT.M A 2 M</td><td>62 &#xB1; 6 (<italic>N</italic> = 16)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>&#x2212;CT.M A 2 M + &#x2212;CT.M C 2 M</td><td>58 &#xB1; 5 (<italic>N</italic> = 10)</td></tr><tr><td>ATP100 M</td><td>Nitrendipine 2 M</td><td>56 &#xB1; 4 (<italic>N</italic> = 21)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Nicardipine 2 M</td><td>47 &#xB1; 9 (<italic>N</italic> = 10)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>Cd<sup>2+</sup> 50 M</td><td>27 &#xB1; 3 (<italic>N</italic> = 14)</td></tr><tr><td/><td>&#x2212;CT.M A 2 M + &#x2212;CT.M C 2 M</td><td>77 &#xB1; 9 (<italic>N</italic> = 4)</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>The mean [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase induced by the first and third applications of ATP (100 &#x3BC;M) or 110 &#x3BC;M KCl were averaged and referred to as 100%, and the response in the presence of the P2 antagonist or Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel blocker was expressed as a percentage of this control value. The cell was pre-treated for 30 s with the indicated agent before the second stimulation with 100 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M ATP or 110 mM KCl. Number of experiments is shown in parentheses. <italic>&#x3C9;</italic>-CT <italic>&#x3C9;</italic>-conotoxin.</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Effects of Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel antagonists on ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase</title>
        <p>Previous results, using cultured rabbit AP neurons, demonstrated the presence of a &#x3C9;-conotoxin-M Csensitive Ca<sup>2+</sup> response, but that did not involve L- or N-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels (Hay et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]). We also investigated the effects of various Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel antagonists on [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases induced by high KCl (110 mM) and ATP (100 &#xB5;M). Antagonist for the L-type (nitrendipine, nicardipine), N-type (&#x3C9;-conotoxin-M A), or P/Q-type (&#x3C9;-conotoxin-M C) Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels each substantially inhibited these [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). In contrast, the selective P-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel antagonist, &#x3C9;-agatoxin IVA (1 &#xB5;M), did not have any inhibitory effect on the [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases (98 &#xB1; 5% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 4).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>ATP-induced current in the absence of external Na<sup>+</sup></title>
        <p>When external Na<sup>+</sup> was completely replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>, and in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> (0 Ca<sup>2+</sup> plus 0.5 mM EGTA), the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was markedly reduced to 8 &#xB1; 1% of the control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> recorded in the presence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> and 150 mM Na<sup>+</sup> (<italic>N</italic> = 9, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). This current was further reduced to 4 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 3) in the presence of 20 &#xB5;M suramin. The small suramin-sensitive, Na<sup>+</sup>-independent current supports the previous suggestion that the P2XR channel is permeable to glucosamine (Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]). To confirm this, ATP did not induce a current at all when sucrose (0.25 M) was substituted for NaCl (again in the absence of external Ca<sup>2+</sup>, <italic>N</italic> = 5). Addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to the NMDG<sup>+</sup>-substituted saline further increased <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. The currents induced by 500 &#xB5;M ATP in the presence of 2 and 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>, but in the absence of external Na<sup>+</sup> (replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>) were 18 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 11) and 29 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 14, Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref>) of the control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, respectively. Similarly, the currents induced by 500 &#xB5;M ATP in the presence of 2 and 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> added to the sucrose-substituted saline were 6 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 6), and 13 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 16; Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3C</xref>) of the control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, respectively.
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig. 3</label><caption><p>ATP-induced current in Na<sup>+</sup>- and NaCl-free saline containing 0 and 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>A</bold>) A representative <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> recorded in Na<sup>+</sup>-free (Na<sup>+</sup> replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>) and Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free saline (containing 0.5 mM EGTA) at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV. <bold>B</bold>) A representative <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in Na<sup>+</sup>-free (NMDG<sup>+</sup>) saline containing 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <bold>C</bold>) A representative <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in NaCl-free (NaCl replaced by sucrose) saline containing 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig3" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>We also measured the <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in the presence of 1 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup> and 150 mM NaCl or 110 mM external Ca<sup>2+</sup> and 0 mM NaCl. The <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> at 110 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> was 21.1 &#xB1; 1.0 mV (<italic>N</italic> = 18), from which we calculated a <italic>P</italic><sub>Ca</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Cs</sub> of 6.3. The <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> at 1 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> was 20.2 &#xB1; 1.0 mV (<italic>N</italic> = 13), from which we calculated a <italic>P</italic><sub>Na</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Cs</sub> ratio of 2.1. From these, we obtained a <italic>P</italic><sub>Ca</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Na</sub> ratio of 3.0, confirming the substantial Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability of P2XRs.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>Negative interaction between P2XR and nAChR channels</title>
        <p>Requirement of actual current flow through receptor channels for cross-inhibition</p>
        <p>It has previously been reported that there is mutual occlusion between P2XR and nAChR in some neurons (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]; Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]; Searl et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]; Zhou and Galligan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; Barajas-Lopez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]; Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]; Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]). To examine whether there were negative interactions between the ACh-activated current (<italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>) and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, one receptor agonist was added in the presence of the other. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref>, the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (100 &#xB5;M) was markedly reduced when activated in the presence of ATP (50 &#xB5;M). We next examined <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (100 &#xB5;M) in the presence of various concentrations of ATP. With 2, 10, 20, and 100 &#xB5;M ATP, <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was reduced to 95 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 20), 84 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 24), 60 &#xB1; 4% (<italic>N</italic> = 15), and 46 &#xB1; 6% (<italic>N</italic> = 7), respectively, of control (<italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01 except at 2 &#xB5;M ATP). Thus, the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> inhibition became stronger as the concentration of ATP was increased and with a higher agonist-receptor occupancy. In fact, when <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> at 100 &#xB5;M ATP was markedly inhibited in the presence of 200 mM PPADS (8 &#xB1; 2% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 6), <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was not occluded (97 &#xB1; 1% of control; <italic>N</italic> = 6). When the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, evoked by various concentrations of ATP, was plotted against the ratio of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> in the presence and absence of ATP, there was an inverse correlation between the amplitudes of these responses (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4B</xref>). Conversely, when ATP (50 &#xB5;M) was applied in the presence of ACh (100 &#xB5;M), <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was also occluded (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref>). Again, when <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> at 200 mM ACh was nullified in the presence of 1 mM hexamethonium, a nAChR antagonist (0.2 &#xB1; 0.2% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 6), <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was 96 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 6) of control. <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> at 10, 20, 50, and 200 &#xB5;M ACh were 6 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 5), 20 &#xB1; 4% (<italic>N</italic> = 5), 61 &#xB1; 8% (<italic>N</italic> = 6), and 139 &#xB1; 8% (<italic>N</italic> = 6) of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> at 100 &#xB5;M. There was also an inverse correlation between the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, evoked by various concentrations of ACh, and the ratio of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in the presence and absence of ACh (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4D</xref>). However, the inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> by nAChR activation was weaker than that of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> by P2XR activation. As the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> desensitized faster than the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, the weaker inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> by ACh could be due to the reduced amplitude of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> at the time of ATP application.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig. 4</label><caption><p>Inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, respectively, in the presence of ATP and ACh. <bold>A</bold>) Sample currents in response to ACh (100 &#xB5;M) in the presence of ATP (50 &#xB5;M). The responses to ACh applied in the presence of ATP were reduced. The extent of occlusion was normalized to the control ACh responses recorded before and after ATP application. This sequence was routinely repeated twice or three times, and the averaged amount of occlusion was plotted in <bold>B. B</bold>) Relative amplitude of the ACh current amplitude in the presence of ATP (<italic>ordinate</italic>) plotted against the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> obtained in the same neuron (<italic>abscissae</italic>). Note the negative correlation between these two variables. The line was drawn using KaleidaGraph (Synergy Software). <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>: &#x2212;70 mV. <bold>C</bold>) The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was recorded in the presence of 100 &#xB5;M ACh and this response was flanked by control ATP alone responses. This sequence was routinely obtained twice or three times in the same cell, and the averaged amount of occlusion was plotted in <bold>D. D</bold>) The ratio of the ATP current amplitude in the presence and absence of ACh (<italic>ordinate</italic>) is negatively correlated with the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (<italic>abscissae</italic>). <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> : &#x2212;70 mV.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig4" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
        <p>To examine this possibility, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was measured in the presence of both ACh and d-tubocurarine (dTc, 10 &#xB5;M) or serotonin (5HT, 50 &#xB5;M), two experimental conditions which change the time course of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> response. The former agent, dTc, has been shown to be both an open channel blocker and a competitive antagonist of nAChR (Manalis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>]), and, as expected, a low concentration (10 &#xB5;M) slightly reduced the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (79 &#xB1; 4% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 11) and caused the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> to be terminated within 0.5 s (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>, insert). Once the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> response had returned to baseline (in the presence of ACh and 10 &#xB5;M dTc) and ATP was applied, there was no inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (95 &#xB1; 1% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 5; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in the presence of ACh alone was 77 &#xB1; 4% of control (<italic>N</italic> = 5, <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>). When we measured the current (<italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub>) induced by a combination of ACh, ATP and dTc, the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub> was occluded under these conditions, being 74 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 10) of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ dTc</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>). The level of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub> at 0.5 s following ligand application, which corresponds to a time when the nAChR channels are completely blocked (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5A</xref>, insert), was 96 &#xB1; 3% (<italic>N</italic> = 8) of the control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, measured immediately before and after (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>). These results suggest that the inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> by <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> disappears immediately after the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> is abolished, although ACh is still present and bound to the nAChRs. 5HT has been shown to also accelerate the decay of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (Grassi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]; Garcia-Colunga and Miledi [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>]; Sorimachi and Wakamori [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]), but not to the same extent as dTc. 5HT at 50 &#xB5;M decreased the peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> slightly, to 88 &#xB1; 4% (<italic>N</italic> = 6) of control, and reduced the time constant (tau) of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> decay from 2.02 &#xB1; 0.18 to 1.06 &#xB1; 0.19 s (<italic>N</italic> = 6). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5D</xref>, the extent of inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> by ACh was smaller (to 92 &#xB1; 2% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 6) in the presence of ACh and 5HT compared to that in the presence of ACh alone (to 73 &#xB1; 3% of control, <italic>N</italic> = 6; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01).
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig. 5</label><caption><p>Loss of the inhibition of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> by ACh in the presence of dTc and 5HT. <bold>A</bold>) Representative <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in control conditions (applied alone), in the presence of ACh and in the presence of ACh and dTc. This sequence was routinely repeated twice, and the averaged response was obtained. Note the very transient nature of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> in the presence of dTc, with the current returning to baseline levels within 0.5 s (insert). Note also the lack of occlusion under these conditions. <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>: &#x2212;70 mV. B) Effect of dTc on <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub>. The sequence of applications was repeated multiple times in each neuron. The peak amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub> was smaller than the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+dTc</sub>. <bold>C</bold>) Rapid recovery of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> from inhibition by ACh in the presence of dTc. The amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub> 0.5 s following application was equal to the mean of two control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> at an equivalent time. Inset shows the rapid decline of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP+dTc</sub> on an expanded time scale. D) Representative <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in control conditions, in the presence of ACh, and in the presence of both ACh and 5HT. In this example, the tau of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> in response to the first application was 2.7 s, while the tau of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+5HT</sub> was 0.9 s, showing the acceleration of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> decay by 5HT. Note the reduced occlusion under these conditions. <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> : &#x2212;70 mV.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig5" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
        <p>Next, we measured the current induced by the concomitant applications of ACh and ATP (<italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub>) at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV. As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> was 75 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 44; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. The decay phase of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> were fit to a single exponential function, giving tau of 3.0 &#xB1; 0.2, 7.5 &#xB1; 0.6 and 3.7 &#xB1; 0.2 s, respectively. When the decay of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was accelerated by the presence of 100 &#xB5;M 5HT, the tau of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> were 0.8 &#xB1; 0.3 s (<italic>N</italic> = 7), 7.4 &#xB1; 1.4 s (<italic>N</italic> = 7) and 2.6 &#xB1; 0.8 s (<italic>N</italic> = 7), respectively (the amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> under these conditions was 76 &#xB1; 2% of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>). Thus, <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> desensitization occurs with kinetics that cannot be explained by the desensitization kinetics of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> or <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> alone, suggesting that <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> is mediated via both receptors.
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig. 6</label><caption><p>Voltage dependence of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> occlusion. <bold>A</bold>) At a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV, co-application of ACh (200 &#xB5;M) and ATP (100 &#xB5;M) induced an inward current that was smaller in amplitude than the predicted sum of the individual <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. <bold>B</bold>) At a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of +40 mV, the amplitude of the outward current induced by the co-application of ACh (500 &#xB5;M) and ATP (200 &#xB5;M) was equal to the predicted sum of the individual <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. <bold>C</bold>) Co-application of ATP and ACh does not markedly change <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> or <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. Representative currents induced by ACh, ATP, and by co-application of ACh and ATP at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of +10 mV. Note that <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> is composed of early outward and delayed inward current, corresponding to the ACh component and the ATP component, respectively.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig6" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
        <p>When Ca<sup>2+</sup> was omitted from extracellular solution, the negative interaction between the two receptor channels was still obtained; with <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> being 77 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 5; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01) of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. Hence negative interaction is not mediated by a Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx-dependent mechanism, although both nAChR and P2XR are Ca<sup>2+</sup>-permeable cation channels (Fieber and Adams [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]; Rogers and Dani [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]). This result, however, does not necessarily rule out the possible involvement of [Ca]<sub>in</sub> in negative interaction.</p>
        <p>Occlusion was not only observed at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV; <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> at <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>s of &#x2212;20, and &#x2212;10 mV were 80 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 12; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), and 76 &#xB1; 2% (<italic>N</italic> = 8; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01), respectively, of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. In sharp contrast, such occlusion was not observed at a positive potential; the outward current caused by coapplication of ACh and ATP at a <italic>V</italic><sub><italic>h</italic></sub> of +40 mV was 100 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 10) of the predicted sum of individual current (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>).</p>
        <p>We next investigated the possibility that the combined addition of ACh and ATP alters the driving force for Na<sup>+</sup>, by attempting to measure <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub>. In these studies, currents in response to ACh, ATP and both ligands were measured at various fixed potentials close to the reversal potential for <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. The <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> were 8.7 &#xB1; 1.5 mV (<italic>N</italic> = 5) and 21.0 &#xB1; 1.6 mV (<italic>N</italic> = 7), respectively, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> measured at a potential between these two reversal potentials (e.g.10 mV, Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6C</xref>) showed a combination of both the ACh-induced outward current and the ATP-induced inward current. These results suggest that the driving force for permeant ions during combined ACh and ATP is similar to that during the application of each ligand separately.</p>
        <p>The question arises as to whether occlusion is specific just for Na<sup>+</sup> ions or whether inward currents carried by cations other than Na<sup>+</sup> can also contribute to occlusion during co-activation of nAChRs and P2XRs. To address this question, we measured <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh +ATP</sub> in the presence of Na<sup>+</sup>-free (NMDG<sup>+</sup>) saline containing 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). NMDG<sup>+</sup> does not permeate through nAChR (Sorimachi and Wakamori [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]), and hence <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> would be mediated by only Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx, whereas <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> would be mediated via both NMDG<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> influx (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). Under these conditions, <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> was again occluded, being 70 &#xB1; 3% of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (<italic>N</italic> = 11; <italic>P</italic> &lt; 0.01; Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>).
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig. 7</label><caption><p>Occlusion of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> in the presence of Na<sup>+</sup>-free saline containing 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>. <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> or <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> was recorded 20 s after switching to Na<sup>+</sup>-free (replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>) saline containing 10 mM Ca<sup>2+</sup>. The sequence of applications was repeated multiple times. Following each ligand application, the external solution was changed back to normal saline containing 150 mM Na<sup>+</sup> before the next ligand application. <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub>: &#x2212;70 mV.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig7" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
        <p>In a further attempt to distinguish whether channel activation or ion permeation was primarily responsible for occlusion of one channel by the other, we compared <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> with <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> under two experimental conditions, in which a higher concentration of ACh should activate nAChR but produce very little current. In the absence of Na<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> (replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>) application of ACh induces a negligible current (Sorimachi and Wakamori [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]), while ATP induces a substantial current under the same conditions (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). As shown in Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>, there was no occlusion in these conditions; the amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP+ACh</sub> was 105 &#xB1; 1% (<italic>N</italic> = 10) of the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>. We also investigated currents in response to the ligands at a potential close to the <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (7 &#xB1; 2 mV in this experiment, <italic>N</italic> = 13), taking advantage of the more positive <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (22.7 &#xB1; 0.9 mV), so that at this potential only the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was observed. The amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP+ACh</sub> was 105 &#xB1; 3% (<italic>N</italic> = 13) of that of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was close to zero (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8D</xref>). These results are, however, in contrast to that obtained in sympathetic neurons (Nakazawa[<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]), in which <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in the absence of both Na<sup>+</sup> (replaced by glucosamine) and Ca<sup>2+</sup> was inhibited in the presence of ACh, which caused no current (Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]). In these experiments, we only included data in which <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was large enough to be clearly resolved, greater than 50 pA (corresponding to a control <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV larger than 1.5 nA). These results suggest that actual current flow through both nAChR and P2XR is responsible for occlusion.
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig. 8</label><caption><p>Lack of inhibition in response to co-application of ACh and ATP under two experimental conditions designed to virtually eliminate <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>. <bold>A</bold>) Control <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> recorded at a <italic>V</italic><italic>h</italic> of &#x2212;70 mV in standard saline. <bold>B</bold>) Current responses recorded at &#x2212;70 mV from 20 s after exchanging the standard saline for a Na<sup>+</sup>-free (replaced by NMDG<sup>+</sup>), Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free saline. This sequence was repeated twice or three times. Note the small amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, and the lack of occlusion of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub>. <bold>C</bold>) Control <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> recorded at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;70 mV in another neuron. <bold>D</bold>) Representative traces of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> recorded at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of +7 mV, which is very close to EACh. Note the lack of occlusion at this potential, when current flow through the AChR is negligible.</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2006_Article_9004_Fig8" id="MO8"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec13" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>In this study, we found that ATP induced an inward current and increased [Ca]<sub>in</sub> in isolated rat AP neurons. The ATP-induced current and [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase were mimicked by ATP&#x3B3;S and 2-methylthio-ATP, but not by &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-methylene-ATP, &#x3B2;, &#x3B3;-methylene-ATP nor ADP, and was inhibited by suramin and PPADS, suggesting that it was mediated by P2XRs. These results are in good agreement with previous histochemical findings, which demonstrated the presence of P2X<sub>2</sub>, P2X<sub>4</sub>, and P2X<sub>6</sub> receptor mRNAs (Collo et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]), and of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor immunoreactivity in AP neurons (Kanjhan et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]; Atkinson et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]).</p>
      <p>The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> showed strong inward rectification and the <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was 22.7 &#xB1; 0.9 mV (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1B</xref>). The amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> varied inversely with the extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentrations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1C</xref>). The inhibitory effect of increasing extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> has also been reported in rat sensory neurons (Krishtal et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>]), PC-12 cells (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]), ventromedial hypothalamic neurons (Sorimachi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]), and in cells expressing recombinant P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors (Evans et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; Virginio et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]), where an allosteric alteration of the ATP binding sites has been suggested to be the underlying mechanism.</p>
      <p>The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was markedly reduced, but still persisted when NMDG<sup>+</sup> was substituted for external Na<sup>+</sup> even in the absence of Ca<sup>2+</sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3A</xref>). Since ATP did not induce a current when sucrose was substituted for external NaCl, our result suggests that NMDG<sup>+</sup> could permeate through P2XR. A substantial <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> has been similarly reported in PC-12 cells and sympathetic neurons when glucosamine was substituted for Na<sup>+</sup> (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]; Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]). The addition of Ca<sup>2+</sup> to NMDG-Cl- and sucrose-substituted saline increased the <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3B</xref> and <xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">C</xref>, respectively), indicating that Ca<sup>2+</sup> also permeates through P2XR channel. We quantified the relatively high Ca<sup>2+</sup> permeability, obtaining a <italic>P</italic><sub>Ca</sub>/<italic>P</italic><sub>Na</sub> ratio of 3.0. A relatively high permeability of P2XR to Ca<sup>2+</sup> has been reported in previous studies (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]; Sorimachi et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>]; Evans et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]; Virginio et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]). Although direct influx of extracellular Ca<sup>2+</sup> through P2XR channel may thus contribute to the ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase, membrane depolarization and the secondary activation of voltage-dependent Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels could also make a significant contribution to the [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increase. In fact, the high K<sup>+</sup>- and ATP-induced [Ca]<sub>in</sub> increases were substantially inhibited by a range of Ca<sup>2+</sup> channel antagonists, including those which block L- and N-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels (Table <xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). This is in contrast to a previous study, which reported an absence of the L- and N-type Ca<sup>2+</sup> channels in rabbit AP neurons (Hay et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>]). The discrepancies between their results and ours could be, at least in part, accounted for by the use of different AP preparations (cultured rabbit neurons <italic>vs</italic>. acutely dissociated rat neurons).</p>
      <p>The present results, in combination with our previous demonstration of nAChR on AP neurons (Sorimachi and Wakamori [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]), suggest that both ATP and ACh may act as excitatory neurotransmitters in AP neurons, although their release from presynaptic nerve terminals has not yet been reported. We also report a negative functional interaction between P2XRs and nAChRs in AP neurons, as has been observed in a variety of peripheral neurons and in recombinant expression systems (Nakazawa et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]; Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]; Zhou and Galligan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; Barajas-Lopez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]; Searl et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]; Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]; Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]). This is the first report, that we are aware of, of such interactions occurring in central neurons. When ACh was applied in the presence of ATP, there was a positive correlation between the peak amplitude of inward <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> and the amount of occlusion of inward <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4A</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">B</xref>). The converse was also true when ATP was applied in the presence of ACh (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4C</xref> and <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">D</xref>). Non-additivity of the <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> was observed even when the inward current was carried by NMDG<sup>+</sup> and/or Ca<sup>2+</sup> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>). Co-application of two agonists did not seem to change the driving force for Na<sup>+</sup>, because at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> between <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> an outward current due to the activation of nAChR, followed by an inward current due to the activation of P2XR, was observed (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6C</xref>). Occlusion was also observed at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of &#x2212;10 mV, which is closer to <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> or <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. Furthermore, the removal of external Ca<sup>2+</sup> did not alter the occlusion, and thus a Ca<sup>2+</sup>-mediated mechanism does not contribute to the current occlusion.</p>
      <p>The <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> occlusion was observed at all negative holding potentials when the current was inward but was not observed for outward currents at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> of +40 mV. Here the outward <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> was not different from the predicted sum of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6B</xref>). The same dependence on current direction has been reported in guinea-pig enteric and submucosal neurons (Zhou and Galligan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; Barajas-Lopez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]), suggesting that the current occlusion was triggered by the inward movement of cations through two channels.</p>
      <p>Some investigators have shown that the amplitude of <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> is equal to or even smaller than that of either <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> or <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>. For instance, the concentration of one agonist causing little or no inward current produced dramatic occlusion of the inward current generated by the other agonist (Searl et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]). Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] using Xenopus oocytes co-expressing P2X<sub>2</sub> and &#x3B1;3&#x3B2;4 nAChR channels, provided several lines of evidence which indicated that occlusion was mostly mediated by the inhibition of the nAChR channel by activation of the P2XR. However, we found that concomitant application of two agonists always caused a larger current than either agonist (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6A</xref>), and that the amount of occlusion of one channel current in the presence of the other channel agonist was correlated with the amplitude of current through the other channel (Fig. <xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>). Furthermore, we found that <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> desensitizes faster than <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, but more slowly than <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub>, and <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> at a <italic>V</italic><sub>h</sub> between <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and <italic>E</italic><sub>ATP</sub> showed a combination pattern of early outward <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> and delayed inward <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6C</xref>). These results both strongly suggest that in AP neurons, <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh+ATP</sub> are carried through both nAChR and P2XR channels, and that inhibition between these channels is reciprocal.</p>
      <p>The <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> was not inhibited by co-application of ACh when the inward <italic>I</italic><sub>ACh</sub> was markedly reduced in the absence of permeant cations (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8B</xref>) or at a Vh very close to <italic>E</italic><sub>ACh</sub> (Fig. <xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8D</xref>), and the inhibited <italic>I</italic><sub>ATP</sub> in the presence of ACh (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5B</xref>) recovered as soon as the nAChR channel closed in the presence of dTc (Fig. <xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5C</xref>). These results thus suggest that the inhibitory interaction not only requires the activation of both receptor channels, but also requires a substantial current to flow through these channels. These results are in contrast to that obtained in sympathetic neurons, in which the ATP-induced glucosamine influx was inhibited in the presence of ACh (Nakazawa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]). The cause of this inconsistency remained unknown, but may reflect a real difference in the underlying mechanisms of occlusion in these two types of neurons.</p>
      <p>Altogether, our results have characterized the P2XR responses in AP neurons and the cross-inhibition between P2XRs and nAChRs in AP neurons. We show that the current flow through one receptor channel hinders the current flow through the other channel. These interactions support the notion that these channels are positioned very close to each other, as has been previously considered (Zhou and Galligan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]; Barajas-Lopez et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]; Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>]; Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]) and more recently demonstrated for recombinant channels (Khakh et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>]). These results will be important to consider when designing ligands to modify excitability of ATP neurons and may have some physiological function during co-activation of P2XRs and nAChRs by synaptically released transmitters.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borison</surname>
              <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Area postrema: Chemoreceptor trigger zone for vomiting is that all?</article-title>
          <source>Life Sci.</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>1807</fpage>
          <lpage>1817</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0024-3205(74)90399-3</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Borison HL (1974) Area postrema: Chemoreceptor trigger zone for vomiting is that all? Life Sci 14:1807&#x2013;817 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4603263</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borison</surname>
              <given-names>H.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>History and status of the area postrema</article-title>
          <source>Fed. Proc.</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <fpage>2937</fpage>
          <lpage>2940</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Borison HL (1984) History and status of the area postrema. Fed Proc 43:2937&#x2013;940 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6500066</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Franchini</surname>
              <given-names>L.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Johnson</surname>
              <given-names>A.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Olmos</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Sodium appetite and Fos activation in serotonergic neurons</article-title>
          <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>282</volume>
          <fpage>R235</fpage>
          <lpage>R243</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Franchini LF, Johnson AK, De Olmos J et al (2002) Sodium appetite and Fos activation in serotonergic neurons. Am J Physio 282:R235&#x2013;43 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fink</surname>
              <given-names>G.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bruner</surname>
              <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mangiapane</surname>
              <given-names>M.L.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The area postrema is critical for angiotensin induced hypertension</article-title>
          <source>Hypertension</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>355</fpage>
          <lpage>361</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fink GD, Bruner CA, Mangiapane ML (1987) The area postrema is critical for angiotensin induced hypertension. Hypertension 9:355&#x2013;61 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3557601</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Undesser</surname>
              <given-names>K.P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasser</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haywood</surname>
              <given-names>J.R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interactions of vasopressin with the area postrema in arterial baroreflex function in conscious rabbits</article-title>
          <source>Circ. Res.</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>56</volume>
          <fpage>410</fpage>
          <lpage>417</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Undesser KP, Hasser EM, Haywood JR et al (1985) Interactions of vasopressin with the area postrema in arterial baroreflex function in conscious rabbits. Circ Res 56:410&#x2013;17 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3971513</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morest</surname>
              <given-names>D.K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Experimental study of the projections of the nucleus of the tractus solitarius and the area postrema in the cat</article-title>
          <source>J. Comp. Neurol.</source>
          <year>1967</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>277</fpage>
          <lpage>299</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.901300402</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Morest DK (1967) Experimental study of the projections of the nucleus of the tractus solitarius and the area postrema in the cat. J Comp Neurol 130:277&#x2013;99 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6059369</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kooy</surname>
              <given-names>V.D.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koda</surname>
              <given-names>L.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Organization of the projections of a cirumventricular organ: The area postrema in the rat</article-title>
          <source>J. Comp.Neurol.</source>
          <year>1983</year>
          <volume>219</volume>
          <fpage>328</fpage>
          <lpage>338</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.902190307</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kooy VDD, Koda LY (1983) Organization of the projections of a cirumventricular organ: The area postrema in the rat. J Comp Neurol 219:328&#x2013;38 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">6619341</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shapiro</surname>
              <given-names>R.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miselis</surname>
              <given-names>R.R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The central neural connections of the area postrema of the rat</article-title>
          <source>J. Comp. Neurol.</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>234</volume>
          <fpage>344</fpage>
          <lpage>364</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/cne.902340306</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Shapiro RE, Miselis RR (1985) The central neural connections of the area postrema of the rat. J Comp Neurol 234:344&#x2013;64 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3988989</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sun</surname>
              <given-names>M.K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spyer</surname>
              <given-names>K.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>GABA-mediated inhibition of medullary vasomotor neurons by area postrema stimulation in rats</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol.(Lond.)</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>436</volume>
          <fpage>669</fpage>
          <lpage>684</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sun MK, Spyer KM (1991) GABA-mediated inhibition of medullary vasomotor neurons by area postrema stimulation in rats. J Physiol (Lond) 436:669&#x2013;84 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2061850</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Papas</surname>
              <given-names>S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Smith</surname>
              <given-names>P.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furguson</surname>
              <given-names>A.V.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Electrophysiological evidence that systemic angiotensin influences rat area postrema neurons</article-title>
          <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>258</volume>
          <fpage>R70</fpage>
          <lpage>R76</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Papas S, Smith P, Furguson AV (1990) Electrophysiological evidence that systemic angiotensin influences rat area postrema neurons. Am J Physiol 258:R70&#x2013;R76 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2301648</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jahn</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bufler</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weindl</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Patch-clamp study on membrane properties and transmitter activated currents of rabbit area postrema neurons</article-title>
          <source>J. Comp. Physiol.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>178</volume>
          <fpage>771</fpage>
          <lpage>778</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jahn K, Bufler J, Weindl A et al (1996) Patch-clamp study on membrane properties and transmitter activated currents of rabbit area postrema neurons. J Comp Physiol 178:771&#x2013;78 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8667290</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindsley</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>AMPA receptor activation of area postrema neurons</article-title>
          <source>Am. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>R586</fpage>
          <lpage>R590</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hay M, Lindsley KA (1999) AMPA receptor activation of area postrema neurons. Am J Physiol 276:R586&#x2013;R590 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9950940</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamagami</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakamori</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Expression of P2X receptors on area postrema neurons of rat brain: Studies with fura-2 microfluorometry</article-title>
          <source>Jpn. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <fpage>s119</fpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Yamagami K, Wakamori M (2002) Expression of P2X receptors on area postrema neurons of rat brain: Studies with fura-2 microfluorometry. Jpn J Physiol 52:suppl. s119 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamagami</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakamori</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP-induced current in area postrema neurons of rat brain: Possible expression of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor</article-title>
          <source>Jpn. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>s203</fpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Yamagami K, Wakamori M (2003) ATP-induced current in area postrema neurons of rat brain: Possible expression of P2X2 receptor. Jpn J Physiol 53: suppl. s203 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Funahashi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mitoh</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matsuo</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nicotinic modulation of area postrema neuronal excitability in rat brain slices</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res.</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>1017</volume>
          <fpage>227</fpage>
          <lpage>233</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainres.2004.05.028</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Funahashi M, Mitoh Y, Matsuo R (2002) Nicotinic modulation of area postrema neuronal excitability in rat brain slices. Brain Res 1017:227&#x2013;33 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15261119</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakamori</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Nicotinic ACh receptor in area postrema neurons of immature rat brain</article-title>
          <source>Neurosci. Lett.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>381</volume>
          <fpage>350</fpage>
          <lpage>353</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2005.02.052</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Wakamori M (2005) Nicotinic ACh receptor in area postrema neurons of immature rat brain. Neurosci Lett 381:350&#x2013;53 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15896498</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Akasu</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koketsu</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of adenosine triphosphate on the sensitivity of the nicotinic acetylcholine-receptor in the bullfrog sympathetic ganglion cell</article-title>
          <source>Brit. J. Pharmacol.</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>84</volume>
          <fpage>525</fpage>
          <lpage>531</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Akasu T, Koketsu K (1985) Effect of adenosine triphosphate on the sensitivity of the nicotinic acetylcholine-receptor in the bullfrog sympathetic ganglion cell. Brit J Pharmacol 84:525&#x2013;31 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2983814</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakazawa</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujimori</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takanaka</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An ATP-activated conductance in pheochromocytoma cells and its suppression by extracellular calcium</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond)</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>428</volume>
          <fpage>257</fpage>
          <lpage>272</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nakazawa K, Fujimori K, Takanaka A et al (1990) An ATP-activated conductance in pheochromocytoma cells and its suppression by extracellular calcium. J Physiol (Lond) 428:257&#x2013;72 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2231413</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Searl</surname>
              <given-names>T.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Redman</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Silinsky</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mutual occlusion of P2X ATP receptors and nicotinic receptors on symapathetic neurons of the guinea-pig</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>510</volume>
          <fpage>783</fpage>
          <lpage>791</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.783bj.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Searl TJ, Redman RS. Silinsky EM (1998) Mutual occlusion of P2X ATP receptors and nicotinic receptors on symapathetic neurons of the guinea-pig. J Physiol (Lond) 510:783&#x2013;91 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9660893</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Galligan</surname>
              <given-names>J.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Non-additive interaction between nicotinic cholinergic and P2X purine receptors in guinea-pig enteric neurons in culture</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>513</volume>
          <fpage>685</fpage>
          <lpage>697</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.685ba.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zhou X, Galligan JJ (1998) Non-additive interaction between nicotinic cholinergic and P2X purine receptors in guinea-pig enteric neurons in culture. J Physiol (Lond) 513: 685&#x2013;97. <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9824710</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barajas-Lopez</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Espinosa-Luna</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional interactions between nicotinic and P2X channels in short-term cultures of guinea-pig submucosal neurons</article-title>
          <source>J.Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>513</volume>
          <fpage>671</fpage>
          <lpage>683</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.671ba.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Barajas-Lopez C, Espinosa-Luna R, Zhu Y (1998) Functional interactions between nicotinic and P2X channels in short-term cultures of guinea-pig submucosal neurons. J Physiol (Lond) 513:671&#x2013;83 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9824709</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khakh</surname>
              <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhou</surname>
              <given-names>X.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sydes</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>State-dependent cross-inhibition between transmitter-gated cation channels</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>406</volume>
          <fpage>405</fpage>
          <lpage>410</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/35019066</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Khakh BS, Zhou X, Sydes J et al (2000) State-dependent cross-inhibition between transmitter-gated cation channels. Nature 406:405&#x2013;10 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10935636</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khakh</surname>
              <given-names>B.S.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fisher</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nashmi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An angstrom scale interaction between plasma membrane ATP-gated P2X<sub>2</sub> and &#x3B1;<sub>4</sub>&#x3B2;<sub>2</sub> nicotinic channels measured with fluorescence resonance energy transfer and total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>6911</fpage>
          <lpage>6920</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0561-05.2005</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Khakh BS, Fisher JA, Nashmi R et al (2005) An angstrom scale interaction between plasma membrane ATP-gated P2X2 and &#x3B1;4&#x3B2;2 nicotinic channels measured with fluorescence resonance energy transfer and total internal reflection fluorescence microscopy. J Neurosci 25:6911&#x2013;920 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16033901</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boue-Grabot</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barajas-Lopez</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chakfe</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracellular cross talk and physical interaction between two classes of neurotransmitter-gated channels</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
          <year>1984</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>1246</fpage>
          <lpage>1253</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Boue-Grabot E, Barajas-Lopez C, Chakfe Y et al (1984) Intracellular cross talk and physical interaction between two classes of neurotransmitter-gated channels. J Neurosci 15:1246&#x2013;253 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>C.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ion-concentration dependence of the reversal potential and the single channel conductance of ion channels at the neuromuscular junction</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1979</year>
          <volume>286</volume>
          <fpage>417</fpage>
          <lpage>445</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lewis CA (1979) Ion-concentration dependence of the reversal potential and the single channel conductance of ion channels at the neuromuscular junction. J Physiol (Lond) 286:417&#x2013;45 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">312319</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grynkiewicz</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Poenie</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsien</surname>
              <given-names>R.Y.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A new generation of Ca<sup>2+</sup> indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties</article-title>
          <source>J. Biol. Chem.</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>260</volume>
          <fpage>3440</fpage>
          <lpage>3450</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grynkiewicz G, Poenie M, Tsien RY (1985) A new generation of Ca2+ indicators with greatly improved fluorescence properties. J Biol Chem 260:3440&#x2013;450 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3838314</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abe</surname>
              <given-names>Y.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Furukawa</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanism underlying the ATP-induced increase in the cytosolic Ca<sup>2+</sup> concentration in chick ciliary ganglion neurons</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurochem.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>64</volume>
          <fpage>1169</fpage>
          <lpage>1174</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Abe Y, Furukawa K et al (1995) Mechanism underlying the ATP-induced increase in the cytosolic Ca2+ concentration in chick ciliary ganglion neurons. J Neurochem 64:1169&#x2013;174 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7861148</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>King</surname>
              <given-names>B.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ziganshina</surname>
              <given-names>L.E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pintor</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Full sensitivity of P2X2 purinoceptor to ATP revealed by changing extracellular pH</article-title>
          <source>Br. J. Pharmacol.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>117</volume>
          <fpage>1371</fpage>
          <lpage>1373</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">King BF, Ziganshina LE, Pintor J et al (1996) Full sensitivity of P2X2 purinoceptor to ATP revealed by changing extracellular pH. Br J Pharmacol 117:1371&#x2013;373 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8730726</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hay</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hasser</surname>
              <given-names>E.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lindsley</surname>
              <given-names>K.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Area postrema voltage-activated calcium currents</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurophysiol.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <fpage>133</fpage>
          <lpage>141</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hay M, Hasser EM, Lindsley KA (1996) Area postrema voltage-activated calcium currents. J Neurophysiol 75:133&#x2013;41 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8822547</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nakazawa</surname>
              <given-names>K.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP-activated current and its interaction with acetylcholine-activated current in rat sympathetic neurons</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>14</volume>
          <fpage>740</fpage>
          <lpage>750</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nakazawa K (1994) ATP-activated current and its interaction with acetylcholine-activated current in rat sympathetic neurons. J Neurosci 14:740&#x2013;50 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7507984</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Manalis</surname>
              <given-names>R.S.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Voltage-dependent effect of curare at the frog neuromuscular junction</article-title>
          <source>Nature</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>267</volume>
          <fpage>366</fpage>
          <lpage>368</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/267366a0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Manalis RS (1977) Voltage-dependent effect of curare at the frog neuromuscular junction. Nature 267:366&#x2013;68 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">301253</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Grassi</surname>
              <given-names>F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Polenzani</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mileo</surname>
              <given-names>A.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Blockage of nicotinic acetylcholine receptors by 5-hydroxytryptamine</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurosci. Res.</source>
          <year>1993</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>562</fpage>
          <lpage>570</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.490340508</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Grassi F, Polenzani L, Mileo AM et al (1993) Blockage of nicotinic acetylcholine receptors by 5-hydroxytryptamine. J Neurosci Res 34:562&#x2013;70 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8478989</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Garcia-Colunga</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Miledi</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of serotonergic agents on neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors</article-title>
          <source>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <fpage>2919</fpage>
          <lpage>2923</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.92.7.2919</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Garcia-Colunga J, Miledi R (1995) Effects of serotonergic agents on neuronal nicotinic acetylcholine receptors. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 92:2919&#x2013;923 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7708749</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wakamori</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inhibitory effect of serotonin on ACh-induced currents in area postrema neurons of rat brain</article-title>
          <source>Jpn. J. Physiol.</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>54</volume>
          <fpage>s137</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2170/jjphysiol.54.137</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Wakamori M (2004) Inhibitory effect of serotonin on ACh-induced currents in area postrema neurons of rat brain. Jpn J Physiol 54:suppl. s137 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fieber</surname>
              <given-names>L.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Adams</surname>
              <given-names>D.J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Adenosine triphosphate-evoked currents in cultured neurons dissociated from rat parasympathetic cardiac ganglia</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>434</volume>
          <fpage>239</fpage>
          <lpage>256</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fieber LA, Adams DJ (1991) Adenosine triphosphate-evoked currents in cultured neurons dissociated from rat parasympathetic cardiac ganglia. J Physiol (Lond) 434:239&#x2013;56 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1708820</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rogers</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dani</surname>
              <given-names>J.A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Comparison of quantitative calcium flux through NMDA, ATP and ACh receptor channels</article-title>
          <source>Biophys. J.</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>68</volume>
          <fpage>501</fpage>
          <lpage>506</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-3495(95)80211-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rogers M, Dani JA (1995) Comparison of quantitative calcium flux through NMDA, ATP and ACh receptor channels. Biophys J 68:501&#x2013;06 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7696503</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Collo</surname>
              <given-names>G.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>North</surname>
              <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kawashima</surname>
              <given-names>E.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cloning of P2X5 and P2X6 receptors and the distribution and properties of an extended family of ATP-gated ion channels</article-title>
          <source>J. Neurosci.</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <fpage>2495</fpage>
          <lpage>2507</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Collo G, North RA, Kawashima E et al (1996) Cloning of P2X5 and P2X6 receptors and the distribution and properties of an extended family of ATP-gated ion channels. J Neurosci 16:2495&#x2013;507 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8786426</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kanjhan</surname>
              <given-names>R.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Housley</surname>
              <given-names>G.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burton</surname>
              <given-names>L.D.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Distribution of the P2X2 receptor subunit of the ATP-gated ion channels in the rat central nervous system</article-title>
          <source>J. Comp. Neurol.</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>407</volume>
          <fpage>11</fpage>
          <lpage>32</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19990428)407:1&lt;11::AID-CNE2&gt;3.0.CO;2-R</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kanjhan R, Housley GD, Burton LD et al (1999) Distribution of the P2X2 receptor subunit of the ATP-gated ion channels in the rat central nervous system. J Comp Neurol 407:11&#x2013;2 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10213185</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Atkinson</surname>
              <given-names>L.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Batten</surname>
              <given-names>T.F.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Deuchars</surname>
              <given-names>J.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor immunoreactivity in the dorsal vagal complex and area postrema of the rat</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>99</volume>
          <fpage>683</fpage>
          <lpage>696</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(00)00233-5</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Atkinson L, Batten TF, Deuchars J (2000) P2X2 receptor immunoreactivity in the dorsal vagal complex and area postrema of the rat. Neuroscience 99:683&#x2013;96 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10974431</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Krishtal</surname>
              <given-names>O.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marchenko</surname>
              <given-names>S.M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Obukhov</surname>
              <given-names>A.G.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cationic channels activated by extracellular ATP in rat sensory neutons</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>995</fpage>
          <lpage>1000</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0306-4522(88)90203-5</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Krishtal OA, Marchenko SM, Obukhov AG (1988) Cationic channels activated by extracellular ATP in rat sensory neutons. Neuroscience 27:995&#x2013;000 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2855265</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sorimachi</surname>
              <given-names>M.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishibashi</surname>
              <given-names>H.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Moritoyo</surname>
              <given-names>T.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Excitatory effect of ATP on acutely dissociated ventromedial hypothalamic neurons of the rat</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>105</volume>
          <fpage>393</fpage>
          <lpage>401</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(01)00192-0</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sorimachi M, Ishibashi H, Moritoyo T et al (2001) Excitatory effect of ATP on acutely dissociated ventromedial hypothalamic neurons of the rat. Neuroscience 105:393&#x2013;01 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11672606</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>R.J.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virginio</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Ionic permeability of, and divalent cation effects on, two ATP-gated cation channels (P2X receptors) expressed in mammalian cells</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>497</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>422</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Evans RJ, Lewis C, Virginio C et al (1996) Ionic permeability of, and divalent cation effects on, two ATP-gated cation channels (P2X receptors) expressed in mammalian cells. J Physiol (Lond) 497:413&#x2013;22 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8961184</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Virginio</surname>
              <given-names>C.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>North</surname>
              <given-names>R.A.</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Surprenant</surname>
              <given-names>A.</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium permeability and block at homomeric and heteromeric P2X2 and P2X3 receptors, and P2X receptors in rat nodose neurones</article-title>
          <source>J. Physiol. (Lond.)</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>510</volume>
          <fpage>27</fpage>
          <lpage>35</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1998.027bz.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Virginio C, North RA, Surprenant A (1998) Calcium permeability and block at homomeric and heteromeric P2X2 and P2X3 receptors, and P2X receptors in rat nodose neurones. J Physiol (Lond) 510:27&#x2013;5 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9625864</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>