<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Purinergic Signal</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Purinergic Signalling</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1573-9538</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-9546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18368533</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2246000</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9076</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11302-007-9076-9</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Purinergic junctional transmission and propagation of calcium waves in cultured spinal cord microglial networks</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Bennett</surname>
            <given-names>Max R.</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+61-2-9351-2034</phone>
            <fax>+61-2-9351-3910</fax>
            <email>maxb@physiol.usyd.edu.au</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Buljan</surname>
            <given-names>Vlado</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Farnell</surname>
            <given-names>Les</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Gibson</surname>
            <given-names>William G.</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff3">3</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>The Neurobiology Laboratory, Department of Physiology, The University of Sydney, New South Wales, 2006 Australia </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>The Neurobiology Laboratory, Institute for Biomedical Research, Department of Physiology, The University of Sydney, New South Wales, 2006 Australia </aff>
        <aff id="Aff3"><label>3</label>The School of Mathematics and Statistics, The University of Sydney, New South Wales, 2006 Australia </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>23</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>3</month>
        <year>2008</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>4</volume>
      <issue>1</issue>
      <fpage>47</fpage>
      <lpage>59</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>13</day>
          <month>8</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer Science + Business Media B.V. 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>In order to elucidate the mechanisms of purinergic transmission of calcium (Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup>) waves between microglial cells, we have employed micro-photolithographic methods to form discrete patterns of microglia that allow quantitative measurements of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation. Microglia were confined to lanes 20&#x2013;100 <inline-formula id="IEq1"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq1.gif --><tex-math id="M1">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide and Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves propagated from a point of mechanical stimulation, with a diminution in amplitude, for about 120 <inline-formula id="IEq2"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq2.gif --><tex-math id="M2">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. The number of cells participating in propagation also decreased over this distance. Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves could propagate across a cell-free lane from one microglia lane to another if this distance of separation was less than about 60 <inline-formula id="IEq3"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq3.gif --><tex-math id="M3">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, indicating that propagation involved diffusion of a chemical transmitter. This transmitter was identified as ATP since all Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation was blocked by the purinoceptor antagonist suramin, which blocks P2Y<sub>2</sub> and P2Y<sub>12</sub> at relatively low concentrations. Antibodies to P2Y<sub>12</sub> showed these at very high density compared with P2Y<sub>2</sub>, indicating a role for P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors. These observations were quantitatively accounted for by a model in which the main determinants are the diffusion of ATP released from a stimulated microglial cell and differences in the dissociation constant of the purinoceptors on the microglial cells.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>Calcium waves</kwd>
        <kwd>Microglia</kwd>
        <kwd>Propagation</kwd>
        <kwd>Purines</kwd>
        <kwd>Transmission</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2008</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>Microglia give a calcium (Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup>) transient in mixed cultures of microglia and astrocytes, following mechanical stimulation of a single astrocyte [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. This transient in the microglia is dependent on the release of ATP by the astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. However, nothing is known about the mechanism of transmission of a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> signal between microglial cells that allows for propagation of a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in populations of microglia [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>]. In the absence of neurons, a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in astrocytes propagates for hundreds of microns from a point of mechanical stimulation (e.g., [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]). It remains to be seen whether a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> signal can be transmitted between microglia in such a way that there is propagation of a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave.</p>
      <p>The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves in astrocytes, when initiated at a point in a culture, can jump cell-free gaps of different widths formed by scraping away cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>]. Such Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves propagate across these gaps with a delay that increases with gap width until this width reaches about 150 <inline-formula id="IEq4"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq4.gif --><tex-math id="M4">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, when such propagation fails. More recent research has used micropatterned arrays of astrocytes in which lanes of cells about 110 <inline-formula id="IEq5"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq5.gif --><tex-math id="M5">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide alternate with cell-free lanes about 40 <inline-formula id="IEq6"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq6.gif --><tex-math id="M6">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. If a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave is initiated by mechanical stimulation in an astrocyte in just one lane it propagates both along the lane as well as transversely across the cell-free lanes into the adjacent astrocyte lanes with a delay of about 10 s. These observations support the idea that the transmission of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves between astrocytes involves the release of a diffusible substance. The question of whether this wave is transmitted between microglia by a diffusible substance has not been addressed. It is known that microglia collecting in the vicinity of a stab wound express connexin CX43 and that these cells are coupled by such connexins in vitro under the control of certain cytokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. However, given the relative low density of resting microglia in the brain compared to that of astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>], it seems unlikely that connexins are used by microglia in normal circumstances to transmit Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves. We have therefore used micropatterned arrays of microglia to ascertain if the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave can propagate across cell-free regions, thus indicating that a diffusible substance is involved in transmission. As shown below, this turns out to be the case.</p>
      <p>Microglia possess P2X<sub>7</sub>, P2Y<sub>1</sub>, P2Y<sub>2/4</sub>, P2Y<sub>6</sub>, P2Y<sub>12</sub>, P2Y<sub>13</sub> and P2Y<sub>14</sub> purinoceptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] with P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors and P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors unique to microglia, at least in the hippocampus [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. There is evidence that some microglia cells possess predominantly P2X receptors and others predominantly P2Y receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]. P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors on microglia are involved in apoptosis, transcription and microvesicle shedding [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. Activation of P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors can lead to the release of pro-inflammatory cytokines, such as TNF<italic>&#x3B1;</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. P2Y<sub>1</sub> and P2Y<sub>2/4</sub> receptors are involved in the release of the cytokine IL-10 that acts to markedly reduce the release of the pro-inflammatory cytokines [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Most (85%) resting microglia respond to ATP with a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] as a consequence of an action of ATP on P2X and P2Y receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. The activation of P2X receptors leads to an influx of calcium ions whereas the activation of P2Y receptors releases calcium from internal stores [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. Microglia can also release ATP using in part ATP-binding cassette (ABC) proteins, such as P-glycoproteins (mdr 1a and mdr 1b) and multi-drug resistant associated proteins (mrp1 and mrp4; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>]). Taken together, these observations on the action of ATP on purinergic receptors possessed by resting microglia suggest the hypothesis that the transmission of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves between microglia is due to ATP, and this we have investigated.</p>
      <p>The experimental work is supplemented by calculations using a theoretical model of extracellular communication in cellular networks, originally developed for astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], and here modified for microglia.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <p>The experimental methods for immunohistochemistry, mechanical stimulation of leading to Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves in cells, application of drugs, recording Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves and seeding cells into lanes were the same as that previously described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. The purification of microglia started when plated mixed glia culture from Sprague-Dawley rat pup spinal cord formed a confluent monolayer (usually between 1 and 2 weeks). The culture was shaken at 200 rpm for 1 h at 37&#xB0;C using rotating shaker (IKA-Vibrax-VXR). During shaking, the astrocytes remained adhered to the poly-D-lysine coating whereas the microglia and oligodendrocytes detached from the astrocyte monolayer. Immediately after shaking, the medium containing the detached cells was transferred to a 15-ml centrifuge tube and centrifuged for 5 min at 500 rpm. The supernatant was discarded and the pellet was resuspended in 1 ml DMEM and triturated. Cell density was adjusted by adding fresh DMEM (typically 1-2 ml) after cell trituration and 300 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>L of the cell suspension was pipetted onto each coverslip containing previously prepared microchannels and then incubated for 15 min. Incubating DMEM was replaced with fresh DMEM containing 50% of spinal cord astrocytic conditioned medium (ACM). After 15 min, microglia selectively adhere to the poly-D-lysine coating whereas other cell types that may be present, such as any remaining astrocytes and oligodendrocytes, take a longer period of time to adhere [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. The purity of the microglial cultures was greater than 98% according to live staining of the cells with the microglial marker FITC-IB4 (Invitrogen). Microglia-plated microchannels were incubated in ACM supplemented DMEM for 48 h before use in experiments (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). The medium was removed and replaced daily.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>The distribution of microglia, immunostained with anti-CSF-1R, in parallel lanes of width 20 <inline-formula id="IEq7"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq7.gif --><tex-math id="M7">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and separation 45 <inline-formula id="IEq8"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq8.gif --><tex-math id="M8">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>; the calibration bar is 45 <inline-formula id="IEq9"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq9.gif --><tex-math id="M9">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>For Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> recording, the relative fluorescence amplitude (<italic>&#x394;F</italic>/<italic>F</italic>), was calculated using the formula
<disp-formula id="Equa"><tex-math id="M10">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$\displaystyle\left(\frac{\Delta F}{F}\right) = \frac{{F}-\overline{F}_0}{\overline{F}_0-\overline{F}_{\rm background}}$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>where <italic>F</italic> is the fluorescent intensity during the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient, <inline-formula id="IEq25"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq25.gif --><tex-math id="M11">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\overline{F}_0$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the intensity averaged over the interval immediately before the calcium transient and <inline-formula id="IEq26"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq26.gif --><tex-math id="M12">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\overline{F}_{\rm background}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> is the average fluorescence intensity measured in several cell-free areas. Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transients with a maximum <italic>&#x394;F</italic>/<italic>F</italic> value less than 0.3 (being 15% of the largest Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient observed in a lane of microglia) were discounted as being too close to the noise level to be reliable. All experiments were repeated at least three times and values are presented as mean &#xB1; s.d. Statistical significance was determined with the use of unpaired <italic>t</italic>-tests and ANOVA, and <italic>P</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05 was considered significant. All P2Y receptor antagonists were obtained from TOCRIS.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec3">
      <title>Mathematical model</title>
      <p>A detailed description of a mathematical model of purinergic transmission in glial networks was given in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>] and subsequently applied to experimental results on such transmission between astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. This model has been adapted to the present case of microglial networks. The basic model is the same, so here we give only a brief summary of the main features, highlighting the changes that have been made.</p>
      <p>Communication between the model microglia is mediated by ATP diffusing in the extracellular space. This ATP binds reversibly to metabotropic receptors (P2Y) on the surface of cells so that the ratio of bound to total receptors is given by
<disp-formula id="Equb"><tex-math id="M13">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$$\rho=\frac{[ATP]}{K_R+[ATP]},$$\end{document}</tex-math></disp-formula>where [<italic>ATP</italic>] is the extracellular ATP concentration and <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> is the dissociation constant for ATP binding. The usual meaning of <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> is the concentration of ATP at which half the total receptors are bound; however, in the present context <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub>, as well as being a measure of the affinity of receptor types, also reflects additional variables such as spatial variations in receptor density, since <italic>&#x3C1;</italic> is a measure of the effective activity of ATP as a function of space and time. Thus <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> is to be interpreted as an effective, rather than an actual, dissociation constant (see the section &#x201C;Receptors&#x201D; in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]).</p>
      <p>Each microglial cell is represented by a cube of side 8.3 <inline-formula id="IEq27"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq27.gif --><tex-math id="M14">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, and these cubes are arranged in 2D arrays with their centres 25 <inline-formula id="IEq28"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq28.gif --><tex-math id="M15">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> apart. As explained in [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], this simplified geometry does not model the spatial complexity of a real cell, but is a lumped approximation. The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave can be initiated either by increasing the IP<sub>3</sub> concentration in a single cell, or by applying ATP extracellularly. In the present calculations, a fixed concentration of ATP (typically 20 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) is applied for an extended time (typically 5 s) to the surface of one model microglial cell. The parameters used are those given in Table 1 of [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>], except that the parameter governing the ATP release rate, <italic>V</italic><sub>ATP</sub>, has been reduced from 2&#xD7;10<sup>&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;11</sup> to 5&#xD7;10<sup>&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;12</sup><italic>&#x3BC;</italic>mol <inline-formula id="IEq29"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq29.gif --><tex-math id="M16">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula><sup>&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;2</sup> s<sup>&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;1</sup> in order to obtain agreement with the experimental observations.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec4" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Quantitative characteristics of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation</title>
        <p>The amplitude and velocity of propagating Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves in microglia at different positions along microglia lanes, from a point of mechanical initiation in a microglia, were determined. Figures&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>A and B show the extent of propagation from the point of stimulation in two lanes, ~80 <inline-formula id="IEq30"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq30.gif --><tex-math id="M17">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and ~40 <inline-formula id="IEq31"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq31.gif --><tex-math id="M18">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide, respectively. The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagates with diminution in amplitude (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>C), at a velocity of about 5&#xA0;<inline-formula id="IEq32"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq32.gif --><tex-math id="M19">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula><italic>s</italic><sup>&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;1</sup>, over a distance of at most 120 <inline-formula id="IEq33"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq33.gif --><tex-math id="M20">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> before becoming undetectable. This velocity is about one-quarter of that for Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation in astrocyte lanes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Quantitation of these observations for four different sets of microglia lanes in four cultures is shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>. Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a shows that there is a continual decrease in amplitude of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave over 120&#xA0;<inline-formula id="IEq34"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq34.gif --><tex-math id="M21">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> at which distance the amplitude falls below 15% to 20% of the initial amplitude and could no longer be reliably detected. The percentage of microglia cells across a lane that gives a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> peak amplitude change that is greater than 15% of the peak amplitude at the site&#xA0;of initiation remains high for about the first 80 <inline-formula id="IEq35"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq35.gif --><tex-math id="M22">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and then declines rapidly over the succeeding 40 <inline-formula id="IEq36"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq36.gif --><tex-math id="M23">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). On the other hand, the peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> amplitude increases rapidly with an increase in the local density of cells that give an observable Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient response (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). 
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagates along a lane of microglia with decreasing amplitude from the point of initiation. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> show results for two different lanes of microglia, of widths 82&#xB1;5 <inline-formula id="IEq10"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq10.gif --><tex-math id="M24">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and 38&#xB1;4 <inline-formula id="IEq11"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq11.gif --><tex-math id="M25">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, respectively. In each case, (a) shows the site of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> initiation by mechanical stimulation with a micropipette and (b) shows the microglia that responded with a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient (indicated by <italic>open circles</italic>) after stimulation at the site indicated by the <italic>arrow</italic>; the calibration bar is 45 <inline-formula id="IEq12"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq12.gif --><tex-math id="M26">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. <bold>C</bold> shows the timecourse of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave at different distances along a lane from the site of initiation, as indicated. The mechanical stimulus was applied for 1 s starting at time zero</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig><fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Quantitative characteristics of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave for a number of microglia lanes. <bold>a</bold> shows the average peak amplitude of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> deliveries along the lanes before becoming undetectable at about 120 <inline-formula id="IEq13"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq13.gif --><tex-math id="M27">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (values normalized to the peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> concentration at the stimulating electrode). <bold>b</bold> shows the number of microglia that give a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response at different positions along the length of a lane, expressed as a percentage of the total number of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> indicator-labeled microglia at that position; this remains high for about 80 <inline-formula id="IEq14"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq14.gif --><tex-math id="M28">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and then declines. <bold>c</bold> shows that the average amplitude of the peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in equal-width segments of a microglia lane increases with the number of microglia that propagate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in the segment. Results in a, b and c are for three different lanes in three different cultures. In a and b the distance is from equal-width segments along a lane (for which the average peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> was calculated for all microglia in the segment) to the site of mechanical initiation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>The restricted local propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave from the point of initiation is emphasized by experiments in which different sites of initiation along a single lane of microglia are determined. As Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref> shows, in each case the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation is restricted to regions of about 100 <inline-formula id="IEq39"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq39.gif --><tex-math id="M29">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> diameter around the site of initiation.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>Evidence for release and diffusion of ATP during Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation</title>
        <p>In order to test for the possibility that mechanically stimulated microglial cells release a diffusible substance, parallel lanes of microglia were constructed, separated by cell-free lanes (see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>). Tests were then made of the extent to which Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves could propagate across these cell-free lanes of widths 70 <inline-formula id="IEq43"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq43.gif --><tex-math id="M30">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> or more, independent of the width of the microglia lanes (Figs.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>A and B). No such propagation was observed in 20 experiments. On the other hand, if the cell-free lanes were less than ~60 <inline-formula id="IEq44"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq44.gif --><tex-math id="M31">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide there was always successful propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave across the cell-free lanes (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>C). It appears then that a diffusible substance is released by the excited microglia and is able to initiate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transients in them.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Propagation of a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave occurs between microglial lanes if these are not separated by distances greater than about 60 <inline-formula id="IEq15"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq15.gif --><tex-math id="M32">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> show parallel lanes of microglia in which the lane widths are 75&#xB1;3 <inline-formula id="IEq16"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq16.gif --><tex-math id="M33">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and 25&#xB1;3 <inline-formula id="IEq17"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq17.gif --><tex-math id="M34">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, respectively, separated by cell-free lanes of 165&#xB1;3 <inline-formula id="IEq18"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq18.gif --><tex-math id="M35">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and 70&#xB1;4 <inline-formula id="IEq19"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq19.gif --><tex-math id="M36">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, respectively; the <italic>open circles</italic> indicate the microglia that gave a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response following mechanical excitation of the microglial cell indicated by the <italic>arrow</italic>; there is no propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave across these lanes. <bold>C</bold> shows parallel lanes of microglia in which lane widths are 50&#xB1;6 <inline-formula id="IEq20"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq20.gif --><tex-math id="M37">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and the cell-free lane 46&#xB1;10 <inline-formula id="IEq21"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq21.gif --><tex-math id="M38">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>; the <italic>open circles</italic> indicate that a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave response was able to propagate across cell-free lanes as well as along the lanes. The calibration bar is 45 <inline-formula id="IEq22"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq22.gif --><tex-math id="M39">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> in A, B and C. The position of the micropipette in C(a) is not evident as it is out of focus</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
        <p>Since astrocytes use ATP as a chemical transmitter, and it is known that microglia initiate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transients in response to ATP, we determined if ATP was likely to be the diffusible substance released by microglia in order to promote Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation. First, Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation was blocked by the ATP-degrading enzyme apyrase (grade III, 60 units per m&#x2113;; Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>). Second, the effects of antagonists to the P2Y class of purinergic receptors on Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation were tested. It is known that the pharmacological profile of P2Y receptor activation on spinal cord microglia and the expression of their mRNA clearly favours P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors, followed by P2Y<sub>6</sub> and P2Y<sub>1</sub> according to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] and P2Y<sub>2</sub>, P2Y<sub>6</sub>, P2Y<sub>12</sub> and P2Y<sub>14</sub> according to [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]. Suramin (100 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) completely blocked all propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave along microglial lanes (compare Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>B with <xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>A), indicating that P2Y<sub>6</sub> and P2Y<sub>14</sub> are not involved, and this was confirmed for P2Y<sub>6</sub> using the specific P2Y<sub>6</sub> antagonist MRS 2578 (30 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M). The specific P2Y<sub>1</sub> antagonist MRS 2500 (100 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) did not block the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave. On the other hand, the P2Y<sub>12</sub>-specific antagonist 2-MeSAMP (300 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) blocked Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation. Any contribution of P2X receptors known to be present on microglial cells, such as P2X<sub>4</sub> and P2X<sub>7</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>], to Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation is likely to be minimal given the blocking effects of the P2Y<sub>12</sub>-specific antagonist 2-MeSAMP. We conclude that Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation between microglial cells involves the release of ATP onto at least P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors. Visentin et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>] have also placed emphasis on the role of P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors in calcium signalling.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Propagation of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves is blocked by the ATP-degrading enzyme apyrase. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> show the extent of propagation of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup>, from the point of mechanical stimulation of a microglial cell, to other microglial cells in a lane. In each case, the top panel (a) shows the position of the mechanically stimulating micropipette and the lower panel (b) shows the microglial cells that gave a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> signal (<italic>open circles</italic>) in response to mechanical stimulation at the <italic>arrow</italic>. A is the control and in B apyrase (60 units/m&#x2113;; grade III, Sigma) was present with only the stimulated cell now giving a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient. The calibration bar is 45<inline-formula id="IEq23"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq23.gif --><tex-math id="M40">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig><fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>Transmission of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave between microglial cells is chemical due to the release of ATP. <bold>A</bold> and <bold>B</bold> show the extent of propagation of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> from the point of mechanical stimulation of a microglial cell to other microglial cells in a lane. In each case, the top panel ((a)) shows the position of the mechanically stimulating micropipette and the lower panel ((b)) the microglial cell(s) that gave a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> signal (<italic>open circles</italic>) in response to mechanical stimulation at the <italic>arrow</italic>. A is the control and in B suramin (100 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) was present blocking P2Y receptors and only the stimulated cell responded with a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transient. The calibration bar is 40 <inline-formula id="IEq24"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq24.gif --><tex-math id="M41">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula></p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Density of P2Y receptors on microglia</title>
        <p>The theoretical requirement that <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> take values from 25 to 45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M may reflect different densities of P2Y receptors on the microglia, since in the present theory <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> depends on this density as well as on the dissociation of ATP from the receptors (see Theory section above, and also the following section). Polyclonal antibody labelling of P2Y<sub>12</sub> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>a) receptors indicated that these are localized in clusters of average diameter 0.45 <inline-formula id="IEq45"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq45.gif --><tex-math id="M42">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, as are P2Y receptors on astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>] and smooth-muscle cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>]. The density of P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors, measured over nine microglial cells, varied about four-fold (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>b). We suggest that P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors mediate the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation. Since in the present model <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values need to vary over at least a two-fold range, it may be that this variability is partly due to differences in P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptor density.
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>Density of P2Y receptors on microglia. <bold>a</bold> Distribution of anti-P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptor immunofluorescence on single spinal-cord microglia in lanes; the shape of the cell is given by the borders of immunohisto chemical staining. <bold>b</bold> Histogram of the density of and anti-P2Y<sub>12</sub> labelled receptors for different microglia. The <italic>error bars</italic> indicate &#xB1;SEM. At least ten areas on each cell were used to determine the P2Y receptor density</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Modelling the quantitative characteristics of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation amongst microglia</title>
        <p>The model of purinergic transmission of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave given in the Methods was used to give a quantitative description for comparison with the experimental results. A lane of microglia five cells wide and 528 <inline-formula id="IEq51"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq51.gif --><tex-math id="M43">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> long was considered in which the centre-to-centre distance between the microglia was 25 <inline-formula id="IEq52"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq52.gif --><tex-math id="M44">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. The whole lane of microglia was placed on a 2D surface 528 <inline-formula id="IEq53"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq53.gif --><tex-math id="M45">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> by 528&#xA0;<inline-formula id="IEq54"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq54.gif --><tex-math id="M46">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>). Each row of five cells possessed <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values assigned by random permutations of the values 25, 30, 35, 40 and 45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M. Note that these are effective <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values that take into account other properties besides dissociation of ATP from P2Y receptors. Activation of a microglial cell in the centre of the lane, by increasing the ATP concentration about the cell to 20 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M for 5 s, generated a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave that propagated with diminution as shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>. The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave varied in amplitude and velocity, both across the width of the lane as well as along its length (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>).
<fig id="Fig8"><label>Fig.&#xA0;8</label><caption><p>Diagrammatic representation of the theoretical spatial and temporal changes in a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in a lane of microglia five cells wide following excitation of the central microglia, according to the mathematical model. The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave is initiated by a 5-s pulse of ATP of concen tration 20 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M. The <italic>vertical bars</italic> give Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M at times t = 7.5, 15, 22.5 and 30 s, as indicated. <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values range from 25 to 45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M for different microglia across each lane</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig8_HTML" id="MO8"/></fig></p>
        <p>A quantitative analysis of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation in a lane, such as that shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, gives the results summarised in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>. The peak amplitude of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in each microglial cell of the lane varied significantly both along the length and across the width of the lane (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a). Normalizing the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> to the largest amplitude observed at the site of initiation shows that many of the cells give a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> amplitude that is less than 15% of the largest one (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a). Using this as a cut-off for the <italic>&#x394;</italic>F/F value that would be observed experimentally (see Methods) gives a rate of decline of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> with distance similar to that observed, from 100% to 20% over about 120 <inline-formula id="IEq55"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq55.gif --><tex-math id="M47">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (compare Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>a with Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a). The percentage of cells that gives a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> amplitude greater than 15% of the largest amplitude at the site of initiation, for different rows of five cells along the length of the lane, remains high for the first 75 <inline-formula id="IEq56"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq56.gif --><tex-math id="M48">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and then declines to about 40% of maximum at 120 <inline-formula id="IEq57"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq57.gif --><tex-math id="M49">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. This is a similar pattern of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> changes to that observed experimentally along a lane of microglia (compare Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>b with Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). The average amplitude of the peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> across rows of cells in a lane increases with the number of cells that are activated in a row (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c). This is also observed experimentally (compare Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig9" ref-type="fig">9</xref>c with Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c).
<fig id="Fig9"><label>Fig.&#xA0;9</label><caption><p>Theoretical characteristics of a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in a microglia lane, according to the mathematical model as in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig8" ref-type="fig">8</xref>, for quantitative comparison with the observed characteristics (see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>). <bold>a</bold> shows that the predicted peak amplitude of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> for all cells in a lane, normalized to that at the site of stimulation, declines with distance along the length of the lane until it becomes undetectable at about 120 <inline-formula id="IEq37"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq37.gif --><tex-math id="M50">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> (compare to Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a); the <italic>horizontal line</italic> indicates the values of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> amplitude below which experimental detection is in the noise level (set at 15%). <bold>b</bold> shows the predicted number of microglia that give a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response greater than 15% of the maximum value at different positions along the length of a lane expressed as a percentage of the total number of cells at that position; this is maintained for about 70 <inline-formula id="IEq38"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq38.gif --><tex-math id="M51">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> and then declines rapidly (compare to Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b). <bold>c</bold> shows that the predicted amplitude of the average peak Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in rows of a microglia lane increases with the number of microglia that propagate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in the row (compare to Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig9_HTML" id="MO9"/></fig></p>
        <p>These theoretical results highlight the fact that Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation amongst microglial cells is very limited compared with that amongst astrocytes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]. Experimentally, this was highlighted by mechanical stimulation of microglial cells at different well-separated sites along a single microglial lane, showing that Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation was restricted to within about 90 <inline-formula id="IEq58"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq58.gif --><tex-math id="M52">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> of the stimulating micropipette (see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). Such restricted propagation was also observed along the model lane following stimulation at well-separated sites (compare Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig11" ref-type="fig">11</xref> with Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig10" ref-type="fig">10</xref>). The clustering of activated cells near the site of initiation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave is, in the model, due to the large amount of ATP released in this region.
<fig id="Fig10"><label>Fig.&#xA0;10</label><caption><p>Stimulation of microglia at different sites in a lane leads to Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation confined to the vicinity of the stimulating electrode. Shown in (<bold>a</bold>), (<bold>b</bold>) and (<bold>c</bold>) are three different sites, greater than 140 <inline-formula id="IEq40"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq40.gif --><tex-math id="M53">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> apart, of mechanical stimulation by a micropipette of a single cell in a single lane of microglia. In (<bold>d</bold>) is shown that the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves initiated in each case ((<bold>a</bold>) to (<bold>c</bold>)) are confined to a region within 90 <inline-formula id="IEq41"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq41.gif --><tex-math id="M54">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> of the stimulating micropipette, with each set of symbols indicating the extent of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation. The calibration bar is 45 <inline-formula id="IEq42"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq42.gif --><tex-math id="M55">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. The position of the micropipette in C(a) is not evident as it is out of focus</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig10_HTML" id="MO10"/></fig><fig id="Fig11"><label>Fig.&#xA0;11</label><caption><p>Theoretical predictions of the distribution of microglia in a lane five cells wide that gave a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response, with an amplitude greater than 15% of maximum, following excitation of a single microglial cell at three different sites along the length of the lane, indicated by <italic>filled circles</italic> (&#x2219;). The <italic>dots</italic> indicate the positions of microglia in the lane. The <italic>diamonds</italic> (&#x22C4;) indicate microglia that gave a response following stimulation of the microglia near the left-hand end of the lane (sixth cell from the left at &#x2212;&#x2009;250&#xA0;<inline-formula id="IEq46"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq46.gif --><tex-math id="M56">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>), the <italic>open circles</italic> (&#x2218;) responses following stimulation of the microglia near the right-hand end of the lane (sixth cell from the right at 250&#xA0;<inline-formula id="IEq47"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq47.gif --><tex-math id="M57">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) and the <italic>plusses</italic> (+) microglia in the centre of the lane (at 0 <inline-formula id="IEq48"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq48.gif --><tex-math id="M58">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>). (A longer lane (800 <inline-formula id="IEq49"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq49.gif --><tex-math id="M59">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>) has been used for this calculation.) The <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values range from 25 to 45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M for different microglia across each lane. Note that there is no overlap in the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave domains of each stimulated microglial cell, the <italic>diamonds</italic>, <italic>crosses</italic> and <italic>circles</italic> designating discrete regions</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig11_HTML" id="MO11"/></fig></p>
        <p>The model of purinergic transmission of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves was used to see if it could account for Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> propagation along and between lanes of microglia, such as those shown in Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>. Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref> shows the propagation of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves in three such parallel lanes of cells, separated by cell-free lanes 42 <inline-formula id="IEq59"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq59.gif --><tex-math id="M60">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide, following initiation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in the middle row of the middle lane by applying 20 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M of ATP for 5 s at a central cell. There is propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave over about six cells of the middle lane before the side lanes are engaged, at about 7 s after application of the initiating stimulus (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). Both side lanes first generate a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave that is in cells in a row opposite or nearly opposite the row containing the initiating cell in the middle lane. By 13 s the crest of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave has reached the limits of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> propagation at about 100 <inline-formula id="IEq60"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq60.gif --><tex-math id="M61">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> from the site of initiation, by which time it has travelled less than 75% of that distance along adjacent lanes (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig12" ref-type="fig">12</xref>). Very few cells are engaged in Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation in these adjacent lanes and propagation fails over distances of about 70 <inline-formula id="IEq61"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq61.gif --><tex-math id="M62">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> along the lane and 50 <inline-formula id="IEq62"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq62.gif --><tex-math id="M63">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> across it.
<fig id="Fig12"><label>Fig.&#xA0;12</label><caption><p>A diagrammatic representation of the theoretical spatial and temporal changes in Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in three lanes of microglia each five cells wide, separated by cell-free lanes 42 <inline-formula id="IEq50"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq50.gif --><tex-math id="M64">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide, following excitation of a single microglial cell in the middle row of the middle lane. The Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave is initiated by a 5-s pulse of ATP of concentration 20 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M on the central microglial cell at time <italic>t</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;0. The <italic>vertical bars</italic> give Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> in <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M at times t = 7.5, 15, 22.5 and 30 s, as indicated. <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values range from 25 to 45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M for different microglia across each lane. Note the limited propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave in both the middle and side lanes</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9076_Fig12_HTML" id="MO12"/></fig></p>
        <p>The question arises as to whether regeneration of ATP in each cell is necessary. Repeating calculations with regenerative release switched off, and thus only pure diffusion of ATP from its initial release site, gave travel distances along lanes reduced by about 20%. We investigated whether this reduced distance could be compensated for by increasing the initial release of ATP, but this then recruited cells in adjacent lanes in a way not observed experimentally. Thus the theoretical calculations indicate a role for intracellular regeneration of ATP, but at a much lower rate than in astrocytes.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec9" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Although activation of P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors by ATP leads to an influx of calcium ions in microglial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>] it does not seem that these receptors mediate the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave propagation in these cells as this is blocked by suramin which does not block P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors. It seems likely that P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors are activated at higher concentrations of ATP than is required for P2Y receptor activation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>], suggesting that the concentration of ATP reached at the receptors after its release from microglia is insufficient to excite P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors. ATP acts on microglial cells to both release calcium from internal stores and to evoke an influx of calcium [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. P2Y receptors mediate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> release from internal stores in microglial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>], the extent of this release being under the modulatory control of P2X receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>] and of toll-like receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>].</p>
      <p>ATP released following stimulation of astrocytes can generate Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> transients in nearby microglial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. Repeated stimulation of the astrocytes releases sufficient ATP to activate P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors on the microglial cells, greatly increasing membrane permeability in the microglial cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>] and leading to the release of inflammatory cytokines, such as IL-2, from the cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>]. The present work suggests that in these experiments the ATP released in moderate amounts from singly stimulated astrocytes most likely acts on P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors on microglial cells. We could block the ATP-dependent Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> propagation in these cells with suramin, which blocks P2Y<sub>1</sub>, P2Y<sub>2</sub> and P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors, but could not be blocked by P2Y<sub>1</sub> receptor antagonists. Given that the predominant receptor on microglial spinal cord cells shows the pharmacological profile of P2Y<sub>12</sub> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>] (see also [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]), we conclude that this receptor, which we found in relatively high density, is most likely to be mediating the effect of ATP. Thus there is no evidence that P2X<sub>7</sub> receptors are engaged in Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> propagation in microglia. It is interesting to note in this regard that microglial cells rapidly re-orientate their processes towards a site of ATP release in vivo as a consequence of the action of the released ATP on P2Y receptors, an action that is blocked by apyrase [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>] and that nucleotides acting on P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors of microglia exert a chemotactic effect [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>].</p>
      <p>We have used soft lithography techniques of micro-fabrication to allow controlled and discrete patterning of microglia so that quantitative investigations can be carried out [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. Such an approach avoids the difficulties inherent in the random seeding of microglial cells on a homogeneous substrate for carrying out quantitative measurements of the properties of propagating calcium waves [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR43">43</xref>]. The technique allows lanes of microglial cells with controlled widths of from 15 <inline-formula id="IEq63"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq63.gif --><tex-math id="M65">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> to over 150 <inline-formula id="IEq64"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq64.gif --><tex-math id="M66">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>, separated by cell-free regions with the same range of widths [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR44">44</xref>]. It is unlikely that this fabrication method affects the seeded microglial cells, since when applied to astrocytes the rates of propagation of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves remain about the same as determined in random seeded cultures [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>].</p>
      <p>The amplitude of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave, and the percentage of microglial cells excited to give a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response, were correlated along the length of a microglial lane, both decreasing from near the site of initiation over a distance of about 120 <inline-formula id="IEq65"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq65.gif --><tex-math id="M67">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> before the wave ceased to be detectable. Decreases in amplitude of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves from a site of mechanical initiation have often been observed in randomly seeded astrocytes over a homogeneous substrate, but in this case over several hundred microns [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR45">45</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR47">47</xref>]. The purinergic gliotransmission model suggests that the decline in amplitude of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave is due to the relatively high level of ATP released from the stimulated microglial cell, which then dominates the concentration profile of ATP within approximately 100 <inline-formula id="IEq66"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq66.gif --><tex-math id="M68">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>. The decline in amplitude of the wave approximately follows this concentration gradient of ATP. The decline in the percentage of microglial cells excited to give a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response within this 100 <inline-formula id="IEq67"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq67.gif --><tex-math id="M69">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> range is then attributed to a failure of microglial cells possessing a relatively high <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> to generate a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response as the concentration of ATP declines over the same range. The more than two-fold range in the <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values used in our model is comparable to the range of P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptor densities found in microglial cells using immunohistochemistry.</p>
      <p>Our work shows that there can be propagation of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> waves between parallel lanes of microglial cells when these are about 30 <inline-formula id="IEq68"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq68.gif --><tex-math id="M70">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide and separated by cell-free lanes about 40 <inline-formula id="IEq69"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq69.gif --><tex-math id="M71">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> wide, but this does not occur until many microglial cells in the initiating lane undergo a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response. It seems likely that a certain minimum amount of ATP must be released from the initiating lane, involving a certain minimum number of microglial cells undergoing a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response, before nearby microglial lanes are excited. Since ATP can diffuse across cell-free lanes as wide as 150 <inline-formula id="IEq70"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq70.gif --><tex-math id="M72">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula> from astrocyte-seeded lanes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>], it seems likely that the ATP released from microglial cells is much less than that from astrocytes since the P2Y<sub>12</sub> receptors in the model for microglia possessed lower <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values (25&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;45 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M) than in the model for astrocytes (25&#x2009;&#x2212;&#x2009;125 <italic>&#x3BC;</italic>M; [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR5">5</xref>]).</p>
      <p>The purinergic transmission model can account for the observed extent of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave provided pure diffusion of ATP from the stimulation site is supplemented by regenerative release of ATP from the microglia. Fluctuations in the density of excited microglia along a lane leads to local fluctuations in the amplitude of the Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> wave due to changes in the local ATP concentration, consequential on the changes in the local number of microglial cells excited. This is modelled by assigning a range of <italic>K</italic><sub><italic>R</italic></sub> values to the P2Y receptors on the microglia, and this also reflects the density of receptors on individual microglial cells.</p>
      <p>Stimulation of three different microglial cells some hundreds of microns apart gave a Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> response in microglia at highest density closest to the site of stimulation. Our model quantitatively explains these observations as arising from the large amount of ATP released by the stimulated microglial cell diffusing to activate microglia within about 100 <inline-formula id="IEq71"><!-- Alternate image not processed: 11302_2007_9076_Article_IEq71.gif --><tex-math id="M73">\documentclass[12pt]{minimal}
\usepackage{amsmath}
\usepackage{wasysym} 
\usepackage{amsfonts} 
\usepackage{amssymb} 
\usepackage{amsbsy}
\usepackage{mathrsfs}
\usepackage{upgreek}
\setlength{\oddsidemargin}{-69pt}
\begin{document}$\mu \mbox{m}$\end{document}</tex-math></inline-formula>.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgements</title>
      <p>This work was supported by ARC (Australia Research Council) Grant DP0665689.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Verderio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matteoli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP mediates calcium signaling between astrocytes and microglial cells: modulation by ifn-gamma</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>166</volume>
          <issue>10</issue>
          <fpage>6383</fpage>
          <lpage>6391</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Verderio C, Matteoli M (2001) ATP mediates calcium signaling between astrocytes and microglial cells: modulation by ifn-gamma. J Immunol 166(10):6383&#x2013;6391 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11342663</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schipke</surname>
              <given-names>CG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Boucsein</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ohlemeyer</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kirchhoff</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettenmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Astrocyte Ca2+ waves trigger responses in microglial cells in brain slices</article-title>
          <source>FASEB J</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>257</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schipke CG, Boucsein C, Ohlemeyer C, Kirchhoff F, Kettenmann H (2002) Astrocyte Ca2+ waves trigger responses in microglial cells in brain slices. FASEB J 16(2): 255&#x2013;257 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11772946</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;ller</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium signaling in microglial cells</article-title>
          <source>GLIA</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>40</volume>
          <fpage>184</fpage>
          <lpage>194</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.10152</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">M&#xF6;ller T (2002) Calcium signaling in microglial cells. GLIA 40:184&#x2013;194 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12379906</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takano</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sul</surname>
              <given-names>JY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mazzanti</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Doyle</surname>
              <given-names>RT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haydon</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Porter</surname>
              <given-names>MD</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Micropatterned substrates: approach to probing intercellular communication pathways</article-title>
          <source>Anal Chem</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>74</volume>
          <issue>18</issue>
          <fpage>4640</fpage>
          <lpage>4661</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac0257400</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Takano H, Sul JY, Mazzanti ML, Doyle RT, Haydon PG, Porter MD (2002) Micropatterned substrates: approach to probing intercellular communication pathways. Anal Chem 74(18):4640&#x2013;4661 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12349965</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Buljan</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farnell</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Purinergic junctional transmission and propagation of calcium waves in spinal cord astrocyte networks</article-title>
          <source>Biophys J</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <fpage>3560</fpage>
          <lpage>3571</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.106.082073</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bennett MR, Buljan V, Farnell L, Gibson WG (2006) Purinergic junctional transmission and propagation of calcium waves in spinal cord astrocyte networks. Biophys J 91:3560&#x2013;3571 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16905605</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hassinger</surname>
              <given-names>TD</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guthrie</surname>
              <given-names>PB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Atkinson</surname>
              <given-names>PB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kater</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>An extracellular signaling component in propagation of astrocytic calcium waves</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>93</volume>
          <issue>23</issue>
          <fpage>13268</fpage>
          <lpage>13273</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.93.23.13268</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hassinger TD, Guthrie PB, Atkinson PB, Bennett MV, Kater SB (1996) An extracellular signaling component in propagation of astrocytic calcium waves. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 93(23):13268&#x2013;13273 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8917580</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Eugenin</surname>
              <given-names>EA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eckardt</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Theis</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Willecke</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saez</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microglia at brain stab wounds express connexin 43 and in vitro form functional gap junctions after treatment with interferon-gamma and tumor necrosis factor-alpha</article-title>
          <source>Proc Natl Acad Sci USA</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>98</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>4190</fpage>
          <lpage>4195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1073/pnas.051634298</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Eugenin EA, Eckardt D, Theis M, Willecke K, Bennett MV, Saez JC (2001) Microglia at brain stab wounds express connexin 43 and in vitro form functional gap junctions after treatment with interferon-gamma and tumor necrosis factor-alpha. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 98(7):4190&#x2013;4195 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11259646</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Graeber</surname>
              <given-names>MB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lopez-Redondo</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ikoma</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ishikawa</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Imai</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakajima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kreutzberg</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohsaka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The microglia/macrophage response in the neonatal rat facial nucleus following axotomy</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>813</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>241</fpage>
          <lpage>253</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(98)00859-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Graeber MB, Lopez-Redondo F, Ikoma E, Ishikawa M, Imai Y, Nakajima K, Kreutzberg GW, Kohsaka S (1998) The microglia/macrophage response in the neonatal rat facial nucleus following axotomy. Brain Res 813(2):241&#x2013;253 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9838143</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mittelbronn</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dietz</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schluesener</surname>
              <given-names>HJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meyermann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Local distribution of microglia in the normal adult human central nervous system differs by up to one order of magnitude</article-title>
          <source>Acta Neuropathol</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>101</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>249</fpage>
          <lpage>255</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mittelbronn M, Dietz K, Schluesener HJ, Meyermann R (2001) Local distribution of microglia in the normal adult human central nervous system differs by up to one order of magnitude. Acta Neuropathol 101(3):249&#x2013;255 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11307625</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ma</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Morton</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nicholson</surname>
              <given-names>LF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microglia density decreases with age in a mouse model of Huntington&#x2019;s disease</article-title>
          <source>GLIA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>274</fpage>
          <lpage>280</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.10261</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ma L, Morton AJ, Nicholson LF (2003) Microglia density decreases with age in a mouse model of Huntington&#x2019;s disease. GLIA 43(3):274&#x2013;280 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12898706</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>James</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Butt</surname>
              <given-names>AM</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2Y and P2X purinoceptor mediated Ca2+ signalling in glial cell pathology in the central nervous system</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>447</volume>
          <issue>2-3</issue>
          <fpage>247</fpage>
          <lpage>260</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0014-2999(02)01756-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">James G, Butt AM (2002) P2Y and P2X purinoceptor mediated Ca2+ signalling in glial cell pathology in the central nervous system. Eur J Pharmacol 447(2-3):247&#x2013;260 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12151016</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Light</surname>
              <given-names>AR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wu</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hughen</surname>
              <given-names>RW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Guthrie</surname>
              <given-names>PB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Purinergic receptors activating rapid intracellular Ca2+ increases in microglia</article-title>
          <source>Neuron Glia Biol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>125</fpage>
          <lpage>138</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S1740925X05000323</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Light AR, Wu Y, Hughen RW, Guthrie PB (2006) Purinergic receptors activating rapid intracellular Ca2+ increases in microglia. Neuron Glia Biol 2(2):125&#x2013;138 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16652167</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bianco</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fumagalli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pravettorsi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Ambrosi</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Volonte</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matteoli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbracchio</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verderio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pathophysiological roles of extracellular nucleotides in glial cells: differential expressions of purinergic receptors in resting and activated microglia</article-title>
          <source>Brains Res Rev</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>144</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.brainresrev.2004.12.004</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bianco F, Fumagalli M, Pravettorsi E, D&#x2019;Ambrosi N, Volonte C, Matteoli M, Abbracchio MP, Verderio C (2005) Pathophysiological roles of extracellular nucleotides in glial cells: differential expressions of purinergic receptors in resting and activated microglia. Brains Res Rev 48:144&#x2013;156 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Visentin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nuccio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bellenchi</surname>
              <given-names>GC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Different patterns of Ca<sup>2&#x2009;+&#x2009;</sup> signals are induced by low compared to high concentrations of P2Y agonists in microglia</article-title>
          <source>Purinergic Signalling</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>2</volume>
          <fpage>605</fpage>
          <lpage>617</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11302-006-9023-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Visentin S, De Nuccio C, Bellenchi GC (2006) Different patterns of Ca2&#x2009;+&#x2009; signals are induced by low compared to high concentrations of P2Y agonists in microglia. Purinergic Signalling 2:605&#x2013;617 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sasaki</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoshi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Akazawa</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakamura</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tsuzuki</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohsaka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Selective expression of Gi/o-coupled ATP receptor P2Y12 in microglia in rat brain</article-title>
          <source>Glia</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>44</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>242</fpage>
          <lpage>250</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.10293</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sasaki Y, Hoshi M, Akazawa C, Nakamura Y, Tsuzuki H, Inoue K, Kohsaka S (2003) Selective expression of Gi/o-coupled ATP receptor P2Y12 in microglia in rat brain. Glia 44(3):242&#x2013;250 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14603465</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boucsein</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zacharias</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farber</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pavlovic</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanisch</surname>
              <given-names>UK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettenmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Purinergic receptors on microglial cells: functional expression in acute brain slices and modulation of microglial activation in vitro</article-title>
          <source>Eur J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>2267</fpage>
          <lpage>2276</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1460-9568.2003.02663.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Boucsein C, Zacharias R, Farber K, Pavlovic S, Hanisch UK, Kettenmann H (2003) Purinergic receptors on microglial cells: functional expression in acute brain slices and modulation of microglial activation in vitro. Eur J Neurosci 17(11):2267&#x2013;2276 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12814360</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wilson</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Francis</surname>
              <given-names>SE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dower</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Crossman</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Secretion of intracellular IL-1 receptor antagonist (type&#xA0;1) is dependent on P2X7 receptor activation</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>173</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>1202</fpage>
          <lpage>1208</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wilson HL, Francis SE, Dower SK, Crossman DC (2004) Secretion of intracellular IL-1 receptor antagonist (type&#xA0;1) is dependent on P2X7 receptor activation. J Immunol 173(2):1202&#x2013;1208 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15240711</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hide</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tanaka</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakajima</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohsaka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extracellular ATP triggers tumor necrosis factor-alpha release from rat microglia</article-title>
          <source>J Neurochem</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>75</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>965</fpage>
          <lpage>972</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1046/j.1471-4159.2000.0750965.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hide I, Tanaka M, Inoue A, Nakajima K, Kohsaka S, Inoue K, Nakata Y (2000) Extracellular ATP triggers tumor necrosis factor-alpha release from rat microglia. J Neurochem 75(3):965&#x2013;972 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10936177</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suzuki</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hide</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ido</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohsaka</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nakata</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Production and release of neuroprotective tumor necrosis factor by P2X7 receptor-activated microglia</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>1</fpage>
          <lpage>7</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3792-03.2004</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Suzuki T, Hide I, Ido K, Kohsaka S, Inoue K, Nakata&#xA0;Y (2004) Production and release of neuroprotective tumor necrosis factor by P2X7 receptor-activated microglia. J Neurosci 24(1):1&#x2013;7 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14715932</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Seo</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>KY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Interleukin-10 expression in lipopolysaccharide-activated microglia is mediated by extracellular ATP in an autocrine fashion</article-title>
          <source>Neuroreport</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <issue>7</issue>
          <fpage>1157</fpage>
          <lpage>1161</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001756-200405190-00015</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Seo DR, Kim KY, Lee YB (2004) Interleukin-10 expression in lipopolysaccharide-activated microglia is mediated by extracellular ATP in an autocrine fashion. Neuroreport 15(7):1157&#x2013;1161 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15129165</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;ller</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kann</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verkhratsky</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettenmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Activation of mouse microglial cells affects P2 receptor signaling</article-title>
          <source>Brain Res</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>853</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>49</fpage>
          <lpage>59</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-8993(99)02244-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">M&#xF6;ller T, Kann O, Verkhratsky A, Kettenmann H (2000) Activation of mouse microglial cells affects P2 receptor signaling. Brain Res 853(1):49&#x2013;59 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10627307</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ferrari</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Villalba</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chiozzi</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Falzoni</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ricciardi-Castagnoli</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Virgilio</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mouse microglial cells express a plasma membrane pore gated by extracellular ATP</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>156</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>1531</fpage>
          <lpage>1539</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ferrari D, Villalba M, Chiozzi P, Falzoni S, Ricciardi-Castagnoli P, Di Virgilio F (1996) Mouse microglial cells express a plasma membrane pore gated by extracellular ATP. J Immunol 156(4):1531&#x2013;1539 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8568257</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Toescu</surname>
              <given-names>EC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;ller</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettenmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verkhratsky</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Long-term activation of capacitative Ca2+ entry in mouse microglial cells</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>86</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>925</fpage>
          <lpage>935</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00123-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Toescu EC, M&#xF6;ller T, Kettenmann H, Verkhratsky A (1998) Long-term activation of capacitative Ca2+ entry in mouse microglial cells. Neuroscience 86(3):925&#x2013;935 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9692728</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Morigiwa</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Quan</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Murakami</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yamashita</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fukuda</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2 purinoceptor expression and functional changes of hypoxia-activated cultured rat retinal microglia</article-title>
          <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>282</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>153</fpage>
          <lpage>156</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0304-3940(00)00887-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Morigiwa K, Quan M, Murakami M, Yamashita M, Fukuda Y (2000) P2 purinoceptor expression and functional changes of hypoxia-activated cultured rat retinal microglia. Neurosci Lett 282(3):153&#x2013;156 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10717414</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Breemen</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLarnon</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Activation of purinergic P2X receptors inhibits p2y-mediated Ca2+ influx in human microglia</article-title>
          <source>Cell Calcium</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>205</fpage>
          <lpage>212</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1054/ceca.2000.0110</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang X, Kim SU, van Breemen C, McLarnon JG (2000) Activation of purinergic P2X receptors inhibits p2y-mediated Ca2+ influx in human microglia. Cell Calcium 27(4):205&#x2013;212 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10858666</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Haydon</surname>
              <given-names>PG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeung</surname>
              <given-names>ES</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Direct observation of calcium-independent intercellular ATP signaling in astrocytes</article-title>
          <source>Anal Chem</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>72</volume>
          <issue>9</issue>
          <fpage>2001</fpage>
          <lpage>2007</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1021/ac9912146</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang Z, Haydon PG, Yeung ES (2000) Direct observation of calcium-independent intercellular ATP signaling in astrocytes. Anal Chem 72(9):2001&#x2013;2007 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10815957</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ballerini</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Iorio</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ciccarelli</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nargi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Alimonte</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Traversa</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rathbone</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caciagli</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Glial cells express multiple binding cassette proteins which are involved in ATP release</article-title>
          <source>Neuroreport</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>13</volume>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <fpage>1789</fpage>
          <lpage>1792</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1097/00001756-200210070-00019</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ballerini P, Di Iorio P, Ciccarelli R, Nargi E, D&#x2019;Alimonte I, Traversa U, Rathbone MP, Caciagli F (2002) Glial cells express multiple binding cassette proteins which are involved in ATP release. Neuroreport 13(14):1789&#x2013;1792 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12395124</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farnell</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A quantitative model of purinergic junctional transmission of calcium waves in astrocyte networks</article-title>
          <source>Biophys J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>89</volume>
          <issue>4</issue>
          <fpage>2235</fpage>
          <lpage>2250</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.105.062968</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bennett MR, Farnell L, Gibson WG (2005) A quantitative model of purinergic junctional transmission of calcium waves in astrocyte networks. Biophys J 89(4):2235&#x2013;250 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16055527</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dobrenis</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microglia in cell culture and in transplantation therapy for central nervous disease</article-title>
          <source>Methods</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>16</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>320</fpage>
          <lpage>344</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/meth.1998.0688</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Dobrenis K (1998) Microglia in cell culture and in transplantation therapy for central nervous disease. Methods 16(3):320&#x2013;344 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10071070</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lemon</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brockhausen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>G-H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gibson</surname>
              <given-names>WG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Calcium mobilization and spontaneous transient outward current characteristics upon agonist activation of P2Y2 receptors in smooth muscle cells</article-title>
          <source>Biophys J</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>88</volume>
          <fpage>1507</fpage>
          <lpage>1523</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1529/biophysj.104.043976</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lemon G, Brockhausen J, Li G-H, Gibson WG, Bennett MR (2005) Calcium mobilization and spontaneous transient outward current characteristics upon agonist activation of P2Y2 receptors in smooth muscle cells. Biophys J 88:1507&#x2013;1523 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15556987</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Takenouchi</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogihara</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sato</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kitani</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inhibitory effects of U73122 and U73343 on Ca2+ influx and pore formation induced by the activation of P2X7 nucleotide receptors in mouse microglial cell line</article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>1726</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>177</fpage>
          <lpage>186</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Takenouchi T, Ogihara K, Sato M, Kitani H (2005) Inhibitory effects of U73122 and U73343 on Ca2+ influx and pore formation induced by the activation of P2X7 nucleotide receptors in mouse microglial cell line. Biochim Biophys Acta 1726(2):177&#x2013;186 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16122875</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McLarnon</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Purinergic mediated changes in Ca2+ mobilization and functional responses in microglia: effects of low levels of ATP</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci Res</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>81</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>349</fpage>
          <lpage>356</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/jnr.20475</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McLarnon JG (2005) Purinergic mediated changes in Ca2+ mobilization and functional responses in microglia: effects of low levels of ATP. J Neurosci Res 81(3):349&#x2013;356 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15948175</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Visentin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Renzi</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Frank</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greco</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Two different ionotropic receptors are activated by ATP in rat microglia</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>519</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>723</fpage>
          <lpage>736</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1469-7793.1999.0723n.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Visentin S, Renzi M, Frank C, Greco A, Levi G (1999) Two different ionotropic receptors are activated by ATP in rat microglia. J Physiol 519(3):723&#x2013;736 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10457086</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>McLarnon</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Goghari</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>YB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walz</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Krieger</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effects of ATP and elevated K+ on K+ currents and intracellular Ca2+ in human microglia</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>91</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>343</fpage>
          <lpage>352</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00491-6</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">McLarnon JG, Zhang L, Goghari V, Lee YB, Walz W, Krieger C, Kim SU (1999) Effects of ATP and elevated K+ on K+ currents and intracellular Ca2+ in human microglia. Neuroscience 91(1):343&#x2013;352 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10336083</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Norenberg</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Langosch</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gebicke-Haerter</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Illes</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Characterization and possible function of adenosine 5&#x2019;-triphosphate receptors in activated rat microglia</article-title>
          <source>Br J Pharmacol</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>111</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>942</fpage>
          <lpage>950</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Norenberg W, Langosch JM, Gebicke-Haerter PJ, Illes P (1994) Characterization and possible function of adenosine 5&#x2019;-triphosphate receptors in activated rat microglia. Br J Pharmacol 111(3):942&#x2013;950 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8019772</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Franchini</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levi</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Visentin</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inwardly rectifying K+ channels influence Ca2+ entry due to nucleotide receptor activation in microglia</article-title>
          <source>Cell Calcium</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>35</volume>
          <issue>5</issue>
          <fpage>449</fpage>
          <lpage>459</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.ceca.2003.11.001</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Franchini L, Levi G, Visentin S (2004) Inwardly rectifying K+ channels influence Ca2+ entry due to nucleotide receptor activation in microglia. Cell Calcium 35(5):449&#x2013;459 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15003854</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Choi</surname>
              <given-names>HB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hong</surname>
              <given-names>SH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ryu</surname>
              <given-names>JK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>SU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McLarnon</surname>
              <given-names>JG</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Differential activation of subtype purinergic receptors modulates Ca(2+) mobilization and COX-2 in human microglia</article-title>
          <source>GLIA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>43</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>95</fpage>
          <lpage>103</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.10239</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Choi HB, Hong SH, Ryu JK, Kim SU, McLarnon JG (2003) Differential activation of subtype purinergic receptors modulates Ca(2+) mobilization and COX-2 in human microglia. GLIA 43(2):95&#x2013;103 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12838502</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kann</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hoffmann</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schumann</surname>
              <given-names>RR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Weber</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kettenmann</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hanisch</surname>
              <given-names>UK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The tyrosine kinase inhibitor AG126 restores receptor signaling and blocks release functions in activated microglia (brain macrophages) by preventing a chronic rise in the intracellular calcium level</article-title>
          <source>J Neurochem</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>90</volume>
          <issue>3</issue>
          <fpage>513</fpage>
          <lpage>525</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1111/j.1471-4159.2004.02534.x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kann O, Hoffmann A, Schumann RR, Weber JR, Kettenmann H, Hanisch UK (2004) The tyrosine kinase inhibitor AG126 restores receptor signaling and blocks release functions in activated microglia (brain macrophages) by preventing a chronic rise in the intracellular calcium level. J Neurochem 90(3):513&#x2013;525 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15255929</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bianco</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pravettoni</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colombo</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schenk</surname>
              <given-names>U</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xF6;ller</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Matteoli</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Verderio</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Astrocyte-derived ATP induces vesicle shedding and IL-1 beta release from microglia</article-title>
          <source>J Immunol</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>174</volume>
          <issue>11</issue>
          <fpage>7268</fpage>
          <lpage>7277</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bianco F, Pravettoni E, Colombo A, Schenk U, M&#xF6;ller T, Matteoli M, Verderio C (2005) Astrocyte-derived ATP induces vesicle shedding and IL-1 beta release from microglia. J Immunol 174(11):7268&#x2013;7277 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15905573</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Davalos</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Grutzendler</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yang</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>JV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zuo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jung</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Littman</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dustin</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gan</surname>
              <given-names>WB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP mediates rapid microglial response to local brain injury in vivo</article-title>
          <source>Nat Neurosci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>8</volume>
          <issue>6</issue>
          <fpage>752</fpage>
          <lpage>758</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1038/nn1472</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Davalos D, Grutzendler J, Yang G, Kim JV, Zuo Y, Jung S, Littman DR, Dustin ML, Gan WB (2005) ATP mediates rapid microglial response to local brain injury in vivo. Nat Neurosci 8(6):752&#x2013;758 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15895084</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nasu-Tada</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koizumi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Inoue</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Involvement of <italic>&#x3B2;</italic>1 integrin in microglial chemotaxis and proliferation on fibronectin: different regulations by ADP through PKA</article-title>
          <source>Glia</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>52</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>98</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.20224</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nasu-Tada K, Koizumi S, Inoue K (2005) Involvement of &#x3B2;1 integrin in microglial chemotaxis and proliferation on fibronectin: different regulations by ADP through PKA. Glia 52(2):98&#x2013;107 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15920726</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Whitesides</surname>
              <given-names>GM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ostuni</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Takayama</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>X</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ingber</surname>
              <given-names>DE</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Soft lithography in biology and biochemistry</article-title>
          <source>Annu Rev Biomed Eng</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>3</volume>
          <fpage>335</fpage>
          <lpage>373</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1146/annurev.bioeng.3.1.335</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Whitesides GM, Ostuni E, Takayama S, Jiang X, Ingber DE (2001) Soft lithography in biology and biochemistry. Annu Rev Biomed Eng 3:335&#x2013;373 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11447067</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR43">
        <label>43.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Folch</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Toner</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Microengineering of cellular interactions</article-title>
          <source>Ann Rev Biomed Eng</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>6</volume>
          <fpage>41</fpage>
          <lpage>75</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Folch A, Toner M (2000) Microengineering of cellular interactions. Ann Rev Biomed Eng 6:41&#x2013;75 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR44">
        <label>44.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Recknor</surname>
              <given-names>JB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Recknor</surname>
              <given-names>JC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sakaguchi</surname>
              <given-names>DS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mallapragada</surname>
              <given-names>SK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Oriented astroglial cell growth on micropatterned polystyrene substrates</article-title>
          <source>Biomaterials</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <issue>14</issue>
          <fpage>2753</fpage>
          <lpage>2767</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.biomaterials.2003.11.045</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Recknor JB, Recknor JC, Sakaguchi DS, Mallapragada SK (2004) Oriented astroglial cell growth on micropatterned polystyrene substrates. Biomaterials 25(14):2753&#x2013;2767 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14962554</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR45">
        <label>45.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Giaume</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Venance</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intercellular calcium signaling and gap junctional communication in astrocytes</article-title>
          <source>GLIA</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>24</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>50</fpage>
          <lpage>64</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/(SICI)1098-1136(199809)24:1&lt;50::AID-GLIA6&gt;3.0.CO;2-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Giaume C, Venance L (1998) Intercellular calcium signaling and gap junctional communication in astrocytes. GLIA 24(1):50&#x2013;64 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9700489</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR46">
        <label>46.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Blomstrand</surname>
              <given-names>F</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aberg</surname>
              <given-names>ND</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eriksson</surname>
              <given-names>PS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hansson</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ronnback</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Extent of intercellular calcium wave propagation is related to gap junction permeability and level of connexin-43 expression in astrocytes in primary cultures from four brain regions</article-title>
          <source>Neuroscience</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>92</volume>
          <issue>1</issue>
          <fpage>255</fpage>
          <lpage>265</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0306-4522(98)00738-6</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Blomstrand F, Aberg ND, Eriksson PS, Hansson E, Ronnback L (1999) Extent of intercellular calcium wave propagation is related to gap junction permeability and level of connexin-43 expression in astrocytes in primary cultures from four brain regions. Neuroscience 92(1):255&#x2013;65 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10392848</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR47">
        <label>47.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Suadicani</surname>
              <given-names>SO</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pina-Benabou</surname>
              <given-names>MH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Urban-Maldonado</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spray</surname>
              <given-names>DC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Scemes</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Acute downregulation of Cx43 alters P2Y receptor expression levels in mouse spinal cord astrocytes</article-title>
          <source>GLIA</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>42</volume>
          <issue>2</issue>
          <fpage>160</fpage>
          <lpage>171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1002/glia.10197</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Suadicani SO, De Pina-Benabou MH, Urban-Maldonado M, Spray DC, Scemes E (2003) Acute downregulation of Cx43 alters P2Y receptor expression levels in mouse spinal cord astrocytes. GLIA 42(2):160&#x2013;171 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12655600</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>