<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Purinergic Signal</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Purinergic Signalling</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">1573-9538</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1573-9546</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Springer Netherlands</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Dordrecht</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">18404451</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">2072911</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">9067</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s11302-007-9067-x</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Lack of evidence for direct phosphorylation of recombinantly expressed P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors by protein kinase C</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Franklin</surname>
            <given-names>Cindy</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Braam</surname>
            <given-names>Ursula</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Eisele</surname>
            <given-names>Thomas</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
            <given-names>G&#xFC;nther</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Hausmann</surname>
            <given-names>Ralf</given-names>
          </name>
          <address>
            <phone>+49-241-8089135</phone>
            <fax>+49-241-803389135</fax>
            <email>rhausmann@ukaachen.de</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1"/>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1">Department of Molecular Pharmacology, University Hospital of RWTH Aachen University, Wendlingweg 2, 52074 Aachen, Germany </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>6</day>
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>9</month>
        <year>2007</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>3</volume>
      <issue>4</issue>
      <fpage>377</fpage>
      <lpage>388</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="received">
          <day>20</day>
          <month>6</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>27</day>
          <month>7</month>
          <year>2007</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Springer Science + Business Media B.V. 2007</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <p>P2X<sub>3</sub> and P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptors are present on sensory neurons, where they contribute not only to transient nociceptive responses, but also to hypersensitivity underlying pathological pain states elicited by nerve injuries. Increased signalling through P2X<sub>3</sub> and P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptors may arise from an increased routing to the plasma membrane and/or gain of function of pre-existing receptors. An obvious effector mechanism for functional modulation is protein kinase C (PKC)-mediated phosphorylation, since all P2X family members share a conserved consensus sequence for PKC, TXR/K, within the intracellularly located N-terminal domain. Contradictory reports have been published regarding the exact role of this motif. In the present study, we confirm that site-directed elimination of the potential phosphor-acceptor threonine or the basic residue in the P+2 position of the TXR/K sequence accelerates desensitization of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors and abolishes P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor function. Moreover, the PKC activator phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate increased P2X<sub>3</sub> (but not P2X<sub>2</sub>) receptor-mediated currents. Biochemically, however, we were unable to demonstrate by various experimental approaches a direct phosphorylation of wild-type P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors expressed in both <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells. In conclusion, our data support the view that the TXR/K motif plays an important role in P2X function and that phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate is capable of modulating some P2X receptor subtypes. The underlying mechanism, however, is unlikely to involve direct PKC-mediated P2X receptor phosphorylation.</p>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>
          <bold>Keywords</bold>
        </title>
        <kwd>Phosphorylation</kwd>
        <kwd>Protein kinase C</kwd>
        <kwd>P2X receptors</kwd>
        <kwd>P2X<sub>2</sub></kwd>
        <kwd>P2X<sub>3</sub></kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Springer Science+Business Media B.V. 2007</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="introduction">
      <title>Introduction</title>
      <p>P2X receptors constitute an abundant class of ligand-gated ion channels, which respond to extracellular ATP and related nucleotides with the opening of an intrinsic pore permeable to Na<sup>+</sup>, K<sup>+</sup> and Ca<sup>2+</sup> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>]. A family encompassing seven P2X subunit genes, designated P2X<sub>1&#x2013;7</sub>, has been identified in rodents and mammals. Six of the seven subunit isoforms (P2X<sub>1</sub>-P2X<sub>5</sub> and P2X<sub>7</sub>) are able to assemble into homotrimeric receptor channels [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>] with distinct pharmacological and electrophysiological phenotypes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR9">9</xref>]. According to their sensitivity to the synthetic ATP analogue &#x3B1;,&#x3B2;-methylene adenosine 5&#x2032;-triphosphate (&#x3B1;&#x3B2;-meATP) and the rate of current desensitization, P2X receptors are generally subgrouped into at least two categories: (1) rapidly desensitizing and &#x3B1;&#x3B2;-meATP sensitive (P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub>) and (2) slowly or non-desensitizing and &#x3B1;&#x3B2;-meATP insensitive (P2X<sub>2</sub>, P2X<sub>4</sub> and P2X<sub>7</sub>) receptors. The term &#x201C;non-desensitizing&#x201D; means that the currents are maintained for at least a few seconds in the continuous presence of agonist. A peculiar phenotype is inherent to heteromeric P2X<sub>2</sub>/P2X<sub>3</sub> (P2X<sub>2+3</sub>) receptors, which feature &#x3B1;&#x3B2;-meATP sensitivity combined with a non-desensitizing current response.</p>
      <p>P2X receptors are found on the surface of a large variety of cells, where they are involved in numerous sensory processes including nociception under both physiological and pathological processes [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR10">10</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. On nociceptive sensory neurons, extracellular ATP acts as a pain-producing neurotransmitter predominantly through homotrimeric P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors or heterotrimeric P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptors. Conditions and mediators that facilitate P2X<sub>3</sub> and P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptor-mediated signalling, apparently by potentiating ionic currents, include (1) substance P and bradykinin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], (2) nerve injury [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>] and (3) calcitonin gene-related peptide (CGRP), a potent vasodilator and proinflammatory agent [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. How this increase in receptor function occurs has not been fully solved. One obvious candidate mechanism is protein kinase C (PKC)-mediated phosphorylation, since all P2X family members share a conserved consensus sequence for PKC-mediated phosphorylation (TXR/K) within the intracellularly located N-terminal domain (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). Indeed, results obtained with pharmacological activators and inhibitors are consistent with PKC being involved in P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor potentiation by substance P and bradykinin [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>], as well as the calcitonin gene-related peptide [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>]. Direct PKC-mediated phosphorylation has so far been demonstrated only for the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor, with <sup>18</sup>T of the <sup>18</sup>TPK<sup>20</sup> sequence as the phospho-acceptor site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Mutational analysis has further shown that the TXR/K sequence of the P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors plays an important role in controlling the rate of receptor desensitization [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>]. Changes of the rate of desensitization could profoundly influence the efficiency of synaptic transmission and thus contribute to pathological pain states. Overall, there is significant interest in a better understanding of the mechanisms involved in the short-term and long-term regulation of P2X receptors.
<fig id="Fig1"><label>Fig.&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Effect of site-directed modification of a putative PKC motif on currents mediated by ATP-activated P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. <bold>a</bold> Schematic model of the transmembrane topology of the rat P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit illustrating the N-terminal position of the <sup>12</sup>TTK<sup>14</sup> sequence. <bold>b</bold> Alignment of intracellular N-terminal amino acid sequences of the seven P2X subunit isoforms reveals a highly conserved consensus motif, TXR/K. <bold>c</bold> Typical current traces elicited by applying 10-s pulses of 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M ATP to oocytes expressing the indicated wild-type or mutant P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors. <bold>d</bold> Typical current traces elicited by applying 10-s pulses of 100 &#x3BC;M ATP to oocytes expressing the indicated wild-type or mutant P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. <italic>Gray areas</italic> indicate the duration of ATP application. <bold>e</bold> All the P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors and receptor mutants were expressed efficiently at the cell surface. Intact, healthy oocytes expressing the indicated proteins for 2&#xA0;days were surface-labelled with the membrane impermeant reactive Cy5 dye and then extracted with dodecylmaltoside. Recombinant proteins were isolated by Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelate chromatography and resolved by reducing SDS-PAGE. Shown is a fluorescence scan of an SDS-PAGE gel</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig1_HTML" id="MO1"/></fig></p>
      <p>The aim of this study was to assess biochemically the conditions in which P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors become directly phosphorylated by PKC in a heterologous system. While this work was in progress, a similar study was published for the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor that arrived at essentially the same conclusion, namely that the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor is unlikely to be a direct PKC substrate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Our results complement and extend this finding by demonstrating that the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor also does not serve as a substrate for direct PKC-mediated phosphorylation.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec2" sec-type="materials|methods">
      <title>Materials and methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Materials</title>
        <p>The sources of antibodies, enzymes or peptide substrates are specified at the appropriate places in the text. Chemicals not otherwise specified were purchased in the highest available quality from Sigma-Aldrich (Taufkirchen, Germany) or Merck (Darmstadt, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Peptide-specific antibodies to P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits</title>
        <p>Peptides ATSSTLGLQENMRTS (residues 385-399 of the P2X<sub>1</sub> subunit), QQDSTSTDPKGLAQL (residues 458&#x2013;472 of the P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit) and VEKQSTDSGAYSIGH (residues 383&#x2013;397 of the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit) were selected based on their lack of similarity with known proteins and predicted hydrophilicity for raising polyclonal antibodies against the C-terminal end of the rat subunits P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub>, respectively. Rabbit polyclonal antibodies were ordered through the Custom Antibody Production Services of Eurogentec (Seraing, Belgium). After 3&#xA0;months and a total of four immunizations, rabbits were sacrificed by complete bleeding. Peptide-specific antibodies were purified from the serum by affinity columns coupled with the peptides used for immunization. Immunoblotting showed that the antibodies recognized only the receptor against which they were raised, thus demonstrating isoform specificity of these antibodies (results not shown). The antibodies were aliquoted at 0.12&#x2013;0.16&#xA0;mg/ml in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) containing 0.1% bovine serum albumin (BSA) and 0.01% thimerosal and stored at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>cDNA constructs</title>
        <p>Plasmids encoding wild-type and N-terminal hexahistidine-tagged (His-tagged) versions of rat P2X<sub>1</sub> subunits (rP2X<sub>1</sub>, GenBank accession no. X80477), P2X<sub>2</sub> subunits (rP2X<sub>2</sub>, GenBank accession no. U14414) or rat P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits (rP2X<sub>3</sub>, GenBank accession no. X90651) in the oocyte expression vector pNKS2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] were available from previous studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>]. Insertion and replacement mutations were introduced by QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA, USA). For protein expression in mammalian cells, the receptor cDNAs were subcloned from the oocyte expression vector pNKS2 into pcDNA3.1. The plasmid His-rP2X<sub>2</sub>-EGFP-pcDNA3.1 with a C-terminal enhanced green fluorescent protein (EGFP) fusion was generated by eliminating the stop codon in His-rP2X<sub>2</sub> and adding the coding sequence of EGFP (Clontech, Palo Alto, CA, USA) in frame. All constructs were verified by restriction analysis and nucleotide sequencing. A pEGFP-C1 plasmid harbouring the N-terminally EGFP-tagged splicing factor SF3B1 was kindly provided by our colleague Dr. Walter Becker [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec6">
        <title>P2X receptor expression in <italic>Xenopus laevis</italic> oocytes</title>
        <p>Capped cRNAs were synthesized from plasmids linearized downstream to the 100&#xA0;bp long polyA tail provided by the oocyte expression vector pNKS2 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] and injected at 0.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/&#x3BC;l in 50-nl aliquots into collagenase-defolliculated <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes using a Nanoliter 2000 injector (WPI, Sarasota, FL, USA), as detailed previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. Oocytes were maintained at 19&#xB0;C in sterile oocyte Ringer&#x2019;s solution [ORi: 90&#xA0;mM NaCl, 1&#xA0;mM KCl, 1&#xA0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 1&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub> and 10&#xA0;mM hydroxyethylpiperazine ethanesulfonic acid (HEPES), pH 7.4] supplemented with 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/ml of gentamicin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec7">
        <title>Heterologous expression in HEK293 cells</title>
        <p>cDNAs encoding P2X subunits in pcDNA3.1 vector (Invitrogen, Karlsruhe, Germany) or the splicing factor SF3B1 in EGFP-C1 vector were transiently transfected into HEK293 cells using Lipofectamine LTX (Invitrogen, Karlsruhe, Germany). Cells were cultured at 37&#xB0;C in Dulbecco&#x2019;s modified Eagle&#x2019;s medium (DMEM) (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum (FCS) (PAA Laboratories, Linz, Austria), 100&#xA0;U/ml of penicillin G and 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/ml of streptomycin.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec8">
        <title>Metabolic [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine labelling of oocytes</title>
        <p>For metabolic [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine labelling of oocyte-expressed recombinant proteins, cRNA-injected oocytes and non-injected controls were incubated overnight with <sc>L</sc>-[<sup>35</sup>S]methionine (&gt;40 TBq/mmol; PerkinElmer, Boston, MA, USA) at about 100&#xA0;MBq/ml (0.4&#xA0;MBq per oocyte) in ORi at 19&#xB0;C, and then chased for 24&#xA0;h.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec9">
        <title>Surface fluorescence labelling of oocytes</title>
        <p>Selective fluorescence labelling of plasma membrane-bound P2X receptors was achieved by using the amino-reactive fluorescent Cy5 dye (GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany), which is membrane impermeant due to its two sulfonic acid groups. Two days after cRNA injection, oocytes were washed with oocyte-PBS pH 8.5 (20&#xA0;mM Na phosphate, 110&#xA0;mM NaCl, 1&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>), and then incubated for 30&#xA0;min at ambient temperature with Cy5 dye, which was diluted 200-fold to a final concentration of 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/ml from a dimethyl sulfoxide (DMSO) stock solution. The reaction was terminated by washing the cells with oocyte-PBS, followed by membrane protein extraction with dodecylmaltoside and receptor purification (see below).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec10">
        <title>Isolation of recombinant P2X receptors from <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes or HEK293 cells</title>
        <p>His-tagged receptors were purified by Ni<sup>2+</sup> nitrilotriacetic acid (NTA) agarose (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany) affinity chromatography from non-ionic detergent extracts of oocytes or HEK293 cells in the presence of iodoacetamide essentially as described [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>]. Slight modifications were that buffers were supplemented with ethylenediaminetetraacetate (EDTA)-free Halt&#x2122; protease inhibitor cocktail (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA), 50&#xA0;mM NaF and 50&#xA0;mM Na<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub> for phosphatase inhibition, and that digitonin was replaced by 0.2% and 0.05% dodecylmaltoside for membrane protein extraction and repetitive washing of resin-bound proteins, respectively. Proteins were released from the washed Ni<sup>2+</sup> NTA agarose beads with non-denaturing elution buffer consisting of 250&#xA0;mM imidazole/HCl (pH 7.4) and 0.02% dodecylmaltoside, and then kept at 0&#xB0;C until analysed on the day of purification.</p>
        <p>In addition, immunoprecipitation assays were performed using either cRNA-injected <italic>Xenopus</italic> oocytes or transiently transfected HEK293 cells. Cells were lysed in ice-cold immunoprecipitation lysis buffer containing 150&#xA0;mM NaCl, 25&#xA0;mM Tris/HCl pH 7.4, 20&#xA0;mM NaF, 20&#xA0;mM Na<sub>4</sub>P<sub>2</sub>O<sub>7</sub>, 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;l/ml Halt&#x2122; protease inhibitor cocktail without EDTA (Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA), 1% sodium dodecyl sulfate (SDS) (w/v) and 50&#xA0;mM iodoacetamide. For efficient solubilization, lysates were incubated for 30&#xA0;min on ice with occasional vortexing, and then cleared by centrifugation for 15&#xA0;min at 16,100&#xA0;<italic>g</italic> and 4&#xB0;C. The cleared SDS extract was diluted 1:1 with immunoprecipitation binding buffer [150&#xA0;mM NaCl, 20&#xA0;mM Tris/HCl pH 7.4, 0.4&#xA0;mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), 0.5% Triton X-100&#xA0;v/v and 25&#xA0;mM iodoacetamide], supplemented 1:1,000 with the desired peptide-specific P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> antibodies or a polyclonal goat anti-EGFP antibody (Rockland, Gilbertsville, PA, USA) and incubated for 2&#xA0;h on ice. Immunocomplexes were bound to the protein A Sepharose by overnight head-over-head rotation at 8&#xB0;C, then washed 5 times with immunoprecipitation binding buffer containing 0.1% Triton X-100 and finally eluted by incubating the beads for 15&#xA0;min at 56&#xB0;C in reducing sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (SDS-PAGE) sample buffer.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec11">
        <title>In vitro PKC phosphorylation assay</title>
        <p>In vitro phosphorylation assays were performed by using P2X receptors as substrates, purified as detailed above. In addition, a selective peptide PKC substrate (RRGRTGRGRRGIYR, Calbiochem-Merck, Darmstadt, Germany, final concentration 150&#xA0;&#x3BC;M) corresponding to the amino acid sequence 1487-1500 of the hepatitis C virus polyprotein [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>] was used as a positive control. The proteins or the peptide were incubated for 30&#xA0;min at 30&#xB0;C with 0.02 unit (0.02&#xA0;&#x3BC;g) of purified catalytic PKC subunit from rat brain and 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;M [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (10&#xA0;mCi/ml, Amersham Biosciences GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany) in phosphorylation buffer containing 6&#xA0;mM CaCl<sub>2</sub>, 10&#xA0;mM MgCl<sub>2</sub>, 20&#xA0;mM Tris/HCl pH 7.5, 1&#xA0;mM EDTA, 1&#xA0;mM mercaptoethanol, 0.05% Triton X-100 (v/v) and 0.1&#xA0;mg/ml BSA. The reaction was terminated by boiling in reducing SDS-PAGE sample buffer for 30&#xA0;s. Proteins were resolved by reducing SDS-PAGE and visualized by immunoblotting or phosphorimaging as detailed below.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec12">
        <title>In vivo phosphorylation assay</title>
        <p>Transiently transfected HEK293 cells were metabolically labelled by a 3-h incubation with 500&#xA0;&#x3BC;Ci/ml of [<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate (Amersham Biosciences GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany) in phosphate-free oocyte Ringer solution or in phosphate-free DMEM (Invitrogen, Karlsruhe, Germany) as appropriate. Cells were treated with or without 100&#xA0;nM phorbol 12-myristate 13-acetate (PMA; Sigma-Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) or 100&#xA0;nM calyculin A (Tocris Bioscience, Ellisville, MO, USA) for 10&#xA0;min at ambient temperature. Non-incorporated radioactivity was removed by rinsing the cells twice with tracer-free medium. Affinity purification or immunoprecipitation was performed as described above followed by SDS-PAGE and immunoblotting or phosphorimaging.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec13">
        <title>SDS-PAGE</title>
        <p>Samples for SDS-PAGE were denatured by incubating in reducing SDS-PAGE sample buffer for 15&#xA0;min at 56&#xB0;C and then electrophoresed on a Laemmli SDS-PAGE gel (10% acrylamide) in parallel with [<sup>14</sup>C]-labelled molecular mass markers (Rainbow&#x2122;, Amersham Biosciences GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany). Cy5-labelled proteins were visualized by scanning the wet SDS-PAGE gel with a fluorescence scanner (Typhoon, GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany). For visualization of radiolabelled or non-labelled proteins, SDS-PAGE gels were either fixed, dried and exposed to a PhosphorImager screen, and scanned using a Storm 820 PhosphorImager (Amersham Biosciences GE Healthcare, Freiburg, Germany) or/and blotted to polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) membranes.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec14">
        <title>Immunoblotting</title>
        <p>Proteins separated by SDS-PAGE were electroblotted onto PVDF membranes. Membranes were blocked for 1&#xA0;h with 5% non-fat milk in PBS (or, alternatively, with 5% BSA if the phosphothreonine monoclonal antibody was used for immunoblotting), washed 3&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5&#xA0;min with PBST (0.1% Tween 20 in PBS) and incubated for 2&#xA0;h at 4&#xB0;C in PBS containing the appropriate primary antibody. Phosphorylated proteins were detected by immunoblotting with a phosphothreonine monoclonal antibody (Cell Signaling Technology, Beverly, MA, USA). Alternatively, the peptide-specific antibodies to P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits were used to verify receptor expression levels. Following washing in PBST, an appropriate horseradish peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody (goat anti-mouse or goat anti-rabbit, Pierce, Rockford, IL, USA) was applied for 1&#xA0;h in PBS supplemented with 1% non-fat milk. After another 3&#x2009;&#xD7;&#x2009;5&#xA0;min washes with PBST, immunoreactive bands were visualized by chemiluminescence imaging using a Fujifilm LAS-3000 system (Tokyo, Japan) and the AIDA Image Analyser Software Version 4.08 (Raytest, Straubenhardt, Germany).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec15">
        <title>Two-electrode voltage clamp current recordings and electrical capacitance measurements</title>
        <p>Two-microelectrode voltage clamp measurements of <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes were performed 2&#xA0;days after cRNA injection using a Turbo TEC-05 amplifier (npi electronics, Tamm, Germany) interfaced by an INT-20X AD/DA converter (npi electronics, Tamm, Germany) to a personal computer running the CellWorks Lite 5.1 software (npi electronics, Tamm, Germany), as detailed previously [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>]. Current traces were elicited by 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M ATP at 1- to 5-min intervals (Sigma&#x2013;Aldrich, Taufkirchen, Germany) at a holding potential of &#x2212;60&#xA0;mV in nominally Ca<sup>2+</sup>-free bath medium (designated Mg-ORi) to avoid activation of endogenous Ca<sup>2+</sup>-activated Cl<sup>&#x2212;</sup> channels. ATP was prepared in Mg&#x2212;ORi at its final concentration and applied by gravity-fed perfusion at a flow rate of 10&#xA0;ml/min to an oocyte held by the two microelectrodes in the bath chamber (volume &#x223C;10&#xA0;&#x3BC;l). Switching between different perfusion solutions was achieved with electromagnetic valves controlled by the CellWorks Lite 5.1 software. Electrophysiological recordings were analysed using the Origin 6.0 software (Microcal Software Inc., Northampton, MA, USA). Single exponentials were fitted to the decay phase of the macroscopic currents with a nonlinear least squares method. The time constant &#x3C4; was taken as an estimate of the rate of receptor desensitization.</p>
        <p>To monitor PMA-induced changes in the oocyte surface area, depolarizing voltage steps of &#x394;<italic>V</italic>&#x2009;=&#x2009;<italic>10&#xA0;mV</italic> were applied from the holding potential to elicit a capacitive transient <italic>I</italic><sub>cap</sub>, the integral of which yields the charge movement Q<sub>cap</sub> and thus the membrane capacitance <italic>C</italic><sub>m</sub>&#x2009;=&#x2009;<italic>Q</italic><sub>cap</sub>/&#x394;<italic>V</italic> [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR30">30</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. PMA was dissolved in DMSO to a stock solution of 10&#xA0;mM and stored at &#x2212;20&#xB0;C. On the day of the experiment, the stock solution was pre-diluted to 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M in DMSO and then further diluted with Mg-ORi to the final concentration of 100&#xA0;nM. Vehicle control experiments with a final concentration of 0.1% DMSO did not reveal any effects on P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor-mediated currents measured with <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes (results not shown). All measurements were made at room temperature (21&#x2013;23&#xB0;C).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec16">
        <title>Data analysis</title>
        <p>Data are shown as means&#xB1;SEM. The paired Student&#x2019;s <italic>t</italic>-test (two-tailed) was used to compare current amplitudes with statistical significance set to <italic>p</italic>&#x2009;&lt;&#x2009;0.05.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec17" sec-type="results">
      <title>Results</title>
      <sec id="Sec18">
        <title>Site-directed modification of a putative N-terminal PKC site affects the electrophysiological phenotype of P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor channels</title>
        <p>First, we tested each of the non-mutated and mutant receptor constructs for expression of an ATP-gated inward current in cRNA-injected <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes. Application of 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M ATP induced typical non-desensitizing currents through oocyte-expressed P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c, left current trace). The P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit shares with other P2X subunit isoforms a conserved consensus site for PKC phosphorylation (TXR/K, where T is the phosphorylation site and X denotes any amino acid; see Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>a, b). Disruption of the conserved N-terminal PKC site by mutating the phosphor-acceptor <sup>18</sup>T to A resulted in a rapidly desensitizing channel (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c, middle current trace). Also, replacement of <sup>20</sup>K by T resulted in a desensitizing phenotype (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>c, right current trace). Since PKC preferentially phosphorylates threonine (or serine) residues that are close to a C-terminal basic residue, replacement of <sup>20</sup>K in the P+2 position by a non-basic residue such as T will destroy the putative PKC site despite preserving the phosphor-acceptor <sup>18</sup>T. Virtually identical findings had previously been reported by Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. The average half-times of desensitization (&#x3C4;) of the <sup>18</sup>A and <sup>20</sup>T P2X<sub>2</sub> mutants were quite similar, with mean &#x3C4; values (&#xB1;SEM) of 4.5&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.4&#xA0;s and 7.3&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;0.5&#xA0;s, respectively, of eight oocytes from two females per value.</p>
        <p>ATP applied to oocytes expressing the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor elicited a rapidly desensitizing inward current (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, left current trace) as is typical for this P2X receptor subtype. Incorporation of similar mutations, as in the P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit in the analogous positions of the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor T<sup>12</sup>A or K<sup>14</sup>T, completely abolished P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor function (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>d, middle and right current traces). Visualization of plasma membrane-bound fluorescence-labelled P2X receptors by affinity purification combined with SDS-PAGE and fluorescence scanning verified that all the receptors were efficiently exported to the oocyte surface (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>e).</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec19">
        <title>The PKC activator PMA augments P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor-mediated currents, yet leaves P2X<sub>2</sub>-mediated currents unchanged</title>
        <p>Since the mutagenesis data for the P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor were consistent with the possibility of a regulatory role for PKC in P2X receptor function, we examined whether the PKC activator PMA was capable of affecting the electrophysiological phenotype of P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. In planning the experiments, we considered that PMA treatment of <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes is known to induce a pronounced endocytotic reduction of the cell surface area, as evidenced microscopically and electrophysiologically by the disappearance of virtually all microvilli and a concomitant decrease of the electrical capacitance of the plasma membrane, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR31">31</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR32">32</xref>]. Associated with oocyte surface reduction is a proportional internalization of membrane proteins, such as endogenous Na<sup>+</sup>-K<sup>+</sup> pumps, suggesting that PMA treatment would stimulate internalization of recombinant P2X receptors as well. Re-examination of the time course of the PMA-induced reduction of the oocyte surface area showed that the electrical capacitance did not start to decline significantly before 10&#xA0;min after PMA application (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>a). Accordingly, all current recordings were done within a time window of 10&#xA0;min after PMA application to prevent any contribution of receptor internalization to the PMA effect on P2X receptor-dependent currents.
<fig id="Fig2"><label>Fig.&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Effect of PMA on ATP-induced currents mediated by expressed P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors in <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes. <bold>a</bold> The electrical membrane capacitance was monitored as a measure of the oocyte surface area during sustained stimulation with PMA. Each <italic>bar</italic> represents the mean C<sub>m</sub>&#xB1;SEM calculated from the areas under the current transients elicited in 10-s intervals by five consecutive 10-mV depolarizing steps. <bold>b</bold>, <bold>c</bold> Representative current traces elicited by 10-s lasting pulses of 100&#xA0;&#x3BC;M ATP applied in 10-min intervals to oocytes expressing the indicated P2X receptors or P2X receptor mutants. Where denoted by a <italic>black bar</italic>, oocytes were pre-incubated with 100&#xA0;nM PMA before ATP was co-applied. PMA was without effect on the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor-mediated current (<bold>b</bold>), but induced a marked increase of the current amplitude mediated by P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors (<bold>c</bold>). <italic>Gray areas</italic> indicate the duration of ATP application</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig2_HTML" id="MO2"/></fig></p>
        <p>Figure&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b and c show typical current traces elicited by ATP from P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor-expressing oocytes before and after a 10-min exposure to PMA. PMA neither affected the shape nor the amplitude of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor-mediated current (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>b). However, PMA produced a marked increase of the current amplitude mediated by the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig2" ref-type="fig">2</xref>c). In one experiment with four oocytes, a statistically significant increase of the P2X<sub>3</sub>-mediated current amplitude by PMA of 155&#x2009;&#xB1;&#x2009;42% (SEM) was determined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec20">
        <title>P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors exist in a non-phosphorylated state in both <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells</title>
        <p>To explain the accelerated desensitization upon site-directed perturbation of the <sup>18</sup>TXK<sup>20</sup> motif, it has been suggested that the wild-type P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor is constitutively phosphorylated at <sup>18</sup>T and that this phosphorylation is responsible for the slow desensitization rate [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. To address this issue, we next examined biochemically whether P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors also exist in a constitutively phosphorylated state; the P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor was also analysed to allow for a direct comparison of the results. Both parent P2X receptors and mutants were purified by Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelate affinity chromatography from dodecylmaltoside extracts of [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine-labelled oocytes, resolved by SDS-PAGE, and blotted onto a PVDF membrane. However, probing with a phosphothreonine-specific monoclonal antibody revealed no discernible signal (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>a) despite the presence of significant amounts of [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine-labelled P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> protein in the SDS-PAGE gel (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>b).
<fig id="Fig3"><label>Fig.&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>Immunoblots show no constitutive phosphorylation of oocyte-expressed P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. The indicated wild-type or mutant P2X subunits were purified by Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelate chromatography from [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine-labelled <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and resolved by denaturing SDS-PAGE. <bold>a</bold> Shown is a representative immunoblot probed with a phosphothreonine-specific monoclonal antibody and a peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody. No phosphorylation signal could be detected at the SDS-PAGE migration position of P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits, which are indicated by the adjacent PhosphorImager scan in panel b. <bold>b</bold> Direct PhosphorImager visualization of metabolically [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine-labelled parent and mutant P2X subunits resolved by SDS-PAGE of the same samples as in panel a. <bold>c</bold><italic>Left panel</italic>: representative immunoblot of P2X<sub>2</sub> subunits tagged with either an N-terminal or C-terminal hexahistidine sequence (designated His-P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>2</sub>-His, respectively) and probed with a phosphothreonine-specific monoclonal antibody and a peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody. No phosphorylation signal could be detected at the SDS-PAGE migration position of P2X<sub>2</sub> subunits, which were visualized by immunoblotting with the P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit polyclonal antibody (<italic>middle panel</italic>) or PhosphorImager scanning of incorporated [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine (<italic>right panel</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig3_HTML" id="MO3"/></fig></p>
        <p>To exclude the possibility that the apparent lack of receptor phosphorylation resulted from an interference between the N-terminal His tag and the PKC site of P2X<sub>3</sub> or P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor subunits, which are separated by only 12 or 20 residues, respectively, we performed analogous experiments with a C-terminally His-tagged P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor, P2X<sub>2</sub>-His. As apparent from Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, neither N-terminally nor C-terminally His-tagged P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor became phosphorylated, as evidenced by immunoblotting with a phosphor-specific anti-threonine antibody (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c). The presence of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor protein was verified by immunoblotting and metabolic labelling with [<sup>35</sup>S]methionine (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig3" ref-type="fig">3</xref>c, middle and right panel).</p>
        <p>Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>] have demonstrated phosphorylation of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors expressed in HEK293 cells. To address the possibility that P2X receptor phosphorylation is host cell specific, we analysed HEK293 cells transiently transfected with P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> expression plasmids. P2X receptor proteins were isolated by immunoprecipitation and resolved by reducing SDS-PAGE. The efficient expression of the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor or the C-terminally EGFP-tagged P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor in HEK293 cells was verified by immunoblotting with subunit bands migrating at 54&#xA0;kDa or 83&#xA0;kDa (27&#xA0;kDa contributed to the P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit by the EGFP tag), respectively (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>b). However, phosphorylated P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits could not be detected by immunoblotting with a phosphothreonine-specific antibody (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a). In contrast, the PKC-phosphorylated splicing factor SF3B1, which was expressed in HEK293 cells as a positive control substrate and immunoprecipitated with an EGFP antibody, was efficiently phosphorylated under identical conditions, assuring that the assay was able to detect phosphorylated proteins (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig4" ref-type="fig">4</xref>a, lane 1). Taken together, these results suggest that both P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors exist constitutively in a non-phosphorylated state in both <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells.
<fig id="Fig4"><label>Fig.&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Immunoblotting reveals no constitutive phosphorylation of HEK293 cell-expressed P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. The indicated proteins were isolated by immunoprecipitation using the peptide-specific P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit polyclonal antibody or an EGFP-specific polyclonal antibody as appropriate and resolved by reducing SDS-PAGE. <bold>a</bold> Shown is an immunoblot probed by phosphothreonine-specific monoclonal antibody and a peroxidase-conjugated secondary antibody. Note that phosphorylation of the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor or the EGFP-tagged P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor is not detectable, whereas a positive control&#x2014;the EGFP-tagged splicing factor SF3B1 (migration mass 97&#xA0;kDa [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>])&#x2014;was detected by the antibody. <bold>b</bold> The same samples as in panel a were immunoblotted using peptide-specific P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit polyclonal antibodies to verify the expression of the transfected genes</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig4_HTML" id="MO4"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec21">
        <title>PMA-activated PKC does not drive the phosphorylation of P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors</title>
        <p>A majority of protein kinases are quiescent unless their activity is stimulated by specific stimuli and effectors. To drive phosphorylation by active endogenous PKC, we incubated non-denatured recombinant His-tagged P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors isolated by Ni<sup>2+</sup> NTA agarose affinity chromatography from dodecylmaltoside extracts of <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes with PMA-stimulated lysates of <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a) or HEK293 cells (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>b) in the presence of [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP. As a positive control, a specific peptide PKC substrate RRGRTGRGRRGIYR was incubated with the lysates. This peptide was equally well phosphorylated by addition of either cell lysate or a commercial preparation of the rat brain PKC subunit (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>a, b). In contrast, however, no <sup>32</sup>P incorporation could be detected in the SDS-PAGE migration position of the P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>3</sub> or P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor subunit at 56&#xA0;kDa, 54&#xA0;kDa or 66&#xA0;kDa, respectively. The presence of purified P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor subunit protein in this assay was verified by immunoblotting using P2X<sub>1</sub>-, P2X<sub>2</sub>- or P2X<sub>3</sub>-specific antibodies (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig5" ref-type="fig">5</xref>c). The phosphorylation of the synthetic peptide clearly demonstrates that both <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells contain sufficient endogenous PKC to drive at least the phosphorylation of a synthetic peptide substrate.
<fig id="Fig5"><label>Fig.&#xA0;5</label><caption><p>Lysates of <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes or HEK293 cells contain endogenous PKC, but do not support PMA-driven phosphorylation of P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. The indicated wild-type and mutant P2X receptors were purified by non-denaturing Ni<sup>2+</sup> chelate chromatography from <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes, supplemented with [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP, 100&#xA0;nM PMA and oocyte lysate (<bold>a</bold>) or HEK293 cell lysate (<bold>b</bold>), and incubated for 30&#xA0;min at ambient temperature. In parallel, a peptide PKC substrate (final concentration 0.5&#xA0;&#x3BC;g/&#x3BC;l) was incubated with [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP, PMA and either of the two cell lysates or the purified rat brain PKC catalytic subunit as indicated. The proteins were resolved by reducing SDS-PAGE and visualized by phosphorimaging. Note that the band pattern was similar irrespective of whether protein of mock-injected oocytes or P2X receptor-expressing oocytes was used as a substrate, arguing against specific labelling of either P2X receptor. <italic>Arrows</italic> indicate migration positions of P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits. <italic>Arrowhead</italic> in a, dominant background band that is present in all oocyte samples. The peptide PKC substrate was similarly labelled by lysates or purified rat brain PKC, confirming the presence of endogenous PKC in <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells. <bold>c</bold> The same samples as in panels a and b were resolved on a separate SDS-PAGE gel. The indicated P2X subunits were detected by immunoblotting using the appropriate P2X subunit-specific polyclonal antibodies. A sample of mock-transfected cells was simultaneously probed with the P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit-specific polyclonal antibodies</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig5_HTML" id="MO5"/></fig></p>
        <p>Discernible phosphorylation of P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors might be obscured by a low level of endogenous PKC. Therefore, an analogous experiment was performed, in which the purified P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors were incubated with purified rat brain PKC catalytic subunit rather than cell lysate in the presence of [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP. Again, the specific peptide PKC substrate was efficiently phosphorylated as demonstrated both by direct phosphorimaging (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a) and immunoblotting with the phosphothreonine monoclonal antibody (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>b). Phosphorylated P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> subunits could not be detected by either method (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>a, b) despite the presence of abundant amounts of the respective P2X subunits in the assays (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig6" ref-type="fig">6</xref>c).
<fig id="Fig6"><label>Fig.&#xA0;6</label><caption><p>PKC phosphorylates a specific PKC substrate in vitro, but does not phosphorylate P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors. The immunoprecipitated recombinant P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor from <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes or a synthetic peptide (1 or 10&#xA0;&#x3BC;g) derived from the non-structural protein 3 of hepatitis C virus, which serves as a specific substrate for PKC, were incubated for 30&#xA0;min with purified rat brain PKC catalytic subunit (0.02&#xA0;&#x3BC;g corresponding to 0.02&#xA0;U/&#x3BC;l) in the presence of 50&#xA0;&#x3BC;M [&#x3B3;-<sup>32</sup>P]ATP (10&#xA0;mCi/ml), and then subjected to SDS-PAGE and phosphorimaging. The rat brain PKC catalytic subunit does not require Ca<sup>2+</sup> and phosphatidylserine for activity [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR42">42</xref>]. <sup>32</sup>P was incorporated into the PKC substrate (<italic>left panel</italic>) and was also detected by immunoblotting with an anti-phosphothreonine antibody (<italic>middle panel</italic>). However, there was no detectable <sup>32</sup>P incorporation at a migration position of &#x223C;66&#xA0;kDa or &#x223C;54&#xA0;kDa of the P2X<sub>2</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit, respectively, the presence of which could be verified by immunoblotting (<italic>right panel</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig6_HTML" id="MO6"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec22">
        <title>PMA or calyculin A do not enhance phosphorylation of P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors in intact HEK cells</title>
        <p>In a final set of experiments, we attempted to directly demonstrate phosphorylation in vivo by using metabolic [<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate labelling combined with immunoprecipitation analysis as a read out. Mock-transfected and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor-transfected HEK293 cells were incubated with [<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate in phosphate-free DMEM, followed by incubation with the PKC activator PMA and/or the phosphoserine/phosphothreonine phosphatase inhibitor calyculin A. The PhosphorImager scan revealed an identical pattern of phosphorylated bands almost irrespective of the experimental conditions, with no evidence for a significant <sup>32</sup>P-labelling of the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, top panel). P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor expression was verified by immunoblotting (Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig7" ref-type="fig">7</xref>, bottom panel).
<fig id="Fig7"><label>Fig.&#xA0;7</label><caption><p>PMA and calyculin A do not induce phosphorylation of P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors in intact HEK cells. Mock- and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor-transfected HEK293 cells were incubated with [<sup>32</sup>P]orthophosphate (500&#xA0;&#x3BC;Ci/ml) for 3&#xA0;h in phosphate-free DMEM, followed by a 10-min incubation with 100&#xA0;nM of each, the PKC activator PMA and/or the phosphatase inhibitor calyculin A. Triton X-100 extracts were then prepared from the cells and subjected to immunoprecipitation using the peptide-specific P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit polyclonal antibody, followed by reducing SDS-PAGE and phosphorimaging. The migration position of the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit is marked by an <italic>arrow</italic>, indicating the absence of <sup>32</sup>P incorporation into the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit. P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor expression was verified by immunoblotting with the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit polyclonal antibody (<italic>bottom panel</italic>)</p></caption><graphic position="anchor" xlink:href="11302_2007_9067_Fig7_HTML" id="MO7"/></fig></p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec23" sec-type="discussion">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Both P2X<sub>3</sub> and P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptors are present on sensory neurons, where they play an important role in nociception. In addition to mediating transient nociceptive responses, these receptors contribute critically to the hyperexcitability that underlies abnormal pain states elicited by nerve injuries. One mechanism for the increased responsiveness to ATP is sensitization of P2X<sub>3</sub> and P2X<sub>2+3</sub> receptors arising from a significant enhancement in the trafficking of P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit-containing receptors and/or an increase in function of pre-existing receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>]. An obvious candidate mechanism for functional modulation is phosphorylation, which is believed to occur universally in all ligand-gated ion channels as reviewed by Levitan [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR33">33</xref>].</p>
      <sec id="Sec24">
        <title>Evidence for a control of P2X receptor channel function by PKC-mediated phosphorylation</title>
        <p>Site-directed elimination of the putative N-terminal PKC site has already previously been shown to severely affect the electrophysiological phenotype of several P2X receptor subtypes, including P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors from rat and/or human [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and P2X<sub>5</sub> receptors from frog [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Replacing the putative phospho-acceptor residue <sup>18</sup>T or the basic residue in the P+2 position (<sup>20</sup>K) by A or a non-basic residue, respectively, imposed rapidly desensitizing properties onto the non-desensitizing wt P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor without grossly affecting the current amplitude. In contrast, when analogous mutations were introduced into the rapidly desensitizing receptor subtypes P2X<sub>1</sub> or P2X<sub>3</sub>, peak currents declined to low or undetectable levels, respectively [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref> ,<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]; the same observation was also made with the slower desensitizing frog P2X<sub>5</sub> receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR35">35</xref>]. Overall, the results obtained by site-directed elimination of the N-terminal TXR/K motif can be plausibly reconciled with the hypothesis that the rate of P2X receptor channel desensitization is controlled by a phosphorylation-dephosphorylation mechanism, with phosphorylation at this site being associated with a decreased rate of desensitization.</p>
        <p>Additional evidence for a possible involvement of PKC-dependent phosphorylation comes from experiments with the PKC activator PMA, which was consistently found to elicit a severalfold increase in currents mediated by the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>] or the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>] without changing the rate of desensitization. A PMA-induced change of the current desensitization was noted for C-terminally truncated P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors, which are known to exhibit a desensitizing phenotype in contrast to the parent full-length P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR37">37</xref>]. PMA treatment converted the rapidly desensitizing phenotype of truncated P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors to slowly desensitizing, but did not affect the kinetic properties or current amplitudes of the full-length P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors. The same lack of effect of PMA has been observed with wild-type P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors stably expressed in HEK293 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR38">38</xref>]. It has been inferred from these data that P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors are constitutively phosphorylated and that this phosphorylation is responsible for their non-desensitizing phenotype. Consistent with this view, immunoblot analysis with a phosphothreonine-proline-specific monoclonal antibody efficiently detected wild-type P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors with an intact PKC site, but not P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor mutants with a disrupted PKC site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>]. Constitutive phosphorylation has been also demonstrated for the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor expressed in HEK293 cells [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>]. Further studies demonstrated that exogenously added uridine triphosphate (UTP) potentiated the current mediated by endogenous and expressed P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors in response to &#x3B1;&#x3B2;-meATP as agonist. Substitution of phospho-acceptor residues of PKC consensus sites located in the ectodomain of the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor abolished this UTP-induced current potentiation, suggesting a role of ecto-protein kinase C in P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor regulation [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR39">39</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR40">40</xref>].</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec25">
        <title>Evidence against a control of P2X receptor channel function by PKC-mediated phosphorylation</title>
        <p>In direct contrast to the results of Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], we were unable to demonstrate a direct phosphorylation of wild-type P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors expressed in <italic>X. laevis</italic> oocytes and HEK293 cells. The various experimental approaches for phosphorylation detection that we applied included immunoblot analysis of purified P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors. In the experiments shown, we used a phosphothreonine-specific monoclonal antibody instead of a phosphothreonine-proline-specific antibody, because the TXK motif of the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor contains a threonine in the -X-position instead of the proline found in the amino acid sequence of the P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>2</sub> subunit (cf. Fig.&#xA0;<xref rid="Fig1" ref-type="fig">1</xref>b). However, even when we used the same phosphothreonine-proline-specific antibody as Boue-Grabot et al. [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR19">19</xref>], we could not demonstrate phosphorylation of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors in our experiments (data not shown).</p>
        <p>Recently, it has been shown that a proline in the P+1 position strongly disfavours substrate recognition by PKC [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR41">41</xref>], suggesting that our negative results with P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors may not result from technical limitations, but reflect the inherent inability of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors to serve as substrates for PKC. Notably, P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors, despite harbouring a T in the P+1 position, could also not be demonstrated to become phosphorylated by PKC in our experiments, as well as in a recently published paper [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. Further evidence against a direct PKC-mediated P2X receptor phosphorylation comes from co-expression studies of P2X<sub>1</sub> and G protein-coupled receptors. Co-expression of the metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR1&#x3B1; with P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors produced a 2.5-fold increase of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor-mediated current that was blocked by the PKC inhibitor staurosporine and could be mimicked by PMA treatment of singly expressed P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors. Although the pharmacological data are basically consistent with PKC-mediated receptor phosphorylation being involved, mutant P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors with a disrupted N-terminal PKC site (T<sup>18</sup>V) still showed PMA-mediated and mGluR1&#x3B1;-mediated potentiation. Also, PMA treatment did not lead to an increase in the (rather weak) basal phosphorylation of the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>].</p>
        <p>Functional data supporting a role of PKC in P2X receptor regulation have been detailed above. There are, however, also functional data that are inconsistent with the view that the TXR/K motif represents a true PKC site: (1) replacement of the phospho-acceptor threonine by an acidic residue to mimic incorporation of a negatively charged phosphate group by constitutive phosphorylation was unable to restore the function of P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR34">34</xref>] and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>]; (2) the PMA-induced potentiation of hP2X<sub>1</sub> receptor currents could be blocked by the PKC inhibitor staurosporine, but surprisingly, not by site-directed elimination of the PKC site [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR36">36</xref>]; thus it is much more likely that PMA exerts its effect on the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor (and the P2X<sub>3</sub> receptor) through a yet to be identified accessory protein.</p>
        <p>Taken together, there is no doubt that the TXR/K motif plays an important role in the functioning of P2X receptors, and that PMA is capable of modulating P2X<sub>1</sub>- and P2X<sub>3</sub>-mediated receptor currents. The underlying mechanism, however, is unlikely to involve direct PKC-mediated phosphorylation of P2X receptors. The existence of a proline in the P+1 position in several P2X subunit isoforms (P2X<sub>1</sub>, P2X<sub>2</sub>, P2X<sub>4</sub>) might be one causative factor preventing direct phosphorylation by PKC. Additional steric constraints may explain why P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors also do not serve as PKC substrates, despite lacking the proline in P+1. The exact role of the TXR/K motif awaits further clarification.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgement</title>
      <p>We gratefully acknowledge helpful discussions with our colleague Dr. Walter Becker and his gift of the EGFP-tagged SF3B1 splicing factor plasmid. This research project was supported by the START-Program of the Faculty of Medicine, RWTH Aachen University to R.H. and a grant of the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (FOR450, TP 11) to G.S.</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burnstock</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Introduction: P2 receptors</article-title>
          <source>Curr Top Med Chem</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>793</fpage>
          <lpage>803</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.2174/1568026043451014</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Burnstock G (2004) Introduction: P2 receptors. Curr Top Med Chem 4:793&#x2013;803 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15078211</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>North</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Molecular physiology of P2X receptors</article-title>
          <source>Physiol Rev</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>82</volume>
          <fpage>1013</fpage>
          <lpage>1067</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">North RA (2002) Molecular physiology of P2X receptors. Physiol Rev 82:1013&#x2013;1067 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12270951</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Aschrafi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sadtler</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Niculescu</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Trimeric architecture of homomeric P2X<sub>2</sub> and heteromeric P2X1+2 receptor subtypes</article-title>
          <source>J Mol Biol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>342</volume>
          <fpage>333</fpage>
          <lpage>343</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.jmb.2004.06.092</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Aschrafi A, Sadtler S, Niculescu C et al (2004) Trimeric architecture of homomeric P2X2 and heteromeric P2X1+2 receptor subtypes. J Mol Biol 342:333&#x2013;343 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15313628</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Barrera</surname>
              <given-names>NP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ormond</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Henderson</surname>
              <given-names>RM</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Atomic force microscopy imaging demonstrates that P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors are trimers but that P2X<sub>6</sub> receptor subunits do not oligomerize</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>280</volume>
          <fpage>10759</fpage>
          <lpage>10765</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M412265200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Barrera NP, Ormond SJ, Henderson RM et al (2005) Atomic force microscopy imaging demonstrates that P2X2 receptors are trimers but that P2X6 receptor subunits do not oligomerize. J Biol Chem 280:10759&#x2013;10765 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15657042</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jiang</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kim</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Spelta</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Subunit arrangement in P2X receptors</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>23</volume>
          <fpage>8903</fpage>
          <lpage>8910</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jiang LH, Kim M, Spelta V et al (2003) Subunit arrangement in P2X receptors. J Neurosci 23:8903&#x2013;8910 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14523092</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Khakh</surname>
              <given-names>BS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burnstock</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>International union of pharmacology. XXIV. Current status of the nomenclature and properties of P2X receptors and their subunits</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacol Rev</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>107</fpage>
          <lpage>118</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Khakh BS, Burnstock G, Kennedy C et al (2001) International union of pharmacology. XXIV. Current status of the nomenclature and properties of P2X receptors and their subunits. Pharmacol Rev 53:107&#x2013;118 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11171941</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mio</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kubo</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ogura</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Visualization of the trimeric P2X<sub>2</sub> receptor with a crown-capped extracellular domain</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>337</volume>
          <fpage>998</fpage>
          <lpage>1005</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbrc.2005.09.141</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mio K, Kubo Y, Ogura T et al (2005) Visualization of the trimeric P2X2 receptor with a crown-capped extracellular domain. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 337:998&#x2013;1005 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16219297</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Nicke</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>B&#xE4;umert</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rettinger</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>1</sub> and P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors form stable trimers: a novel structural motif of ligand-gated ion channels</article-title>
          <source>EMBO J</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>17</volume>
          <fpage>3016</fpage>
          <lpage>3028</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1093/emboj/17.11.3016</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Nicke A, B&#xE4;umert HG, Rettinger J et al (1998) P2X1 and P2X3 receptors form stable trimers: a novel structural motif of ligand-gated ion channels. EMBO J 17:3016&#x2013;3028 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9606184</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gever</surname>
              <given-names>JR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cockayne</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dillon</surname>
              <given-names>MP</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Pharmacology of P2X channels</article-title>
          <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>452</volume>
          <fpage>513</fpage>
          <lpage>537</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00424-006-0070-9</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gever JR, Cockayne DA, Dillon MP et al (2006) Pharmacology of P2X channels. Pflugers Arch 452:513&#x2013;537 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16649055</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Burnstock</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Purinergic P2 receptors as targets for novel analgesics</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacol Ther</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>110</volume>
          <fpage>433</fpage>
          <lpage>454</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pharmthera.2005.08.013</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Burnstock G (2005) Purinergic P2 receptors as targets for novel analgesics. Pharmacol Ther 110:433&#x2013;454 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16226312</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chizh</surname>
              <given-names>BA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Illes</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X receptors and nociception</article-title>
          <source>Pharmacol Rev</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>553</fpage>
          <lpage>568</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chizh BA, Illes P (2001) P2X receptors and nociception. Pharmacol Rev 53:553&#x2013;568 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11734618</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jarvis</surname>
              <given-names>MF</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>;Contributions of P2X<sub>3</sub> homomeric and heteromeric channels to acute and chronic pain</article-title>
          <source>Expert Opin Ther Targets</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>513</fpage>
          <lpage>522</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1517/14728222.7.4.513</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jarvis MF (2003) Contributions of P2X3 homomeric and heteromeric channels to acute and chronic pain. Expert Opin Ther Targets 7:513&#x2013;522 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12885270</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kennedy</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Assis</surname>
              <given-names>TS</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Currie</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crossing the pain barrier: P2 receptors as targets for novel analgesics</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>553</volume>
          <fpage>683</fpage>
          <lpage>694</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2003.049114</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kennedy C, Assis TS, Currie AJ et al (2003) Crossing the pain barrier: P2 receptors as targets for novel analgesics. J Physiol 553:683&#x2013;694 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14514872</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>North</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors and peripheral pain mechanisms</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>554</volume>
          <fpage>301</fpage>
          <lpage>308</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1113/jphysiol.2003.048587</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">North RA (2004) P2X3 receptors and peripheral pain mechanisms. J Physiol 554:301&#x2013;308 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12832496</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>North</surname>
              <given-names>RA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit: a molecular target in pain therapeutics</article-title>
          <source>Curr Opin Investig Drugs</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>833</fpage>
          <lpage>840</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">North RA (2003) The P2X3 subunit: a molecular target in pain therapeutics. Curr Opin Investig Drugs 4:833&#x2013;840 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14619405</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paukert</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Osteroth</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Geisler</surname>
              <given-names>HS</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Inflammatory mediators potentiate ATP-gated channels through the P2X<sub>3</sub> subunit</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>21077</fpage>
          <lpage>21082</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M101465200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Paukert M, Osteroth R, Geisler HS et al (2001) Inflammatory mediators potentiate ATP-gated channels through the P2X3 subunit. J Biol Chem 276:21077&#x2013;21082 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11264291</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chen</surname>
              <given-names>Y</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Li</surname>
              <given-names>GW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mechanisms underlying enhanced P2X receptor-mediated responses in the neuropathic pain state</article-title>
          <source>Pain</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>119</volume>
          <fpage>38</fpage>
          <lpage>48</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.pain.2005.09.007</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chen Y, Li GW, Wang C et al (2005) Mechanisms underlying enhanced P2X receptor-mediated responses in the neuropathic pain state. Pain 119:38&#x2013;48 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16298067</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Fabbretti</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>D&#x2019;Arco</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fabbro</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Delayed upregulation of ATP P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors of trigeminal sensory neurons by calcitonin gene-related peptide</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>26</volume>
          <fpage>6163</fpage>
          <lpage>6171</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0647-06.2006</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Fabbretti E, D&#x2019;Arco M, Fabbro A et al (2006) Delayed upregulation of ATP P2X3 receptors of trigeminal sensory neurons by calcitonin gene-related peptide. J Neurosci 26:6163&#x2013;6171 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16763024</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Boue-Grabot</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Archambault</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Seguela</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A protein kinase C site highly conserved in P2X subunits controls the desensitization kinetics of P2X<sub>2</sub> ATP-gated channels</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>275</volume>
          <fpage>10190</fpage>
          <lpage>10195</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.275.14.10190</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Boue-Grabot E, Archambault V, Seguela P (2000) A protein kinase C site highly conserved in P2X subunits controls the desensitization kinetics of P2X2 ATP-gated channels. J Biol Chem 275:10190&#x2013;10195 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10744703</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Ennion</surname>
              <given-names>SJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor subunit contribution to gating revealed by a dominant negative PKC mutant</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>291</volume>
          <fpage>611</fpage>
          <lpage>616</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1006/bbrc.2002.6488</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Ennion SJ, Evans RJ (2002) P2X1 receptor subunit contribution to gating revealed by a dominant negative PKC mutant. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 291:611&#x2013;616 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11855833</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Brown</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yule</surname>
              <given-names>DI</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Protein kinase C regulation of P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors is unlikely to involve direct receptor phosphorylation</article-title>
          <source>Biochim Biophys Acta</source>
          <year>2007</year>
          <volume>1773</volume>
          <fpage>166</fpage>
          <lpage>175</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.bbamcr.2006.09.020</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Brown DA, Yule DI (2007) Protein kinase C regulation of P2X3 receptors is unlikely to involve direct receptor phosphorylation. Biochim Biophys Acta 1773:166&#x2013;175 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17052768</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Gloor</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pongs</surname>
              <given-names>O</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A vector for the synthesis of cRNAs encoding Myc epitope-tagged proteins in Xenopus laevis oocytes</article-title>
          <source>Gene</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>160</volume>
          <fpage>213</fpage>
          <lpage>217</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/0378-1119(95)00226-V</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Gloor S, Pongs O, Schmalzing G (1995) A vector for the synthesis of cRNAs encoding Myc epitope-tagged proteins in Xenopus laevis oocytes. Gene 160:213&#x2013;217 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7543868</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>de Graaf</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Czajkowska</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rottmann</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The protein kinase DYRK1A phosphorylates the splicing factor SF3b1/SAP155 at Thr434, a novel in vivo phosphorylation site</article-title>
          <source>BMC Biochem</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>7</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1186/1471-2091-7-7</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">de Graaf K, Czajkowska H, Rottmann S et al (2006) The protein kinase DYRK1A phosphorylates the splicing factor SF3b1/SAP155 at Thr434, a novel in vivo phosphorylation site. BMC Biochem 7:7 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16512921</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gloor</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Omay</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Up-regulation of sodium pump activity in Xenopus laevis oocytes by expression of heterologous &#x3B2;1 subunits of the sodium pump</article-title>
          <source>Biochem J</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <fpage>329</fpage>
          <lpage>336</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmalzing G, Gloor S, Omay H et al (1991) Up-regulation of sodium pump activity in Xenopus laevis oocytes by expression of heterologous &#x3B2;1 subunits of the sodium pump. Biochem J 279:329&#x2013;336 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1719955</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Duckwitz</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hausmann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Aschrafi</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>5</sub> subunit assembly requires scaffolding by the second transmembrane domain and a conserved aspartate</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>281</volume>
          <fpage>39561</fpage>
          <lpage>39572</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M606113200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Duckwitz W, Hausmann R, Aschrafi A et al (2006) P2X5 subunit assembly requires scaffolding by the second transmembrane domain and a conserved aspartate. J Biol Chem 281:39561&#x2013;39572 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">17001079</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Borowski</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Resch</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmitz</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>A synthetic peptide derived from the non-structural protein 3 of hepatitis C virus serves as a specific substrate for PKC</article-title>
          <source>Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>381</volume>
          <fpage>19</fpage>
          <lpage>27</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1515/BC.2000.003</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Borowski P, Resch K, Schmitz H et al (2000) A synthetic peptide derived from the non-structural protein 3 of hepatitis C virus serves as a specific substrate for PKC. Biol Chem 381:19&#x2013;27 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10722046</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rettinger</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Activation and desensitization of the recombinant P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor at nanomolar ATP concentrations</article-title>
          <source>J Gen Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>121</volume>
          <fpage>451</fpage>
          <lpage>461</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1085/jgp.200208730</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rettinger J, Schmalzing G (2003) Activation and desensitization of the recombinant P2X1 receptor at nanomolar ATP concentrations. J Gen Physiol 121:451&#x2013;461 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12719485</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Rettinger</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Desensitization masks nanomolar potency of ATP at the P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>279</volume>
          <fpage>6426</fpage>
          <lpage>6433</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M306987200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Rettinger J, Schmalzing G (2004) Desensitization masks nanomolar potency of ATP at the P2X1 receptor. J Biol Chem 279:6426&#x2013;6433 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14625300</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hausmann</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rettinger</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerevich</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The suramin analog 4,4prime,4&#x2033;,4&#x2032;&#x2032;&#x2032;-(carbonylbis(imino-5,1,3-benzenetriylbis (carbonylimino)))tetra-kis-benzenesulfonic acid (NF110) potently blocks P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors: subtype selectivity is determined by location of sulfonic acid groups</article-title>
          <source>Mol Pharmacol</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>69</volume>
          <fpage>2058</fpage>
          <lpage>2067</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1124/mol.106.022665</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hausmann R, Rettinger J, Gerevich Z et al (2006) The suramin analog 4,4&#x2032;,4&#x2033;,4&#x2032;&#x2032;&#x2032;-(carbonylbis(imino-5,1,3-benzenetriylbis (carbonylimino)))tetra-kis-benzenesulfonic acid (NF110) potently blocks P2X3 receptors: subtype selectivity is determined by location of sulfonic acid groups. Mol Pharmacol 69:2058&#x2013;2067 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16551782</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR30">
        <label>30.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Adrian</surname>
              <given-names>RH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almers</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Membrane capacity measurements on frog skeletal muscle in media of low ion content</article-title>
          <source>J Physiol</source>
          <year>1974</year>
          <volume>237</volume>
          <fpage>573</fpage>
          <lpage>605</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Adrian RH, Almers W (1974) Membrane capacity measurements on frog skeletal muscle in media of low ion content. J Physiol 237:573&#x2013;605 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">4545185</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR31">
        <label>31.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vasilets</surname>
              <given-names>LA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>M&#xE4;defessel</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Activation of protein kinase C by phorbol ester induces downregulation of the Na+/K+-ATPase in oocytes of Xenopus laevis</article-title>
          <source>J Membr Biol</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <volume>118</volume>
          <fpage>131</fpage>
          <lpage>142</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/BF01868470</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vasilets LA, Schmalzing G, M&#xE4;defessel K et al (1990) Activation of protein kinase C by phorbol ester induces downregulation of the Na+/K+-ATPase in oocytes of Xenopus laevis. J Membr Biol 118:131&#x2013;142 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2176238</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR32">
        <label>32.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Schmalzing</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Richter</surname>
              <given-names>H-P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hansen</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Involvement of the GTP binding protein Rho in constitutive endocytosis in Xenopus laevis oocytes</article-title>
          <source>J Cell Biol</source>
          <year>1995</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>1319</fpage>
          <lpage>1332</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1083/jcb.130.6.1319</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Schmalzing G, Richter H-P, Hansen A et al (1995) Involvement of the GTP binding protein Rho in constitutive endocytosis in Xenopus laevis oocytes. J Cell Biol 130:1319&#x2013;1332 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">7559755</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR33">
        <label>33.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Levitan</surname>
              <given-names>IB</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Modulation of ion channels by protein phosphorylation. How the brain works</article-title>
          <source>Adv Second Messenger Phosphoprotein Res</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>33</volume>
          <fpage>3</fpage>
          <lpage>22</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Levitan IB (1999) Modulation of ion channels by protein phosphorylation. How the brain works. Adv Second Messenger Phosphoprotein Res 33:3&#x2013;22 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10218112</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR34">
        <label>34.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brockhausen</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bennett</surname>
              <given-names>MR</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>P2X<sub>1</sub> receptor currents after disruption of the PKC site and its surroundings by dominant negative mutations in HEK293 cells</article-title>
          <source>Auton Neurosci</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>108</volume>
          <fpage>12</fpage>
          <lpage>16</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S1566-0702(03)00154-1</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Liu GJ, Brockhausen J, Bennett MR (2003) P2X1 receptor currents after disruption of the PKC site and its surroundings by dominant negative mutations in HEK293 cells. Auton Neurosci 108:12&#x2013;16 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">14614959</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR35">
        <label>35.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Jensik</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cox</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>ATP-induced internalization of amphibian epithelial P2X receptors is linked to channel opening</article-title>
          <source>Pflugers Arch</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>444</volume>
          <fpage>795</fpage>
          <lpage>800</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00424-002-0881-2</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Jensik P, Cox T (2002) ATP-induced internalization of amphibian epithelial P2X receptors is linked to channel opening. Pflugers Arch 444:795&#x2013;800 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12355180</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR36">
        <label>36.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vial</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Tobin</surname>
              <given-names>AB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Evans</surname>
              <given-names>RJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>G-protein-coupled receptor regulation of P2X<sub>1</sub> receptors does not involve direct channel phosphorylation</article-title>
          <source>Biochem J</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>382</volume>
          <fpage>101</fpage>
          <lpage>110</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1042/BJ20031910</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vial C, Tobin AB, Evans RJ (2004) G-protein-coupled receptor regulation of P2X1 receptors does not involve direct channel phosphorylation. Biochem J 382:101&#x2013;110 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15144237</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR37">
        <label>37.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>He</surname>
              <given-names>ML</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zemkova</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koshimizu</surname>
              <given-names>TA</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Intracellular calcium measurements as a method in studies on activity of purinergic P2X receptor channels</article-title>
          <source>Am J Physiol Cell Physiol</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>285</volume>
          <fpage>C467</fpage>
          <lpage>C479</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">He ML, Zemkova H, Koshimizu TA et al (2003) Intracellular calcium measurements as a method in studies on activity of purinergic P2X receptor channels. Am J Physiol Cell Physiol 285:C467&#x2013;C479 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12711592</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR38">
        <label>38.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Chow</surname>
              <given-names>YW</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>HL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Functional modulation of P2X<sub>2</sub> receptors by cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase</article-title>
          <source>J Neurochem</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>70</volume>
          <fpage>2606</fpage>
          <lpage>2612</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Chow YW, Wang HL (1998) Functional modulation of P2X2 receptors by cyclic AMP-dependent protein kinase. J Neurochem 70:2606&#x2013;2612 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9603227</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR39">
        <label>39.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wirkner</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Stanchev</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Koles</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regulation of human recombinant P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors by ecto-protein kinase C</article-title>
          <source>J Neurosci</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>25</volume>
          <fpage>7734</fpage>
          <lpage>7742</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2028-05.2005</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wirkner K, Stanchev D, Koles L et al (2005) Regulation of human recombinant P2X3 receptors by ecto-protein kinase C. J Neurosci 25:7734&#x2013;7742 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16120774</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR40">
        <label>40.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Stanchev</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Flehmig</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gerevich</surname>
              <given-names>Z</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Decrease of current responses at human recombinant P2X<sub>3</sub> receptors after substitution by Asp of Ser/Thr residues in protein kinase C phosphorylation sites of their ecto-domains</article-title>
          <source>Neurosci Lett</source>
          <year>2006</year>
          <volume>393</volume>
          <fpage>78</fpage>
          <lpage>83</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/j.neulet.2005.09.045</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Stanchev D, Flehmig G, Gerevich Z et al (2006) Decrease of current responses at human recombinant P2X3 receptors after substitution by Asp of Ser/Thr residues in protein kinase C phosphorylation sites of their ecto-domains. Neurosci Lett 393:78&#x2013;83 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16226373</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR41">
        <label>41.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Zhu</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fujii</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Belkina</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <etal/>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Exceptional disfavor for proline at the P+1 position among AGC and CAMK kinases establishes reciprocal specificity between them and the proline-directed kinases</article-title>
          <source>J Biol Chem</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>280</volume>
          <fpage>10743</fpage>
          <lpage>10748</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1074/jbc.M413159200</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Zhu G, Fujii K, Belkina N et al (2005) Exceptional disfavor for proline at the P+1 position among AGC and CAMK kinases establishes reciprocal specificity between them and the proline-directed kinases. J Biol Chem 280:10743&#x2013;10748 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15647260</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR42">
        <label>42.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>KP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Huang</surname>
              <given-names>FL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Conversion of protein kinase C from a Ca2+-dependent to an independent form of phorbol ester-binding protein by digestion with trypsin</article-title>
          <source>Biochem Biophys Res Commun</source>
          <year>1986</year>
          <volume>139</volume>
          <fpage>320</fpage>
          <lpage>326</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1016/S0006-291X(86)80116-4</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Huang KP, Huang FL (1986) Conversion of protein kinase C from a Ca2+-dependent to an independent form of phorbol ester-binding protein by digestion with trypsin. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 139:320&#x2013;326 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">3464276</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>