<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<!DOCTYPE pmc-articleset PUBLIC "-//NLM//DTD ARTICLE SET 2.0//EN" "https://dtd.nlm.nih.gov/ncbi/pmc/articleset/nlm-articleset-2.0.dtd">
<pmc-articleset><article xmlns:xlink="http://www.w3.org/1999/xlink" article-type="research-article">
  <?properties open_access?>
  <front>
    <journal-meta>
      <journal-id journal-id-type="nlm-ta">Soc Psychiatry Psychiatr Epidemiol</journal-id>
      <journal-title>Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology</journal-title>
      <issn pub-type="ppub">0933-7954</issn>
      <issn pub-type="epub">1433-9285</issn>
      <publisher>
        <publisher-name>Steinkopff-Verlag</publisher-name>
        <publisher-loc>Darmstadt</publisher-loc>
      </publisher>
    </journal-meta>
    <article-meta>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmid">17036264</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="pmc">1764204</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="publisher-id">124</article-id>
      <article-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00127-006-0124-5</article-id>
      <article-categories>
        <subj-group subj-group-type="heading">
          <subject>Original Paper</subject>
        </subj-group>
      </article-categories>
      <title-group>
        <article-title>Regional differences in psychiatric disorders in Chile</article-title>
      </title-group>
      <contrib-group>
        <contrib contrib-type="author" corresp="yes">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Vicente</surname>
            <given-names>Benjamin</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD, PhD</degrees>
          <address>
            <phone>+56-41/31-2799</phone>
            <fax>+56-41/31-2799</fax>
            <email>bvicent@udec.cl</email>
          </address>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Kohn</surname>
            <given-names>Robert</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff2">2</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Rioseco</surname>
            <given-names>Pedro</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Saldivia</surname>
            <given-names>Sandra</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>PhD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Navarrette</surname>
            <given-names>Gonzalo</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Veloso</surname>
            <given-names>Paula</given-names>
          </name>
          <degrees>MD</degrees>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <contrib contrib-type="author">
          <name name-style="western">
            <surname>Torres</surname>
            <given-names>Silverio</given-names>
          </name>
          <xref ref-type="aff" rid="Aff1">1</xref>
        </contrib>
        <aff id="Aff1"><label>1</label>Depto. de Psiquiatr&#xED;a y Salud Mental, Universidad de Concepci&#xF3;n, Casilla 60-C, Concepci&#xF3;n, Chile </aff>
        <aff id="Aff2"><label>2</label>Dept. of Psychiatry and Human Behavior, Brown University, Providence, RI USA </aff>
      </contrib-group>
      <pub-date pub-type="epub">
        <day>11</day>
        <month>10</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <pub-date pub-type="ppub">
        <month>12</month>
        <year>2006</year>
      </pub-date>
      <volume>41</volume>
      <issue>12</issue>
      <fpage>935</fpage>
      <lpage>942</lpage>
      <history>
        <date date-type="accepted">
          <day>7</day>
          <month>9</month>
          <year>2006</year>
        </date>
      </history>
      <permissions>
        <copyright-statement>&#xA9; Steinkopff Verlag Darmstadt 2006</copyright-statement>
      </permissions>
      <abstract>
        <sec>
          <title>Background</title>
          <p>Psychiatric epidemiological surveys in developing countries are rare and are frequently conducted in regions that are not necessarily representative of the entire country. In addition, in large countries with dispersed populations national rates may have low value for estimating the need for mental health services and programs.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Methods</title>
          <p>The Chile Psychiatric Prevalence Study using the Composite International Diagnostic Interview was conducted in four distinct regions of the country on a stratified random sample of 2,978 people. Lifetime and 12-month prevalence and service utilization rates were estimated.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Results</title>
          <p>Significant differences in the rates of major depressive disorder, substance abuse disorders, non-affective psychosis, and service utilization were found across the regions. The differential prevalence rates could not be accounted by socio-demographic differences between sites.</p>
        </sec>
        <sec>
          <title>Conclusions</title>
          <p>Regional differences across countries may exist that have both implications for prevalence rates and service utilization. Planning mental health services for population centers that span wide geographical areas based on studies conducted in a single region may be misleading, and may result in areas with high need being underserved.</p>
        </sec>
      </abstract>
      <kwd-group>
        <title>Keywords</title>
        <kwd>community prevalences</kwd>
        <kwd>psychiatric disorders</kwd>
        <kwd>regional differences</kwd>
        <kwd>Chile</kwd>
      </kwd-group>
      <custom-meta-wrap>
        <custom-meta>
          <meta-name>issue-copyright-statement</meta-name>
          <meta-value>&#xA9; Steinkopff Verlag Darmstadt 2006</meta-value>
        </custom-meta>
      </custom-meta-wrap>
    </article-meta>
  </front>
  <body>
    <p>Cross-national psychiatric epidemiological prevalence studies using similar diagnostic instruments have resulted in disparate rates for specific disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR1">1</xref>]. The reasons for these differences in rates have been attributed to methodological issues between studies; socio-demographic factors such as socio-economic status differences between countries; and cultural differences. Cross-national comparative studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR2">2</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR3">3</xref>] attempt to correct for socio-demographic variability; yet, differences persist. In some regions of the world, such as prevalence rates in Chinese based studies [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR4">4</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>], the rates are markedly different than the rest of the world. This either suggests true differences in the rates of pathology or lack of cultural appropriateness of the diagnostic tools and the Western diagnostic systems utilized [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR7">7</xref>]. Understanding these cross-national differences may provide clues into the etiology of psychopathology.</p>
    <p>Regional differences also exist within countries as evidenced by studies where the methodology is similar across geographic areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR8">8</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR11">11</xref>]. Regional differences in the presence of serious mental illness have been attributed to migration of the mentally ill [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR12">12</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR13">13</xref>]; birth in urban areas [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR14">14</xref>]; and genetic pooling [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR15">15</xref>]. The most studied regional differences are those between urban and rural populations, where urban environmental adversity is argued to contribute to pathology [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR16">16</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR17">17</xref>].</p>
    <p>An understanding of regional differences in countries where the population is spread across large distances is relevant for health care planning. Potentially risk factors may differ across a country resulting in the need to address mental health needs on a regional basis rather than centrally. Furthermore, an understanding of geographic variability permits allocation of resources to be distributed in a proportional basis by need.</p>
    <p>This issue is of particular importance to developing countries such as in Latin America, where frequently services are only provided centrally, or disproportionately to the wealthier regions of a country. In addition, epidemiological studies based on single regions of the country [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR18">18</xref>&#x2013;<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR20">20</xref>] are extrapolated to larger population bases for which they may or may not be representative.</p>
    <p>Population studies about psychiatric disorders in Latin America, as well as other developing regions of the world, are rare. They are important, however, for understanding variations in patterns of disorders, underlying determinants, and service needs. Chile, given its rather extraordinary geography provides an important test of variations in disorder rates across a spatially dispersed population, and offers perhaps the best case example of a country where national rates would seemingly have low value for estimating the need for mental health services and programs.</p>
    <p>The Chile Psychiatric Prevalence Study (CPPS) was developed to address issues regarding the prevalence and risk factors for mental illness based on a nationally representative sample, and service utilization. Chile has a population of approximately 16&#xA0;millions people. The country is composed of 51 provinces grouped in 13 regions covering an area spanning 2&#xA0;million&#xA0;km<sup>2</sup> (including Antarctica and Insular Territories) over a length of 8,000&#xA0;km. The large distances between major population centers resulted in the CPPS being conducted in four regions of the country, Bio Bio, the south-central region containing the second largest city, Metropolitana, the north-central region which includes the capital Santiago, Tarapaca, the north, and Araucania, the south of the country, in order to obtain a representative sampling of the population of the nation. This report focuses on whether regional differences in the prevalence of psychiatric disorders and service utilization, if present, are due to factors other than socio-demographic differences between population centers.</p>
    <sec id="Sec1" sec-type="methods">
      <title>Methods</title>
      <sec id="Sec2">
        <title>Sample selection</title>
        <p>The CPPS was based on a household stratified sample of people age 15 and older. A more detailed description of the methods used in the CPPS is available in earlier publications [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR21">21</xref>]. The sample frame was developed to be representative of the nation&#x2019;s population. Four regions and their most representative province and comunas were selected. These were subsequently subdivided into districts, and then randomly selected blocks. The number of households available on each block was enumerated. The 1992 census of each region was used to determine the number of households required on each block. A list of the inhabitants, age 15 and older, in each household was generated. Using pre-assigned Kish tables (Kish 1965) one person per household was selected from the list to be interviewed.</p>
        <p>The survey was conducted by the University of Concepcion, Department of Psychiatry and Mental Health, between July 1992 and June 1999, with each site being completed in the following order based on funding: Bio Bio, Metropolitana, Tarapaca, and Araucania. A total of 2,987 individuals participated in the survey. Response rate did differ by site (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup> = 11.08, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.02) with Metropolitana having the highest non-response rate 12.6% and Tarapaca the lowest 7.5%. A weight was used to account for the probability of the comuna, district, block, household, and respondent being selected. The data was adjusted to the 1992 census of each region based on age, gender, and marital status using a second weight.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec3">
        <title>Diagnostic assessment</title>
        <p>Composite International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI) versions 1.0 and 1.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR22">22</xref>] were used to generate the diagnoses using well-trained lay interviewers. DSM-III-R [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR23">23</xref>] diagnostic criteria were employed. A section on health service utilization in the 6-months prior to the interview was also included. The Spanish translation was conducted using the protocol outlined by the World Health Organization (WHO) [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR24">24</xref>]. A validation study of the Chilean CIDI was found to have kappas that ranged from 0.52 for somatiform disorders up to 0.94 for affective disorders [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR25">25</xref>] using a sample of patients and volunteers for each CIDI section. After double entry of data and verification for logical inconsistencies diagnoses were generated using the CIDI computer programs for 1.0 and 1.1 [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR26">26</xref>]. The DSM-III-R diagnoses included in this report are all affective disorders; all anxiety disorders defined as panic disorder, agoraphobia, and generalized anxiety disorder; substance use disorder which does not include nicotine dependence, and any diagnosis. Lifetime and 12-month prevalence rates were examined.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec4">
        <title>Interviewers and training</title>
        <p>Social science university students in their senior year underwent training following the WHO protocol at the University of Concepcion, a WHO CIDI training and reference center. The 64 interviewers received over 80&#xA0;h of instruction and practice sessions. Each interviewer had to conduct practice interviews with volunteer adult subjects with and without psychiatric disorders selected from local clinics, as well as a pilot interview on an individual in a non-selected household in the community. Approximately 80% of the interviews were audiotaped following the subject&#x2019;s consent, and 20% randomly reviewed for quality control.</p>
      </sec>
      <sec id="Sec5">
        <title>Analysis procedures</title>
        <p>The SUDAAN statistical package [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR27">27</xref>], Taylor series linearization method, was used to estimate the standard errors due to the sample design and the need for weighting. The analysis was conducted using procedures without replacement for non-respondents. The comuna and district selected were used as the defined strata. Chi-square analyses were used to examine the association of disorders and service utilization between regions. Logistic regression was used to adjust for socio-demographic differences across regions accounting for differential rates or service utilization. Additional analyses were conducted to examine urban&#x2013;rural differences. The logistic regression analyses included gender, marital status, age group, education, and income as potential confounders. All results are presented as weighted data.</p>
      </sec>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec6">
      <title>Results</title>
      <p>The distribution of income and marital status were found to differ across the four regions of the country (see Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab1" ref-type="table">1</xref>). The population of Bio Bio had significantly lower incomes than the other regions (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;67.96, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;9, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.0001). In addition, Bio Bio had the lowest rate of individuals who were separated or had annulled marriages (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;25.31, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;12, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05). In two of the regions the rural population was under-represented relative to the census. In Bio Bio 22% of population was rural the sample only included 2.7%, and in Araucania 38% of the population was rural and the sample only included 7.7%.
<table-wrap id="Tab1"><label>Table&#xA0;1</label><caption><p>Socio-demographic characteristics by region</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left" rowspan="2">Disorders</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Bio Bio (<italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;800)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Metropolitana (<italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;1363)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Tarapaca (<italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;306)</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Araucania (<italic>N</italic>&#xA0;=&#xA0;509)</th><th align="left" rowspan="2">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left" rowspan="2">df</th><th align="left" rowspan="2"><italic>P</italic></th></tr><tr><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Gender</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Male</td><td align="left">48.2</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">46.4</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">48.9</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">47.4</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">3.23</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.38</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Female</td><td align="left">51.8</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">53.6</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">51.1</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">52.6</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Age</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;15&#x2013;24</td><td align="left">26.7</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">24.9</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">27.3</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">27.0</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td align="left">7.3</td><td align="left">15</td><td align="left">0.94</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;25&#x2013;34</td><td align="left">25.4</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">26.1</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">27.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">23.2</td><td align="left">4.6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;35&#x2013;44</td><td align="left">18.2</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">18.5</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">21.1</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">17.5</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;45&#x2013;54</td><td align="left">12.1</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">12.8</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">11.8</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">12.3</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;55&#x2013;64</td><td align="left">9.0</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">9.2</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">6.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">9.8</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;65+</td><td align="left">8.7</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">8.5</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">6.2</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">10.4</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Education</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;No education</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">11.13</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">0.31</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Basic</td><td align="left">19.7</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">17.9</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">7.8</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td align="left">7.6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Medium</td><td align="left">52.3</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">47.9</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">52.7</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">38.2</td><td align="left">7.3</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;High</td><td align="left">25.2</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">33.2</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">39.1</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">45.2</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Marital status</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Married</td><td align="left">54.7</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">52.8</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">53.7</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">52.3</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left">25.31</td><td align="left">12</td><td align="left">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Widowed</td><td align="left">5.2</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">4.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Separated/anulled</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Never Married</td><td align="left">34.4</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">32.6</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">33.9</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">36.1</td><td align="left">8.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Common Law</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Income</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;U$100&#x2013;U$400</td><td align="left">70.5</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">54.5</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">12.2</td><td align="left">4.8</td><td align="left">47.7</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td align="left">67.96</td><td align="left">9</td><td align="left">0.0001</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;U$401&#x2013;U$800</td><td align="left">19.3</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">21.9</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">29.6</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">20.6</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;U$801&#x2013;U$1500</td><td align="left">6.9</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">11.9</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">35.6</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">12.5</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;U$1501+</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">11.7</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">22.7</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">19.2</td><td align="left">7.2</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="12"><italic>Urban/rural</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Urban</td><td align="left">97.3</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">99.2</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">98.9</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">92.3</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">3</td><td align="left">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;Rural</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">7.7</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left"/><td align="left"/><td align="left"/></tr></tbody></table></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Prior to adjusting for socio-demographic differences between the regions, a number of differences in prevalence rates were noted (see Tables&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab2" ref-type="table">2</xref>, <xref rid="Tab3" ref-type="table">3</xref>). Lifetime rates for major depressive disorder were markedly elevated in Tarapaca, 17.2%, and lowest in Bio Bio, 11.6% (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;9.76, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.04). Drug abuse, but not dependence, also had the highest prevalence rate in Tarapaca, 2.4% (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;8.59, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05). Interestingly, in Araucania the rate of non-affective psychosis was the lowest (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;11.45, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.02). When females were examined the differential rates for major depressive disorder (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;11.76, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.02) and substance use disorders were noted (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;10.88, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.03). Among males the only lifetime difference in prevalence rates was for elevated alcohol abuse in Tarapaca (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;9.17, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.04). For 12-month prevalence the increased risk for major depression in Tarapaca persisted (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;8.78, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.05) for both genders combined and for females (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;10.08, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.03). The differences noted in the prevalence of substance use disorders were no longer evident at 12-months.
<table-wrap id="Tab2"><label>Table&#xA0;2</label><caption><p>Lifetime prevalence rates of DSM-III-R disorders by region</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Bio Bio</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Metropolitana</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Tarapaca</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Araucania</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">Disorders</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">11.6</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">17.2</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">9.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">9.76</td><td align="left">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">1.11</td><td align="left">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">7.5</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">7.3</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">12.2</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">6.0</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">3.65</td><td align="left">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">13.6</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">23.2</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">14.0</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">3.88</td><td align="left">0.30</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.16</td><td align="left">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">14.2</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">9.8</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">9.7</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">5.46</td><td align="left">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">5.13</td><td align="left">0.19</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">19.2</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">14.8</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">17.9</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">8.6</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">6.79</td><td align="left">0.11</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">16.9</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">7.2</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">8.20</td><td align="left">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">3.63</td><td align="left">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">8.59</td><td align="left">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">7.72</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">6.5</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">5.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">7.86</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">11.0</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">11.2</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">24.3</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">12.3</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">1.94</td><td align="left">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">13.0</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">12.9</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">29.6</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">14.6</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">2.43</td><td align="left">0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">11.45</td><td align="left">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.75</td><td align="left">0.63</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Cognitive disorder</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">5.70</td><td align="left">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">32.2</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">30.8</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">44.4</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">28.9</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">2.51</td><td align="left">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11"><italic>Female</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">20.6</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">11.2</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">11.76</td><td align="left">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">3.62</td><td align="left">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">10.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">11.6</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">17.2</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">8.7</td><td align="left">5.1</td><td align="left">2.43</td><td align="left">0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">16.4</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">21.0</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">28.3</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">16.0</td><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left">3.60</td><td align="left">0.32</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">1.15</td><td align="left">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">20.3</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">13.6</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">12.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">4.88</td><td align="left">0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">6.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">5.98</td><td align="left">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">26.4</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">20.9</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">24.8</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">12.3</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">5.19</td><td align="left">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.06</td><td align="left">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">7.53</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">7.38</td><td align="left">0.08</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">6.86</td><td align="left">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">10.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.45</td><td align="left">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">6.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">11.80</td><td align="left">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">8.9</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">16.5</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">10.88</td><td align="left">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">7.81</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">4.10</td><td align="left">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">35.6</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">34.7</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">37.8</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">23.4</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">3.02</td><td align="left">0.40</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11"><italic>Male</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">7.4</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">13.6</td><td align="left">4.6</td><td align="left">8.3</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">6.84</td><td align="left">0.10</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">1.18</td><td align="left">0.76</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">7.1</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">4.10</td><td align="left">0.27</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">10.5</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">9.0</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">18.0</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">11.8</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">14.57</td><td align="left">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">4.39</td><td align="left">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">7.7</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">7.2</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">3.94</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.83</td><td align="left">0.61</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">11.5</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">7.9</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">10.6</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">7.59</td><td align="left">0.07</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">31.9</td><td align="left">5.6</td><td align="left">14.1</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">9.17</td><td align="left">0.04</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">12.5</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">11.6</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">10.2</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">1.11</td><td align="left">0.77</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">6.93</td><td align="left">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.40</td><td align="left">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">8.6</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">6.05</td><td align="left">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">18.9</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">15.9</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">42.6</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td align="left">24.3</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">4.83</td><td align="left">0.20</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">20.5</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">17.6</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">43.3</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left">26.2</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">5.55</td><td align="left">0.16</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">5.78</td><td align="left">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.23</td><td align="left">0.97</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">28.5</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">26.4</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">51.2</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">35.0</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">4.46</td><td align="left">0.23</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Non-affective psychosis includes schizophrenia, schizophreniform disorder, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, and atypical psychosis</p><p>Any CPSS disorder does not include nicotine dependence or cognitive disorder; &#x3C7;<sup>2</sup> df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab3"><label>Table&#xA0;3</label><caption><p>12-Month prevalence rates of DSM-III-R disorders by region</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Bio Bio</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Metropolitana</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Tarapaca</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Araucania</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">Disorders</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left" colspan="11"><italic>Total</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">7.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">10.3</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">5.1</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">8.78</td><td align="left">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">2.05</td><td align="left">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">7.9</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">6.10</td><td align="left">0.13</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">7.8</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">10.8</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">15.0</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">7.5</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">5.19</td><td align="left">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">4.1</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.32</td><td align="left">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">6.1</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">7.5</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">4.44</td><td align="left">0.24</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">2.41</td><td align="left">0.50</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">11.1</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">9.2</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">11.9</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">5.69</td><td align="left">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">5.8</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">4.05</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">5.2</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">4.8</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">4.26</td><td align="left">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">3.99</td><td align="left">0.28</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.91</td><td align="left">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">5.6</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">4.18</td><td align="left">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">7.9</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">10.7</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">6.2</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">2.84</td><td align="left">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">10.0</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">9.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">15.7</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">8.2</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">2.38</td><td align="left">0.51</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">8.45</td><td align="left">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.95</td><td align="left">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">23.9</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">23.0</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">25.3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">14.7</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">2.84</td><td align="left">0.43</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11"><italic>Female</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">4.8</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">10.5</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">14.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">10.08</td><td align="left">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">6.25</td><td align="left">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">4.3</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">6.9</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">8.8</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">6.92</td><td align="left">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">9.6</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">20.0</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">8.2</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">5.72</td><td align="left">0.15</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">6.6</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">1.37</td><td align="left">0.71</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">11.9</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">8.4</td><td align="left">2.4</td><td align="left">10.4</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">5.78</td><td align="left">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">3.9</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">3.24</td><td align="left">0.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td align="left">2.3</td><td align="left">13.0</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">17.5</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">5.90</td><td align="left">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.93</td><td align="left">0.82</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">5.16</td><td align="left">0.18</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">2.48</td><td align="left">0.49</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">8.50</td><td align="left">0.05</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">8.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">1.71</td><td align="left">0.64</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">5.1</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">7.98</td><td align="left">0.06</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">4.9</td><td align="left">1.4</td><td align="left">6.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">13.3</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">14.74</td><td align="left">0.01</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">7.05</td><td align="left">0.09</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">4.2</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">4.50</td><td align="left">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">23.4</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">24.7</td><td align="left">2.9</td><td align="left">28.4</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">12.3</td><td align="left">5.1</td><td align="left">2.83</td><td align="left">0.42</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11"><italic>Male</italic></td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Affective disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Major depressive episode</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">4.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">5.5</td><td align="left">3.6</td><td align="left">5.0</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.30</td><td align="left">0.73</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Manic episode</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.68</td><td align="left">0.88</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Dysthmia</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">3.3</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">4.78</td><td align="left">0.21</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any affective disorder</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">5.7</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">9.8</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">4.46</td><td align="left">0.23</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Anxiety disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Panic disorder</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">3.07</td><td align="left">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Agoraphobia without panic</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">1.7</td><td align="left">4.5</td><td align="left">3.8</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">1.94</td><td align="left">0.59</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Generalized anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.97</td><td align="left">0.58</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any anxiety disorder</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">4.7</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">6.1</td><td align="left">3.5</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">3.26</td><td align="left">0.37</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Substance use disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol abuse</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">2.7</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">10.9</td><td align="left">3.7</td><td align="left">6.3</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">6.20</td><td align="left">0.12</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Alcohol dependence</td><td align="left">9.7</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">8.8</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">3.1</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">5.9</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">3.88</td><td align="left">0.29</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug abuse</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">3.47</td><td align="left">0.34</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Drug dependence</td><td align="left">1.5</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.6</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.33</td><td align="left">0.95</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Nicotine dependence</td><td align="left">2.2</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">7.0</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">3.08</td><td align="left">0.39</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any alcohol or drug use disorder</td><td align="left">14.4</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">11.8</td><td align="left">2.0</td><td align="left">16.6</td><td align="left">4.4</td><td align="left">12.1</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">1.25</td><td align="left">0.74</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Any substance use disorder</td><td align="left">15.4</td><td align="left">3.2</td><td align="left">13.3</td><td align="left">2.1</td><td align="left">18.2</td><td align="left">4.0</td><td align="left">14.1</td><td align="left">2.8</td><td align="left">1.07</td><td align="left">0.78</td></tr><tr><td align="left" colspan="11">Other disorders</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Non-affective psychosis</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">0.7</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">0.0</td><td align="left">5.75</td><td align="left">0.14</td></tr><tr><td align="left">&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;&#xA0;Somatoform disorder</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">1.2</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">2.6</td><td align="left">0.5</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">0.8</td><td align="left">2.05</td><td align="left">0.57</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Any CPPS disorder</td><td align="left">21.8</td><td align="left">5.3</td><td align="left">20.5</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">22.0</td><td align="left">3.0</td><td align="left">17.3</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">1.12</td><td align="left">0.77</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>Non-affective psychosis includes schizophrenia, schizophreniform disorder, schizoaffective disorder, delusional disorder, and atypical psychosis</p><p>Any CPSS disorder does not include nicotine dependence or cognitive disorder; &#x3C7;<sup>2</sup> df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap><table-wrap id="Tab4"><label>Table&#xA0;4</label><caption><p>Mental health service utilization in the past 6-months by region among those with DSM-III-R 12-month prevalent disorder</p></caption><table frame="hsides" rules="groups"><thead><tr><th align="left"/><th align="left" colspan="2">Bio Bio</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Metropolitana</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Tarapaca</th><th align="left" colspan="2">Araucania</th><th align="left"/><th align="left"/></tr><tr><th align="left">Disorders</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">%</th><th align="left">SE</th><th align="left">&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup></th><th align="left"><italic>P</italic></th></tr></thead><tbody><tr><td align="left">Any MH service</td><td align="left">17.6</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">21.1</td><td align="left">2.5</td><td align="left">25.9</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">12.0</td><td align="left">1.9</td><td align="left">10.09</td><td align="left">0.03</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Non-specialized MH service</td><td align="left">15.2</td><td align="left">1.0</td><td align="left">17.1</td><td align="left">1.8</td><td align="left">24.3</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">10.7</td><td align="left">1.6</td><td align="left">12.63</td><td align="left">0.02</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Specialized MH service</td><td align="left">5.2</td><td align="left">0.9</td><td align="left">6.7</td><td align="left">1.3</td><td align="left">5.6</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">3.4</td><td align="left">1.1</td><td align="left">4.26</td><td align="left">0.26</td></tr><tr><td align="left">Substance service</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.3</td><td align="left">0.2</td><td align="left">0.4</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">0.1</td><td align="left">2.87</td><td align="left">0.43</td></tr></tbody></table><table-wrap-foot><p>&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup> df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, MH&#xA0;=&#xA0;Mental Health</p><p>Non-Specialized MH Services&#xA0;=&#xA0;primary care physicians; Specialized Mental Health Services&#xA0;=&#xA0;inpatient or outpatient services provided by a psychiatrist or a psychologist or formal substance abuse services; Substance abuse services included inpatient and outpatient detoxification or Alcoholics Anonymous</p></table-wrap-foot></table-wrap></p>
      <p>Using logistic regression controlling for socio-demographic variables the regional differences for major depression were maintained for both lifetime and 12-month prevalence, as well as among females in both prevalence periods. Males with lifetime prevalent affective disorders were also at increased risk in Tarapaca. In addition regional differences in lifetime prevalence for alcohol abuse, drug abuse, and nicotine dependence were found. Among females, regional differences in lifetime prevalence were noted for drug abuse, drug dependence, any alcohol or drug use disorder, and cognitive disorders, and among men alcohol abuse with increased risk among those residing in Tarapaca. The statistical differences in regional lifetime prevalence of non-affective psychosis for both genders combined, and females in both prevalence periods, persisted with the rates for Araucania remaining low. As the rates for not only major depression, but also alcohol and drug use disorders were elevated in Tarapaca, additional analyses were conducted controlling for comorbidity in the logistic regressions, the regional differences noted were not altered.</p>
      <p>Differences in service utilization across the four regions were also found. Araucania had the lowest use of mental health services utilization (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;0.03, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.03), in particular in the non-specialized health care sector (&#x3C7;<sup>2</sup>&#xA0;=&#xA0;12.63, df&#xA0;=&#xA0;3, <italic>P</italic>&#xA0;&lt;&#xA0;0.02). The rates of service utilization by region are presented in Table&#xA0;<xref rid="Tab4" ref-type="table">4</xref>. The lower use of services persisted after controlling for socio-demographic variables in a logistic regression.</p>
      <p>When urban versus rural was examined across all sites no statistical differences in the rates of disorders were noted. In addition, there were no socio-demographic differences. The sample size of the rural population was small, 203.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec7">
      <title>Discussion</title>
      <p>Regional differences that persisted after adjusting for potential confounders persisted in the CPPS. Major depression and substance use disorders were highly prevalent in Tarapaca. The high rates of substance use disorders, especially drugs, and were not surprising as the region bordering Bolivia and Peru is heavily involved in the drug trade. The increased rates of major depression, however, could not be accounted for by substance use disorder comorbidity. The differences in rates for non-affective psychosis, although may simply be due to a type 1 error, are nonetheless surprising as the Araucania region&#x2019;s population and our sample has a sizable proportion of Mapuche indigenous people. The Mapuche in earlier psychiatric literature were thought to be at increased risk for psychosis [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR28">28</xref>]. The small sample size of the rural population precluded finding statistically significant differences.</p>
      <p>The utilization of health service was lowest in Araucania and Bio Bio. This may be consistent with the inequities in availability and access that do exist in health and mental health resources across different regions of Chile. The southern half of the country is the poorest and has the least resources; therefore, the lower rates may be due to a lack of access rather than demand. For example across the regions the number of available mental health beds 2001 in the public health service per 100,000 were Araucania 2.2; Bio Bio 4.8; Metropolitana 34.2; and Tarapaca 47.2. The number of primary care physicians per 100,000 populations also was lowest in Araucania, 57.0, compared to Bio Bio with 169.7, Tarapaca with 61.6 and Metropolitana with 185.8.</p>
      <p>It could be argued that these regional differences are simply artifact due to sampling differences. Clearly the population investigated in Tarapaca is small for a prevalence study and may have resulted in rates that may prove unstable. Another potential limitation is that the four regions were investigated sequentially, with the potential for socio-cultural influences to impact on the rates during the intervals between data collection. The high proportion of low-income individuals in the Bio Bio sample in comparison to the other sites and in particular Aracucania, the poorest region of the country, reflects the improved economic conditions in Chile during the course of data collection and supports a cohort effect. A cohort effect, however, is highly unlikely to explain the rates of psychopathology given that data collection was obtained from Araucania last, yet it has the highest rate of major depressive disorder.</p>
    </sec>
    <sec id="Sec8">
      <title>Conclusion</title>
      <p>Regional differences across countries may exist that have both implications for prevalence rates and service utilization. Planning mental health services for population centers that span wide geographical areas based on studies conducted in a single region may be misleading, and may result in areas with high need being underserved. Psychiatric epidemiological studies that are nationally representative of developing nations are needed that have a sufficient sampling frame to examine populations believed to be at high risk and regions where increased inequities may exist. Even the most recent epidemiological studies representing Latin America [<xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR6">6</xref>, <xref ref-type="bibr" rid="CR29">29</xref>] have ignored large segments of the population, such as those countries and regions of countries with large indigenous populations or segments of the population that are very poor. Fewer studies in the region have examined service needs and none have addressed regional differences in services. Data that is more representative of the Latin American population is needed in order to improve mental health services planning and addresses the large under-estimated treatment gap.</p>
    </sec>
  </body>
  <back>
    <ack>
      <title>Acknowledgment</title>
      <p>The authors wish to thank the Pan American Health Organization/World Health Organization for their technical and financial support. We also wish to acknowledge the financial support of FONDECYT (No. 90-229, 92-233, 1971315, 1990325) and Direcci&#xF3;n de Investigaci&#xF3;n de la Universidad de Concepci&#xF3;n (No. 201.087.027-1.0).</p>
    </ack>
    <ref-list id="Bib1">
      <title>References</title>
      <ref id="CR1">
        <label>1.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Bjil</surname>
              <given-names>RV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Graff</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hiripi</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kessler</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Offord</surname>
              <given-names>DR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Ustun</surname>
              <given-names>TB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vicente</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vollebergh</surname>
              <given-names>WAM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walters</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittchen</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The prevalence of treated and untreated mental disorders in five countries</article-title>
          <source>Health Affairs</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>22</volume>
          <fpage>122</fpage>
          <lpage>133</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1377/hlthaff.22.3.122</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Bjil RV, de Graff R, Hiripi E, Kessler RC, Kohn R, Offord DR, Ustun TB, Vicente B, Vollebergh WAM, Walters EE, Wittchen HU (2003) The prevalence of treated and untreated mental disorders in five countries. Health Affairs 22:122&#x2013;133 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12757277</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR2">
        <label>2.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>WHO International Consortium in Psychiatric Epidemiology</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cross-national comparisons of the prevalences and correlates of mental disorders</article-title>
          <source>Bull World Health Organ</source>
          <year>2000</year>
          <volume>78</volume>
          <fpage>413</fpage>
          <lpage>25</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">WHO International Consortium in Psychiatric Epidemiology (2000) Cross-national comparisons of the prevalences and correlates of mental disorders. Bull World Health Organ 78:413&#x2013;25 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">10885160</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR3">
        <label>3.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Weissman</surname>
              <given-names>MM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bland</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Canino</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Garavelli</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Greenwald</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hwu</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Joyce</surname>
              <given-names>PR</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Karam</surname>
              <given-names>EG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lee</surname>
              <given-names>CK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lellouch</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lepine</surname>
              <given-names>JP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Newman</surname>
              <given-names>SC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rubio-Stipec</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wells</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wickramaratne</surname>
              <given-names>PJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittchen</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Cross-national epidemiology of major depression and bipolar disorder</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>1996</year>
          <volume>276</volume>
          <fpage>293</fpage>
          <lpage>299</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.276.4.293</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Weissman MM, Bland RC, Canino GJ, Garavelli C, Greenwald S, Hwu HG, Joyce PR, Karam EG, Lee CK, Lellouch J, Lepine JP, Newman SC, Rubio-Stipec M, Wells JE, Wickramaratne PJ, Wittchen HU, Yeh EK (1996) Cross-national epidemiology of major depression and bipolar disorder. JAMA 276:293&#x2013;299 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8656541</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR4">
        <label>4.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hwu</surname>
              <given-names>HG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yeh</surname>
              <given-names>EK</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Chang</surname>
              <given-names>LY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of psychiatric disorders in Taiwan defined by the Chinese Diagnostic Interview Schedule</article-title>
          <source>Acta Psychiatr Scand</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <volume>79</volume>
          <fpage>136</fpage>
          <lpage>147</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hwu HG, Yeh EK, Chang LY (1989) Prevalence of psychiatric disorders in Taiwan defined by the Chinese Diagnostic Interview Schedule. Acta Psychiatr Scand 79:136&#x2013;147 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2923007</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR5">
        <label>5.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Wang</surname>
              <given-names>CH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Liu</surname>
              <given-names>WT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhang</surname>
              <given-names>MY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Yu</surname>
              <given-names>ESH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xia</surname>
              <given-names>ZY</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandez</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Lung</surname>
              <given-names>CT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Xu</surname>
              <given-names>CL</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Qu</surname>
              <given-names>GY</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Helzer</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Canino</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Alcohol use, abuse, and dependency in Shanghai</article-title>
          <source>Alcoholism in North America, Europe, and Asia</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Oxford University Press</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Wang CH, Liu WT, Zhang MY, Yu ESH, Xia ZY, Fernandez M, Lung CT, Xu CL, Qu GY (1992) Alcohol use, abuse, and dependency in Shanghai. In: Helzer JE, Canino GJ (eds) Alcoholism in North America, Europe, and Asia. Oxford University Press, New York </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR6">
        <label>6.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <collab>WHO World Mental Health Survey Consortium</collab>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence, severity, and unmet need for treatment of mental disorders in the World Health Organization World Mental Health Surveys</article-title>
          <source>JAMA</source>
          <year>2004</year>
          <volume>291</volume>
          <fpage>2581</fpage>
          <lpage>2590</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1001/jama.291.21.2581</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">WHO World Mental Health Survey Consortium (2004) Prevalence, severity, and unmet need for treatment of mental disorders in the World Health Organization World Mental Health Surveys. JAMA 291:2581&#x2013;2590 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">15173149</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR7">
        <label>7.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kleinman</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Rethinking psychiatry from cultural category to personal experience</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Simon and Schuster</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kleinman A (1997) Rethinking psychiatry from cultural category to personal experience. Simon and Schuster, New York </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR8">
        <label>8.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kessler</surname>
              <given-names>RC</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>McGonagle</surname>
              <given-names>KA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Zhao</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Nelson</surname>
              <given-names>CB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Hughes</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Eshleman</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittchen</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kendler</surname>
              <given-names>K</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Lifetime and 12-month prevalence of DSM-III-R psychiatric disorders in the United States</article-title>
          <source>Arch Gen Psychiatr</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <volume>51</volume>
          <fpage>8</fpage>
          <lpage>19</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kessler RC, McGonagle KA, Zhao S, Nelson CB, Hughes M, Eshleman S, Wittchen HU, Kendler K (1994) Lifetime and 12-month prevalence of DSM-III-R psychiatric disorders in the United States. Arch Gen Psychiatr 51:8&#x2013;19 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">8279933</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR9">
        <label>9.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Robins</surname>
              <given-names>LN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regier</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>Psychiatric disorders in America: the epidemiologic catchment area study</source>
          <year>1989</year>
          <publisher-loc>New York</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Free Press</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Robins LN, Regier DA (eds) (1989) Psychiatric disorders in America: the epidemiologic catchment area study. Free Press, New York </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR10">
        <label>10.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida-Filho</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mari</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Coutinho</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fran&#xE7;a</surname>
              <given-names>JF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fernandes</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andreoli</surname>
              <given-names>SB</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Busnello</surname>
              <given-names>ED</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Brazilian multicentric study of psychiatric morbidity. Methodological features and prevalence estimates</article-title>
          <source>Br J Psychiatr</source>
          <year>1977</year>
          <volume>171</volume>
          <fpage>524</fpage>
          <lpage>529</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Almeida-Filho N, Mari JJ, Coutinho E, Fran&#xE7;a JF, Fernandes J, Andreoli SB, Busnello ED (1977) Brazilian multicentric study of psychiatric morbidity. Methodological features and prevalence estimates. Br J Psychiatr 171:524&#x2013;529 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR11">
        <label>11.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Lewis</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Booth</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regional differences in mental health in Great Britain</article-title>
          <source>J Epidemiol Community Health</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>46</volume>
          <fpage>608</fpage>
          <lpage>611</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Lewis G, Booth M (1992) Regional differences in mental health in Great Britain. J Epidemiol Community Health 46:608&#x2013;611 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1494077</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR12">
        <label>12.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Dembling</surname>
              <given-names>BP</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rovnyak</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Mackey</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Blank</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Effect of geographic migration on SMI prevalence estimates</article-title>
          <source>Ment Health Serv Res</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>4</volume>
          <fpage>7</fpage>
          <lpage>12</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1023/A:1014041024787</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Dembling BP, Rovnyak V, Mackey S, Blank M (2002) Effect of geographic migration on SMI prevalence estimates. Ment Health Serv Res 4:7&#x2013;12 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12090306</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR13">
        <label>13.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Harrison</surname>
              <given-names>G</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Glazebrook</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brewin</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Cantwell</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Dalkin</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Fox</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jones</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Medley</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Increased incidence of psychotic disorders in migrants from the Caribbean to the United Kingdom</article-title>
          <source>Psychol Med</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <volume>27</volume>
          <fpage>799</fpage>
          <lpage>806</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291796004643</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Harrison G, Glazebrook C, Brewin J, Cantwell R, Dalkin T, Fox R, Jones P, Medley I (1997) Increased incidence of psychotic disorders in migrants from the Caribbean to the United Kingdom. Psychol Med 27:799&#x2013;806 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9234458</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR14">
        <label>14.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Haukka</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Suvisaari</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Varilo</surname>
              <given-names>T</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>L&#xF6;nnqvist</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Regional variation in the incidence of schizophrenia in Findland: a study of birth corhorts born from 1950 to 1969</article-title>
          <source>Psychol Med</source>
          <year>2001</year>
          <volume>31</volume>
          <fpage>1045</fpage>
          <lpage>1053</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1017/S0033291701004299</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Haukka J, Suvisaari J, Varilo T, L&#xF6;nnqvist J (2001) Regional variation in the incidence of schizophrenia in Findland: a study of birth corhorts born from 1950 to 1969. Psychol Med 31:1045&#x2013;1053 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">11513372</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR15">
        <label>15.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Youssef</surname>
              <given-names>HA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname> Kinsella </surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Waddington</surname>
              <given-names>JL</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Evidence for geographical variations in the prevalence of schizophrenia in rural Ireland</article-title>
          <source>Arch Gen Psychiatr</source>
          <year>1991</year>
          <volume>48</volume>
          <fpage>254</fpage>
          <lpage>255</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Youssef HA, Kinsella A, Waddington JL (1991) Evidence for geographical variations in the prevalence of schizophrenia in rural Ireland. Arch Gen Psychiatr 48:254&#x2013;255 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">1996920</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR16">
        <label>16.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Marsella</surname>
              <given-names>AJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Urbanization, mental health, and social deviancy. A review of issues and research</article-title>
          <source>Am Psychol</source>
          <year>1998</year>
          <volume>53</volume>
          <fpage>624</fpage>
          <lpage>634</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1037/0003-066X.53.6.624</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Marsella AJ (1998) Urbanization, mental health, and social deviancy. A review of issues and research. Am Psychol 53:624&#x2013;634 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">9633263</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR17">
        <label>17.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Paykel</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Abbott</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jenkins</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Brugha</surname>
              <given-names>TT</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Meltzer</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Urban&#x2013;rural mental health differences in Great Britain findings from the National Morbidity Survey</article-title>
          <source>Int Rev Psychiatry</source>
          <year>2003</year>
          <volume>15</volume>
          <fpage>87</fpage>
          <lpage>107</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Paykel E, Abbott R, Jenkins R, Brugha TT, Meltzer H (2003) Urban&#x2013;rural mental health differences in Great Britain findings from the National Morbidity Survey. Int Rev Psychiatry 15:87&#x2013;107 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR18">
        <label>18.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Caraveo-Anduaga</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Colmenares</surname>
              <given-names>E</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saldivar</surname>
              <given-names>GJ</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Morbilidad psiqui&#xE1;trica en la ciudad de M&#xE9;xico: prevalencia y comorbilidad a lo largo de la vida</article-title>
          <source>Salud Mental</source>
          <year>1999</year>
          <volume>34</volume>
          <fpage>62</fpage>
          <lpage>67</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Caraveo-Anduaga JJ, Colmenares E, Saldivar GJ (1999) Morbilidad psiqui&#xE1;trica en la ciudad de M&#xE9;xico: prevalencia y comorbilidad a lo largo de la vida. Salud Mental 34:62&#x2013;67 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR19">
        <label>19.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Walters</surname>
              <given-names>EE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Gentil</surname>
              <given-names>V</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Laurenti</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalence of ICD-10 mental disorders in a catchment area in the city of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil</article-title>
          <source>Soc Psychiatr Psychiat Epidemiol</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>37</volume>
          <fpage>316</fpage>
          <lpage>325</lpage>
          <pub-id pub-id-type="doi">10.1007/s00127-002-0551-x</pub-id>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Andrade LH, Walters EE, Gentil V, Laurenti R (2002) Prevalence of ICD-10 mental disorders in a catchment area in the city of S&#xE3;o Paulo, Brazil. Soc Psychiatr Psychiat Epidemiol 37:316&#x2013;325 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR20">
        <label>20.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Hayashi</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Perales</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sogi</surname>
              <given-names>C</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Warthon</surname>
              <given-names>D</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Llanos</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Novara</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Prevalencia de vida de trastornos mentales en Independencia (Lima, Peru)</article-title>
          <source>Anales de Salud Mental</source>
          <year>1985</year>
          <volume>1</volume>
          <fpage>206</fpage>
          <lpage>222</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Hayashi S, Perales A, Sogi C, Warthon D, Llanos R, Novara J (1985) Prevalencia de vida de trastornos mentales en Independencia (Lima, Peru). Anales de Salud Mental 1:206&#x2013;222 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR21">
        <label>21.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vicente</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rioseco</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saldivia</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kohn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Estudio Chileno de prevalencia de patolog&#xED;a psiqui&#xE1;trica (DSM-III-R/CIDI) (ECPP)</article-title>
          <source>Rev Med Chile</source>
          <year>2002</year>
          <volume>130</volume>
          <fpage>527</fpage>
          <lpage>536</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vicente B, Rioseco P, Saldivia S, Kohn R, Torres S (2002) Estudio Chileno de prevalencia de patolog&#xED;a psiqui&#xE1;trica (DSM-III-R/CIDI) (ECPP). Rev Med Chile 130:527&#x2013;536 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">12143273</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR22">
        <label>22.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Robins</surname>
              <given-names>LN</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wing</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittchen</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Helzer</surname>
              <given-names>JE</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Babor</surname>
              <given-names>TF</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Burke</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Farmer</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Jablensky</surname>
              <given-names>A</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Pickens</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Regier</surname>
              <given-names>DA</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Sartorius</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Towle</surname>
              <given-names>LH</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>The composite international diagnostic interview: an epidemiologic instrument suitable for use in conjunction with different diagnostic systems and in different cultures</article-title>
          <source>Arch Gen Psychiatr</source>
          <year>1988</year>
          <volume>45</volume>
          <fpage>1069</fpage>
          <lpage>1077</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Robins LN, Wing J, Wittchen HU, Helzer JE, Babor TF, Burke J, Farmer A, Jablensky A, Pickens R, Regier DA, Sartorius N, Towle LH (1988) The composite international diagnostic interview: an epidemiologic instrument suitable for use in conjunction with different diagnostic systems and in different cultures. Arch Gen Psychiatr 45:1069&#x2013;1077 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">2848472</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR23">
        <label>23.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <source>Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, DSM-III-R</source>
          <year>1987</year>
          <edition>3</edition>
          <publisher-loc>Washington, DC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>American Psychiatric Association</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">American Psychiatric Association (1987) Diagnostic and statistical manual of mental disorders, DSM-III-R, 3rd edn. revised. American Psychiatric Association, Washington, DC </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR24">
        <label>24.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Sartorius</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuyken</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <person-group person-group-type="editor">
            <name>
              <surname>Orley</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Kuyken</surname>
              <given-names>W</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Translation of health status instruments</article-title>
          <source>Quality of life assessment in health care settings, volume 1</source>
          <year>1994</year>
          <publisher-loc>Berlin</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Springer</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Sartorius N, Kuyken W (1994) Translation of health status instruments. In: Orley J, Kuyken W (eds) Quality of life assessment in health care settings, volume 1. Springer, Berlin </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR25">
        <label>25.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Vielma</surname>
              <given-names>M</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vicente</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Rioseco</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castro</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Castro</surname>
              <given-names>N</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Torres</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Validaci&#xF3;n en Chile de la entrevista diagn&#xF3;stica estandarizada para estudios epidemiol&#xF3;gicos CIDI</article-title>
          <source>Rev Psiquiatr&#xED;a</source>
          <year>1992</year>
          <volume>9</volume>
          <fpage>1039</fpage>
          <lpage>1049</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Vielma M, Vicente B, Rioseco P, Castro P, Castro N, Torres S (1992) Validaci&#xF3;n en Chile de la entrevista diagn&#xF3;stica estandarizada para estudios epidemiol&#xF3;gicos CIDI. Rev Psiquiatr&#xED;a 9:1039&#x2013;1049 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR26">
        <label>26.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Pfister</surname>
              <given-names>H</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Wittchen</surname>
              <given-names>HU</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>CIDI core computer manual for data entry and diagnostic programmes for the composite international diagnostic interview (CIDI)</source>
          <year>1990</year>
          <publisher-loc>Geneva</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>World Health Organization</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Pfister H, Wittchen HU (1990) CIDI core computer manual for data entry and diagnostic programmes for the composite international diagnostic interview (CIDI). World Health Organization, Geneva </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR27">
        <label>27.</label>
        <citation citation-type="book">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Shah</surname>
              <given-names>BV</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Barnwell</surname>
              <given-names>BG</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Bieler</surname>
              <given-names>GS</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <source>SUDAAN user&#x2019;s manual. Release 7.5</source>
          <year>1997</year>
          <publisher-loc>Research Triangle Park, NC</publisher-loc>
          <publisher-name>Research Triangle Institute</publisher-name>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Shah BV, Barnwell BG, Bieler GS (1997) SUDAAN user&#x2019;s manual. Release 7.5. Research Triangle Institute, Research Triangle Park, NC </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR28">
        <label>28.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Mu&#xF1;oz</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Marconi</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Horwitz</surname>
              <given-names>J</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Naveillan</surname>
              <given-names>P</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Crosscultural definitions applied to the study of functional psychoses in Chilean Mapuches</article-title>
          <source>Br J Psychiatr</source>
          <year>1966</year>
          <volume>112</volume>
          <fpage>1205</fpage>
          <lpage>1215</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Mu&#xF1;oz L, Marconi J, Horwitz J, Naveillan P (1966) Crosscultural definitions applied to the study of functional psychoses in Chilean Mapuches. Br J Psychiatr 112:1205&#x2013;1215 </citation>
      </ref>
      <ref id="CR29">
        <label>29.</label>
        <citation citation-type="journal">
          <person-group person-group-type="author">
            <name>
              <surname>Kohn</surname>
              <given-names>R</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Levav</surname>
              <given-names>I</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Almeida</surname>
              <given-names>JM</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Vicente</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Andrade</surname>
              <given-names>L</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Caraveo-Anduaga</surname>
              <given-names>JJ</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saxena</surname>
              <given-names>S</given-names>
            </name>
            <name>
              <surname>Saraceno</surname>
              <given-names>B</given-names>
            </name>
          </person-group>
          <article-title>Mental disorders in Latin America and the Caribbean: a public health priority</article-title>
          <source>Rev Panam Salud Publica</source>
          <year>2005</year>
          <volume>18</volume>
          <fpage>229</fpage>
          <lpage>240</lpage>
        </citation>
        <citation citation-type="display-unstructured">Kohn R, Levav I, de Almeida JM, Vicente B, Andrade L, Caraveo-Anduaga JJ, Saxena S, Saraceno B (2005) Mental disorders in Latin America and the Caribbean: a public health priority. Rev Panam Salud Publica 18:229&#x2013;240 <pub-id pub-id-type="pmid">16354419</pub-id></citation>
      </ref>
    </ref-list>
  </back>
</article>
</pmc-articleset>